<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author>Greg Van Buskirk</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2022-09-21</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2023-06-09T21:54:51Z</date><name>Greg Van Buskirk</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p style="text-align: center;"><hi rend="bold">&lt;pb n="466"/&gt;</hi>Sermons 21-33</p>
            <p style="text-align: center;">Upon Our Lord’s Sermon On The Mount</p>
            <p style="text-align: center;">An Introductory Comment</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi>The unifying theme of these next
                thirteen ‘discourses’ on the Sermon on the Mount, with all their variations and
                nuancings, is the Christian life understood as the fruit of justifying faith. But
                given such faith, what follows? Wesley’s answer is given in this extended exposition
                of the Christian life based on the <hi rend="bold">&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>locus
                    classicus<hi rend="bold">&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi> of evangelical ethics,
                ‘The Sermon on the Mount’ (i.e., Matthew 5-7). Since Tyndale, this ‘sermon’ had been
                understood as ‘the epitome of God’s laws and promises’ for Christian believers; cf.
                Clebsch, <hi rend="bold">&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>England’s Earliest Protestants<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi>, p. 184; see also William Burkitt, <hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>Expository Notes…on the New Testament<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi> (eleven editions between 1700 and 1739), Preface
                to chapter 5: ‘Christ’s famous Sermon on the Mount comprehends the sum and substance
                of both the Old and New Testaments.’</p>
            <p>Taken together, the following sermons are not a thirteen-part essay, tightly
                organized and argued. Instead, they are separate sermons, drawn from materials
                running back to 1725, arranged in a triadic pattern that seems to have been original
                with Wesley. Each is a discourse in its own right; yet the series is designed so
                that each appears as a part of a whole. This means that the sermons may be read
                singly or together, but with an eye on their shared aim: ‘to assert and prove every
                branch of <hi rend="bold">&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>gospel obedience<hi rend="bold">&lt;hi
                    rend="italic"&gt;</hi> as indispensably necessary to eternal salvation’; cf.
                Wesley’s open letter (Nov. 17, 1759) to John Downes in reply to the latter’s abusive
                    <hi rend="bold">&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>Methodism Examined and Exposed<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi> (1759).</p>
            <p>Many of the great and near-great commentators of the seventeenth and eighteenth
                centuries had devoted their talents to the interpretation of Matthew 5-7 as the
                principal summary of Christian ethics, or, in Henry Hammond’s phrase, as ‘an
                abstract of Christian philosophy’; cf. his <hi rend="bold">&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>Practical
                    Catechism<hi rend="bold">&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi> (1st edn., <hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>c.<hi rend="bold">&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi>
                1644), II.1, in the <hi rend="bold">&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>Library of Anglo-Catholic
                    Theology<hi rend="bold">&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi> (1847), p. 83. Chief among
                these earlier works, in the order of their influences upon Wesley’s thought, were
                Bishop Offspring Blackall, ‘Eighty-Seven Practical Discourses Upon Our Saviour’s
                Sermon on the Mount’, <hi rend="bold">&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>Works<hi rend="bold">&lt;hi
                    rend="italic"&gt;</hi>, I.1-561; II.609-939; <hi rend="bold">&lt;pb
                    n="467"/&gt;</hi>John Norris, <hi rend="bold">&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>Practical
                    Discourses<hi rend="bold">&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi>; the American, James
                Blair, <hi rend="bold">&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>Our Saviour’s Divine Sermon on the Mount in
                IV Volumes<hi rend="bold">&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi> (1722; 2nd edn., 1740, with
                a preface by Daniel Waterland); John Cardinal Bona, <hi rend="bold"
                >&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>Guide to Eternity…<hi rend="bold">&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi>
                (six editions in English between 1672 and 1712); and Henry Hammond, <hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>op. cit.<hi rend="bold">&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi> Echoes of
                all these are scattered along the way, together with lesser borrowings from Bengel,
                Poole, and Henry. This makes it all the more remarkable that Wesley came up with a
                model of his own, both inform and substance. This series thus reminds us, yet again,
                of Wesley’s ready appeal to tradition—even while he maintains his own originality
                and independence.</p>
            <p>Benjamin Ingham records in his Journal that ‘during the voyage [to Georgia] Wesley
                went over our Saviour’s Sermon on the Mount’ with the ship’s company aboard the <hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>Simmonds<hi rend="bold">&lt;hi
                    rend="italic"&gt;</hi>. There are also other records of his preaching, very
                early on, from one or another text in Matthew 5-7. For example, his second sermon
                was preached at Binsey (near Oxford), November 21, 1725, on Matt. 6:33. A first
                draft of the sermon which appears here as ‘Discourse VIII’ seems to have been
                written out in 1736. Later, it was the example of the Sermon on the Mount that
                encouraged Wesley to break out of his High Church prejudices in Bristol, April 1,
                1739: ‘In the evening (Mr. Whitefield being gone) I begun expounding our Lord’s
                Sermon on the Mount (one pretty remarkable precedent of <hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>field preaching<hi rend="bold">&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi>,
                though I suppose <hi rend="bold">&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>there were churches<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi> at that time also) to a little society which was
                accustomed to meet once or twice a week in Nicholas Street;’ cf. <hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>Journal<hi rend="bold">&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi> entries
                for this whole story of the unplanned outbreak of the Wesleyan Revival.</p>
            <p>The records show that, between 1739 and 1746, Wesley preached more than one hundred
                sermons from separate texts in the Sermon on the Mount. There is, however, no
                recorded instance of his having treated that Sermon as a whole anywhere else.
                Evidently, he was prepared to allow this series, once published, to stand as his
                sufficient comment on the subject.</p>
            <p>In his introduction to ‘Discourse X’, §§1-3, Wesley repeats his explanation (cf.
                ‘Discourse I’, Proem, §10) of how he had conceived the design of Matthew 5-7,
                according to its three unfolding themes: (1) ‘the sum of true religion’; (2) ‘rules
                touching that right intention which we are to preserve in all our outward actions’;
                and (3) ‘the main hindrances of this religion’. He then adds a clarifying summary:
                ‘In the fifth chapter [of St. Matthew] our great Teacher…has laid before us those
                    <hi rend="bold">&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>dispositions of the soul<hi rend="bold">&lt;hi
                    rend="italic"&gt;</hi> which constitute real Christianity…. In the sixth
                [chapter] he has shown how all our <hi rend="bold">&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>actions<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi>…may be made holy, and good, and
                acceptable to God, by a pure and holy intention…. In <hi rend="bold">&lt;pb
                    n="468"/&gt;</hi>the former part of [ch. 7] he points out the most common and
                fatal hindrances of this holiness; in the latter [part] he exhorts us, by various
                motives, to break through all [such hindrances] and secure that prize of our high
                calling [of God in Christ Jesus]’ (cf. Phil. 3:14).</p>
            <p>The thirteen discourses are divided almost equally over the three chapters of St.
                Matthew: five for chapter five, four each for six and seven. Of the first five,
                Discourse I is devoted to the first two Beatitudes; Discourse II to Beatitudes three
                through five (with a hymn to love based on 1 Cor. 13); Discourse III to the
                remainder of the Beatitudes; Discourse IV turns to Christianity as ‘a social
                religion’ in which inward holiness (our love of God) prompts outward holiness (love
                of neighbour); Discourse V is a balancing of law <hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>and<hi rend="bold">&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi> gospel.
                Discourses VI-IX are based on chapter six: VI to the problems of purity and holiness
                of intention (to the ‘works of piety and of mercy’); VII to fasting; VIII to a
                denunciation of greed and surplus accumulation; IX to the mutually exclusive
                services of God and Mammon. Discourses X-XIII turn to various hindrances to holy
                living and to their avoidance: X to ‘judging’ (contrary to love), ‘intemperate
                zeal’, ‘neglect of prayer’, ‘neglect of charity’; XI to the noxious influences of
                ill-example and ill-advice with which the world deludes us; XII to false prophets
                and unedifying preachers (and yet also our duties to attend church nonetheless and
                to avail ourselves of all means of grace); XIII is an inevitable comment on the
                parable of the houses built on sand and rock. Discourse XII was also published
                separately in the same year that it appeared in <hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>SOSO<hi rend="bold">&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi>, III (1750),
                under the title, ‘A Caution Against False Prophets. A Sermon on Matt. vii. 15-20.
                Particularly recommended to the People Called Methodists’. This went through seven
                editions during Wesley’s lifetime. For a stemma delineating the publishing history
                of that sermon (‘collected’ and ‘separate’) and a list of variant readings, see
                Appendix, ‘Wesley’s Text’, Vol. IV, see also <hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>Bibliog<hi rend="bold">&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi>, Nos. 130
                and 13o.i.</p>
            <p>Obviously there is no interest, in any of these sermons, in critical textual problems
                or in the historical context. Everywhere it is assumed that in St. Matthew’s text we
                are dealing with divine <hi rend="bold">&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>ipsissima verba<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi>—i.e., with a direct address from
                    <anchor type="commentRangeStart" n="0"/>ὁ<anchor type="commentRangeEnd" n="0"
                    /><hi rend="annotation_reference"><note place="comment" resp="#Greg_Van_Buskirk"
                        n="0"><date when="2022-09-20T13:14:00Z"/>Corrected from “τὸ”
                        (Errata).</note></hi> ὤν, ‘the self-existent, the Supreme, the God who is
                over all, blessed for ever’ (§9 below). The Sermon on the Mount, in Wesley’s view,
                is the only Gospel passage where Christ designed ‘to lay down at once the whole plan
                of his religion, to give us a full prospect of Christianity’. What matters most in
                our reading, therefore, is an awareness of Wesley’s sense of the wholeness of the
                message he is interpreting, of his conviction of the honest integration of an
                evangel profoundly ethical with an ethic that is also vividly <hi rend="bold">&lt;pb
                    n="469"/&gt;</hi>evangelical. Maybe more than anywhere else in <hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>SOSO<hi rend="bold">&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi> this
                particular bloc displays Wesley’s distinctive concern for integration and
                balance—between the faith that justifies and the faith that works by love.<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;/hi&gt;</hi></p>
            <p style="text-align: center;">Sermon 21</p>
            <p style="text-align: center;">Upon our Lord’s Sermon on the Mount</p>
            <p style="text-align: center;">Discourse the First</p>
            <p style="text-align: center;">Matthew 5:1-4</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi>And seeing the multitudes, he went up
                into a mountain, and when he was set, his disciples came unto him:</p>
            <p>And he opened his mouth and taught them, saying,</p>
            <p>Blessed are the poor in spirit; for theirs is the kingdom of heaven.</p>
            <p>Blessed are they that mourn; for they shall be comforted.<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/hi&gt;</hi></p>
            <p>1. Our Lord had now ‘gone about all Galilee’,<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot"
                    n="a"&gt;</hi>Matt. 4:23.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> beginning at the
                time ‘when John was cast into prison’,<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot"
                    n="b"&gt;</hi>Ver. 12.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> not only ‘teaching in
                their synagogues, and preaching the gospel of the kingdom’, but likewise ‘healing
                all manner of sickness, and all manner of disease among the people’.<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;note place="foot" n="1"&gt;</hi>Matt. 4:23.<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/note&gt;</hi> It was a natural consequence of this that ‘there followed
                him great multitudes from Galilee and from Decapolis, and from Jerusalem and from
                Judea, and from the region beyond Jordan.’<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot"
                    n="c"&gt;</hi>Ver. 25.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> ‘And seeing the
                multitudes’, whom no synagogue could contain, even had there been any at hand, ‘he
                went up into a mountain’,<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="d"&gt;</hi>Matt.
                5:1, etc.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> where there was room for all that ‘came
                unto him from every quarter’.<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot"
                n="2"&gt;</hi>Mark 1:45.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> ‘And when he was set’, as
                the manner of the Jews was, ‘his disciples came unto him. And he opened his mouth’
                (an expression denoting the beginning of a solemn discourse) ‘and taught them,
                    saying….’<hi rend="bold">&lt;pb n="470"/&gt;</hi></p>
            <p>2. Let us observe who it is that is here speaking, that we may ‘take heed how we
                    hear’.<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="3"&gt;</hi>Cf. Luke 8:18.<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> It is the Lord of heaven and earth, the Creator
                of all, who, as such, has a right to dispose of all his creatures; the Lord our
                Governor, whose kingdom is from everlasting, and ruleth over all; the great
                Lawgiver, who can well enforce all his laws, ‘being able to save and to destroy’;<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="4"&gt;</hi>Cf. Jas. 4:12.<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/note&gt;</hi> yea, to punish with everlasting destruction from his
                presence and from the glory of his power.<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot"
                    n="5"&gt;</hi>See. 2 Thess. 1:9.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> It is the
                eternal Wisdom of the Father, who knoweth whereof we are made,<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;note place="foot" n="6"&gt;</hi>Ps. 103:14 (BCP).<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/note&gt;</hi> and understands our inmost frame: who knows how we stand
                related to God, to one another, to every creature which God hath made; and
                consequently, how to adapt every law he prescribes to all the circumstances wherein
                he hath placed us. It is he who is ‘loving unto every man, whose mercy is over all
                his works’:<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="7"&gt;</hi>Ps. 145:9 (BCP).<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> the God of love, who, having emptied himself of
                his eternal glory, is come forth from his Father to declare his will to the children
                of men, and then goeth again to the Father; who is sent to God to ‘open the eyes of
                the blind’,<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="8"&gt;</hi>John 10:21; cf.
                    11:37.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> ‘to give light to them that sit in
                    darkness’.<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="9"&gt;</hi>Luke 1:79.<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> It is the great Prophet of the Lord, concerning
                whom God had solemnly declared long ago, ‘Whosoever will not hearken unto my words,
                which he shall speak in my name, I will require it of him;’<hi rend="bold">&lt;note
                    place="foot" n="e"&gt;</hi>Deut. 18:19.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> or, as
                the Apostle expresses it, ‘Every soul which will not hear that prophet shall be
                destroyed from among the people.’<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot"
                    n="f"&gt;</hi>Acts 3:23. [‘The Apostle’ here is St. Peter. Note the direct
                correlation <anchor type="commentRangeStart" n="1"/>between<anchor
                    type="commentRangeEnd" n="1"/><hi rend="annotation_reference"><note
                        place="comment" resp="#Greg_Van_Buskirk" n="1"><date
                            when="2022-09-20T13:14:00Z"/>Corrected from “beween” (added to
                        Errata).</note></hi> the human Jesus and the Second Person of the Trinity:
                no kenosis here, but more than a hint of Wesley’s practical monophysitism; cf. §9,
                    below.]<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi></p>
            <p>3. And what is it which he is teaching? The Son of God, who came from heaven, is here
                showing us the way to heaven,<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot"
                n="10"&gt;</hi>Cf. Wesley’s Pref. to <hi rend="bold">&lt;hi
                    rend="italic"&gt;</hi>SOSO<hi rend="bold">&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>, §5: ‘I want to know
                one thing—the way to heaven…. God himself has condescended to teach the way….’<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> to the place which he hath prepared for us,<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="11"&gt;</hi>See John 14:2, 3.<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> the glory he had before the world began.<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="12"&gt;</hi>John 17:5.<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/note&gt;</hi> He is teaching us the true way to life everlasting, the
                royal way which leads to the kingdom. And the only true way, for there is none
                besides—all other paths lead to destruction. From the character of the speaker we
                are well assured that he hath declared the full and perfect will of God.<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="13"&gt;</hi>Rom. 12:2.<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/note&gt;</hi> He hath uttered <hi rend="bold">&lt;pb n="471"/&gt;</hi>not
                one tittle too much: nothing more than he had received of the Father. Nor too
                little: he hath not shunned to declare the whole counsel of God.<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;note place="foot" n="14"&gt;</hi>Acts 20:27.<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/note&gt;</hi> Much less hath he uttered anything wrong, anything contrary
                to the will of him that sent him.<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot"
                    n="15"&gt;</hi>See John 4:34; 6:38, 40.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> All
                his words are true and right concerning all things, and shall stand fast for ever
                and ever.</p>
            <p>And we may easily remark that in explaining and confirming these faithful and true
                sayings he takes care to refute not only the mistakes of the scribes and Pharisees
                which then were, the false comments whereby the Jewish teachers of that age had
                perverted the Word of God, but all the practical mistakes that are inconsistent with
                salvation which should ever arise in the Christian Church; all the comments whereby
                the Christian teachers (so called) of any age or nation should pervert the Word of
                God, and teach unwary souls to seek death in the error of their life.<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;note place="foot" n="16"&gt;</hi>See Wisd. 1:12. Cf. also No. 6, ‘The
                Righteousness of Faith’, §2 and n.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi></p>
            <p>4. And hence we are naturally led to observe whom it is that he is here teaching. Not
                the apostles alone; if so, he had no need to have gone ‘up into the mountain’. A
                room in the house of Matthew, or any of his disciples, would have contained the
                Twelve. Nor does it in any wise appear that the ‘disciples who came unto him’ were
                the Twelve only. Οἱ μαθηταὶ αὐτοῦ, without any force put upon the expression, may be
                understood of all who desired to ‘learn of him’.<hi rend="bold">&lt;note
                    place="foot" n="17"&gt;</hi>Cf. Matt. 11:29.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi>
                But to put this out of all question, to make it undeniably plain that where it is
                said, ‘He opened his mouth and taught them,’ the word ‘them’ includes all the
                multitudes who went up with him into the mountain, we need only observe the
                concluding verses of the seventh chapter: ‘And it came to pass, when Jesus had ended
                these sayings, the multitudes, οἱ ὄχλοι, were astonished at his doctrine (or
                teaching). For he taught <hi rend="bold">&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi>them<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;/hi&gt;</hi> (the multitudes) as one having authority, and not
                as the scribes.’<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="18"&gt;</hi>Cf. Matt.
                7:28-29 (‘the multitudes were astonished’). This question of the intended auditory
                of the Sermon on the Mount had exercised most of the commentators. Henry, <hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi>Exposition<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>, <hi rend="bold">&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi>loc. cit.<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>, had insisted that the ‘discourse was directed to
                the disciples [only], though in the hearing of the multitudes’; Blackall, <hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi>Works<hi rend="bold">&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>,
                I.2, had suggested that the ‘sermon was designed only for his own disciples…’;
                later, John Heylyn makes the distinction even more sharply in <hi rend="bold">&lt;hi
                    rend="italic"&gt;</hi>Theological Lectures<hi rend="bold">&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>,
                I.74. But Hammond, <hi rend="bold">&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi>Practical
                    Catechism<hi rend="bold">&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>, p. 84, had remarked that the term
                ‘disciple’ was ‘of latitude enough to contain <hi rend="bold">&lt;hi
                    rend="italic"&gt;</hi>all<hi rend="bold">&lt;/hi&gt;</hi> Christians…; what is
                said in this sermon, all Christians are concerned in…’; and Poole, <hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi>Annotations<hi rend="bold">&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>, <hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi>loc. cit.<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>, had lumped the disciples together, ‘both those strictly s0
                called and others also’. Later, in <hi rend="bold">&lt;hi
                    rend="italic"&gt;</hi>Notes<hi rend="bold">&lt;/hi&gt;</hi> on Matt. 5:1, Wesley
                will repeat his point here: ‘His disciples: not only his twelve disciples, but <hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi>all<hi rend="bold">&lt;/hi&gt;</hi> who
                desired to learn of him.’<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;&lt;pb n="472"/&gt;</hi></p>
            <p>Nor was it only those multitudes who were with him on the mount to whom he now taught
                the way of salvation,<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="19"&gt;</hi>Acts
                    16:17.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> but all the children of men, the whole
                race of mankind, the children that were yet unborn—all the generations to come even
                to the end of the world who should ever hear the words of this life.</p>
            <p>5. And this all men allow with regard to some parts of the ensuing discourse. No man,
                for instance, denies that what is said of ‘poverty of spirit’ relates to all
                mankind. But many have supposed that other parts concerned only the apostles, or the
                first Christians, or the ministers of Christ; and were never designed for the
                generality of men,<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="20"&gt;</hi>I.e., the
                monastic tradition of ‘the counsels of perfection’ based on Matt. 5:48, which,
                incidentally, Wesley translated as a future tense (‘Therefore ye shall be perfect…’)
                rather than its usual reading as an imperative. But he accepts Blackall’s
                qualification that ‘it would be very absurd for any <hi rend="bold">&lt;hi
                    rend="italic"&gt;</hi>private<hi rend="bold">&lt;/hi&gt;</hi> discourse to be
                given so prominent a place in a public Gospel…. This sermon was spoken by our Lord
                to all his disciples…, i.e., <hi rend="bold">&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi>to all
                    Christians<hi rend="bold">&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>; …every one of the flock as well as
                every <hi rend="bold">&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi>pastor<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/hi&gt;</hi> of the flock is obliged to lead his life according to those
                rules and prescriptions which are here given by our Saviour’ (cf. <hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi>Works<hi rend="bold">&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>, I.3).<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> who consequently have nothing at all to do with
                them.</p>
            <p>But may we not justly inquire who told them this—that some parts of this discourse
                concerned only the apostles, or the Christians of the apostolic age, or the
                ministers of Christ? Bare assertions are not a sufficient proof to establish a point
                of so great importance. Has then our Lord himself taught us that some parts of his
                discourse do not concern all mankind? Without doubt had it been so he would have
                told us; he could not have omitted so necessary an information. But has he told us
                so? Where? In the discourse itself? No: here is not the least intimation of it. Has
                he said so elsewhere? In any other of his discourses? Not one word so much as
                glancing this way can we find in anything he ever spoke, either to the multitudes or
                to his disciples. Has any of the apostles, or other inspired writers, left such an
                instruction upon record? No such thing. No assertion of this kind is to be found in
                all the oracles of God. Who then are the men who are so much wiser than God? Wise so
                far above that [which] is written?<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot"
                    n="21"&gt;</hi>1 Cor. 4:6.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi></p>
            <p>6. Perhaps they will say that the reason of the thing requires such a restriction to
                be made. If it does, it must be on one of these <hi rend="bold">&lt;pb
                    n="473"/&gt;</hi>two accounts: because without such a restriction the discourse
                would either be apparently absurd, or would contradict some other Scripture. But
                this is not the case. It will plainly appear, when we come to examine the several
                particulars, that there is no absurdity at all in applying all which our Lord hath
                here delivered to all mankind. Neither will it infer any contradiction to anything
                else he has delivered, nor to any other Scripture whatever. Nay, it will farther
                appear that either all the parts of this discourse are to be applied to men in
                general or no part; seeing they are all connected together, all joined as the stones
                in an arch, of which you cannot take one away without destroying the whole
                    fabric.<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="22"&gt;</hi>A crucial example of
                Wesley’s twin principles of hermeneutics. The first is that Scripture is Scripture’s
                own best interpreter; thus, ‘the analogy of faith’ (i.e., one’s sense of the whole)
                should govern one’s exegesis of each part; cf. No. 5, ‘Justification by Faith’, §2
                and n.). The second is that one begins, always, with a literal translation and holds
                to it unless it should lead into a palpable absurdity; in which case, analogy and
                even allegory become allowable options. Cf. Nos. 74, ‘Of the Church’, §12; 84, <hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi>The Important Question<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>, I.1; 86, <hi rend="bold">&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi>A Call
                to Backsliders<hi rend="bold">&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>, I.2(4); 87, ‘The Danger of Riches’,
                §2; 139, ‘On the Sabbath’, II.1;and 144, ‘The Love of God’, II.5. Cf. also Wesley’s
                letter to Lady Cox, Mar. 7, 1738; to Samuel Furly, May 10, 1755; and to Dr.
                Lavington, Dec. 1751. For exceptions cf. Nos. 48, ‘Self-denial’, I.7; 99, <hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi>The Reward of Righteousness<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>, §4; and 110, <hi rend="bold">&lt;hi
                    rend="italic"&gt;</hi>Free Grace<hi rend="bold">&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>, §20.<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi></p>
            <p>7. We may, lastly, observe how our Lord teaches here. And surely, as at all times, so
                particularly at this, he speaks ‘as never man spake’.<hi rend="bold">&lt;note
                    place="foot" n="23"&gt;</hi>Cf. John 7:46.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> Not
                as the holy men of old; although they also spoke ‘as they were moved by the Holy
                    Ghost’.<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="24"&gt;</hi>2 Pet. 1:21.<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> Not as Peter, or James, or John, or Paul. They
                were indeed wise masterbuilders in his church.<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot"
                    n="25"&gt;</hi>See 1 Cor. 3:10.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> But still in
                this, in the degrees of heavenly wisdom, the servant is not as his Lord.<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="26"&gt;</hi>See John 15:20.<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/note&gt;</hi> No, nor even as himself at any other time, or on any other
                occasion. It does not appear that it was ever his design, at any other time or
                place, to lay down at once the whole plan of his religion, to give us a full
                prospect of Christianity, to describe at large the nature of that holiness without
                which no man shall see the Lord.<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot"
                    n="27"&gt;</hi>Heb. 12:14.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> Particular branches
                of this he has indeed described on a thousand different occasions. But never besides
                here did he give, of set purpose, a general view of the whole. Nay, we have nothing
                else of this land in all the Bible; unless one should except that short sketch of
                holiness delivered by God in those ten words or commandments to Moses on Mount
                Sinai. But even here how wide a difference is there between one and the <hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;pb n="474"/&gt;</hi>other! ‘Even that which was made glorious
                had no glory in this respect, by reason of the glory that excelleth.’<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;note place="foot" n="g"&gt;</hi>2 Cor. 3:10.<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/note&gt;</hi></p>
            <p>8. Above all, with what amazing love does the Son of God here reveal his Father’s
                will to man! He does not bring us again ‘to the mount that […] burned with fire, nor
                unto blackness, and darkness, and tempest’.<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot"
                    n="28"&gt;</hi>Heb. 12:18.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> He does not speak
                as when he ‘thundered out of heaven, when the highest gave his thunder, hailstones,
                and coals of fire’.<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="29"&gt;</hi>Ps. 18:14
                    (BCP).<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> He now addresses us with his still,
                small voice.<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="30"&gt;</hi>1 Kgs. 19:12.<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> ‘Blessed (or happy) are the poor in spirit.’
                Happy are the mourners, the meek; those that hunger after righteousness; the
                merciful, the pure in heart: happy in the end and in the way; happy in this life and
                in life everlasting! As if he had said, ‘Who is he that lusteth to live, and would
                fain see good days? Behold, I show you the thing which your soul longeth for; see
                the way you have so long sought in vain! The way of pleasantness; the path to calm,
                joyous peace,<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="31"&gt;</hi>See Prov. 3:17.<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> to heaven below and heaven above!’</p>
            <p>9. At the same time with what authority does he teach! Well might they say, ‘not as
                the scribes’.<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="32"&gt;</hi>Matt. 7:29; Mark
                    1:22.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> Observe the manner (but it cannot be
                expressed in words), the air with which he speaks! Not as Moses, the servant of God;
                not as Abraham, his friend; not as any of the prophets; nor as any of the sons of
                men. It is something more than human; more than can agree to any created being. It
                speaks the Creator of all—a God, a God appears! Yea, ὁ ὤν, the being of beings,
                Jehovah, the self-existent, the supreme, the God who is over all, blessed for
                    ever!<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="33"&gt;</hi>See Rom. 9:5.<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi></p>
            <p>10. This divine discourse, delivered in the most excellent method, every subsequent
                part illustrating those that precede, is commonly, and not improperly, divided into
                three principal branches: the first contained in the fifth, the second in the sixth,
                and the third in the seventh chapter. In the first the sum of all true religion is
                laid down in eight particulars, which are explained and guarded against the false
                glosses of man in the following parts of the fifth chapter. In the second are rules
                for that right intention which we are to preserve in all our outward actions,
                unmixed with <hi rend="bold">&lt;pb n="475"/&gt;</hi>worldly desires, or anxious
                cares for even the necessaries of life. In the third are cautions against the main
                hindrances of religion, closed with an application of the whole.<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;note place="foot" n="34"&gt;</hi>See below, Discourse X, §§1-3, for a
                recapitulation of this same outline.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi></p>
            <p>I.1. Our Lord, first, lays down the sum of all true religion in eight particulars,
                which he explains and guards against the false glosses of men, to the end of the
                fifth chapter.</p>
            <p>Some have supposed that he designed in these to point out the several stages of the
                Christian course, the steps which a Christian successively takes in his journey to
                the promised land; others, that all the particulars here set down belong at all
                times to every Christian. And why may we not allow both the one and the other?<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="35"&gt;</hi>Cf. Wesley’s <hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi>Dialogues between an Antinomian and his Friend<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>, 1745 (<hi rend="bold">&lt;hi
                    rend="italic"&gt;</hi>Bibliog<hi rend="bold">&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>, Nos. 102, 106,
                and 226; see Vol. 13 of this edn.).<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> What
                inconsistency is there between them? It is undoubtedly true that both ‘poverty of
                    spirit’<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="36"&gt;</hi>Cf. Matt. 5:3.<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> and every other temper which is here mentioned
                are at all times found in a greater or less degree in every real Christian. And it
                is equally true that real Christianity always begins in poverty of spirit, and goes
                on in the order here set down till the ‘man of God’ is made ‘perfect’.<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="37"&gt;</hi>2 Tim. 3:17.<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/note&gt;</hi> We begin at the lowest of these gifts of God; yet so as not
                to relinquish this when we are called of God to come up higher:<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;note place="foot" n="38"&gt;</hi>Cf. Luke 14:10.<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/note&gt;</hi> but ‘whereunto we have already attained’<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;note place="foot" n="39"&gt;</hi>Phil. 3:16.<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/note&gt;</hi> we ‘hold fast’,<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot"
                    n="40"&gt;</hi>Heb. 3:6, etc.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> while we ‘press
                    on’<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="41"&gt;</hi>Cf. Phil. 3:14.<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> to what is yet before, to the highest blessings
                of God in Christ Jesus.</p>
            <p>2. The foundation of all is ‘poverty of spirit’.<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot"
                    n="42"&gt;</hi>A positive transvaluation of William Law; cf. <hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi>Serious Call<hi rend="bold">&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>, <hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi>Works<hi rend="bold">&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>,
                    IV.170-80.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> Here therefore our Lord begins:
                ‘Blessed (saith he) are the poor in spirit, for theirs is the kingdom of
                heaven.’</p>
            <p>It may not improbably be supposed that our Lord, looking on those who were round
                about him, and observing that not many rich were there, but rather the poor of the
                world, took occasion from thence to make a transition from temporal to spiritual
                things. ‘Blessed’, saith he (or <hi rend="bold">&lt;hi
                    rend="italic"&gt;</hi>happy<hi rend="bold">&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>: so the word should
                be rendered both in this and the following verses) ‘are the poor in spirit.’ He does
                not say they that are poor as to <hi rend="bold">&lt;hi
                rend="italic"&gt;</hi>outward circumstances<hi rend="bold">&lt;/hi&gt;</hi> (it
                being not impossible that some of these maybe as far from happiness as a monarch
                upon his throne) but ‘the poor in <hi rend="bold">&lt;pb n="476"/&gt;</hi>spirit’;
                they who, whatever their outward circumstances are, have that disposition of heart
                which is the first step to all real, substantial happiness, either in this world or
                that which is to come.<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="43"&gt;</hi>See No.
                17, ‘The Circumcision of the Heart’, I.2.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi></p>
            <p>3. Some have judged that by the ‘poor in spirit’ here are meant those who love
                poverty; those who are free from covetousness, from the love of money; who fear
                rather than desire riches. Perhaps they have been induced so to judge by wholly
                confining their thought to the very term, or by considering that weighty observation
                of St. Paul, that ‘the love of money is the root of all evil.’<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;note place="foot" n="44"&gt;</hi>1 Tim. 6:10.<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/note&gt;</hi> And hence many have wholly divested themselves, not only of
                riches, but of all worldly goods. Hence also the vows of voluntary poverty seem to
                have arisen in the Romish Church; it being supposed that so eminent a degree of this
                fundamental grace must be a large step toward the kingdom of heaven.<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;note place="foot" n="45"&gt;</hi>Cf. Blackall, <hi rend="bold">&lt;hi
                    rend="italic"&gt;</hi>Works<hi rend="bold">&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>, I.7: ‘…the
                Papists…who do so much magnify voluntary poverty…. And in this sense Maldonate, and
                divers others of the popish commentators, do expound this passage…. But this
                interpretation is perfectly groundless and also manifestly false.’ The reference
                here is to Johannes Maldonatus (1534-83), Spanish exegete and theologian, whose
                chief work was <hi rend="bold">&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi>Commentarii in Quattuor
                    Evangelistas<hi rend="bold">&lt;/hi&gt;</hi> (2 vols., 1596-97, and many later
                edns., none in English until 1888). It is worth noting that Wesley has already begun
                to inveigh against surplus accumulation and ‘the danger of riches’; cf. Discourse
                VIII, below, reflecting as it does the counsels of Richard Lucas and William Law
                against greed and self-indulgence—and about voluntary poverty as the Christian
                counterweight to the dangers of riches. This will become a lifelong theme of
                Wesley’s, and his emphasis on it will increase with the passing years and growing
                affluence amongst the Methodists.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi></p>
            <p>But these do not seem to have observed, first, that the expression of St. Paul must
                be understood with some restriction; otherwise it is not true. For the love of money
                is not ‘the root’—the sole root—‘of all evil’. There are a thousand other roots of
                evil in the world, as sad experience daily shows. His meaning can only be, it is the
                root of very many evils; perhaps of more than any single vice besides. Secondly,
                that this sense of the expression ‘poor in spirit’ will by no means suit our Lord’s
                present design, which is to lay a general foundation whereon the whole fabric of
                Christianity may be built; a design which would be in no wise answered by guarding
                against one particular vice: so that even if this were supposed to be one part of
                his meaning, it could not possibly be the whole. Thirdly, that it cannot be supposed
                to be any part of his meaning unless we charge him with <hi rend="bold">&lt;pb
                    n="477"/&gt;</hi>manifest tautology: seeing if ‘poverty of spirit’ were only
                freedom from covetousness, from the love of money, or the desire of riches, it would
                coincide with what he afterwards mentions; it would be only a branch of ‘purity of
                    heart’.<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="46"&gt;</hi>Cf. Matt. 5:8.<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi></p>
            <p>4. Who then are the ‘poor in spirit’? Without question, the humble;<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;note place="foot" n="47"&gt;</hi>This equivalence of ‘the poor in spirit’
                and ‘the humble’ is also Blackall’s line. Wesley compresses his exposition into six
                duodecimo pages; the bishop’s runs to twenty-two folio pages. See also Hammond, <hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi>Practical Catechism<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>, p. 85.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> they who know
                themselves, who are convinced of sin; those to whom God hath given that first
                repentance which is previous to faith in Christ.<hi rend="bold">&lt;note
                    place="foot" n="48"&gt;</hi>The notion of self-knowledge as that ‘first
                repentance which is <hi rend="bold">&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi>previous<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;/hi&gt;</hi> to faith in Christ’ is crucial in Wesley’s doctrine
                of justification. It is, regularly, a prevenient work of the Holy Spirit, but it
                involves human ‘re-action’, <hi rend="bold">&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi>viz.<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>, recognition of one’s alienation from God and
                acknowledgement of the truth of one’s sinful affections. Cf. John Norris, <hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi>Practical Discourses<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>, I.4: ‘Poverty of spirit…is not a state of <hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi>life<hi rend="bold">&lt;/hi&gt;</hi> but a state
                of <hi rend="bold">&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi>mind<hi rend="bold"
                >&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>, and we may take it either in opposition to covetousness or…to
                pride and highmindedness.’ On p. 16 the phrase is more clearly defined as
                ‘humility’, although for Norris ‘poverty of spirit’ is more nearly self-abasement
                than self-knowledge as in Wesley. Norris, p. 28: ‘Humility is the proper foundation
                of grace and the theatre of all divine operations.’ See Nos. 7, ‘The Way to the
                Kingdom’, II.1 and n.; and 17, ‘The Circumcision of the Heart’, I.2 and n.; see also
                Wesley’s extract from Edward Young (the elder) in the <hi rend="bold">&lt;hi
                    rend="italic"&gt;</hi>Christian Lib.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>,
                XLVI.144-45. This notion of humility as a ‘right judgment of ourselves’ (i.e.,
                authentic self-knowledge) is one of William Law’s salient themes. Wesley goes a step
                further and correlates it with ‘true repentance’.<hi rend="bold"
                >&lt;/note&gt;</hi></p>
            <p>One of these can no longer say, ‘I am rich, and increased in goods, and have need of
                nothing:’ as now knowing that he is ‘wretched, and poor, and miserable, and blind,
                and naked’.<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="49"&gt;</hi>Rev. 3:17.<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> He is convinced that he is spiritually poor
                indeed; having no spiritual good abiding in him. ‘In me (saith he) dwelleth no good
                    thing;’<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="50"&gt;</hi>Rom. 7:18.<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> but whatsoever is evil and abominable. He has a
                deep sense of the loathsome leprosy of sin, which he brought with him from his
                mother’s womb, which overspreads his whole soul, and totally corrupts every power
                and faculty thereof. He sees more and more of the evil tempers which spring from
                that evil root: the pride and haughtiness of spirit,<hi rend="bold">&lt;note
                    place="foot" n="51"&gt;</hi>Cf. No. 14, <hi rend="bold">&lt;hi
                    rend="italic"&gt;</hi>The Repentance of Believers<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>, I.3 and n.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> the constant
                bias to think of himself more highly than he ought to think;<hi rend="bold">&lt;note
                    place="foot" n="52"&gt;</hi>Rom. 12:3.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> the
                vanity, the thirst after the esteem or honour that cometh from men;<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;note place="foot" n="53"&gt;</hi>Cf. No. 14, <hi rend="bold">&lt;hi
                    rend="italic"&gt;</hi>The Repentance of Believers<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>, I.7 and n.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> the hatred or
                envy, the jealousy or revenge, the anger, malice, or bitterness; the inbred <hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;pb n="478"/&gt;</hi>enmity both against God and man<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="54"&gt;</hi>See Rom. 8:7.<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/note&gt;</hi> which appears in ten thousand shapes; the love of the world,
                the self-will, the foolish and hurtful desires<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot"
                    n="55"&gt;</hi>1 Tim. 6:9.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> which cleave to his
                inmost soul.<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="56"&gt;</hi>Note this impromptu
                catalogue of the classical ‘deadly sins’.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> He is
                conscious how deeply he has offended by his tongue; if not by profane, immodest,
                untrue, or unkind words, yet by discourse which was not ‘good to the use of
                edifying’, not ‘meet to minister grace to the hearers’;<hi rend="bold">&lt;note
                    place="foot" n="57"&gt;</hi>Cf. Eph. 4:29.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi>
                which consequently was all <hi rend="bold">&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi>corrupt<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;/hi&gt;</hi> in God’s account, and grievous to his Holy Spirit.
                His evil works are now likewise ever in his sight; if he tell them ‘they are more
                than he is able to express’.<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="58"&gt;</hi>Cf.
                Ps. 40:7 (BCP).<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> He may as well think to number the
                ‘drops of rain, the sands of the sea, or the days of eternity’.<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;note place="foot" n="59"&gt;</hi>Cf. Ecclus. 1:2.<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/note&gt;</hi></p>
            <p>5. His guilt is now also before his face: he knows the punishment he has deserved,
                were it only on account of his ‘carnal mind’,<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot"
                    n="60"&gt;</hi>Rom. 8:7.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> the entire, universal
                corruption of his nature; how much more on account of all his evil desires and
                thoughts, of all his sinful words and actions! He cannot doubt for a moment but the
                least of these deserves the damnation of hell, ‘the worm that dieth not’, and ‘the
                fire that never shall be quenched’.<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot"
                    n="61"&gt;</hi>Cf. Mark 9:43, 45.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> Above all,
                the guilt of ‘not believing on the name of the only-begotten Son of God’<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="62"&gt;</hi>Cf. John 3:18.<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/note&gt;</hi> lies heavy upon him ‘How (saith he) shall I escape, who
                neglect so great salvation!’<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="63"&gt;</hi>Cf.
                Heb. 2:3.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> ‘He that believeth not is condemned
                already’, and ‘the wrath of God abideth on him.’<hi rend="bold">&lt;note
                    place="foot" n="64"&gt;</hi>John 3:18, 36.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi></p>
            <p>6. But what shall he give in exchange for his soul,<hi rend="bold">&lt;note
                    place="foot" n="65"&gt;</hi>See Matt. 16:26.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi>
                which is forfeit to the just vengeance of God? ‘Wherewithal shall he come before the
                    Lord?’<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="66"&gt;</hi>Cf. Mic. 6:6.<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> How shall he pay him that he oweth? Were he from
                this moment to perform the most perfect obedience to every command of God, this
                would make no amends for a single sin, for any one act of past disobedience: seeing
                he owes God all the service he is able to perform from this moment to all eternity,
                could he pay this it would make no manner of amends for what he ought to have done
                before. He sees himself therefore utterly helpless with regard to atoning for his
                past sins; utterly unable to make any amends to God, to pay any ransom for his own
                soul.</p>
            <p>But if God would forgive him all that is past,<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot"
                    n="67"&gt;</hi>Cf. BCP, Communion, General Confession.<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/note&gt;</hi> on this one condition, that he should sin no more, that for
                the time to come he <hi rend="bold">&lt;pb n="479"/&gt;</hi>should entirely and
                constantly obey all his commands: he well knows that this would profit him nothing,
                being a condition he could never perform. He knows and feels that he is not able to
                obey even the outward commands of God; seeing these cannot be obeyed while his heart
                remains in its natural sinfulness and corruption—inasmuch as an evil tree cannot
                bring forth good fruit.<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="68"&gt;</hi>See
                Matt. 7:18; Luke 6:43.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> But he cannot cleanse a
                sinful heart: with men this is impossible.<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot"
                    n="69"&gt;</hi>Matt. 19:26.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> So that he is
                utterly at a loss even how to begin walking in the path of God’s commandments.<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="70"&gt;</hi>See Ps. 119:35.<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/note&gt;</hi> He knows not how to get one step forward in the way.
                Encompassed with sin and sorrow and fear, and finding no way to escape, he can only
                cry out, ‘Lord, save, or I perish!’<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot"
                    n="71"&gt;</hi>Cf. Matt. 8:25.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi></p>
            <p>7. ‘Poverty of spirit’<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="72"&gt;</hi>Cf. above,
                I.4 and n.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi>, then, as it implies the first step we
                take in running the race which is set before us,<hi rend="bold">&lt;note
                    place="foot" n="73"&gt;</hi>See Heb. 12:1.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> is
                a just sense of our inward and outward sins, and of our guilt and helplessness. This
                some have monstrously styled the ‘virtue of humility’;<hi rend="bold">&lt;note
                    place="foot" n="74"&gt;</hi>This phrase had been used almost casually by Law in
                    <hi rend="bold">&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi>Christian Perfection<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/hi&gt;</hi> (<hi rend="bold">&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi>Works<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>, III.67), and before him by John Selden, <hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi>Table Talk<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/hi&gt;</hi> (1689), p. 54: ‘The master thinks the virtue of humility is
                good doctrine for his servant, the laity for the clergy and the clergy for the
                laity;’ cf. Robert Burton in <hi rend="bold">&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi>The
                Anatomy of Melancholy<hi rend="bold">&lt;/hi&gt;</hi> (1st edn., 1621; 8th edn.,
                1676), I.ii.3-14. See also St. Francis de Sales, <hi rend="bold">&lt;hi
                    rend="italic"&gt;</hi>An Introduction to the Devout Life<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/hi&gt;</hi> (1608), Pt. III, iv. For other references to humility in the
                sermons, cf. below, I.9; and Nos. 17, ‘The Circumcision of the Heart’, I.2; 65, ‘The
                Duty of Reproving our Neighbour’, IIΙ.3; 92, ‘On Zeal’, II.1; 108, ‘On Riches’, I.6;
                120, ‘The Unity of the Divine Being’, §22.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> thus
                teaching us to be proud of knowing we deserve damnation. But our Lord’s expression
                is quite of another kind; conveying no idea to the hearer but that of mere want, of
                naked sin, of helpless guilt and misery.</p>
            <p>8. The great Apostle, where he endeavours to bring sinners to God, speaks in a manner
                just answerable to this. ‘The wrath of God (saith he) is revealed from heaven
                against all ungodliness and unrighteousness of men’<hi rend="bold">&lt;note
                    place="foot" n="h"&gt;</hi>Rom. 1:18.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi>—a charge
                which he immediately fixes on the heathen world, and thereby proves they were under
                the wrath of God. He next shows that the Jews were no better than they, and were
                therefore under the same condemnation: and all this not in order to their attaining
                ‘the noble virtue of humility’, <hi rend="bold">&lt;pb n="480"/&gt;</hi>‘but that
                every mouth might be stopped, and all the world become guilty before God’.<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="75"&gt;</hi>Cf. Rom. 3:19.<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/note&gt;</hi></p>
            <p>He proceeds to show that they were helpless as well as guilty; which is the plain
                purport of all those expressions—‘Therefore by the deeds of the law there shall no
                flesh be justified’<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="76"&gt;</hi>Rom.
                    3:20.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi>—‘But now the righteousness of God, which
                is by faith of Jesus Christ, without the law is manifested’<hi rend="bold">&lt;note
                    place="foot" n="77"&gt;</hi>Rom. 3:21, 22.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi>—‘We
                conclude that a man is justified by faith, without the deeds of the law’<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="78"&gt;</hi>Rom. 3:28.<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/note&gt;</hi>—expressions all tending to the same point, even to ‘hide
                pride from man’;<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="79"&gt;</hi>Job 33:17. Cf.
                No. 129, ‘Heavenly Treasure in Earthen Vessels’, II.5.<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/note&gt;</hi> to humble him to the dust, without teaching him to reflect
                upon his humility as a virtue; to inspire him with that full piercing conviction of
                his utter sinfulness, guilt, and helplessness, which casts the sinner, stripped of
                all, lost, and undone, on his strong helper, ‘Jesus Christ the righteous’.<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="80"&gt;</hi>1 John 2:1.<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/note&gt;</hi></p>
            <p>9. One cannot but observe here that Christianity begins just where heathen morality
                ends: ‘poverty of spirit’, ‘conviction of sin’,<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot"
                    n="81"&gt;</hi>Cf. John 8:46.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> the ‘renouncing
                    ourselves’,<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="82"&gt;</hi>Cf. 2 Cor. 4:2;
                see also Mark 8:34.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> the ‘not having our own
                    righteousness’,<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="83"&gt;</hi>Cf. Phil.
                    3:9.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> the very first point in the religion of
                Jesus Christ, leaving all pagan religion behind. This was ever hid from the wise men
                of this world;<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="84"&gt;</hi>See Matt.
                    11:25.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> insomuch that the whole Roman language,
                even with all the improvements of the Augustan age, does not afford so much as a
                name for <hi rend="bold">&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi>humility<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/hi&gt;</hi> (the word from whence we borrow this, as is well known,
                bearing in Latin a quite different meaning): no, nor was one found in all the
                copious language of Greece till it was <hi rend="bold">&lt;hi
                    rend="italic"&gt;</hi>made<hi rend="bold">&lt;/hi&gt;</hi> by the great
                    Apostle.<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="85"&gt;</hi>In classical Latin
                the meaning of <hi rend="bold">&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi>humilitas<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/hi&gt;</hi> ranges between ‘lowness’ (of stature or status) to
                ‘insignificance’ to ‘baseness’. By the time of Lactantius (<hi rend="bold">&lt;hi
                    rend="italic"&gt;</hi>c.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/hi&gt;</hi> 240-<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi>c.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/hi&gt;</hi> 320) and
                Sulpicius Severus (<hi rend="bold">&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi>c.<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/hi&gt;</hi> 360-<hi rend="bold">&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi>c.<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;/hi&gt;</hi> 420), it had acquired a specific Christian
                connotation. In the light of the lexical evolution of ταπεινοφροσύνη and <hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi>humilitas<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/hi&gt;</hi> in patristic Christian literature Wesley has an important
                point here for the history of Christian ethics. Cf. above, I.7.<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/note&gt;</hi></p>
            <p>10. O that we may feel what they were not able to express! Sinner, awake! Know
                thyself! Know and feel that thou ‘wert shapen in wickedness, and that in sin did thy
                mother conceive thee’,<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="86"&gt;</hi>Cf. Ps.
                51:5 (BCP).<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> and that thou thyself hast been
                heaping sin upon sin ever since thou couldst discern good from evil. Sink under the
                mighty <hi rend="bold">&lt;pb n="481"/&gt;</hi>hand of God, as guilty of death
                eternal; and cast off, renounce, abhor all imagination of ever being able to help
                thyself! Be it all thy hope to be washed in his blood and renewed by his almighty
                Spirit ‘who himself bare all our sins in his own body on the tree’.<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;note place="foot" n="87"&gt;</hi>1 Pet. 2:24.<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/note&gt;</hi> So shalt thou witness, ‘Happy are the poor in spirit; for
                theirs is the kingdom of heaven.’</p>
            <p>11. This is that kingdom of heaven or of God which is ‘within’ us,<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;note place="foot" n="88"&gt;</hi>Luke 17:21.<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/note&gt;</hi> even ‘righteousness, and peace, and joy in the Holy
                    Ghost’.<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="89"&gt;</hi>Rom. 14:17.<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> And what is righteousness but the life of God in
                the soul, the mind which was in Christ Jesus,<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot"
                    n="90"&gt;</hi>See Phil. 2:5.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> the image of God
                stamped upon the heart, now renewed after the likeness of him that created it? What
                is it but the love of God because he first loved us,<hi rend="bold">&lt;note
                    place="foot" n="91"&gt;</hi>1 John 4:19.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> and
                the love of all mankind for his sake?</p>
            <p>And what is this peace, the peace of God, but that calm serenity of soul, that sweet
                repose in the blood of Jesus, which leaves no doubt of our acceptance in him? Which
                excludes all fear but the loving, filial fear of offending our Father which is in
                heaven?</p>
            <p>This inward kingdom implies also ‘joy in the Holy Ghost’,<hi rend="bold">&lt;note
                    place="foot" n="92"&gt;</hi>Rom. 14:17.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> who
                seals upon our hearts ‘the redemption which is in Jesus’, the righteousness of
                Christ, imputed to us<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="93"&gt;</hi>Here, and
                again in Discourse IX, §21, Wesley uses this commonplace Puritan phrase about the
                imputation of Christ’s righteousness to the pardoned sinner in justification with
                studied indifference to its controversial overtones—with no indication that, later,
                he will reject it as misleading (see No. 20, <hi rend="bold">&lt;hi
                    rend="italic"&gt;</hi>The Lord Our Righteousness<hi rend="bold"
                >&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>, II.19-20). Still later, when the Calvinists had made it one of
                their shibboleths, Wesley will renounce the phrase itself as ‘ambiguous,
                unscriptural, …so liable to be misinterpreted’; cf. <hi rend="bold">&lt;hi
                    rend="italic"&gt;</hi>Some Remarks on Mr. Hill’s Review…<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>, 1772 (Vol. 13 of this edn.). In the following year Wesley
                repeated the point against Hill’s <hi rend="bold">&lt;hi
                rend="italic"&gt;</hi>Farrago Double-Distilled<hi rend="bold">&lt;/hi&gt;</hi> (<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi>ibid.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>),
                §25: ‘The doctrine which I believe has done immense hurt is that of the imputed
                righteousness of Christ in the antinomian [Hill’s] sense. The doctrine which I have
                constantly held and preached is that faith is imputed [to us] for righteousness.’<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> for ‘the remission of the sins that are past’:<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="94"&gt;</hi>Rom. 3:24-25.<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/note&gt;</hi> who giveth us now ‘the earnest of our inheritance’<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="95"&gt;</hi>Eph. 1:14.<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/note&gt;</hi> of the crown which the Lord, the righteous Judge, will give
                at that day.<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="96"&gt;</hi>2 Tim. 4:8.<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> And well may this be termed ‘the kingdom of
                heaven’; seeing it is heaven already opened in the soul, the first springing up of
                those rivers of pleasure<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="97"&gt;</hi>See Ps.
                    36:8.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> which flow at God’s right hand for
                    evermore.<hi rend="bold">&lt;pb n="482"/&gt;</hi></p>
            <p>12. ‘Theirs is the kingdom of heaven.’ Whosoever thou art to whom God hath given to
                be ‘poor in spirit’, to feel thyself lost, thou hast a right thereto, through the
                gracious promise of him who cannot lie.<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot"
                    n="98"&gt;</hi>See Titus 1:2.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> It is purchased
                for thee by the blood of the Lamb.<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot"
                    n="99"&gt;</hi>Rev. 7:14; 12:11.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> It is very
                nigh: thou art on the brink of heaven. Another step, and thou enterest into the
                kingdom of righteousness, and peace, and joy.<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot"
                    n="100"&gt;</hi>Rom. 14:17.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> Art thou all sin?
                ‘Behold the Lamb of God who taketh away the sin of the world.’<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;note place="foot" n="101"&gt;</hi>John 1:29.<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/note&gt;</hi> All unholy? See thy ‘advocate with the Father, Jesus Christ
                the righteous’.<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="102"&gt;</hi>1 John 2:1.<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> Art thou unable to atone for the least of thy
                sins? ‘He is the propitiation for’ all thy ‘sins.’<hi rend="bold">&lt;note
                    place="foot" n="103"&gt;</hi>Cf. 1 John 2:2.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi>
                Now believe on the Lord Jesus Christ, and all thy sins are blotted out. Art thou
                totally unclean in soul and in body? Here is the ‘fountain for sin and
                    uncleanness’.<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="104"&gt;</hi>Zech.
                    13:1.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> ‘Arise, […] and wash away thy sins:’<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="105"&gt;</hi>Acts 22:16.<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/note&gt;</hi> stagger no more at the promise through unbelief. Give glory
                to God. Dare to believe! Now cry out, from the ground of thy heart:<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;lg&gt;&lt;l&gt;</hi>Yes, I yield, I yield at last,<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/l&gt;&lt;l&gt;</hi>Listen to thy speaking blood;<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/l&gt;&lt;l&gt;</hi>Me with all my sins I cast<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/l&gt;&lt;l&gt;</hi>On my atoning God!<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot"
                    n="106"&gt;</hi>‘Waiting for Christ the Prophet’ (the second hymn with this
                title), st. 5, last 4 ll. In <hi rend="bold">&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi>Hymns and
                Sacred Poems<hi rend="bold">&lt;/hi&gt;</hi> (1742), p. 211 (<hi rend="bold">&lt;hi
                    rend="italic"&gt;</hi>Poet. Wks.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>, II.265).<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;&lt;/l&gt;&lt;/lg&gt;</hi></p>
            <p>13. Then thou learnest of him to be ‘lowly of heart’.<hi rend="bold">&lt;note
                    place="foot" n="107"&gt;</hi>Cf. Matt. 11:29.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi>
                And this is the true, genuine, Christian humility, which flows from a sense of the
                love of God, reconciled to us in Christ Jesus.<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot"
                    n="108"&gt;</hi>See 2 Cor. 5:18.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> ‘Poverty of
                spirit’, in this meaning of the word, begins where a sense of guilt and of the wrath
                of God ends; and is a continual sense of our total dependence on him for every good
                thought or word or work; of our utter inability to all good unless he ‘water us
                every moment’:<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="109"&gt;</hi>Cf. Isa.
                    27:3.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> and an abhorrence of the praise of men,
                knowing that all praise is due unto God only. With this is joined a loving shame, a
                tender humiliation before God, even for the sins which we know he hath forgiven us,
                and for the sin which still remaineth in our hearts, although we know it is not
                imputed to our condemnation. Nevertheless the conviction we feel of inbred sin<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="110"&gt;</hi>Cf. 2 Pet. 2:14; See also Rom.
                    7:14-23.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> is deeper and deeper every day. The
                more we grow in grace the more do we see <hi rend="bold">&lt;pb n="483"/&gt;</hi>of
                the desperate wickedness of our heart. The more we advance in the knowledge and love
                of God, through our Lord Jesus Christ (as great a mystery as this may appear to
                those who know not the power of God unto salvation),<hi rend="bold">&lt;note
                    place="foot" n="111"&gt;</hi>Cf. the intro, to No. 44, <hi rend="bold">&lt;hi
                    rend="italic"&gt;</hi>Original Sin<hi rend="bold">&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>.<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> the more do we discern of our alienation from
                God, of the enmity that is in our carnal mind,<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot"
                    n="112"&gt;</hi>See Rom. 8:7.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> and the
                necessity of our being entirely renewed in righteousness and true holiness.<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="113"&gt;</hi>Eph. 4:24. Cf. No. 45, ‘The
                New Birth’, I.1.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi></p>
            <p>II.1. It is true, he has scarce any conception of this who now begins to know the
                inward kingdom of heaven. ‘In his prosperity he saith, I shall never be moved; Thou,
                Lord, hast made my hill so strong.’<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot"
                    n="114"&gt;</hi>Cf. Ps. 30:6 (BCP).<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> Sin is so
                utterly bruised beneath his feet that he can scarce believe it remaineth in him.
                Even temptation is silenced and speaks not again; it cannot approach, but stands
                afar off. He is borne aloft on the chariots of joy and love; he soars ‘as upon the
                wings of an eagle’.<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="115"&gt;</hi>Cf. Isa.
                    40:31.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> But our Lord well knew that this
                triumphant state does not often continue long. He therefore presently subjoins,
                ‘Blessed are they that mourn; for they shall be comforted.’<hi rend="bold">&lt;note
                    place="foot" n="116"&gt;</hi>Matt. 5:4.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi></p>
            <p>2. Not that we can imagine this promise belongs to those who mourn only on some
                worldly account; who are in sorrow and heaviness merely on account of some worldly
                trouble or disappointment, such as the loss of their reputation, or friends, or the
                impairing of their fortune. As little title to it have they who are afflicting
                themselves, through fear of some temporal evil; or who pine away with anxious care,
                or that desire of earthly things which ‘maketh the heart sick’.<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;note place="foot" n="117"&gt;</hi>Prov. 13:12.<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/note&gt;</hi> Let us not think these ‘shall receive any thing from the
                    Lord’:<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="118"&gt;</hi>Jas. 1:7.<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> he is not in all their thoughts.<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;note place="foot" n="119"&gt;</hi>See Ps. 10:4.<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/note&gt;</hi> Therefore it is that they thus ‘walk in a vain shadow, and
                disquiet themselves in vain’.<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot"
                n="120"&gt;</hi>120 Cf. Ps. 39:7 (BCP).<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> And ‘This
                shall ye have of mine hand;’ saith the Lord, ‘ye shall lie down in sorrow.’<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="121"&gt;</hi>Isa. 50:11.<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/note&gt;</hi></p>
            <p>3. The mourners of whom our Lord here speaks are those that mourn on quite another
                account: they that mourn after God, after him in whom they did ‘rejoice with joy
                    unspeakable’<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="122"&gt;</hi>1 Pet. 1:8.<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> when he gave them to ‘taste the good’, the
                pardoning ‘word, and the <hi rend="bold">&lt;pb n="484"/&gt;</hi>powers of the world
                to come’.<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="123"&gt;</hi>Heb. 6:5.<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> But he now ‘hides his face, and they are
                    troubled’;<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="124"&gt;</hi>Cf. Ps.
                    104:29.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> they cannot see him through the dark
                cloud. But they see temptation and sin—which they fondly supposed were gone never to
                return—arising again, following after them amain, and holding them in on every side.
                It is not strange if their soul is now disquieted within them,<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;note place="foot" n="125"&gt;</hi>See Ps. 42:5, 11; 43:5.<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/note&gt;</hi> if trouble and heaviness take hold upon them.<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;note place="foot" n="126"&gt;</hi>See below, No. 47, ‘Heaviness through
                Manifold Temptations’. Proem and II.1-3.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> Nor will
                their great enemy fail to improve the occasion; to ask, ‘Where is now thy God?<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="127"&gt;</hi>Ps. 42:10.<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/note&gt;</hi> Where is now the blessedness whereof thou spakest?<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="128"&gt;</hi>See Gal. 4:15.<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/note&gt;</hi> The beginning of the kingdom of heaven? Yea, hath God said,
                “Thy sins are forgiven thee”?<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot"
                n="129"&gt;</hi>Luke 5:20.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> Surely God hath not
                said it. It was only a dream, a mere delusion, a creature of thy own imagination. If
                thy sins are forgiven, why art thou thus? Can a pardoned sinner be thus unholy?’ And
                if then, instead of immediately crying to God, they reason with him that is wiser
                than they, they will be in heaviness indeed, in sorrow of heart, in anguish not to
                be expressed. Nay, even when God shines again upon the soul, and takes away all
                doubt of his past mercy, still he that is ‘weak in faith’<hi rend="bold">&lt;note
                    place="foot" n="130"&gt;</hi>Cf. 1 Cor. 8:7-12.<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/note&gt;</hi> may be tempted and troubled on account of what is to come;
                especially when inward sin revives, and thrusts sore at him that he may fall. Then
                may he again cry out:<hi rend="bold">&lt;lg&gt;&lt;l&gt;</hi>I have a sin of fear,
                that when I’ve spun<hi rend="bold">&lt;/l&gt;&lt;l&gt;</hi>My last thread, I shall
                perish on the shore!<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="131"&gt;</hi>John
                Donne, ‘A Hymn to God the Father’; cf. JWJ, Jan. 24, 1738; see also, <hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi>AM<hi rend="bold">&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>, 1779, 459-60,
                where Wesley again quotes this couplet in his extract from Donne’s biography.<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi>—<hi rend="bold">&lt;/l&gt;&lt;/lg&gt;</hi>lest I
                should make shipwreck of the faith,<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot"
                    n="132"&gt;</hi>See 1 Tim. 1:19.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> and my last
                state be worse than the first<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot"
                n="133"&gt;</hi>See Luke 11:26.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi>—<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;lg&gt;&lt;l&gt;</hi>Lest all my bread of life should fail,<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/l&gt;&lt;l&gt;</hi>And I sink down unchanged to hell.<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;note place="foot" n="134"&gt;&lt;p&gt;</hi>‘Groaning for Redemption’, Pt.
                II, ver. 3, last two ll., in <hi rend="bold">&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi>Hymns and
                Sacred Poems<hi rend="bold">&lt;/hi&gt;</hi> (1742), p. 106 (<hi rend="bold">&lt;hi
                    rend="italic"&gt;</hi>Poet. Wks.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>, II.161). Could
                ‘bread’ here be an uncorrected misprint of ‘breath’?<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;</hi>This equivalence of ‘mourning’ and ‘heaviness of
                spirit’ is rather different from Blackall’s exegesis of this passage (<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi>Works<hi rend="bold">&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>,
                I.24-31). The bishop takes it to refer both to those who are in ‘trouble, sorrow, or
                affliction’ and also to those ‘full of sorrow and trouble in their own minds, on
                account of their sins which lie as a heavy load on them’. But Hammond, <hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi>Practical Catechism<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>, p. 86, had defined mourning as ‘contrition’ both for our
                ‘spiritual wants’ and also for our ‘actual sins’. Later, John Heylyn, <hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi>Theological Lectures<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>, I.65 ff., will follow the same line.<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/note&gt;&lt;/l&gt;&lt;/lg&gt;&lt;pb n="485"/&gt;</hi></p>
            <p>4. Sure it is that this affliction ‘for the present is not joyous, but grievous.
                Nevertheless afterward it bringeth forth peaceable fruit unto them that are
                exercised thereby.’<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="135"&gt;</hi>Cf. Heb.
                    12:11.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> ‘Blessed’ therefore ‘are they that’
                thus ‘mourn,’ if they ‘tarry the Lord’s leisure’,<hi rend="bold">&lt;note
                    place="foot" n="136"&gt;</hi>Ps. 27:16 (BCP).<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi>
                and suffer not themselves to be turned out of the way<hi rend="bold">&lt;note
                    place="foot" n="137"&gt;</hi>Job 31:7; Heb. 12:13.<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/note&gt;</hi> by the miserable comforters<hi rend="bold">&lt;note
                    place="foot" n="138"&gt;</hi>Job 16:2.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> of the
                world; if they resolutely reject all the comforts of sin, of folly, and vanity; all
                the idle diversions and amusements of the world, all the pleasures which ‘perish in
                the using’,<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="139"&gt;</hi>Col. 2:22 (cf. <hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi>Notes<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>).<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> and which only tend to
                benumb and stupefy the soul, that it may neither be sensible of itself nor God.
                Blessed are they who ‘follow on to know the Lord’,<hi rend="bold">&lt;note
                    place="foot" n="140"&gt;</hi>Hos. 6:3.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> and
                steadily refuse all other comfort. They shall be comforted by the consolations of
                his Spirit, by a fresh manifestation of his love: by such a witness of his accepting
                them in the Beloved<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="141"&gt;</hi>See Eph.
                    1:6.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> as shall never more be taken away from
                them. This ‘full assurance of faith’<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot"
                    n="142"&gt;</hi>Heb. 10:22. Cf. No. 117, ‘On the Discoveries of Faith’, §15 and
                    n.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> swallows up all doubt, as well as all
                tormenting fear, God now giving them a sure hope of an enduring substance and
                ‘strong consolation through grace’.<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot"
                    n="143"&gt;</hi>Cf. 2 Thess. 2:16.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> Without
                disputing whether it be possible for any of those to ‘fall away’<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;note place="foot" n="144"&gt;</hi>Heb. 6:6.<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/note&gt;</hi> ‘who were once enlightened and […] made partakers of the
                Holy Ghost’,<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="145"&gt;</hi>Heb. 6:4.<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> it suffices them to say, by the power now resting
                upon them, ‘Who shall separate us from the love of Christ? […] I am persuaded, that
                neither death nor life, […] nor things present, nor things to come; nor height nor
                depth…, shall be able to separate us from the love of God, which is in Christ Jesus
                our Lord!’<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="i"&gt;</hi>Rom. 8:35, 38-39. [The
                comment here about ‘falling away’ (cf. 2 Thess. 2:3) is related to Wesley’s
                rejection of the Calvinists’ doctrine of final perseverance, and he returns to it
                again and again; cf. No. 1, <hi rend="bold">&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi>Salvation
                by Faith<hi rend="bold">&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>, II.4 and n.]<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/note&gt;</hi></p>
            <p>5. This whole process, both of mourning for an absent God<hi rend="bold">&lt;note
                    place="foot" n="146"&gt;</hi>Cf. Luther’s notion of <hi rend="bold">&lt;hi
                    rend="italic"&gt;</hi>Deus absconditus<hi rend="bold">&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>, as well
                as the mystical idea about ‘the dark night of the soul’.<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/note&gt;</hi> and recovering the joy of his countenance, seems to be
                shadowed out in what our Lord spoke to his apostles the night before his <hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;pb n="486"/&gt;</hi>Passion: ‘Do ye inquire of that I said, a
                little while and ye shall not see me, and again a little while and ye shall see me?
                Verily, verily, I say unto you, that ye shall weep and lament,’ namely, when ye do
                not see me; ‘but the world shall rejoice,’ shall triumph over you, as though your
                hope were now come to an end. ‘And ye shall be sorrowful,’ through doubt, through
                fear, through temptation, through vehement desire; ‘but your sorrow shall be turned
                into joy,’ by the return of him whom your soul loveth. ‘A woman when she is in
                travail hath sorrow because her hour is come. But as soon as she is delivered of the
                child, she remembereth no more the anguish, for joy that a man is born into the
                world. And ye now have sorrow:’ ye mourn and cannot be comforted. ‘But I will see
                you again; and your heart shall rejoice’ with calm, inward joy, ‘and your joy no man
                taketh from you.’<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="j"&gt;</hi>John
                    16:19-22.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi></p>
            <p>6. But although this mourning is at an end, is lost in holy joy, by the return of the
                Comforter, yet is there another, and a blessed mourning it is, which abides in the
                children of God. They still mourn for the sins and miseries of mankind: they ‘weep
                with them that weep’.<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="147"&gt;</hi>Rom.
                    12:15.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> They weep for them that weep not for
                themselves, for the sinners against their own souls. They mourn for the weakness and
                unfaithfulness of those that are in some measure saved from their sins. ‘Who is weak
                and they are not weak? Who is offended, and they burn not?’<hi rend="bold">&lt;note
                    place="foot" n="148"&gt;</hi>Cf. 2 Cor. 11:29.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi>
                They are grieved for the dishonour continually done to the Majesty of heaven and
                earth. At all times they have an awful sense of this, which brings a deep
                seriousness upon their spirit; a seriousness which is not a little increased since
                the eyes of their understanding were opened<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot"
                    n="149"&gt;</hi>See Eph. 1:18.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> by their
                continually seeing the vast ocean of eternity,<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot"
                    n="150"&gt;</hi>Cf. No. 54, ‘On Eternity’, §4 and n.<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/note&gt;</hi> without a bottom or a shore,<hi rend="bold">&lt;note
                    place="foot" n="151"&gt;&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;</hi>Ibid.<hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;/hi&gt;</hi>, §18 and n.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> which has
                already swallowed up millions of millions of men, and is gaping to devour them that
                yet remain. They see here the house of God eternal in the heavens; there, hell and
                destruction without a covering;<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot"
                    n="152"&gt;</hi>See Job 26:6.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> and thence feel
                the importance of every moment, which just appears, and is gone for ever.</p>
            <p>7. But all this wisdom of God is foolishness with the world.<hi rend="bold">&lt;note
                    place="foot" n="153"&gt;</hi>See 1 Cor. 3:19.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi>
                The whole affair of ‘mourning’ and ‘poverty of spirit’ is with them <hi rend="bold"
                    >&lt;pb n="487"/&gt;</hi>stupidity and dullness. Nay, ’tis well if they pass so
                favourable a judgment upon it, if they do not vote it to be mere moping and
                melancholy, if not downright lunacy and distraction. And it is no wonder at all that
                this judgment should be passed by those who know not God. Suppose as two persons
                were walking together one should suddenly stop, and with the strongest signs of fear
                and amazement cry out: ‘On what a precipice do we stand! See, we are on the point of
                being dashed in pieces! Another step and we fall into that huge abyss. Stop! I will
                not go on for all the world.’ When the other, who seemed to himself at least equally
                sharp-sighted, looked forward and saw nothing of all this, what would he think of
                his companion but that ‘he was beside himself’,<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot"
                    n="154"&gt;</hi>Cf. Mark 3:21.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> that his head
                was out of order, that much religion (if he was not guilty of much learning) had
                certainly ‘made him mad’?<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="155"&gt;</hi>Cf.
                Acts 26:24.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi></p>
            <p>8. But let not the children of God, ‘the mourners in Zion’,<hi rend="bold">&lt;note
                    place="foot" n="156"&gt;</hi>Cf. Isa. 61:3.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> be
                moved by any of these things. Ye whose eyes are enlightened, be not troubled by
                those who walk on still in darkness. Ye do not walk on in a vain shadow:<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="157"&gt;</hi>See Ps. 39:7 (BCP).<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> God and eternity are real things. Heaven and hell
                are in very deed open before you: and ye are on the edge of the great gulf. It has
                already swallowed up more than words can express, nations and kindreds and peoples
                and tongues,<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="158"&gt;</hi>See Rev. 14:6.<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> and still yawns to devour, whether they see it or
                no, the giddy, miserable children of men. O cry aloud! Spare not! Lift up your
                    voice<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="159"&gt;</hi>See Isa. 58:1.<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> to him who grasps both time and eternity, both
                for yourselves and your brethren, that ye may be counted worthy to escape the
                destruction that cometh as a whirlwind!<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot"
                    n="160"&gt;</hi>See Prov. 1:27.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> That ye may be
                brought safe, through all the waves and storms, into the haven where you would
                    be.<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="161"&gt;</hi>See Ps. 107:30.<hi
                    rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> Weep for yourselves, till he wipes away the tears
                from your eyes.<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot" n="162"&gt;</hi>See Rev. 7:17;
                    21:4.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi> And even then weep for the miseries that
                come upon the earth, till the Lord of all shall put a period to misery and sin,
                shall wipe away the tears from all faces, and ‘the knowledge of the Lord shall cover
                the earth, as the waters cover the sea.’<hi rend="bold">&lt;note place="foot"
                    n="163"&gt;</hi>Cf. Isa. 11:9; Hab. 2:14. Cf. No. 47, ‘Heaviness through
                Manifold Temptations’, V. 2-4.<hi rend="bold">&lt;/note&gt;</hi></p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
