<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Letter from George Colman to the Duke of Montrose, 29 September 1825.</title><author> </author><editor>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</editor><sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford Project</orgName></sponsor><sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor><principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal><respStmt><resp>Transcription and coding by</resp><persName>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Proofing and corrections by</resp><persName/></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>First digital edition in TEI, date: 2 August 2013. P5.</edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority><pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace><date>2013</date><availability><licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Mitford Letters: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title></seriesStmt><notesStmt><note>Any special notes on this text? (optional)</note><note>You can have multiple notes here.</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><repository>British Library</repository><idno>Add MS 42873, folio page 408</idno></msIdentifier><head>Letter from [George Colman] to James Graham, the Duke of Montrose, <date when="1825-09-29">29 September, 1825</date>. Inscribed as a Copy.</head><physDesc><objectDesc><supportDesc><support><p><material>Paper</material>. One quarto? [larger than octavo] sized sheet folded twice. No address leaf.</p></support><condition>Letter complete, marked at the top above the date in Colman's hand as a copy.</condition></supportDesc></objectDesc><sealDesc><p>Missing address leaf and seal.</p></sealDesc></physDesc></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><handNotes><handNote><!--None--></handNote></handNotes></profileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><p>The letter writer's spelling and punctuation are retained, except where a word is split at the end of a line and the beginning of the next in the manuscript. Where the spelling and hyphenation of words deviates from the standard, in order to facilitate searching we are using the TEI elements “choice,” “sic,” and “reg” to encode both Mitford’s spelling and the regular international standard of Oxford English spelling, following the first listed spelling in the Oxford English Dictionary. The long s and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="letter"><opener>
               (Copy.)<lb/><dateline><date when="1825-09-29">29<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> September. 1825.</date><lb/><placeName>Brompton Square</placeName></dateline><salute>My Lord,</salute></opener><p>--- ------<lb/>
            --- ---. --- ----<!--EBB: lines drawn thus, perhaps to indicate uncopied material.--></p><p>As a point of duty, I forward the enclosed form of License; but it will surprise me if your Grace should think proper to sign it. It refers to a Play the very title of which,--Charles the First (of England),--brings, instantly, to mind the violent commotions, &amp; <unclear><supplied resp="#ebb">striking</supplied></unclear> catastrophes of that unhappy Monarchar's reign.--&amp;, in following closely the historical facts previous to his Death, the <hi rend="underline">Dramatis Personae</hi> (as far as Cromwell &amp; his adherents are concerned) exhibit the fanatical manners &amp; utter all the puritanical cant, peculiar to their times:--consequently, the Piece abounds (blasphemously, I think,) with Scriptural allusions, &amp; quotations &amp; the name of the Almighty is introduced, &amp; invoked, over<pb/> &amp; over again, by the hypocrites, &amp; regicides.</p><p>If it be <hi rend="underline">in keeping</hi> thus to delineate the morals &amp; religion of the Cromwell party, the political <unclear><supplied resp="#ebb">part</supplied></unclear> of their dialogue is, by the same rule, democratical; most insulting to Charles, in particular, &amp; to Monarchy, in general.</p><p>I subjoin an outline of the Play, giving its progressive conduct Act by Act.</p><p>I think there can be but one impartial opinion upon the nature of this Drama.</p><p>At all events, I certainly cannot represent to the Lord Chamberlain that "it does not contain anything immoral, or otherwise improper for the Stage."</p><p>Shall I forward the manuscript for Your Grace's perusal.</p><closer><lb/>I have the honoour to be Sir<lb/>---<lb/><lb/><address><addrLine>His Grace,</addrLine><addrLine><persName>The Duke of Montrose</persName></addrLine><addrLine>&amp;c, &amp;c, &amp;c.</addrLine></address></closer></div></body><back><div type="context"/></back></text></TEI>