<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>George Colman's Comments Written on the Back of the first leaf of Act the Fifth in Mitford's Charles I Manuscript</title><author> </author><editor>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</editor><sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford Project</orgName></sponsor><sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor><principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal><respStmt><resp>Transcription and coding by</resp><persName>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Proofing and corrections by</resp><persName/></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>First digital edition in TEI, date: 2 August 2013. P5.</edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority><pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace><date>2013</date><availability><licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title></seriesStmt><notesStmt><note>Any special notes on this text? (optional)</note><note>You can have multiple notes here.</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><repository>British Library</repository><idno>Add MS 42873, folio page 480 [back of sheet]</idno></msIdentifier><head>George Colman's Commentary written on the back of the first leaf of Act the Fifth of Mitford's Charles I.</head><physDesc><objectDesc><supportDesc><support><p><material>Paper</material> verso side of Mitford's manuscript page</p></support><condition>complete and initialed by G. C.</condition></supportDesc></objectDesc></physDesc></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><handNotes><handNote><!--None--></handNote></handNotes></profileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><p>The writer's spelling and punctuation are retained, except where a word is split at the end of a line and the beginning of the next in the manuscript. Where the spelling and hyphenation of words deviates from the standard, in order to facilitate searching we are using the TEI elements “choice,” “sic,” and “reg” to encode both the writer's spelling and the regular international standard of Oxford English spelling, following the first listed spelling in the Oxford English Dictionary. The long s and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="comments"><head><hi rend="underline">Extract from the <bibl><hi rend="underline">Biographia Dramatica</hi></bibl></hi></head><p>'<bibl>King Charles the 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>. Histor<hi rend="superscript">l</hi>. Trag. by <persName>W. Havard</persName>, 8.<hi rend="superscript">vo</hi>. <date>1737</date>.</bibl> This piece was performed in the theatre in Lincoln's Inn Fields with very good success; &amp; indeed there are some parts of it which seem to approach <del rend="diagonal_strike-through" quantity="1" unit="letter"><unclear/></del><add place="above">as</add> near to the style of Shakespeare, as any of the attempts that have been made to imitate him. Some of the Characters are well drawn, &amp; the catastrophe is pathetick and affecting. Lord Chesterfield, in his Speech on the Licencing Act, [<hi rend="underline">of which Act His Lordship was a violent opponent</hi>] mentioning this Play, Says,"the catastrophe was too recent, too melancholy, &amp; too solemn in nature to be heard of anywhere but in a pulpit."'</p><p>It is to be remembered that the above Play was acted <hi rend="underline">before</hi> The Lord Chamberlain's control over Drama was established, by Act of Parliament. <persName>G. C.</persName></p></div></body><back><div type="context"/></back></text></TEI>