<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Our Village: Sketches of Rural Character and Scenery: Preface</title><author>Mary Russell Mitford</author><editor>Alexandra Drayton</editor><editor>Samantha Webb</editor><sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford
                    Project</orgName></sponsor><sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor><principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal><respStmt><resp>Transcription and coding by</resp><persName>Alexandra Drayton</persName><persName>Samantha Webb</persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Proofing and corrections by</resp><persName>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>This is optional, used to describe this edition, and "should contain
                    phrases describing the edition or version": First digital edition in TEI, date:
                    2 June 2013. P5.</edition><respStmt><resp>We can include a respStmt here.</resp><persName>Who?</persName></respStmt></editionStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority><pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace><date>2013</date><availability><licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0
                        Unported License</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title></seriesStmt><notesStmt><note>Any special notes on this text? (optional)</note><note>You can have multiple notes here.</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc>
                <!--Notice, this is simpler than the sourceDesc we used in our Letters file.--><p>Our text is based on public domain, Google-digitized text<bibl><title>Our Village: Sketches of Rural Character and
                            Scenery</title><edition>Third Edition</edition> by <author>Mary Russell
                            Mitford</author><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><publisher>Geo. B.
                            Whittaker</publisher><placeName>Ave Maria
                            Lane</placeName><date>1825</date>. </bibl> This text appears to be
                    identical in pagination and content to the first edition published in 1824. </p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><p>Describes our editorial practice.</p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><pb n="ii"/><docTitle><titlePart type="main">Our Village:</titlePart><titlePart type="subtitle">Sketches of Rural Character and Scenery.</titlePart></docTitle><byline>by <docAuthor>Mary Russell Mitford</docAuthor>, Author of <title>Julian, A
                        Tragedy</title><lb/></byline><docEdition>Third Edition.</docEdition><docImprint><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><lb/><publisher>Geo. B.
                        Whittaker</publisher>,<lb/><placeName>Ave-Maria-Lane</placeName>.
                        <docDate>1825</docDate>.</docImprint></titlePage><pb n="iii"/></front><body><div type="sketch"><head>A COUNTRY CRICKET-MATCH.</head><p> I doubt if there be any scene in the world more animating or delightful than a
                    cricket-match :—I do not mean a set match at Lord's Ground for money, hard
                    money, between a certain number of gentlemen and players, as they are
                    called—people who make a trade of that noble sport, and degrade it into an
                    affair of bettings, and hedgings, and cheatings, it may be, like boxing or
                    horse-racing; nor do I mean a pretty fête in a gentleman's park, where one club
                    of cricketing dandies encounter another such club, and where they show off in
                    graceful costume to a gay marquee of admiring belles, who condescend so to
                    purchase admiration, and while away a long summer morning in partaking cold
                    collations, conversing occasionally, and seeming to understand the game;—the
                    whole being conducted according to ball-room etiquette, so as to be exceedingly
                    elegant and exceedingly dull. No! the cricket that I mean is a real solid
                    old-fashioned match between neighbouring parishes, where each attacks the other
                    for ho<pb n="146"/>nour and a supper, glory and half-a-crown a man. If there be
                    any gentlemen amongst them, it is well—if not, it is so much the better. Elderly
                    gentlemen are obviously good for nothing; and young beaux are, for the most
                    part, hampered and trammelled by dress and habit; the stiff cravat, the
                    pinched-in waist, the dandy-walk—oh they will never do for cricket! Now, our
                    country lads, accustomed to the flail or the hammer (your blacksmiths are
                    capital hitters,) have the free use of their arms; they know how to move their
                    shoulders; and they can move their feet too—they can run; then they are so much
                    better made, so much more athletic, and yet so much lissomer—to use a Hampshire
                    phrase, which deserves at least to be good English. Here and there, indeed, one
                    meets with an old Etonian, who retains his boyish love for that game which
                    formed so considerable a branch of his education: some even preserve their
                    boyish proficiency, but in general it wears away like the Greek, quite as
                    certainly, and almost as fast; a few years of Oxford, or Cambridge, or the
                    continent, are sufficient to annihilate both the power and the incliation. No! a
                    village match is the thing,—where our highest officer—our conductor (to borrow a
                    musical term) is but a little farmer's second son; where a day-labourer is our
                    bowler, and a blacksmith our long-stop; where the<pb n="147"/> spectators
                    consist of the retired cricketers, the veterans of the green, the careful
                    mothers, the girls, and all the boys of two parishes, together with a few
                    amateurs, little above them in rank, and not at all in pretension; where
                    laughing and shouting, and the very ecstasy of merriment and good humour,
                    prevail: such a match, in short, as I attended yesterday, at the expense of
                    getting twice wet through, and as I would attend tomorrow, at the certainty of
                    having that ducking doubled.</p><p>For the last three weeks our village has been in a state of great excitement,
                    occasioned by a challenge from our north-western neighbours, the men of B., to
                    contend with us at cricket. Now we have not been much in the habit of playing
                    matches. Three or four years ago, indeed, we encountered the men of S., our
                    neighbours south-by-east, with a sort of doubtful success, beating them on our
                    own ground, whilst they in the second match returned the compliment on theirs.
                    This discouraged us. Then an unnatural coalition between a high-church curate
                    and an evangelical gentleman-farmer drove our lads from the Sunday-evening
                    practice, which, as it did not begin before both services were concluded, and as
                    it tended to keep the young men from the ale-house, our magistrates had winked
                    at, if not encouraged. The sport therefore had languished until the present
                    season, when under another change of circumstances the spirit began to
                        revive.<pb n="148"/> Half a dozen fine active lads, of influence amongst
                    their comrades, grew into men and yearned for cricket: an enterprising publican
                    gave a set of ribands: his rival, mine host of the Rose, an out-doer by
                    profession, gave two; and the clergyman and his lay-ally, both well-disposed and
                    good-natured men, gratified by the submission to their authority, and finding,
                    perhaps, that no great good resulted from the substitution of public houses
                    for-out-of door diversions, relaxed. In short the practice recommenced, and the
                    hill was again alive with men and boys, and innocent merriment; but farther than
                    the riband matches amongst ourselves nobody dreamed of going, till this
                    challenge—we were modest, and doubted our own strength. The B. people, on the
                    other hand, must have been braggers born, a whole parish of gasconaders. Never
                    was such boast- ing! such crowing! such ostentatious display of practice! such
                    mutual compliments from man to man—bowler to batter, batter to bowler! It was a
                    wonder they did not challenge all of England. It must be confessed that we were
                    a little astounded; yet we firmly resolved not to decline the combat; and one of
                    the most spirited of the new growth, William Grey by name, took up the glove in
                    a style of manly courtesy, that would have done honour to a knight in the days
                    of chivalry.—" We were not professed players," he said; "being little better
                    than school-boys, and scarcely<pb n="149"/> older: but, since they had done us
                    the honour to challenge us, we would try our strength. It would be no discredit
                    to be beaten by such a field."</p><p> Having accepted the wager of battle, our champion began forthwith to collect his
                    forces. William Grey is himself one of the finest youths that one shall
                    see,—tall, active, slender and yet strong, with a piercing eye full of sagacity,
                    and a smile full of good humour,—a farmer's son by station, and used to hard
                    work as farmers' sons are now, liked by every body, and admitted to be an
                    excellent cricketer. He immediately set forth to muster his men, remembering
                    with great complacency that Samuel Long, a bowler comme il y en a peu, the very
                    man who had knocked down nine wickets, had beaten us, bowled us out at the fatal
                    return match some years ago at S., had luckily, in a remove of a quarter of a
                    mile last Lady-day, crossed the boundaries of his old parish, and actually
                    belonged to us. Here was a stroke of good fortune! Our captain applied to him
                    instantly; and he agreed at a word. Indeed Samuel Long is a very civilized
                    person. He is a middle-aged man who looks rather old amongst our young lads, and
                    whose thickness and breadth give no token of remarkable activity; but he is very
                    active, and so steady a player! so safe! We had half gained the match when we
                    had secured him. He is a man of substance, too, in every way; owns one cow, two
                        don<pb n="150"/>keys, six pigs, and geese and ducks beyond count; dresses
                    like a farmer, and owes no man a shilling;— and all this from pure industry,
                    sheer day-labour. Note that your good cricketer is commonly the most industrious
                    man in the parish; the habits that make him such are precisely those which make
                    a good workman—steadiness, sobriety, and activity—Samuel Long might pass for the
                    beau ideal of the two characters. Happy were we to possess him! Then we had
                    another piece of good luck. James Brown, a journeyman blacksmith and a native,
                    who, being of a rambling disposition, had roamed from place to place for half a
                    dozen years, had just returned to settle with his brother at another corner of
                    our village, bringing with him a prodigious reputation in cricket and in
                    gallantry—the gay Lothario of the neighborhood. He is said to have made more
                    conquests in love and in cricket than any blacksmith in the county. To him also
                    went the indefatigable William Grey, and he also consented to play. No end to
                    our good fortune! Another celebrated batter, called Joseph Hearne, had likewise
                    recently married into the parish. He worked, it is true, at the A. mills, but
                    slept at the house of his wife's father in our territories. He also was sought
                    and found by our leader. But he was grand and shy; made an immense favour of the
                    thing; courted courting and then hung back ;—" Did not know that he could be
                    spared; had partly resolved<pb n="151"/> not to play again—at least not this
                    season; thought it rash to accept the challenge; thought they might do without
                    him——"—"Truly I think so too," said our spirited champion; "we will not trouble
                    you, Mr. Hearne."</p><p> Having thus secured two powerful auxiliaries, and rejected a third, we began to
                    reckon and select the regular native forces. Thus ran our list:—William Grey,
                    1.—Samuel Long, 2.—James Brown, 3.—George and John Simmons, one capital, the
                    other so, so,—an uncertain hitter, but a good fieldsman, 5.— Joel Brent,
                    excellent, 6.—Ben Appleton—Here was a little pause—Ben's abilities at cricket
                    were not completely ascertained; but then he was so good a fellow, so full of
                    fun and waggery! no doing without Ben. So he figured in the list, 7.—George
                    Harris—a short halt there too! Slowish—slow but sure. I think the proverb
                    brought him in, 8.—Tom Coper—oh, beyond the world, Tom Coper! the red-headed
                    gardening lad, whose left-handed strokes send her (a cricket-ball, like that
                    other moving thing a ship, is always of the feminine gender,) send her spinning
                    a mile, 9.—Harry Willis, another blacksmith, 10. </p><p>We had now ten of our eleven, but the choice of the last occasioned some demure.
                    Three young Martins, rich farmers of the neighbourhood, successively presented
                    themselves, and were all rejected by our inde<pb n="152"/>pendent and impartial
                    general for want of merit—cricketal merit. "Not good enough," was his pithy
                    answer. Then our worthy neighbour, the half-pay lieutenant, offered his
                    services—he, too, though with some hesitation and modesty, was refused—"Not
                    quite young enough" was his sentence. John Strong, the exceeding long son of our
                    dwarfish mason, was the next candidate,—a nice youth—every body likes John
                    Strong,—and a willing, but so tall and so limp, bent in the middle—a
                    thread-paper, six feet high! We were all afraid that, in spite of his name, his
                    strength would never hold out. "Wait till next year, John," quoth William Grey,
                    with all the dignified seniority of twenty speaking to eighteen. "Coper's a year
                    younger," said John. "Coper's a foot shorter," replied William: so John retired;
                    and the eleventh man remained unchosen, almost to the eleventh hour. The eve of
                    the match arrived, and the post was still vacant, when a little boy of fifteen,
                    David Willis, brother to Harry, admitted by accident to the last practice, saw
                    eight of them out, and was voted in by acclamation.</p><p>That Sunday evening's practice (for Monday was the important day) was a period of
                    great anxiety, and, to say the truth, of great pleasure. There is something
                    strangely delightful in the innocent spirit of party. To be one of a numerous
                    body, to be authorised to say we, to have a rightful interest in triumph or
                    defeat, is gra<pb n="153"/>tifying at once to social feeling and to personal
                    pride. There was not a ten-year old urchin, or a septuagenary woman in the
                    parish, who did not feel an additional importance, a reflected consequence, in
                    speaking of "our side." An election interests in the same way; but that feeling
                    is less pure. Money is there, and hatred, and politics, and lies. Oh, to be a
                    voter, or a voter's wife, comes nothing near the genuine and hearty sympathy of
                    belonging to a parish, breathing the same air, looking on the same trees,
                    listening to the same nightingales! Talk of a patriotic elector!— Give me a
                    parochial patriot, a man who loves his parish! Even we, the female partisans,
                    may partake the common ardour. I am sure I did. I never, though tolerably eager
                    and enthusiastic at all times, remember being in a more delicious state of
                    excitation than on the eve of that battle. Our hopes waxed stronger and
                    stronger. Those of our players, who were present, were excellent. William Grey
                    got forty notches off his own bat; and that brilliant hitter Tom Coper gained
                    eight from two successive balls. As the evening advanced, too, we had
                    encouragement of another sort. A spy, who had been despatched to reconnoitre the
                    enemy's quarters, returned from their practising ground, with a most consolatory
                    report. "Really," said Charles Grover, our intelligence—a fine old steady judge,
                    one who had played well in his day—" they are no better<pb n="154"/> than so
                    many old women. Any five of ours would beat their eleven." This sent us to bed
                    in high spirits.</p><p>Morning dawned less favourably. The sky promised a series of deluging showers,
                    and kept its word, as English skies are wont to do on such occasions; and a
                    lamentable message arrived at the head-quarters from our trusty comrade Joel
                    Brent. His master, a great farmer, had begun the hay-harvest that very morning,
                    and Joel, being as eminent in one field as in another, could not be spared.
                    Imagine Joel's plight! the most ardent of all our eleven! a knight held back
                    from the tourney! a soldier from the battle! The poor swain was inconsolable. At
                    last, one who is always ready to do a good-natured action, great or little, set
                    forth to back his petition; and, by dint of appealing to the public spirit of
                    our worthy neighbour, and the state of the barometer, talking alternately of the
                    parish honour and thunder showers, of lost matches and sopped hay, he carried
                    his point, and returned triumphantly with the delighted Joel.</p><p>In the mean time we became sensible of another defalcation. On calling over our
                    roll, Brown was missing; and the spy of the preceding night, Charles Grover,—the
                    universal scout and messenger of the village, a man who will run half-a-dozen
                    miles for a pint of beer, who does errands for the very love of the<pb n="155"/>
                    trade, who, if he had been a lord, would have been an ambassador—was instantly
                    despatched to summon the truant. His report spread general consternation. Brown
                    had set off at four o'clock in the morning to play in a cricket-match at M., a
                    little town twelve miles off, which had been his last residence. Here was
                    desertion! Here was treachery! Here was treachery against that goodly state, our
                    parish! To send James Brown to Coventry was the immediate resolution; but even
                    that seemed too light a punishment for such delinquency. Then how we cried him
                    down! At ten, on Sunday-night, (for the rascal had actually practised with us,
                    and never said a word of his intended disloyalty,) he was our faithful mate, and
                    the best player (take him for all in all) of the eleven. At ten in the morning
                    he had run away, and we were well rid of him; he was no batter compared with
                    William Grey or Tom Coper; not fit to wipe the shoes of Samuel Long, as a
                    bowler; nothing of a scout to John Simmons; the boy David Willis was worth fifty
                    of him—
                    <!-- presented in nearly verse format. <lg>"<l>I trust we have within our realm </l><l>Five hundred good as he,</l>"<lg>-->So
                    we took tall John Strong, who, with an incurable hankering after the honour of
                    being admitted, had kept constantly with<pb n="156"/> the players, to take the
                    chance of some such accident—we took John for our pis-aller. I never saw any one
                    prouder than the good-humoured lad was of this not very flattering piece of
                    preferment.</p><p>John Strong was elected, and Brown sent to Coventry; and, when I first heard of
                    his delinquency, I thought the punishment only too mild for the crime. But I
                    have since learned the secret history of the offence; (if we could know the
                    secret histories of all offences, how much better the world would seem than it
                    does now!)It was a piece of gallantry, of devotion to the sex, or rather a
                    chivalrous obedience to one chosen fair. I must tell my readers the story. Mary
                    Allen, the prettiest girl of M., had it seems revenged upon our blacksmith the
                    numberless inconsistencies of which he stood accused. He was in love over head
                    and ears, but the nymph was cruel. She said no, and no, and no, and poor Brown,
                    three times rejected, at last resolved to leave the place, partly in despair,
                    and partly in that hope which often mingles strangely with a lover's despair,
                    the hope that when he was gone he should be missed. He came home to his
                    brother's accordingly; but for five weeks he heard nothing from or of the
                    inexorable Mary, and was glad to beguile his own "vexing thoughts," by
                    endeavouring to create in his mind an artificial and factitious interest in
                        our<pb n="157"/> cricket-match—all unimportant as such a trifle must have
                    seemed to a man in love. Poor James, however, is a social and warm-hearted
                    person, not likely to resist a contagious sympathy. As the time for the play
                    advanced, the interest which he had at first affected became genuine and
                    sincere: and he was really, when he left the ground on Sunday-night, almost as
                    enthusiastically absorbed in the event of the next day as Joel Brent himself. He
                    little foresaw the new and delightful interest which awaited him at home, where,
                    on the moment of his arrival, his sister-in-law and confidante, presented him
                    with a billet from the lady of his heart. It had, with the usual delay of
                    letters sent by private hands, in that rank of life, loitered on the road in a
                    degree inconceivable to those who are accustomed to the punctual speed of the
                    post, and had taken ten days for its twelve-miles' journey. Have my readers any
                    wish to see this billet-doux? I can show them (but in strict confidence) a
                    kuterak copy. It was addressed, "For mistur jem browne "blaxmith by "S." </p><p>The inside ran thus:—" Mistur browne this is to Inform yew that oure parish
                    playes bramley men next monday is a week, i think we shall lose without yew.
                    from your humbell servant to command "Mary Allen."<pb n="158"/></p><p>Was there ever a prettier relenting? a summons more flattering, more delicate,
                    more irresistible? The precious epistle was undated; but, having ascertained who
                    brought it, and found, by cross-examining the messenger, that the Monday in
                    question was the very next day, we were not surprised to find that Mistur browne
                    forgot his engagement to us, forgot all but Mary and Mary's letter, and set off
                    at four o'clock the next morning to walk twelve miles, and play for her parish
                    and in her sight. Really we must not send James Browne to Coventry—must we?
                    Though if, as his sister-in-law tells our damsel Harriet he hopes to do, he
                    should bring the fair Mary home as his bride, he will not greatly care how
                    little we say to him. But he must not be sent to Coventry—True-love forbid!</p><p> At last we were all assembled, and marched down to H. common, the appointed
                    ground, which, though in our dominions according to the map, was the constant
                    practising place of our opponents, and terra incognita to us. We found our
                    adversaries on the ground as we expected, for our various delays had hindered us
                    from taking the field so early as we wished; and, as soon as we had settled all
                    preliminaries, the match began.</p><p>But, alas! I have been so long settling my preliminaries that I have left myself
                    no room for the detail<pb n="159"/> of our victory, and must squeeze the account
                    of our grand achievements into as little compass as Cowley, when he crammed the
                    names of eleven of his mistresses into the narrow space of four eight-syllable
                    lines. They began the warfare—these boastful men of B. And what think you,
                    gentle reader, was the amount of their innings? These challengers—the famous
                    eleven—how many did they get? Think! imagine! guess! — You cannot?—Well!—they
                    got twenty-two, or rather they got twenty; for two of theirs were short notches,
                    and would never have been allowed, only that, seeing what they were made of, we
                    and our umpires were not particular.—They should have had twenty more, if they
                    had chosen to claim them. Oh, how well we fielded! and how well we bowled! our
                    good play had quite as much to do with their miserable failure as their bad.
                    Samuel Long is a slow bowler, George Simmons a fast one, and the change from
                    Long's lobbing, to Simmons's fast balls posed them completely. Poor simpletons!
                    they were always wrong, expecting the slow for the quick, and the quick for the
                    slow. Well, we went in. And what were our innings? Guess again!—guess! A hundred
                    and sixty-nine! in spite of soaking showers, and wretched ground, where the ball
                    would not run a yard, we headed them by a hundred and forty-seven; and then they
                    gave in, as well they might. William<pb n="160"/> Grey pressed them to try
                    another innings. "There was so much chance," as he courteously observed, "in
                    cricket, that advantageous as our position seemed, we might, very possibly, be
                    overtaken. The B. men had better try." But they were beaten sulky, and would not
                    move—to my great disappointment; I wanted to prolong the pleasure of success.
                    What a glorious sensation it is to be for five hours together
                    winning—winning—winning! always feeling what a whist-player feels when he takes
                    up four honours, seven trumps! Who would think that a little bit of leather, and
                    two pieces of wood, had such a delightful and delighting power? </p><p>The only drawback on my enjoyment, was the failure of the pretty boy, David
                    Willis, who injudiciously put in first, and playing for the first time in a
                    match amongst men and strangers, who talked to him, and stared at him, was
                    seized with such a fit of shamefaced shyness, that he could scarcely hold his
                    bat, and was bowled out, without a stroke, from actual nervousness. "He will
                    come of that," Tom Coper says.—I am afraid he will. I wonder whether Tom had
                    ever any modesty to lose. Our other modest lad, John Strong, did very well; his
                    length told in fielding, and he got good frame. Joel Brent, the rescued mower,
                    got into a scrape, and out of it again: his fortune for the day. He ran out his
                    mate, Samuel Long; who, I <pb n="161"/>do believe, but for the excess of Joel's
                    eagerness, would have staid in till this time, by which exploit he got into sad
                    disgrace; and then he himself got thirty-seven runs, which redeemed his
                    reputation. William Grey made a hit which actually lost the cricket-ball. We
                    think she lodged in a hedge, a quarter of a mile off, but nobody could find her.
                    And George Simmons had nearly lost his shoe, which he tossed away in a passion,
                    for having been caught out, owing to the ball glancing against it. These,
                    together with a very complete somerset of Ben Appleton, our long-stop, who
                    floundered about in the mud, making faces and attitudes as laughable as
                    Grimaldi, none could tell whether by accident or design, there were chief
                    incidents of the scene of action. Amongst the spectators nothing remarkable
                    occurred, beyond the general calamity of two or three drenchings, except that a
                    form, placed by the side of a hedge, under a very insufficient shelter, was
                    knocked into the ditch, in a sudden rush of the cricketers to escape a pelting
                    shower, by which means all parties shared the fate of Ben Appleton, some on land
                    and some by water; and that, amidst the scramble, a saucy gipsy of a girl
                    contrived to steal from the knee of the demure and well-appareled Samuel Long, a
                    smart handkerchief, which his careful dame had tied around it, to preserve his
                    new (what is the mincing feminine word?) his new—inexpressibles;<pb n="162"/>
                    thus reversing the story of Desdemona, and causing the new Othello to call aloud
                    for his handkerchief, to the great diversion of the company. And so we parted;
                    the players retired to their supper, and we to our homes; all wet through, all
                    good-humoured, and all happy—except the losers.</p><p>To-day we are happy too. Hats, with ribands in them, go glancing up and down; and
                    William Grey says, with a proud humility, "We do not challenge any parish; but,
                    if we be challenged, we are ready." <pb n="163"/></p></div></body><back/></text></TEI>