<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><!--<?xml-model href="MRMValidate.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>--><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc>
            <!-- MAH: June 15, so footnotes. Not sure what we've decided to do with this, so I'm just leaving them in the text. --><titleStmt><title>Our Village: Sketches of Rural Character and Scenery: Preface</title><author>Mary Russell Mitford</author><editor>Alexandra Drayton</editor><editor>Samantha Webb</editor><sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford
                    Project</orgName></sponsor><sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor><principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal><respStmt><resp>Transcription and coding by</resp><persName>Alexandra Drayton</persName><persName>Samantha Webb</persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Proofing and corrections by</resp><persName>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>This is optional, used to describe this edition, and "should contain phrases
                    describing the edition or version": First digital edition in TEI, date: 2 June 2013.
                    P5.</edition><respStmt><resp>We can include a respStmt here.</resp><persName>Who?</persName></respStmt></editionStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority><pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace><date>2013</date><availability><licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                        License</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title></seriesStmt><notesStmt><note>Any special notes on this text? (optional)</note><note>You can have multiple notes here.</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc>
                <!--Notice, this is simpler than the sourceDesc we used in our Letters file.--><p>Our text is based on  public domain, Google-digitized text<bibl><title>Our Village: Sketches of Rural Character and Scenery</title><edition>Third Edition</edition> by <author>Mary Russell Mitford</author><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><publisher>Geo. B. Whittaker</publisher><placeName>Ave Maria Lane</placeName><date>1825</date>.
                </bibl> This text appears to be identical in pagination and content to the first edition published in 1824.  
                </p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><p>Describes our editorial practice.</p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><pb n="ii"/><docTitle><titlePart type="main">Our Village:</titlePart><titlePart type="subtitle">Sketches of Rural Character and Scenery.</titlePart></docTitle><byline>by <docAuthor>Mary Russell Mitford</docAuthor>, Author of <title>Julian, A Tragedy</title><lb/></byline><docEdition>Third Edition.</docEdition><docImprint><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><lb/><publisher>Geo. B. Whittaker</publisher>,<lb/><placeName>Ave-Maria-Lane</placeName>.
                    <docDate>1825</docDate>.</docImprint></titlePage><pb n="iii"/></front><body><div type="sketch"><head>HANNAH.</head><p>The prettiest <placeName type="arch">cottage</placeName> on our <placeName type="land">village-green</placeName> is the little dwelling of <persName type="fict" subtype="int" ref="#DameWilson">Dame Wilson</persName>. It stands in a corner of the <placeName type="land">common</placeName>, where the <rs type="plant" nymRef="plant">hedgerows</rs> go curving off into a sort of bay round a clear bright <placeName type="land">pond</placeName>, the earliest haunt of the swallow. A deep, woody, green <placeName type="geog">lane</placeName>, such as <sic><persName type="hist" subtype="ext" ref="#Hobbema">Hobbima</persName></sic><!--scw: Hobbema and Ruysdael need to be put in SI--> or <persName type="hist" subtype="ext" ref="#Ruydsdael">Ruydsdael</persName> might have painted, a lane that hints of nightingales, forms one boundary of the garden, and a sloping <placeName type="land">meadow</placeName> the other; whilst the cottage itself, a <placeName type="arch">low thatched irregular building</placeName>, backed by a blooming <placeName type="land">orchard</placeName>, and covered with <rs type="plant" nymRef="floral">honeysuckle</rs> and <rs type="plant" nymRef="floral">jessamine</rs>, looks like the chosen abode of snugness and comfort. And so it is. </p><p><persName ref="#DameWilson">Dame Wilson</persName> was a respected servant in a most respectable family, where she passed all the early part of her life, and which she quitted only on her marriage with a <rs type="person" subtype="fict" ref="#JohnWilson">man of character and industry</rs>, and of that peculiar universality of genius which forms, what is called in country phrase, a <rs type="person" ref="#JohnWilson">handy fellow</rs>. He could do any sort of work; was <rs type="person" subtype="fict" ref="#JohnWilson">thatcher, carpenter, bricklayer,<pb n="17"/> painter, gardener,gamekeeper</rs>, <quote>"every thing by turns, and nothing long."</quote> No job came amiss to him. He killed pigs, mended shoes, cleaned clocks, doctored cows, dogs, and horses, and even went as far as bleeding and drawing teeth in his experiments on the human subject. In addition to these multifarious talents, he was ready, obliging, and unfearing; jovial withal, and fond of good-fellowship; and endowed with a promptness of resource which made him the general adviser of the stupid, the puzzled, and the timid. He was universally admitted to be the cleverest man in the parish; and his death, which happened about ten years ago, in consequence of standing in the water, drawing a <placeName type="land">pond</placeName> for one neighbour, at a time when he was over-heated by loading hay for another, made quite a gap in our <placeName type="geog" ref="#ThreeMileCross">village</placeName> commonwealth. <persName ref="#JohnWilson">John Wilson</persName> had no rival, and has had no successor:—for the <persName type="fict" subtype="int" ref="#RobertEllis">Robert Ellis</persName>, whom certain youngsters would fain exalt to a co-partnery of fame, is simply nobody—a <persName ref="#RobertEllis">bell-ringer, a ballad-singer—a troller of profane catches—a fiddler—a bruiser—a loller on <placeName type="arch">alehouse</placeName> benches—a teller of good stories—a mimic—a poet!</persName>—What is all this to compare with the solid parts of <persName ref="#JohnWilson">John Wilson?</persName> Whose clock hath <persName ref="#RobertEllis">Robert Ellis</persName> cleaned?—whose windows hath he mended?—whose dog hath he broken?—whose pigs hath he rung?—whose pond hath he fished?—whose hay hath he saved?—whose cow hath he cured?—whose calf hath<pb n="18"/> he killed?—whose teeth hath he drawn? whom hath he bled? Tell me that, irreverent whipsters! No! <persName ref="#JohnWilson">John Wilson</persName> is not to be replaced. He was missed by the whole <orgName type="place" subtype="parish" ref="#Shinfield">parish;</orgName> and most of all he was missed at home. His excellent <rs type="fict" subtype="int" ref="DameWilson">wife</rs> was left the sole guardian and protector of two fatherless girls; one an <persName type="fict" subtype="int" ref="#SusanWilson">infant</persName> at her knee, the other a pretty handy <persName type="fict" subtype="int" ref="#HannahWilson">lass about nine years old</persName>. Cast thus upon the world, there must have been much to endure, much to suffer; but it was borne with a smiling patience, a hopeful cheeriness of spirit, and a decent pride, which seemed to command success as well as respect in their struggle for independence. Without assistance of any sort, by needle-work, by by washing and by mending lace and fine linen, and other by skilful and profitable labours, and by the produce of her <placeName type="land">orchard</placeName> and poultry, <persName ref="#DameWilson">Dame Wilson</persName> contrived to maintain herself and <orgName type="person" subtype="WilsonChildren" ref="#WilsonChildren">her children</orgName> in their old comfortable home. There was no visible change; she and the <orgName ref="#WilsonChildren">little girls</orgName> were as neat as ever; the house had still within and without the same sunshiny cleanliness, and the garden was still famous over all other gardens for its <rs type="plant" nymRef="plant">cloves</rs>, and <rs type="plant" nymRef="floral">stocks</rs>, and double <rs type="plant" nymRef="floral">wall-flowers</rs>. But the sweetest <rs type="plant" nymRef="floral">flower</rs> of the garden, the joy and pride of her <rs type="person" subtype="fict" ref="#DameWilson">mother's</rs> heart, was her daughter <persName ref="#HannahWilson">Hannah</persName>. Well might she be proud of her! At sixteen <persName ref="#HannahWilson">Hannah Wilson</persName> was, beyond a doubt, the <rs type="person" subtype="fict" ref="#HannahWilson">prettiest girl in the village, and the best</rs>. Her beauty was quite in a different style from the common <pb n="19"/>country rosebud—far more choice and rare. Its chief characteristic was modesty. A light youthful figure, exquisitely graceful and rapid in all its movements; springy, elastic, and buoyant as a and almost as shy; a fair innocent face, with downcast blue eyes, and smiles and blushes coming and going almost with her thoughts; a low soft voice, sweet even in its monosyllables; a dress remarkable for neatness and propriety, and borrowing from her delicate beauty an air of superiority not its own;—such was the outward woman of <persName ref="#HannahWilson">Hannah</persName>. Her mind was very like her person; modest, graceful, gentle, affectionate, grateful, and generous above all. The generosity of the poor is always a very real and fine thing: they give what they want; and <persName ref="#HannahWilson">Hannah</persName> was of all poor people the most generous. She loved to give; it was her pleasure, her luxury. Rosy-cheeked apples, plums with the bloom on them, nosegays of cloves and blossomed myrtle; these were offerings which <persName ref="#HannahWilson">Hannah</persName> delighted to bring to those whom she loved, or those who had shown her kindness; whilst to such of her neighbours as needed other attentions than <rs type="plant" nymRef="plant">fruit</rs> and <rs type="plant" nymRef="floral">flowers</rs>, she would give her time, her assistance, her skill; for <persName ref="#HannahWilson">Hannah</persName> inherited her <rs type="person" ref="#DameWilson">mother's</rs> dexterity in feminine employments, with something of her <rs type="person" ref="#JohnWilson">father's</rs> versatile power. Besides being an excellent laundress, she was accomplished in all the arts of the needle, millinery, dress-making, and plain work; a capital cutter-<pb n="20"/>out, an incomparable mender, and endowed with a gift of altering, which made old things better than new. She had no rival at a <emph><foreign>rifacimento</foreign></emph>,<!--scw: FOR EDITOR'S NOTE: "A new version or remodelling of a literary or artistic work." OED.--> as half the turned gowns on the <placeName type="land">common</placeName> can witness. As a dairy-woman, and a rearer of pigs and poultry, she was equally successful: none of her ducks and turkeys ever died of neglect or carelessness, or, to use the phrase of the poultry-yard on such occasions, of <quote><soCalled>"ill luck."</soCalled></quote><persName ref="#HannahWilson">Hannah's</persName> fowls never dreamed of sliding out of the world in such an ignoble way; they all lived to be killed, to make a noise at their deaths, as chickens should do. She was also a famous <quote><soCalled>"scholar;"</soCalled></quote> kept accounts, wrote bills, read letters, and answered them; was a trusty accomptant, and a safe confidante. There was no end to <persName ref="#HannahWilson">Hannah's</persName> usefulness or <persName ref="#HannahWilson">Hannah's</persName> kindness; and her prudence was equal to either. Except to be kind or useful, she never left her home; attended no fairs, or revels, or Mayings; went no where but to <orgName>church</orgName>; and seldom made a nearer approach to rustic revelry than by standing at her own garden-gate on a Sunday evening, with her little sister in her hand, to look at the lads and lasses on the <placeName type="land">green</placeName>. In short, our <rs type="person" ref="#HannahWilson">village beauty</rs> had fairly reached her twentieth year without a sweetheart, without the slightest suspicion of her having ever written a love-letter on her own account; when, all on a sudden, appearances changed. She was missing at the <quote>"accustomed gate;"</quote><!--scw: I haven't yet been able to identify this quote--> and one had seen a<pb n="21"/><rs type="person" subtype="fict" ref="#WilliamSmith">young man</rs> go into <persName ref="#DameWilson">Dame Wilson's</persName>; and another had descried a <rs type="person" ref="#WilliamSmith">trim elastic figure</rs> walking, not unaccompanied, down a <placeName type="geog">shady lane</placeName>. Matters were quite clear. <persName ref="#HannahWilson">Hannah</persName> had gotten a lover; and, when poor little <persName type="fict" subtype="int" ref="#SusanWilson">Susan</persName>, who, deserted by <rs type="person" ref="#HannahWilson">her sister</rs>, ventured to peep rather nearer to the gay groupe, was laughingly questioned on the subject, the hesitating <said who="#SusanWilson">No</said>, and the half <said who="#SusanWilson">Yes</said>, of the <rs type="person" ref="#SusanWilson">smiling child</rs>, were equally conclusive. </p><p>Since the new marriage act*,<note type="author" anchored="true">It is almost unnecessary to observe that this little story was written during the short life of that whimsical experiment in legislation.</note> we, who belong to <orgName type="person">country magistrates</orgName>, have gained a priority over the rest of the <orgName type="place" subtype="parish" ref="#Shinfield">parish</orgName> in matrimonial news. We (the privileged) see on a work-day the names which the sabbath announces to the generality.<!--scw: FOR EDITOR'S NOTE: MRM is referring to the 1753 Act for the Better Preventing of Clandestine Marriages (also known as the Hardwicke Marriages Act), which sought to prevent clandestine marriages by requiring that banns be posted and that the ceremony take place in a church and according to the Book of Common Prayer. The law was abolished in 1823. Ref in part: Boulton, Jeremy. "Marriage Act." Oxford Companion to British History. Ed. John Cannon. Oxford: Oxford UP, 2009. Oxford Reference. Online. University of Montevallo. --> Many a blushing awkward pair hath our little lame <persName type="fict" subtype="int" ref="#Clerk">clerk</persName> (a sorry <persName type="myth" subtype="ext" ref="#Cupid">Cupid</persName>!) ushered in between dark and light to stammer and hacker, to bow and curtsey, to sign or make a mark, as it pleases Heaven. One Saturday, at the usual hour, the limping <persName ref="#Clerk">clerk</persName> made his appearance; and, walking through our little hall, I saw a <rs type="person" subtype="fict" ref="#WilliamSmith">fine athletic young man</rs>, the very image of health and vigour, mental and bodily, holding the hand of a <rs type="person" ref="#HannahWilson">young woman</rs>, who, with her head half buried in a <rs type="plant" nymRef="floral">geranium</rs> in the window, was turning bashfully away, listening, and yet not seeming to listen, to his tender whispers. The shrinking grace of that <pb n="22"/>bending figure was not to be mistaken. <said who="#OVNarrator">"<persName ref="#HannahWilson">Hannah</persName>!"</said> and she went aside with me, a rapid series of questions and answers conveyed the story of courtship. <said who="#HannahWilson">"<persName ref="#WilliamSmith">William</persName> was,"</said> said <persName ref="#HannahWilson">Hannah</persName>,<said who="#HannahWilson">"a <persName>journeyman hatter</persName> in <placeName>B.</placeName><!--scw: Is it the same B. as mentioned in first sketch with the stagecoach from B. to S.?--> He had walked over one Sunday evening to see the cricketing, and then he came again. <rs type="person" ref="#DameWilson">Her mother</rs> liked him. Every body liked her <persName type="fict" ref="#WilliamSmith">William</persName>—and she had promised—she was going—was it wrong?"</said>— <said who="#OVNarrator">" Oh no!—and where are you to live?"</said>—<said who="#HannahWilson">"<persName ref="#WilliamSmith">William</persName> has got a room in <placeName>B.</placeName> He works for <persName ref="#MrSmiththeHatter">Mr. Smith</persName>, the <rs type="person" ref="#MrSmiththeHatter">rich hatter</rs> in the <orgName>market-place</orgName>, and <persName ref="#MrSmiththeHatter">Mr. Smith</persName> speaks of him—oh, so well! But <persName ref="#WilliamSmith">William</persName> will not tell me where our room is. I suppose in some narrow street or lane, which he is afraid I shall not like, as our <placeName type="land">common</placeName> is so pleasant. He little thinks—any where."</said>—She stopped suddenly; but her blush and her clasped hands finished the sentence, <said who="#HannahWilson">"any where with him!"</said>—<said who="#OVNarrator">"And when is the happy day?"</said>—<said who="#WilliamSmith">"On Monday fortnight, Madam,"</said> said the <rs type="person" ref="#WilliamSmith">bridegroom elect</rs>, advancing with the little <persName type="fict" subtype="int" ref="#Clerk">clerk</persName> to summon <persName ref="#HannahWilson">Hannah</persName> to the parlour, <said who="#WilliamSmith">"the earliest day possible."</said> He drew her arm through his, and we parted.</p><p>The Monday <date dur="P14D">fortnight</date> was a glorious morning; one of those rare <date when="--11">November</date> days when the sky and the air are soft and bright as in <date>April</date>. <said who="#OVNarrator">"What a beautiful day for <persName ref="#HannahWilson">Hannah!</persName>"</said> was the first exclamation of the breakfast table. <said who="#OVNarrator">"Did she tell you where they should dine?"</said><pb n="23"/>—<said>"No, Ma'am; I forgot to ask."</said>—<said>"I can tell you,"</said> said the <persName type="fict" subtype="int" ref="#OVNarratorsFather">master of the house</persName>,<!--tagged as narrator's father, or should it be something else?--> with somewhat of good-humoured importance in his air, somewhat of the look of a man who, having kept a secret as long as it was necessary, is not sorry to get rid of the burthen. <said who="#OVNarratorsFather">"I can tell you: in <placeName ref="#London">London</placeName>."</said>—<said who="#OVNarrator">"In <placeName type="geog" ref="#London">London</placeName>!"</said>—<said who="#OVNarratorsFather">"Yes. <rs type="person" ref="#HannahWilson">Your little favourite</rs> has been in high luck. She has married the <rs type="person" ref="#WilliamSmith">only son of one of the best and richest men in <placeName>B.</placeName>, <persName ref="#MrSmiththeHatter">Mr. Smith</persName>, the great hatter</rs>. It is quite a romance,"</said> continued he: <said who="#OVNarratorsFather">"<persName ref="#WilliamSmith">William Smith</persName> walked over one Sunday evening to see a match at cricket. He saw our pretty <persName ref="#HannahWilson">Hannah</persName>, and forgot to look at the <orgName type="person">cricketers</orgName>. After having gazed his fill, he approached to address her, and the <rs type="person" ref="#HannahWilson">little damsel</rs> was off like a bird. <persName ref="#WilliamSmith">William</persName> did not like her the less for that, and thought of her the more. He came again and again; and at last contrived to tame this <rs type="person" ref="#HannahWilson">wild dove</rs>, and even to get the <foreign><emph>entrée</emph></foreign> of the <placeName type="arch">cottage</placeName>. Hearing <persName ref="#HannahWilson">Hannah</persName> talk, is not the way to fall out of love with her. So <persName ref="#WilliamSmith">William</persName>, at last finding his case serious, laid the matter before <rs type="person" ref="#MrSmiththeHatter">his father</rs>, and requested his consent to the marriage. <persName ref="#MrSmiththeHatter">Mr. Smith</persName> was at first a little startled; but <persName ref="#WilliamSmith">William</persName> is an only son, and an excellent son; and, after talking with me, and looking at <persName type="fict" subtype="int" ref="HannahWilson">Hannah</persName>, (I believe her sweet face was the more eloquent advocate of the two,) he relented; and having a spice of <rs type="person" ref="#WilliamSmith">his son's</rs> romance, finding that he had not mentioned his situation in life, he made a point of its<pb n="24"/> being kept secret till the wedding-day. We have managed the business of settlements; and <persName ref="#WilliamSmith">William</persName>, having discovered that his <rs type="person" ref="HannahWilson">fair bride</rs> has some curiosity to see <placeName type="geog" ref="#London">London</placeName>, (a curiosity, by the bye, which I suspect she owes to you or poor <persName type="fict" subtype="int" ref="#Lucy">Lucy</persName>,) intends taking her tither for a <date dur="P14D">fortnight</date>. He will then bring her home to one of the best houses in <placeName>B.</placeName>, a fine garden, fine furniture, fine clothes, fine servants, and more money than she will know what to do with. Really the surprise of <rs type="person" subtype="hist" ref="#Hoggins_Sarah"><rs type="person" subtype="hist" ref="#Cecil_Henry">Lord E.</rs>'s farmer's daughter</rs>, when, thinking she had married his steward, he brought her to <placeName type="geog" ref="#Burleigh">Burleigh</placeName>, and installed her as its mistress,<!--scw: FOR NOTE: MRM is referring to the story of Henry Cecil, the possibly not-quite divorced heir to the Earl of Exeter who, in 1791, disguised his identity, married Sarah Hoggins (28 June, 1773-26 December, 1797) a Shropshire farmer's daughter from Bolas Magna, lived with her for several years until the death of his uncle the Earl, and only revealed the true state of affairs upon his uncle's death in 1793. Upon assuming his title, Cecil took Sarah to live with him at his seat in Burleigh. She bore three children, and became known as the "Cottage Countess" or "Peasant Countess." She died in 1797. The story of this courtship is told in some detail a weird book published after OV: Thornton Hall, Love Romances of the Aristocracy. London: T. Werner Laurie, n.d. (accessed Project Gutenberg). Other refs: Thepeerage.com. MRM's likely source, if timing checks out, is Hazlitt's Table Talk, New Monthly Magazine, No. IV, Vol. XVII, (1822) "Burleigh House." In it, Hazlitt intimates that Sarah "never recovered" from the shock of the truth. MRM may be referring to a particular source, as the ones I've looked at don't seem to contain anything about Sarah thinking she'd married a steward. Need to check Thomas Moore's poem. Tennyson's poem, "The Lord of Burleigh," wasn't published till 1842. See Millais's illustration of the poem at Victorianweb, which turn Sarah into a romantic heroine. Nothing in ODNB. I have other notes cobbled from other places if necessary. Interesting story. See Julie Shaffer, et. al. A Noble Affair (2013).--> could hardly have been greater. I hope the shock will not kill <persName ref="#HannahWilson">Hannah</persName> though, as is said to have been the case with that <rs type="person" ref="#Hoggins_Sarah">poor lady</rs>."</said>— <said who="#OVNarrator">"Oh no! <persName ref="#HannahWilson">Hannah</persName> loves <rs type="person" ref="#WilliamSmith">her husband</rs> too well. Any where with him!"</said></p><p>And I was right. <persName ref="#HannahWilson">Hannah</persName> has survived the shock. She is returned to <placeName>B.</placeName>, and I have been to call on her. I never saw any thing so delicate and bride-like as she looked in her white gown and her lace mob, in a room light and simple, and tasteful and elegant, with nothing fine except some beautiful <rs type="plant" nymRef="plant">green-house plants</rs>. Her reception was a charming mixture of sweetness and modesty, a little more respectful than usual, and far more shamefaced! Poor thing! her cheeks must have pained her! But this was the only difference. In every thing else she is still the same <persName ref="#HannahWilson">Hannah</persName>, and has lost none of<pb n="25"/> her old habits of kindness and gratitude. She was making a handsome matronly cap, evidently for <rs type="person" ref="#DameWilson">her mother</rs>, and spoke, even with tears, of <rs type="person" ref="#MrSmiththeHatter">her new father's</rs> goodness to her and to <persName ref="#SusanWilson">Susan</persName>. She would fetch the cake and wine herself, and would gather, in spite of all remonstrance, some of her choicest flowers as a parting nosegay. She did, indeed, just hint at her troubles with visitors and servants,—how strange and sad it was! seemed distressed at ringing the bell, and visibly shrank from the sound of a double knock. But, in spite of these calamities, <persName ref="#HannahWilson">Hannah</persName> is a happy woman. The double rap was <rs type="person" ref="#WilliamSmith">her husband's</rs>; and the glow on her cheek, and the smile of her lips and eyes when he appeared, spoke more plainly than ever, <said who="#HannahWilson">"Any where with him!"</said></p></div></body><back><div><listPerson type="hist"><person xml:id="Hobbema"/><person xml:id="Ruydsdael"/><person xml:id="Hoggins_Sarah"/>      <!-- scw: Need to incorporate more in personography from editor's notes.--><person xml:id="Cecil_Henry"/></listPerson><listPerson type="fict" subtype="int"><person xml:id="DameWilson"/><person xml:id="JohnWilson"/><person xml:id="RobertEllis"/><person xml:id="SusanWilson"/><person xml:id="HannahWilson"/><person xml:id="WilliamSmith"/><person xml:id="MrSmiththeHatter"/><person xml:id="Clerk"/><person xml:id="OVNarrator"/><person xml:id="Lucy"/><person xml:id="OVNarratorsFather"/></listPerson><listPlace type="geog"><place xml:id="London_city"/><place xml:id="ThreeMileCross"/>    <!--scw: the town of B is mentioned several times here and elsewhere. Unidentified as yet.--><place xml:id="Burleigh"/></listPlace></div></back></text></TEI>