<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--<?xml-model href="../../../Downloads/SI_Ref_and_Resp.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>--><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><!--<?xml-model href="http://ebeshero.github.io/MRMValidate.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>--><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc>
            <!-- MAH: June 15, so footnotes. Not sure what we've decided to do with this, so I'm just leaving them in the text. -->
            <!--EBB: For Mitford's footnotes, use the <note> element inline with the text (as we've done with notes in the past). The note goes right a the point marked for insertion in the copy-text, and looks like this: <note type="author" anchored="true"> text of note </note>.--><titleStmt><title>Our Village: Sketches of Rural Character and Scenery: Preface</title><author>Mary Russell Mitford</author><editor ref="ad">Alexandra Drayton</editor><editor ref="scw">Samantha Webb</editor><sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford
                    Project</orgName></sponsor><sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor><principal ref="ebb">Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal><respStmt><resp>Transcription and coding by</resp><persName ref="ad">Alexandra Drayton</persName><persName ref="scw">Samantha Webb</persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Proofing and corrections by</resp><persName ref="ebb">Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>This is optional, used to describe this edition, and "should contain
                    phrases describing the edition or version": First digital edition in TEI, date:
                    2 June 2013. P5.</edition><respStmt><resp>We can include a respStmt here.</resp><persName>Who?</persName></respStmt></editionStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority><pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace><date>2013</date><availability><licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0
                        Unported License</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title></seriesStmt><sourceDesc>
                <!--Notice, this is simpler than the sourceDesc we used in our Letters file.--><p>Our text is based on public domain, Google-digitized text<bibl><title>Our Village: Sketches of Rural Character and
                            Scenery</title><edition>Third Edition</edition> by <author>Mary Russell
                            Mitford</author><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><publisher>Geo. B.
                            Whittaker</publisher><placeName>Ave Maria
                            Lane</placeName><date>1825</date>. </bibl> This text appears to be
                    identical in pagination and content to the first edition published in 1824. </p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><p>Describes our editorial practice.</p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><pb n="ii"/><docTitle><titlePart type="main">Our Village:</titlePart><titlePart type="subtitle">Sketches of Rural Character and Scenery.</titlePart></docTitle><byline>by <docAuthor>Mary Russell Mitford</docAuthor>, Author of <title>Julian, A
                        Tragedy</title><lb/></byline><docEdition>Third Edition.</docEdition><docImprint><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><lb/><publisher>Geo. B.
                        Whittaker</publisher>,<lb/><placeName>Ave-Maria-Lane</placeName>.
                        <docDate>1825</docDate>.</docImprint></titlePage><pb n="iii"/></front><body><div type="sketch"><head>OUR VILLAGE.</head><p> Of all situations for a constant residence, that which appears to me most
                    delightful is a little <placeName ref="#ThreeMileCross">village</placeName> far
                    in the country; a small neighbourhood, not of fine <placeName type="arch">mansions</placeName> finely peopled, but
                    of <placeName type="arch">cottages</placeName> and <placeName type="arch">cottage-like houses</placeName>, <quote>"messuages or tenements</quote>," as
                    a <rs type="person">friend of mine</rs> calls such ignoble and non-descript
                    dwellings, with inhabitants whose faces are as familiar to us as the <rs type="plant">flowers</rs> in
                    our <placeName type="land">garden</placeName>; a little world of our own, close-packed
                    and insulated like <orgName>ants</orgName> in an ant-hill, or <orgName>bees</orgName> in a hive, or
                    <orgName>sheep</orgName> in a fold, or <orgName type="person">nuns</orgName> in a convent, or <orgName type="person">sailors</orgName> in a ship; where we know every one, are known to
                    every one, interested in every one, and authorised to hope that every one feels
                    an interest in us. How pleasant it is to slide into these true-hearted feelings
                    from the kindly and unconscious influence of habit, and to learn to know and to
                    love the people about us, with all their peculiarities, just as we learn to know
                    and to love the nooks and turns of the shady <placeName type="geog">lanes</placeName> and
                    sunny <placeName type="land">commons</placeName> that we pass every day. Even in books <persName type="fict" subtype="int" ref="#OVNarrator">I</persName> like
                    a con<pb n="1"/>fined locality, and so do the <rs type="person">critics</rs> when
                    they talk of the unities. Nothing is so tiresome as to be
                    whirled half over <placeName ref="#Europe">Europe</placeName> at the chariot-wheels of a <rs type="person">hero</rs>, to go to sleep at <placeName ref="#Vienna">Vienna</placeName>,
                    and awaken at <placeName ref="#Madrid">Madrid</placeName>; it produces a real fatigue, a
                    weariness of spirit. On the other hand, nothing is so delightful as to sit down
                    in a <placeName type="geog">country village</placeName> in one of <persName type="hist" subtype="ext" ref="#Austen_Jane">Miss Austen</persName>'s delicious novels, quite sure before
                    we leave it to become intimate with every spot and every person it contains; or
                    to ramble with <persName type="hist" subtype="ext" ref="#WhiteGilbert">Mr. White</persName> *<note type="author" anchored="true">* <persName ref="#WhiteGilbert">White</persName>'s
                        <bibl>Natural History and Antiquities of
                            <placeName ref="#Selborne">Selborne</placeName></bibl>; one of the most fascinating
                        books ever written. I wonder that no naturalist has adopted the same
                        plan</note>..--&gt; over his own parish of <placeName type="geog" ref="#Selborne">Selborne</placeName>, and
                    form a friendship with the <placeName type="land">fields</placeName> and
                    <placeName type="land">coppices</placeName>,as well as with the birds, squirrels, who
                    inhabit them; or to sail with <persName type="fict" subtype="ext" ref="#RobinsonCrusoe">Robinson
                        Crusoe</persName> to <placeName type="fict" subtype="ext" ref="#RobinsonCrusoesIsland">his
                            island</placeName>, and live there with him and his goats and his man
                    <persName type="fict" subtype="ext" ref="#Friday">Friday</persName>;—how much we dread any
                    new comers, any fresh importation of savage or
                        sailor! we never sympathise for a moment in <rs type="person" ref="#RobinsonCrusoe">our hero</rs>'s want of company, and are quite grieved when he
                    gets away;—or to be shipwrecked with <persName type="fict" subtype="ext">Ferdinand</persName> on that other <placeName type="fict" subtype="ext" ref="#ProsperosIsland">lovelier island</placeName>—the island of <persName type="fict" subtype="ext" ref="#Prospero">Prospero</persName>, and <persName type="fict" subtype="ext" ref="#Miranda">Miranda</persName>, and <persName type="fict" subtype="ext" ref="#Caliban">Caliban</persName>, and <persName type="fict" subtype="ext" ref="#Ariel">Ariel</persName>, and nobody else, none of <persName type="hist" ref="#Dryden">Dryden</persName>'s exotic inventions;— that is best of all. And a small
                    neighbourhood is as good in sober waking reality as in poetry or prose; a
                        village neighbourhood, such as this <pb n="2"/><placeName type="geog" ref="#Berkshire">Berkshire</placeName><placeName ref="#ThreeMileCross">hamlet</placeName> in which I write, a long, straggling, winding
                    street at the bottom of a fine <placeName type="land">eminence,</placeName> with a road
                    through it, always abounding in carts, <orgName type="person">horsemen,</orgName> and
                    carriages, and lately enlivened by a stage-coach from
                        <!--scw: identify B and S.--><placeName>B——</placeName> to
                        <placeName>S——</placeName>, which passed through about ten days ago, and
                    will I suppose return some time or other. There are coaches of all varieties
                    now-a-days; perhaps this may be intended for a monthly diligence, or a fortnight
                    fly. Will you walk with me through <placeName ref="#ThreeMileCross">our
                        village</placeName>, courteous reader? The journey is not long. We will
                    begin at the lower end, and proceed up the <placeName type="land">hill</placeName>.</p><p> The tidy, square, red cottage on the right hand, with the long well-stocked
                    garden by the side of the road, belongs to a <persName type="fict" subtype="int" ref="#RetiredPublican">retired publican</persName> from a <rs type="place">neighbouring town</rs>; a substantial person with a <persName type="fict" subtype="int" ref="#RetiredPublicansWife">comely wife</persName>; one who piques
                    himself on independence and idleness, talks politics, reads
                    newspapers, hates <rs type="person" subtype="hist">the minister</rs>, and cries out for
                            reform. He
                    introduced into our peaceful vicinage the rebellious innovation of an
                    illumination on <rs type="event" ref="#Qu_Caroline_Affair">the <persName ref="#Queen_Caroline">queen's</persName> acquittal</rs>. Remonstrance and persuasion were in
                    vain; he talked of liberty and broken windows—so we all lighted up. Oh! how he
                    shone that night with candles and laurel, and white bows, and gold paper, and a
                    transparency (originally designed for a pockethandkerchief) with
                    a flaming portrait of <rs type="person" ref="#Queen_Caroline">her Majesty,</rs>
                    hatted and feathered, in red ochre. He had no rival in <pb n="3"/><placeName ref="#ThreeMileCross">the village</placeName>, that we all acknowledged; the
                    very bonfire was less splendid; the <orgName type="person">little boys</orgName> reserved
                    their best crackers to be expended in his honour, and he gave them full sixpence
                    more than any one else. He would like an illumination once a month; for it must
                    not be concealed that, in spite of gardening, of newspaper reading, of jaunting
                    about in his little cart, and frequenting both church and
                    meeting,
                    <rs type="person" ref="#RetiredPublican">our worthy neighbour</rs> begins to feel the weariness of
                    idleness. He hangs over his gate, and tries to entice passengers to stop and
                    chat; he volunteers little jobs all round, smokes cherrytrees to cure the
                    blight, and traces and blows up all the wasp-nests in the <orgName type="place" subtype="parish" ref="#Shinfield">parish</orgName>. I have seen a great many wasps in <placeName type="land">our
                            garden</placeName> to-day, and shall enchant him with the intelligence. He even assists
                        <persName type="fict" subtype="int" ref="#RetiredPublicansWife">his
                        wife</persName> in her sweepings and dustings. Poor man! he is a very
                    respectable person, and would be a very happy one, if he would add a little
                    employment to his dignity. It would be the salt of life to him.</p><p>Next to his house, though parted from it by another <placeName type="land">long garden</placeName> with a
                            <placeName type="land"><rs type="plant" ref="#yew_tree">yew</rs> arbour</placeName> at
                    the end, is the pretty dwelling of the <persName type="fict" subtype="int" ref="#Shoemaker">shoemaker</persName>, a pale, sickly-looking, black-haired
                    man, the very model of sober industry. There he sits in his <orgName ref="#shoemakers_shop">little
                        shop</orgName> from early morning till late at night. An earthquake would
                    hardly stir him: the illumination did not. He stuck immoveably to his last, from
                    the first lighting up, through the long<pb n="4"/> blaze and the slow decay,
                    till his large solitary candle was the only light in the place. One cannot
                    conceive any thing more perfect than the contempt which the <rs type="person" ref="#RetiredPublican">man of
                        transparencies</rs> and the <rs type="person" ref="#Shoemaker">man of shoes</rs> must have felt for each other on
                    that evening. There was at least as much vanity in the sturdy industry as in the
                    strenuous idleness, for our <persName ref="#Shoemaker">shoemaker</persName> is a man of substance, he employs <orgName type="person" ref="#journeymen_shoemakers">three
                    journeymen</orgName>,
                    <rs type="person">two lame</rs>, and one a <rs type="person" subtype="fict">dwarf</rs>, so that his <orgName ref="shoemakers_shop">shop</orgName> looks like an hospital; he
                    has purchased the lease of his commodious dwelling, some even say that he has
                    bought it out and out; and he has only one pretty <persName type="fict" subtype="int" ref="#ShoemakersDaughter">daughter</persName>, a light,
                    delicate, fair-haired girl of fourteen, the champion, protectress, and
                    playfellow of every brat under three years old, whom she jumps, dances, dandles,
                    and feeds all day long. A very attractive person is that <persName ref="#ShoemakersDaughter">child-loving
                        girl</persName>. I have never seen any one in her station who possessed so
                    thoroughly that undefinable charm, the lady-look. See her on a
                    Sunday in her simplicity and her white frock, and she might pass for an earl's
                    daughter. She likes <rs type="plant">flowers</rs> too, and has a
                    profusion of white <rs type="plant" ref="#stock">stocks</rs> under her
                    window, as pure and delicate as herself.</p><p> The first house on the opposite side of the way is the <persName type="fict" subtype="int" ref="#Blacksmith">blacksmith</persName>'s; a gloomy dwelling,
                    where the sun never seems to shine; dark and smoky within and without, like a
                    forge. The <persName ref="#Blacksmith">blacksmith</persName> is a high officer
                    in <placeName ref="#ThreeMileCross">our <pb n="5"/>little state</placeName>, nothing less than a constable;
                    but, alas! alas! when tumults arise, and the <rs type="person" ref="#Blacksmith">constable</rs> is called for, he will commonly be found in the
                    thickest of the fray. Lucky would it be for his <persName type="fict" subtype="int" ref="#BlacksmithsWife">wife</persName> and <orgName type="person" ref="#lacksmithsChildren">her eight children</orgName> if there were no <orgName ref="#public_house">public-house</orgName> in
                    the land: an inveterate inclination to enter those bewitching doors is <rs type="person" ref="#Blacksmith">Mr. Constable's</rs> only fault.</p><p>Next to this official dwelling is a spruce brick tenement, red, high, and narrow,
                    boasting, one above another, three-sash windows, the only sash-windows in the
                    village, with a <rs type="plant" ref="#clematis">clematis</rs> on one side and a
                        <rs type="plant" ref="#rose">rose</rs> on the other, tall and narrow
                    like itself. That slender mansion has a fine genteel look. The little parlour
                    seems made for <!--scw: I believe this might be a reference to Hogarth's "Morning" from the series "Four Times of the Day" (1736), but not entirely sure.--><persName type="hist" subtype="ext" ref="#Hogarth">Hogarth's</persName><persName type="fict" subtype="ext">old maid</persName> and her <persName type="fict" subtype="ext">stunted footboy</persName>; for tea and
                    card-parties,—it would just hold one table; for the
                    rustle of faded silks, and the splendour of <placeName ref="#China">old China</placeName>; for the delight of four
                    by honours, and a little snug quiet scandal between the deals; for affected
                    gentility and real starvation. This should have been its destiny; but fate has
                    been unpropitious: it belongs to a <persName type="fict" subtype="int" ref="#BustlingDame">plump, merry, bustling dame</persName>, with <orgName type="person" ref="#BustlingDamesChildren">four fat, rosy, noisy
                            children</orgName>, the very essence of vulgarity and plenty. </p><p>Then comes the <orgName ref="#village_shop">village shop</orgName>, like other village shops,
                    multifarious as a bazaar; a repository for bread, shoes, tea,
                    cheese, tape, ribands, and bacon; for
                    every thing, in short, except the one particular thing which you happen to want
                    at the moment, and will be sure not to<pb n="6"/>find. The <persName type="fict" subtype="int" ref="#Shopkeeper"/><persName type="fict" subtype="int" ref="#ShopkeepersWife">people</persName> are civil and
                    thriving, and frugal withal; they have let the upper part of their house to
                        <persName type="fict" subtype="int" ref="#ShopkeepersLodger1"/><persName type="fict" subtype="int" ref="#ShopkeepersLodger2">two young women</persName> (one of them is a
                        <persName ref="#ShopkeepersLodger1">pretty blue-eyed girl</persName>) who
                    teach little children their ABC, and make caps and gowns
                    for their mammas,—parcel
                    schoolmistress, parcel
                    mantua-maker. I believe they find adorning the body a
                    more profitable vocation than adorning the mind.</p>
                    <!--the previous paragraph is full of general passing references to multiple people, not sure how or whether give xml:ids to each--><p>Divided from the shop by a narrow yard, and opposite the
                        <orgName ref="shoemakers_shop"><persName ref="#Shoemaker">shoemaker</persName>'s</orgName>, is a habitation of whose
                    inmates I shall say nothing. A cottage—no—a miniature house, with many
                    additions, little odds and ends of places, pantries, and what not; all angles,
                    and of a charming in-and-outness; a little bricked court before one half, and a
                    little flower-yard before the other; the walls, old and weather-stained, covered
                    with <rs type="plant" ref="#hollyhock">hollyhocks</rs>,
                    <rs type="plant" ref="#rose">roses</rs>,
                    <rs type="plant" ref="honeysuckle">honeysuckles</rs>, and a great <rs type="plant" ref="#apricot_tree">apricot-tree</rs>; the casements full of <rs type="plant" ref="#geranium">geraniums</rs>; (ah, there is our superb white cat peeping
                    out from amongst them!) the closets (our <persName type="fict" subtype="int" ref="#landlord">landlord</persName> has the assurance to call them rooms)
                    full of contrivances and corner-cupboards; and the little garden behind full of
                    <rs type="plant">common flowers</rs>,
                    <rs type="plant" ref="#tulip">tulips</rs>,
                    <rs type="plant" ref="#pink">pinks</rs>,
                    <rs type="plant" ref="#larkspur">larkspurs</rs>,
                    <rs type="plant" ref="#peony"><sic>pionies</sic></rs>,
                    <rs type="plant" ref="#stock">stocks</rs>, and <rs type="plant" ref="#carnation">carnations</rs>, with an <placeName type="land">arbour</placeName> of <rs type="plant" ref="#privet">privet</rs>, not unlike a sentry-box, where one
                    lives in a delicious green light, and looks out on the gayest of all gay <rs type="plant">flower-beds</rs>. That house was built on
                    purpose to show in what an exceedingly small compass<pb n="7"/>comfort may be
                    packed. Well, I will loiter there no longer. </p><p>The next tenement is a place of importance, the
                    <orgName ref="#Rose_inn">Rose inn</orgName>; a white-washed
                        building, retired from the road behind its fine swinging sign, with a
                    little bow-window room coming out on one side, and forming, with our
                        stable on the other, a sort of open square, which is
                    the constant resort of carts,
                    waggons, and return chaises. There
                    are two carts there now, and mine
                        <persName type="fict" subtype="int" ref="#RoseInnLandlord">host</persName> is serving them with beer in his eternal red
                    waistcoat. He is a thriving man, and a portly, as his waistcoat attests, which
                    has been twice let our within this twelvemonth. Our
                    <persName ref="#RoseInnLandlord">landlord</persName> has a <persName type="fict" subtype="int" ref="#RoseInnLandlordsWife">stirring wife</persName>, a
                    hopeful <persName type="fict" subtype="int" ref="#RoseInnLandlordsSon">son</persName>, and a <persName type="fict" subtype="int" ref="#Phoebe">daughter</persName>, the
                        <rs type="person" ref="#Phoebe">belle of the village</rs>; not so pretty as the
                        <rs type="person" ref="#ShoemakersDaughter">fair nymph of the shoe-shop</rs>, and far less elegant, but
                    ten times as fine; all curl-papers in the morning, like a porcupine, all curls in the afternoon, like a
                         poodle, with more flounces than curl-papers, and more lovers than
                    curls. <persName ref="#Phoebe">Miss Phoebe</persName> is fitter for
                        town than country; and, to do
                    her justice, she has a consciousness of that fitness, and turns her steps
                        town-ward as often as she can. She is gone to
                        <placeName>B——</placeName>to-day with her last and principal lover, a
                        <persName type="fict" subtype="int" ref="#RecruitingSerjeant">recruiting serjeant</persName>—a man as tall as <bibl corresp="The_Recruiting_Serjeant"><persName type="fict" subtype="ext" ref="#Serjeant_Kite">Serjeant
                            Kite</persName></bibl>, and as impudent. Some day of other he will carry off
                        <persName ref="#Phoebe">Miss Phoebe</persName>.</p><p>In a line with the bow-window room is a low garden-wall, belonging to a house
                    under repair:—the white<pb n="8"/> house opposite the
                    <orgName ref="#collar_makers_shop">collar-maker's shop</orgName>, with four
                        <rs type="plant" ref="#lime_tree">lime-trees</rs> before it, and a
                        waggon-load of bricks at the door. That house is the plaything of a
                    <persName type="fict" subtype="int" ref="#WhimsicalPerson">wealthy, wellmeaning, whimsical person</persName>, who lives about
                    a mile off. He has a passion for brick and mortar, and, being too wise to meddle
                    with his own residence, diverts himself with altering and re-altering, improving
                    and re-improving, doing and undoing here. It is a perfect
                    <bibl corresp="#Odyssey"><persName type="myth" ref="#Penelope">Penelope</persName>'s web</bibl>.<!--scw: FOR EDITOR'S NOTE: In Homer's The Odyssey, Penelope, Odysseus' wife, weaves a tapestry every day, and undoes it every night, in order to delay giving her answer to any one of the suitors requesting her hand in marriage.--><orgName type="person" ref="#OVCarpenters">Carpenters</orgName> and
                    <orgName type="person" ref="#OVBricklayers">bricklayers</orgName> have been at work
                    for these eighteen months, and yet I sometimes stand and wonder whether any
                    thing has really been done. One exploit in last <!--a single month?--><date>June</date> was, however, by no means
                    equivocal. Our <rs type="person" ref="#WhimsicalPerson">good neighbour</rs> fancied that the <rs type="plant" ref="#lime_tree">limes</rs> shaded the rooms, and made them dark, (there was not
                    a creature in the house but the <orgName type="person" ref="#OVWorkmen">workmen</orgName>,) so he had all the
                    leaves stripped from every <rs type="plant">tree</rs>. There they stood, poor
                    miserable skeletons, as bare as <date when="--12-25">Christmas</date> under the glowing midsummer sun.
                    Nature revenged herself, in her own sweet and gracious manner; fresh leaves
                    sprang out, and at nearly Christmas the foliage was as brilliant as when the
                    outrage was committed.</p><p>Next door lives a <persName type="fict" subtype="int" ref="#LizzysFather">carpenter</persName>,
                    <quote>"famed ten miles round, and worthy all his fame,"</quote>—few
                        <orgName type="person" ref="#OVCabinet_makers">cabinet-makers</orgName> surpass him, with his
                    <persName type="fict" subtype="int" ref="#LizzysMother">excellent wife</persName>, and their little daughter
                    <persName type="fict" subtype="fict" ref="#Lizzy">Lizzy</persName>, the <rs type="person" ref="#Lizzy">plaything</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="#Lizzy">queen of the village</rs>, a child
                    three years old according to the register, but six in size and strength and
                    intellect, in power and in self<pb n="9"/>will. She manages every body in the
                    place, her <rs type="person" subtype="fict" ref="#SchoolMistress">school-mistress</rs> included; turns the
                        <orgName type="person">wheeler's children</orgName>out of their own little cart, and
                    makes them draw her; seduces cakes and lollypops from the very
                    <orgName ref="#village_shop">shop</orgName> window; makes the lazy carry her, the silent talk to
                    her, the grave romp with her; does any thing she pleases; is absolutely
                    irresistible. Her chief attraction lies in her exceeding power of loving, and
                    her firm reliance on the love and indulgence of others. How impossible it would
                    be to disappoint the <rs type="person" ref="#Lizzy">dear little girl</rs> when she runs to meet you, slides her
                    pretty hand into yours, looks up gladly in your face, and says, <said who="#Lizzy">"Come!"</said> You must
                    go: you cannot help it. Another part of her charm is her singular beauty.
                    Together with a good deal of the character of <persName type="hist" subtype="ext" ref="#Napoleon">Napoleon</persName>, she has something of his square, sturdy, upright form,
                    with the finest limbs in the world, a complexion purely English, a round
                    laughing face, sunburnt and rosy, large merry blue eyes, curling brown hair, and
                    wonderful play of countenance. She has the imperial attitudes too, and loves to
                    stand with her hands behind her, or folded over her bosom; and sometimes, when
                    she has a little touch of shyness, she clasps them together on the top of her
                    head, pressing down her shining curls, and looking so exquisitely pretty! Yes,
                    <persName ref="#Lizzy">Lizzy</persName> is <rs type="person" ref="#Lizzy">queen of the village</rs>! She has but one rival in
                    her dominions, a certain white greyhound called <persName type="fict" subtype="int" ref="#May-flower">May-flower</persName>,
                    much her friend, who re<pb n="10"/>sembles her in beauty and strength, in
                    playfulness, and almost in sagacity, and reigns over the animal world as she
                    over the human. They are both coming with me, <persName ref="#Lizzy">Lizzy</persName> and
                    Lizzy's <said who="Lizzy">"pretty <persName ref="#May-flower">May</persName>."</said> We are now at the end
                    of <placeName type="geog">the street</placeName>; a <placeName type="geog">cross lane</placeName>, a
                    <placeName type="geog">rope-walk</placeName>, shaded with <rs type="plant" ref="#lime_tree">limes</rs> and
                    <rs type="plant" ref="#oak_tree">oaks</rs>, and a cool clear <placeName type="land">pond</placeName>
                    overhung with <rs type="plant" ref="#elm_tree">elms</rs>, lead us to the bottom of the
                    <placeName type="land">hill</placeName>. There is still one house
                        round the corner, ending in a picturesque
                    <orgName ref="#wheelers_shop">wheeler's shop</orgName>. The
                        dwelling house is more ambitious. Look at the fine
                    flowered window-blinds, the green door with the brass knocker, and the somewhat
                    prim but very civil <persName type="fict" subtype="int" ref="#WheelersWife">person</persName>, who is sending off the
                        <persName type="fict" subtype="int" ref="#Wheeler">labouring man</persName> with sirs and curtsies enough for a
                    prince of the blood. Those are the
                    <persName type="fict" subtype="int" ref="#Curate">curate</persName>'s lodgings—apartments
                    his <rs type="person" ref="#WheelersWife">landlady</rs> would call them: he lives with <orgName type="person">his
                        own family</orgName> four miles off, but once or twice a week he comes to
                    his neat little parlour to write sermons,
                    to marry, or to bury, as the case may
                    require. Never were better or kinder people than his <rs type="person" ref="#Wheeler">host</rs>
                    and <rs type="person" ref="#WheelersWife">hostess</rs>: and there is a reflection of clerical
                    importance about them, since their connection with the
                    <orgName ref="#church">Church</orgName>, which is quite edifying—a decorum, a gravity, a
                    solemn politeness. Oh, to see the worthy <persName ref="#Wheeler">wheeler</persName> carry the
                    gown after his <rs type="person" ref="#Curate">lodger</rs> on a Sunday, nicely pinned up in his
                        <rs type="person" ref="#WheelersWife">wife's</rs> best handkerchief!—or to hear him rebuke a
                    squalling <rs type="person" subtype="fict">child</rs> or a squabbling <rs type="person" subtype="fict">woman</rs>!
                    The <persName ref="#Curate">curate</persName> is nothing to him. He is fit to be perpetual
                    churchwarden.</p><pb n="11"/><p>We must now cross the <placeName type="geog">lane</placeName> into the shady <placeName type="geog">rope-walk</placeName>. That
                        pretty white cottage opposite, which stands
                    straggling at the end of the <placeName ref="#ThreeMileCross">village</placeName> in a
                    <placeName type="land">garden</placeName> full of <rs type="plant">flowers</rs>, belongs
                    to our <persName type="fict" subtype="int" ref="#Mason">mason</persName>, the <rs type="person" ref="#Mason">shortest of men</rs>, and his
                    handsome, tall <persName type="fict" subtype="int" ref="#MasonsWife">wife</persName>: he, a <rs type="person" ref="#Mason">dwarf, with the voice of a giant</rs>; one
                    starts when he begins to talk as if he were shouting through a speaking trumpet;
                    she, the <rs type="person" ref="MasonsWife">sister,
                    daughter, and grand-daughter, of a
                    long line of <orgName type="person" ref="OVGardeners">gardeners</orgName>, and no contemptible one herself</rs>. It
                    is very magnanimous in me not to hate her; for she beats me in my own way, in
                    <rs type="plant" ref="#chrysanthemum">chrysanthemums,</rs> and <rs type="plant" ref="#dahlia">dahlias</rs>, and
                    the like gauds. Her <rs type="plant">plants</rs> are sure to live; mine have a
                    sad trick of dying, perhaps because I love them, <quote>"not wisely, but too
                        well,"</quote><!--scw: FOR EDITOR'S NOTE: These lines are spoken by Othello in Shakespeare's Othello, Act V, scene 2: "...When you shall these unlucky deeds relate, speak of me as I am; nothing extenuate, / Nor set down aught in malice: then you must speak of one that loved not wisely but too well;"--> and kill them with over-kindness. Half-way up the
                    <placeName type="land">hill</placeName> is another <placeName type="arch">detached cottage</placeName>, the residence of an
                    <persName type="fict" subtype="int" ref="#Officer">officer</persName>, and his beautiful <orgName type="person">family</orgName>.
                    That <persName type="fict" subtype="int" ref="#OfficersEldestSon">eldest boy</persName>, who is hanging over the gate, and looking
                    with such intense childish admiration at my <persName ref="#Lizzy">Lizzy</persName>, might be
                    a model for a <persName type="myth" subtype="ext" ref="#Cupid">Cupid</persName>.</p><p>How pleasantly the road winds up the <placeName type="land">hill,</placeName> with its broad
                        green borders and <rs type="plant" ref="#hedge_row">hedge-rows</rs> so
                    thickly timbered! How finely the evening sun falls on that sandy
                        excavated <placeName type="land">bank</placeName>, and touches the 
                            farm-house on the top of the <placeName type="land">eminence</placeName>! and how
                    clearly defined and relieved is the figure of the <persName type="fict" subtype="int" ref="#JohnEvans">man</persName> who
                    is just coming down! It is poor <persName ref="#JohnEvans">John Evans</persName>, the
                        gardener—an excellent gardener till about ten years
                    ago, when he lost his <persName type="fict" subtype="int" ref="#JohnEvansWife">wife</persName>, and became<pb n="12"/> insane.
                    He was sent to <orgName ref="#St_Lukes_Hospital">St. Luke's</orgName>, and dismissed as cured; but his
                    power was gone and his strength; he could no longer manage a garden, nor submit
                    to the restraint, nor encounter the fatigue of regular employment; so he
                    retreated to the <orgName ref="#workhouse">workhouse</orgName>, the pensioner and factotum of the
                    village, amongst whom he divides his services. His mind often wanders, intent on
                    some fantastic and impracticable plan, and lost to present objects; but he is
                    perfectly harmless, and full of a child-like simplicity, a smiling
                    contentedness, a most touching gratitude. Every one is kind to <persName ref="#JohnEvans">John
                        Evans</persName>, for there is that about him which must be loved; and his
                    unprotectedness, his utter defencelessness, have an irresistible claim on every
                    better feeling. I know nobody who inspires so deep and tender a pity; he
                    improves all aroud him. He is useful, too, to the extent of his little power;
                    will do any thing, but loves gardening best, and still
                    piques himself on his old arts of pruning
                    fruit-trees, and raising <rs type="plant" ref="#cucumber">cucumbers</rs>.
                    He is the happiest of men just now, for he has the management of a
                      melon bed—a melon bed!—fie! What a
                    grand pompous name was that for three <rs type="plant">melon plants</rs> under a
                    hand-light! <persName ref="#JohnEvans">John Evans</persName> is sure that they will succeed. We
                    shall see: as the <persName>chancellor</persName> said, <quote>"I
                        doubt."</quote><!--scw: Have not been able to identify this quote.--></p><p> We are now on the very brow of the <placeName type="land">eminence</placeName>, close to the
                            <placeName type="arch">Hill-house</placeName> and <placeName type="land">its
                                beautiful garden</placeName>. On the outer edge of the
                    paling, hanging over the <placeName type="land">bank</placeName>
                    that<pb n="13"/> skirts the <placeName type="geog">road</placeName>, is an old <rs type="plant" ref="#thorn">thorn</rs>—such
                    a <rs type="plant" ref="#thorn">thorn</rs>! The long sprays covered with snowy
                    blossoms, so graceful, so elegant, so lightsome, and
                    yet so rich! There only wants a pool under the <rs type="plant" ref="#thorn">thorn</rs> to give a still lovelier reflection, quivering and
                    trembling, like a tuft of feathers, whiter and greener than the life, and more
                    prettily mixed with the bright blue sky. There should indeed be a
                    pool; but on the dark <placeName type="land">grass-plat</placeName>,
                    under the high <placeName type="land">bank</placeName>, which is crowned by that
                        magnificent plume, there is something that does almost as
                        well,—<persName ref="#Lizzy">Lizzy</persName> and <persName ref="#May-flower">May-flower</persName> in the
                    midst of a game at romps, <quote>"making a sun-shine in the shady
                        place,"</quote><persName ref="Lizzy">Lizzy</persName> rolling, laughing, clapping her hands, and glowing
                    like a <rs type="plant" ref="#rose">rose</rs>;
                    <persName ref="#May-flower">May-flower</persName> playing about her like summer lightning,
                    dazzling the eyes with her sudden turns, her leaps, her bounds, her attacks and
                    her escapes. She darts round the lovely little <rs type="person" ref="#Lizzy">girl</rs>, with
                    the same momentary touch that the swallow skims over the
                    water, and has exactly the same power of flight, the same matchless ease and
                    strength and grace. What a pretty picture they would make; what a pretty
                    foreground they do make to the real landscape! The road winding down the
                        <placeName type="land">hill</placeName> with a slight bend, like that in the
                    <placeName type="geog" ref="#Oxford_High-street">High-street at <placeName type="geog" ref="#Oxford">Oxford</placeName></placeName>; a
                     waggon slowly ascending, and a
                        <rs type="person">horseman</rs> passing it at a full trot—(ah!
                    <persName ref="#Lizzy">Lizzy</persName>,
                    <persName ref="#May-flower">May-flower</persName> will certainly desert you to have a gambol with
                    that blood-horse!) half-way down, just at the turn, the
                        red cottage of the <pb n="14"/><persName type="fict" subtype="int" ref="#Lieutenant">lieutenant</persName>, covered with <rs type="plant" ref="#vine">vines</rs>,
                    the very image of comfort and content; farther down, on the opposite side, the
                        small white dwelling of the little
                    <persName ref="#Mason">mason</persName>; then the <rs type="plant" ref="#lime_tree">limes</rs> and the
                    <placeName type="geog">rope-walk</placeName>; then the <placeName type="geog">village
                        street</placeName>, peeping through the <rs type="plant">trees</rs>, whose
                    clustering tops hide all but the chimneys, and various roofs of the houses, and
                    here and there some angle of a wall: farther on, the elegant town of
                    <placeName>B——</placeName>, with its fine old
                    church-towers and spires; the whole view shut in by a range of
                    <placeName type="land">chalky hills</placeName>; and over every part of the picture, <rs type="plant">trees</rs> so profusely scattered, that it appears like a
                    woodland scene, with <placeName type="land">glades</placeName> and
                        <rs type="place">villages</rs> intermixed. The <rs type="plant">trees</rs>
                    are of all kinds and all hues, chiefly the finely-shaped <rs type="plant" ref="#elm_tree">elm</rs>, of so deep and bright a green, the tips of whose high outer
                    branches drop down with such a crisp and garland-like richness, and the <rs type="plant" ref="#oak_tree">oak</rs>, whose stately form is just now so splendidly adorned
                    by the sunny colouring of the young leaves. Turning again up the
                    <placeName type="land">hill</placeName>, we find ourselves on that peculiar charm of
                    English scenery, a green <placeName type="land">common</placeName>, divided by the road; the
                    right side fringed by <rs type="plant" ref="#hedge_row">hedge-rows</rs> and <rs type="plant">trees</rs>, with cottages and 
                        farm-houses irregularly placed, and terminated by a <placeName type="land">double avenue of
                            noble <rs type="plant" ref="#oak_tree">oaks</rs></placeName>; the left, prettier still, dappled by bright
                    <placeName type="land">pools of water</placeName>, and islands of 
                    <placeName type="arch">cottages</placeName> and <placeName type="land">cottage-gardens</placeName>, and sinking
                    gradually down to <placeName type="land">corn-fields</placeName> and
                    <placeName type="land">meadows</placeName>, and an old
                        farm-house, with pointed roofs and clustered chimneys, looking out<pb n="15"/>from its blooming orchard, and backed by
                    <placeName type="land">woody hills</placeName>. The <placeName type="land">common</placeName> is itself
                    the prettiest part of the prospect; half covered with low <rs type="plant" ref="#furze">furze</rs>, whose golden blossoms reflect so intensely the last beams of
                    the setting sun, and alive with cows and 
                        sheep, and two sets of <orgName type="person" ref="#OVCricketers">cricketers</orgName>: one
                    of young men, surrounded with
                    <orgName type="person">spectators</orgName>, some standing, some sitting, some stretched
                    on the grass, all taking a delighted interest in the game;
                    the other, a <orgName type="person" ref="#OVCountryBoys">merry groupe of little boys</orgName>, at a humble
                    distance, for whom even cricket is scarcely lively enough, shouting,
                    leaping, and enjoying themselves to their hearts' content. But
                        <orgName type="person" ref="#OVCricketers">cricketers</orgName> and <orgName type="person" ref="#OVCountryBoys">country boys</orgName> are too
                    important persons in our <placeName ref="#ThreeMileCross">village</placeName> to be talked of merely
                    as figures in the landscape. They deserve an individual introduction—an essay to
                    themselves—and they shall have it. No fear of forgetting the good-humoured faces
                    that meet us in our walks every day.</p></div></body><back><div><listPerson type="hist"><!--ebb: 30 May 2014: added versions of these from the OVSI.xml file--><person xml:id="Queen_Caroline"/><person xml:id="Austen_Jane"/><person xml:id="White_Gilbert"/><person xml:id="Napoleon"/><person xml:id="Hogarth_William"/> <!--scw: 16 August 2014: Not found in main SI--><person xml:id="Dryden"/></listPerson><listPerson type="fict" subtype="int"><!--ebb: added as stubs to main site index.--><person xml:id="RetiredPublican"/><person xml:id="RetiredPublicansWife"/><person xml:id="Blacksmith"/><!--scw:The blacksmith is also the Constable, so should he be listed as such in a note or listRelation?--><person xml:id="BlacksmithsWife"/><person xml:id="Shoemaker"/><person xml:id="ShoemakersWife"/><person xml:id="ShoemakersDaughter"/><person xml:id="BustlingDame"/><person xml:id="Shopkeeper"/><person xml:id="ShopkeepersWife"/><person xml:id="ShopkeepersLodger1"/><person xml:id="ShopkeepersLodger2"/><person xml:id="RoseInnLandlord"/><person xml:id="RoseInnLandlordsWife"/><person xml:id="RoseInnLandlordsSon"/><person xml:id="Phoebe"/><!--She is the RoseInnLandlords daughter, named--><person xml:id="WhimsicalPerson"/><!--I am not sure this is the best descriptor, I am using MRM's term--><person xml:id="RecruitingSerjeant"/><!--We may also find that some of these people are named later or described more fully as with the RetiredPublican who is MrH--><person xml:id="LizzysFather"/><person xml:id="LizzysMother"/><person xml:id="Lizzy"/><person xml:id="Mayflower"/><person xml:id="Officer"/><person xml:id="OfficersEldestSon"/><person xml:id="Mason"/><person xml:id="MasonsWife"/><person xml:id="Wheeler"/><person xml:id="WheelersWife"/><person xml:id="Curate"/><person xml:id="Lieutenant"/><person xml:id="JohnEvans"/><person xml:id="JohnEvansWife"/><person xml:id="OVNarrator"/></listPerson><listPerson type="fict" subtype="ext"><!--ebb: added as stubs to the site index.--><person xml:id="Robinson_Crusoe"/><person xml:id="Friday"/><person xml:id="Ferdinand"/><person xml:id="Miranda"/><person xml:id="Ariel"/><person xml:id="Prospero"/><person xml:id="Caliban"/><person xml:id="Serjeant_Kite"/> <!--scw: Aug 16, 2014: added today. Character from George Farquhar's The Recruiting Officer of 1703.-->
               

               <!--MANY OF THESE MAY HAVE XML:ID'S ALREADY. I NEED TO CHECK MORE CAREFULLY AGAINST SI FILE.--></listPerson><listPerson type="myth" subtype="ext"><!--ebb: added as stubs to the site index.--><person xml:id="Penelope"/><person xml:id="Cupid"/></listPerson><listPlace><!--ebb: added as stubs to the site index.--><place xml:id="ThreeMileCross"/><place xml:id="Vienna"/><place xml:id="Madrid"/><place xml:id="Berkshire"/><place xml:id="Europe"/><place xml:id="China"/><place xml:id="Selborne"/><place xml:id="Oxford"/><place xml:id="B--"/><place xml:id="S--"/>
          <!--scw: place tags added to this file July 16, 2014: China and Oxford added.--><!-- scw: xml's added for B and S. These could be a couple of places.--></listPlace><listPlace type="fict" subtype="ext"><!--ebb: added as stubs to the site index.--><place xml:id="RobinsonCrusoesIsland"/><place xml:id="ProsperosIsland"/></listPlace><listPlace type="land">  <!--scw: I'm not sure if these need xml:id's and whether they need to be spatialized more within the ID.--><place xml:id="garden"/><place xml:id="common"/><place xml:id="fields"/><!--scw: problem of distinguising between plural and singular, general and specific--><place xml:id="coppices"/><place xml:id="eminence"/><place xml:id="hill"/><place xml:id="double_avenue_of_oaks"/><place xml:id="yew_arbour"/><place xml:id="pond"/><place xml:id="bank"/><place xml:id="grass-plat"/><place xml:id="chalky_hills"/><place xml:id="glades"/><place xml:id="pools_of_water"/><place xml:id="meadows"/><place xml:id="corn_fields"/><place xml:id="woody_hills"/></listPlace><listPlace type="arch"> <!--scw: some of these are specific houses, while others are general. Consider only tagging specifics?--><place xml:id="cottages"/><place xml:id="mansions"/><place xml:id="cottage_like_houses"/><place xml:id="officers_cottage"/><place xml:id="Hill_house"/><place xml:id="detached_cottage"/>
                  <!--scw: note that not all houses are tagged in this text. They can be tagged or untagged later if necessary.--><listPlace type="geog"><place xml:id="lanes"/><place xml:id="street"/><place xml:id="cross_lane"/><place xml:id="rope_walk"/><place xml:id="road"/> <!--scw: the road that skirts the bank.--><place xml:id="village_street"/></listPlace></listPlace><listOrg><listOrg type="person"><org xml:id="OVBricklayers"/><org xml:id="OVCabinet_makers"/><org xml:id="OVCountryBoys"/><org xml:id="OVCricketers"/><org xml:id="journeymen_shoemakers"/><org xml:id="BlacksmithsChildren"/><org xml:id="OVCarpenters"/><org xml:id="BustlingDamesChildren"/><org xml:id="CuratesFamily"/><org xml:id="OVWorkmen"/><org xml:id="WheelersChildren"/><org xml:id="OVGardeners"/><org xml:id="OfficersFamily"/></listOrg><listOrg><org xml:id="shoemakers_shop"/><org xml:id="public_house"/><org xml:id="Rose_inn"/><org xml:id="village_shop"/><org xml:id="collar_makers_shop"/><org xml:id="wheelers_shop"/><org xml:id="church"/><org xml:id="St_Lukes_hospital"/><!--scw: for site Index: St.Luke's Hospital for Lunatics in London.--><org xml:id="workhouse"/><org xml:id="Shinfield"/></listOrg></listOrg><list type="plant"><item xml:id="stocks"/><item xml:id="clematis"/><item xml:id="rose"/><item xml:id="geranium"/><item xml:id="yew_tree"/><item xml:id="hollyhock"/><item xml:id="honeysuckle"/><item xml:id="apricot_tree"/><item xml:id="tulip"/><item xml:id="pink"/><item xml:id="larkspur"/><item xml:id="peony"/><item xml:id="carnation"/><item xml:id="privet"/><item xml:id="lime_tree"/><item xml:id="oak_tree"/><item xml:id="elm_tree"/><item xml:id="chrysanthemum"/><item xml:id="dahlia"/><item xml:id="hedge_row"/><item xml:id="cucumber"/><item xml:id="melon_plant"/><item xml:id="thorn"/><item xml:id="vine"/><item xml:id="furze"/></list><listBibl><bibl xml:id="Nat_Hist_Selborne"/><bibl xml:id="The_Recruiting_Serjeant"/><bibl xml:id="Odyssey"/></listBibl></div></back></text></TEI>