<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<member>
   <header level="main">
      <name>A. Olsen</name>
      <speechCount n="5"/>
   </header>
   <speeches>
      <proceedings fk="202304271000-house">Routine Business</proceedings>
      <speech>
         <p>This statement is dedicated to my sisters, Joni and Heather, my nieces, nephews, cousins, and our relatives in W̱SÁNEĆ and all of our relatives working in bands and administrative offices in First Nations communities across the province and country.</p>
         <p>HÍSW̱ḴE SIÁM.</p>
      </speech>
      <proceedings fk="202304271000-house">Routine Business</proceedings>
      <speech>
         <p>First, Mr. Speaker, a bit of business.</p>
         <p>This week I became agitated in a committee for pay-transparency legislation. For that, I apologize to the Chair from Richmond-Steveston; I apologize to my colleague in the official opposition, in Kelowna-Mission; and I also apologize to the Minister of Finance, her staff, Hansard staff, anyone watching and to my colleagues attending to their House duty.</p>
         <p>I try to raise my points without raising my voice, and this week, I failed.</p>
      </speech>
      <proceedings fk="202304271000-house">Routine Business</proceedings>
      <speech>
         <p>I’ve noted several times the administration and financial burden this government puts on Indigenous communities through our consultation policies. The steady flow of referrals comes with meagre financial resources, time constrained to 30 days to respond and a policy of silence being compliance.</p>
         <p>My heart here is for my relatives, who work so hard on behalf of our communities — one or two often showing up to meetings with government officials, sitting across the table from a half dozen technical staff from the ministry. Then, after only a short break, they find themselves at yet another table, on a different topic and with a new group of government workers — always outnumbered, always out-resourced.</p>
         <p>They inspire me to stand in here and demand government recognize the crushing workload that we are creating and the psychological trauma that is sustained from it. We love our communities, and we want to flourish. We are proud and passionate, and as the government referrals clog our in-boxes, it’s overwhelming.</p>
         <p>When legislation is introduced, it creates another stream of consultation referrals. The minister introducing that legislation should be required to have the resources that can be provided to First Nations to do their technical and their legal work, because it makes for better work.</p>
         <p>HÍSW̱ḴE SIÁM.</p>
      </speech>
      <proceedings fk="202304271000-house">Routine Business</proceedings>
      <speech>
         <p>My question is to the Premier. Will he commit to a full, comprehensive review of the Mental Health Act?</p>
      </speech>
      <proceedings fk="202304271000-house">Routine Business</proceedings>
      <speech>
         <p>I was listening to the Minister of Mental Health and Addictions, and that was a long way of not saying no.</p>
         <p>The reality is that the two committees that have made recommendations didn’t make recommendations to ensure the operation of the act. Those two committees called for a full review of the Mental Health Act. The language was very clear. It had nothing to do with ensuring the operation of the act.</p>
         <p>In fact, the Minister of Public Safety and Solicitor General chose to talk about how effective that committee process was on a variety of other issues around policing. So what we have is a government that is picking and choosing the recommendations that suit their purpose, rather than listening to the good work that’s done by members from all sides of this House.</p>
         <p>We’re expanding access to mental health care, investing billions of dollars in an outdated act. Our understanding of mental health and substance use disorders has changed drastically in the last decade, yet B.C.’s Mental Health Act hasn’t been substantially updated for 60 years.</p>
         <p>We can’t rely on a broken legislative framework while trying to tackle a modern mental health crisis. Stakeholders, advocates, experts, officers of the Legislature, including the Ombudsperson and the Representative for Children and Youth, and two committees of this House have tasked this government with updating the Mental Health Act. The most recent recommended a comprehensive review within six months of the report’s release — that was the Health Committee — meaning Monday, May 1, of this year.</p>
         <p>My question is again to the Premier. Will this government heed the advice of the stakeholders, the experts, the all-party committees and urgently initiate a full review of B.C.’s Mental Health Act?</p>
      </speech>
   </speeches>
</member>
