<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<member>
   <header level="main">
      <name>E. Ross</name>
      <speechCount n="2"/>
   </header>
   <speeches>
      <proceedings fk="202304271000-house">Routine Business</proceedings>
      <procedure>Introductions by Members</procedure>
      <speech>
         <p>Last year I was leaving my apartment here in Victoria and somebody was yelling my name, which is not unusual. In this case, it was friends from Kitimat, who actually moved to Victoria. They were both born and raised in Kitimat, B.C. They spent their working careers with Rio Tinto Alcan, which is an aluminum smelter, both in Kitimat and Kemano. Kemano is the power source for the smelter in Kitimat. They chose to retire to Victoria, B.C.</p>
         <p>Susan and Perry Minaker live just up the street from us with their dog, who I’ve met as well. They also have a son, who is a retinal surgeon currently working at Chicago Rush Hospital in the U.S.A., and a daughter, who is a pharmacist and currently working for Shoppers Drug Mart and lives also in Victoria, B.C.</p>
         <p>Would the House please make them feel welcome.</p>
      </speech>
      <proceedings fk="202304271000-house">Routine Business</proceedings>
      <procedure>Introductions by Members</procedure>
      <speech>
         <p>In the House today we have Collen Middleton. Collen Middleton is an environmental scientist with over 18 years in the professional consulting services industry. He got involved in public safety advocacy after moving to south Nanaimo two years ago with his wife and two young boys. Upon discovering how unsafe the streets in his neighbourhood had become in the years prior to moving to the city, he felt unable to sit idly by and watch it continued to deteriorate.</p>
         <p>Collen Middleton is also here to participate in the Enough Is Enough rally that’s going to happen on the Legislature lawn today. Collen is the founder and president of the Nanaimo Area Public Safety Association and is determined to see crime and street disorder improve in his city through advocacy and activism. He and his association will rattle whatever cages they need to, to improve the situation on the streets for the sake of his family, neighbours, fellow citizens of Nanaimo and British Columbians broadly.</p>
         <p>Would the House please welcome Collen Middleton.</p>
      </speech>
   </speeches>
</member>
