<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<member>
   <header level="main">
      <name>E. Sturko</name>
      <speechCount n="2"/>
   </header>
   <speeches>
      <proceedings fk="202304271000-house">Routine Business</proceedings>
      <speech>
         <p>You know, this government has been stoking the flames of the fire of crime, chaos and social disorder occurring in this province. Now, two terms and six years later, when that fire is burning out of control, they’re finally, finally trying to scramble to put the fire out.</p>
         <p>Collen Middleton is an organizer of the Enough Is Enough rallies that started in Nanaimo over a year ago, and they’re happening today across this province. He’s present in the gallery today, and he says that the Premier’s policies have “created a monster, a positive feedback loop of addiction and suffering.”</p>
         <p>In many ways, Nanaimo has become ground zero for the crisis plaguing communities across this province. Violent crime has more than doubled in that community. Just yesterday a popular downtown coffee shop had its windows smashed, and that was the seventh time it’s been vandalized in just one month. Enough Is enough.</p>
         <p>How much longer must communities like Nanaimo endure the violence and total disorder caused by this Premier’s failed catch-and-release policies?</p>
      </speech>
      <proceedings fk="202304271000-house">Routine Business</proceedings>
      <speech>
         <p>I agree with the Solicitor General. Police are doing a great job. Police are doing a great job, and it’s this government that is failing the police, failing them, failing to address the social and behavioural issues that are causing chaos, failing to address the substance use issues in this province, failing to provide the direction needed by the courts in this province. Enough is enough. Enough is enough. People across this province are saying: “Enough is enough. Enough.”</p>
         <p>When will this soft-on-crime Premier end his catch-and-release justice system? At the rally in Penticton, they say: “Rampant crime has left us feeling victimized, and pervasive evidence of homelessness has resulted in each of us feeling hopeless and vulnerable. Our concerns lie in the total lack of appropriate and successful management of those issues by the government.”</p>
         <p>Penticton is the community that the Premier threatened as Housing Minister. He bullied the community, saying that if they didn’t accept his plan to warehouse people with severe mental health and addictions issues without proper supports, that he would send 1,000 tents and sleeping bags to create a tent city.</p>
         <p>What does this Premier have to say to communities like Penticton and Nanaimo who are now suffering the ongoing consequences of his failed social and justice policies?</p>
      </speech>
   </speeches>
</member>
