<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<member>
   <header level="main">
      <name>Hon. M. Farnworth</name>
      <speechCount n="17"/>
   </header>
   <speeches>
      <proceedings fk="202304271000-house">Routine Business</proceedings>
      <speech>
         <p>I thank the Leader of the Opposition for the question. This government, as every government across this country, takes the issue of public safety and the challenges that we have seen of some of the increase in crime rates very seriously.</p>
         <p>That’s why it was this government that led the charge at the federal level to get changes to the Criminal Code when it comes to bail, to expand the terms of reverse onus, so that it’s not just for firearms but is in fact a much broader definition of a weapon used in violent crime and also taking into account previous violence by the offender.</p>
         <p>We worked with other Premiers of political stripes right across this country. The federal government, the Justice Minister made a commitment to us that those changes would be put in place in this legislative session in Ottawa.</p>
         <p>At the same time, this government, as the member well knows, has done what we can do in the province, investing the largest amount of money into new police officers for small rural communities across the province, the specialized investigation teams that are crucial, the largest investment in RCMP funding. There’s over $1 billion in the budget for mental health supports right across the full spectrum, and housing initiatives.</p>
         <p>We take this issue very seriously. People in this province deserve to feel safe, and we will continue to make sure that they are.</p>
      </speech>
      <proceedings fk="202304271000-house">Routine Business</proceedings>
      <speech>
         <p>Again, I thank the member for the question. The actions that he described are illegal. They were illegal seven years ago. They are illegal today, and the police do their job every day to ensure that those individuals are arrested.</p>
         <p>What I also want to make clear is that this government has been taking action since day one. The largest investments in policing in the history of this province…</p>
      </speech>
      <proceedings fk="202304271000-house">Routine Business</proceedings>
      <speech>
         <p>…to put police in communities is not a radical agenda. Putting in place a witness protection program that has resulted in prosecution after prosecution and the solving of cold cases is not a radical agenda.</p>
         <p>Putting in place a forensic firearms lab so that police are able to build a stronger case is not a radical agenda. Putting in place more than $1 billion for mental health supports is not a radical agenda. Putting in place housing initiatives, which did not take place when that side sat on this side, is not a radical agenda.</p>
         <p>It is a public safety agenda, designed to put in place the tools police have asked for, working with local communities to put in place the resources that they have been needing, and at the same time going to Ottawa.</p>
         <p>This province is taking the leadership role to get the Criminal Code changed, so that those who are violent offenders are not given bail. That is not a radical agenda. That is a public safety agenda that we will continue.</p>
      </speech>
      <proceedings fk="202304271000-house">Routine Business</proceedings>
      <speech>
         <p>I appreciate the question from the member, who also sat on this side of the House and who, as Attorney General, when he was Attorney General, knows that the Criminal Code is a federal responsibility.</p>
         <p>He also knows, as does the opposition, the challenges that we face in this province and that every other province is facing when it comes to the issues of violence and public safety. We have seen it on our transit system here and in Edmonton and Calgary and Toronto, right across this country. It’s why this government has worked with other provinces to get the federal government to change the Criminal Code. That is taking place.</p>
         <p>At the same time, we also know, on the social side in terms of the opioid epidemic, which was taking place when they sat on this side of the House, that it’s taking place again right across this country.</p>
      </speech>
      <proceedings fk="202304271000-house">Routine Business</proceedings>
      <speech>
         <p>It is. It is.</p>
      </speech>
      <proceedings fk="202304271000-house">Routine Business</proceedings>
      <speech>
         <p>The member will know that this side of the House worked on the all-party committee to come up with solutions, initiatives and approaches, which all of us in this chamber agreed upon. Many of those things have been implemented. Decriminalization was part of that.</p>
         <p>At the same time, we also know that there needed to be significant increase in mental health services and supports — $1 billion in this budget to do just that. Whether it is the social side or the enforcement side, all four pillars are required to deal with this challenge that we face in this province. This government is putting the tools in place that police need and that health authorities need. We are doing everything we can to ensure that our communities are safe.</p>
      </speech>
      <proceedings fk="202304271000-house">Routine Business</proceedings>
      <speech>
         <p>I appreciate the question from my colleague across the way. I have pointed out to this House the initiatives undertaken by our government, that our Premier has led, in terms of ensuring that we are doing everything we can in terms of public safety by working with the police, the men and women on the ground who deal with these situations every day, and giving them the tools that they, the experts on the street, ask for.</p>
         <p>We have worked with local governments to deal with the specific challenges that they face in their individual communities. That’s why we put in place the hubs across the province, the 12 hubs. It’s why we’ve expanded the car program, the mental health supports, the peer-assisted care teams, and we will continue to do that. It’s also why, as I’ve said, we went to Ottawa to get changes to the Criminal Code.</p>
         <p>But it is much more than that that’s required. It’s also dealing with the mental health side of things. Since this government took office, in 2017, not only have we been investing in mental health supports, but we have also been undoing the damage, the very damage that….</p>
      </speech>
      <proceedings fk="202304271000-house">Routine Business</proceedings>
      <speech>
         <p>Oh, I hear the member of the opposition.</p>
      </speech>
      <proceedings fk="202304271000-house">Routine Business</proceedings>
      <speech>
         <p>Let me put it this way. We invested in mental health facilities.</p>
         <p>We didn’t close the adolescent psychiatric unit in Abbotsford. We didn’t eliminate psychology services for adult rehabilitation at the Royal Inland Hospital. We didn’t close the only withdrawal management program in the Fraser Valley. We didn’t cut the social work budget in the Fraser health region. We didn’t close the Waddell’s Haven Guest Home in Mission, a residential mental health facility that provides addiction services. We didn’t close the 11 residential care beds at Bear Creek Lodge, at Newton Regency in Surrey.</p>
      </speech>
      <proceedings fk="202304271000-house">Routine Business</proceedings>
      <speech>
         <p>We’ve invested in mental health services, and we will continue. I’m sorry that they don’t like their record, but that’s a fact.</p>
      </speech>
      <proceedings fk="202304271000-house">Routine Business</proceedings>
      <speech>
         <p>What I will tell the Leader of the Opposition from that comment is the men and women on the front line in our province, the police officers, do an amazing job every single day. The mental health workers in our province do an incredible job every single day. This government gives those men and women the tools that they have been asking for to do that job.</p>
      </speech>
      <proceedings fk="202304271000-house">Routine Business</proceedings>
      <speech>
         <p>It is this government — under the leadership of our Premier and Attorney General, when he was Attorney General — that went to Ottawa. We put on the table, we put on the agenda, the need to make changes to the Criminal Code to deal with the unintended consequences of the changes that were made to the Criminal Code when it came to bail reform.</p>
         <p>We said: “We’re experiencing an increase in violence. It’s related to those changes — the inability to keep people behind bars when they should be.” Other provinces agreed with us. Whether it was Alberta, Saskatchewan, Manitoba, Ontario, we were all on the same page.</p>
         <p>We made it clear that changes need to be made. We received the commitment from the federal government to get those change so that we have an expanded definition on reverse onus so that if you’re using a weapon, you could be denied bail; if you have a history of violence, you could be denied bail. Those are changes that police wanted to see. Those are changes that we asked for. Those are changes that we’re going to get. We are committed to making communities safe, and we’ll do everything we can to ensure that happens.</p>
      </speech>
      <proceedings fk="202304271000-house">Routine Business</proceedings>
      <speech>
         <p>I appreciate the question from the member. Right from day one, this Premier, this government, has taken public safety incredibly seriously, from putting in place the very tools that police have been asking for, which is what the member says we need to do.</p>
         <p>Right from day one, we put in place the witness security program, modelled for the situation here in British Columbia that’s resulted in more than 32 cold case convictions of individuals being charged and now behind bars where they belong. Putting in place the first forensic firearms lab so that….</p>
      </speech>
      <proceedings fk="202304271000-house">Routine Business</proceedings>
      <speech>
         <p>Well, hon. Member, when you say that nothing is being done, I’m going to point out to you everything that is being done.</p>
         <p>That forensic firearms lab saved police time and money, and it allowed them to build stronger cases to put those kinds of people behind bars where they belong.</p>
         <p>The largest investment in policing in the history of this province to hire 277 additional RCMP officers for communities right across the province, communities that that side of the House asked for, whether it is Kelowna, whether it is Cranbrook, whether it is Terrace. That’s where they’re going — to those communities. This side of the House is taking action, and we will continue to take action to ensure our communities are safe.</p>
      </speech>
      <proceedings fk="202304271000-house">Routine Business</proceedings>
      <speech>
         <p>I appreciate the question from the member. Everyone deserves to be safe, and no one should have to deal with the situation that the member outlined. I can tell the honourable member that the two individuals that dug up that weapon were, in fact, arrested by the police. I hope that they are charged.</p>
         <p>I’ve also outlined the actions that this government is taking by working with police, working with communities, working with the federal government. I want to remind that member, because he was a cabinet minister at one time, that the Criminal Code is not a policy. The Criminal Code of Canada is federal law. Rulings are made by the Supreme Court of Canada. That’s not a policy; that’s a fact.</p>
         <p>What I can tell you is that we’ve needed changes to that Criminal Code, and it is this side of the House that has pushed to get those changes and a commitment from the federal government to change it so that those kinds of individuals can be held.</p>
      </speech>
      <proceedings fk="202304271000-house">Routine Business</proceedings>
      <speech>
         <p>Thank you, hon. Speaker.</p>
         <p>When it comes to the social side and looking at the impacts and recognizing that you make investments early on, what did that member and his colleagues think when they sat on this side of the House and cut $187½ million from child and family protection, or $34½ million from youth justice, youth services and youth and child mental health? Those were cuts that had consequences down the road.</p>
      </speech>
      <proceedings fk="202304271000-house">Routine Business</proceedings>
      <speech>
         <p>This government is investing in mental health services, investing in health, in housing, and in criminal justice reform to ensure that we are able to deal with those problems and keep our communities safe.</p>
      </speech>
   </speeches>
</member>
