<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<member>
   <header level="main">
      <name>M. Elmore</name>
      <speechCount n="2"/>
   </header>
   <speeches>
      <proceedings fk="202304271000-house">Routine Business</proceedings>
      <procedure>Introductions by Members</procedure>
      <speech>
         <p>We have a number of representatives today from the Filipino community across British Columbia. They are here to mark April 27, which will be proclaimed as Lapu-Lapu Day. I’m not going to introduce everybody individually, but I would like to give a very warm welcome to the Philippine consul general, Arlene Magno; the Philippine Consulate General cultural officer, Maria Lyra Ocampo; and Philippine consulate staff, Arnel Anacion.</p>
         <p>I invite all members of the House to join at 11:30 at the Rattenbury Room for the proclamation.</p>
         <p>I ask everybody to please give them a very warm welcome.</p>
      </speech>
      <proceedings fk="202304271000-house">Routine Business</proceedings>
      <speech>
         <p>Today, April 27, will be proclaimed as Lapu-Lapu Day in B.C.</p>
         <p>The history of the Philippines is a saga of unrelenting resistance against foreign colonization and domination. It is an unbroken epic of struggle for freedom, self-determination, independence and national sovereignty.</p>
         <p>The Philippines was a colony of Spain for more than 300 years. Based on historical accounts, at least 200 revolts broke out during this time. Filipinos took up arms to rebel against the imposition of levies, forced labour, land grabbing, commercial monopolies and other unjust practices. These uprisings culminated in a nationalist revolution, which succeeded in 1898, with the declaration of national independence by the Philippines.</p>
         <p>I recall all of these, because the struggle against foreign subjugation began on the shores of Mactan-Cebu in central Philippines, my mom’s home province, where an Indigenous leader named Lapu-Lapu refused to bow down to Spanish rule. On April 27, 1521, Lapu-Lapu and his warriors repulsed a Spanish expeditionary force, commanded by Portuguese explorer Ferdinand Magellan, in an assertion of liberty against foreign rule, and 502 years ago this day, Lapu-Lapu stood unbowed before invaders, so that he and his people could remain free.</p>
         <p>Lapu-Lapu is thus recognized as the first national and Indigenous hero, with April 27 designated as a special holiday in the Philippines.</p>
         <p>The legacy of Lapu-Lapu runs deep in the psyche of Filipinos. It lives in their deep-seated value of bayanihan, which is made up of two words: bayan, which means community, and bayani, which means hero. Bayanihan is the communal desire and act of helping one another, of being connected with others.</p>
         <p>I’d like to extend an invitation for everyone here to join the proclamation at 11:30 in the Rattenbury Room and 2 p.m. on Saturday at the Bayanihan Centre in Victoria. There’s a production by the very talented Francis Matheu.</p>
         <p>Mabuhay. [Filipino was spoken.] Thank you, everybody. Let’s hear it for Lapu-Lapu Day. Mabuhay.</p>
      </speech>
   </speeches>
</member>
