<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<member>
   <header level="main">
      <name>M. Lee</name>
      <speechCount n="1"/>
   </header>
   <speeches>
      <proceedings fk="202304271000-house">Routine Business</proceedings>
      <procedure>Introductions by Members</procedure>
      <speech>
         <p>I would like to, on behalf of the Minister of Municipal Affairs and myself, welcome two guests that we have in the gallery here today behind me, I understand. That is Chris Chan and Stella Chan. Chris and Stella recently participated in the 50th anniversary gala, which the Minister of Municipal Affairs and myself were at, for SUCCESS. They’re celebrating 50 years, as both the members for Richmond-Queensborough and Richmond North Centre have commemorated in this place, in terms of the importance of SUCCESS as an organization.</p>
         <p>Stella is someone who has been the honorary chair of the SHINE Mother’s Day Tea gala, as well as the founding chair. She has also been the co-chair of the Chinese-Canadian Miracle Weekend committee of the B.C. Children’s Hospital Foundation. She serves on the board of directors for Women in Primerica, an organization.</p>
         <p>Chris Chan is the managing broker of Regent Park Realty. He served on the board of directors for St. Mark’s College at the University of British Columbia’s Corpus Christi College. Members that participated yesterday in the Parliamentary Reform Committee were addressing some potential changes to their governing legislation. He’s also a past vice-chair of the SUCCESS foundation.</p>
         <p>One other note that I wanted to make here is that Chris and Stella clearly are just other good examples of individuals that have strong professional careers but also do a lot to give back to community. That’s been a fine example to their son, Arthur, who, as some of you may know, was diagnosed with leukemia at the age of 3½ years old. He spent the next 3½ years in chemo and made a full recovery. He is a healthy and strong Sauder grad at UBC. He is also the president and co-founder of another organization called Dare to Dream Destiny Foundation, which was founded in 2015 and strives for progressive change in society.</p>
         <p>I would just ask all members of this House to join me and the Minister of Municipal Affairs to welcome Chris and Stella Chan to our House.</p>
      </speech>
   </speeches>
</member>
