<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<member>
   <header level="main">
      <name>P. Milobar</name>
      <speechCount n="14"/>
   </header>
   <speeches>
      <proceedings fk="202304271000-house">Orders of the Day</proceedings>
      <speech>
         <p>Again, I’ll recognize…. I am well aware that there are a lot of clauses to do with the Greenhouse Gas Industrial Reporting and Control Act within Bill 10. We go up to clause 46, and we’re only on 19. I may be touching on a clause that might be ahead, but it’s still on the same theme.</p>
         <p>I’m just trying to get some better understanding of the process the minister is planning on embarking on when the bill gets enacted, given that we’re going to be in, best-case scenario, a year’s worth of limbo as we try to bring on board the OBPS system that these sections are going to lay the groundwork for.</p>
         <p>The first process that B.C. was operating under, in terms of industrial credits — it would be net 30 of the greenhouse gas tax or carbon tax — actually wound up being a year or two behind schedule, by the time all the negotiations were done between the government and the individual industries on coming up with what was deemed to be an agreed-upon, world-leading emissions standard that the industry would have to meet to be able to qualify to pay $30 a tonne in carbon tax instead of $50.</p>
         <p>We don’t have the OBPS in front of us. It’s still being crafted and worked on. It’s my understanding those discussions still need to take place, in terms of how this will all work within British Columbia.</p>
         <p>What is the timeline — the minister’s expectation — to have this in place and to be ready for next year’s budget — and, more importantly, so that industry also knows what to expect heading into next year’s budget?</p>
      </speech>
      <proceedings fk="202304271000-house">Orders of the Day</proceedings>
      <speech>
         <p>Given the uncertainty and the missed timelines previously, what is the fallback position if there is not something in place in time, as the minister just laid out?</p>
      </speech>
      <proceedings fk="202304271000-house">Orders of the Day</proceedings>
      <speech>
         <p>I’ll get into the dollars side of this whole sphere in estimates, recognizing that this isn’t estimates. It’s more to deal with the technical side of implementation.</p>
         <p>In terms of the work that will be undertaken, I’m assuming, by this ministry but also by the Ministry of Environment or other ministries…. The Ministry of Finance seems to be appropriate for setting out these schedules of emissions standards.</p>
         <p>It seems that there still needs to be a lot of work done in terms of consultation with industry. There are also business groups seeking to be afforded the opportunity to provide their input. Is it the expectation of the minister that the feedback being sought, and the discussions that will happen, to develop the OBPS system will be strictly industry-based? Will there also be industry associations meaningfully worked with as well?</p>
         <p>I’ll cite one in particular. The Business Council of B.C. has actually written to the province, seeking consultation on the OBPS.</p>
      </speech>
      <proceedings fk="202304271000-house">Orders of the Day</proceedings>
      <speech>
         <p>Part of the other concern that we’ve been hearing is that this will be done in an open and transparent way. We’ve heard that from both industry but we’ve also heard it from environmental groups trying to get an understanding of how this will be rolled out, how those discussions and what the inputs into the final decisions are and how they are arrived at.</p>
         <p>Will the groups that are being engaged with be required to be signing NDAs or will they be free to discuss, with their associations and the broader public, updates of where they feel things are heading with discussions with government?</p>
      </speech>
      <proceedings fk="202304271000-house">Orders of the Day</proceedings>
      <speech>
         <p>Certainly I think we all recognize the need for some, especially on the protected information, especially on an industry when its competitive.</p>
         <p>That kind of leads into my next question around competitiveness, because that’s a key piece of all of this. How we keep British Columbia industry competitive with the rest of North America and, indeed, the world? Especially when you’re talking natural resources. It truly is a global market you’re competing with a lot of times, depending on the commodity.</p>
         <p>It appears that this year…. Again, this is out of a BCBC report on the OBPS. They’re saying that, this year, absent this new system in place, we’ll have about a $27.83 a tonne disadvantage in comparison to California and Quebec. It actually goes up when you can compare it with electricity only in certain jurisdictions in North America.</p>
         <p>I guess I say — in framing up the concern, I guess, with the discussions and the length of time — that that competitiveness each year starts to tip, especially against American jurisdictions, especially with the new IRA act down in the U.S.</p>
         <p>Next year, when the minister has indicated the new system will be in place in time for the start of the fiscal, carbon tax will be $80 a tonne. It will have gone from $65 to $80. So the march to $170 is going to be upon us very quickly and very fast.</p>
         <p>That means big dollars involved as well. So that’s why I think there’s this worry about transparency out there. If you use LNG alone, just on their first phase, with $170 carbon tax and with the new suggested parameters…. Both the Minister of Environment and the Minister of Finance have indicated that if you meet your benchmark, you pay zero. That’s about $680 million a year just to that one project of carbon tax that’s waived. It’s about $27 billion over the 40-year span of that project.</p>
         <p>It starts to be very big, big dollars when you’re talking industry. That’s why I think there’s a mood within industry to make sure that it’s being dealt with properly because of the competitive side. But there’s also a mood on the environmental organization side to make sure that things are being done to the standard that will see actual meaningful improvement to emission profiles.</p>
         <p>Will recognized environmental groups also be a part of those same tables that industry is sitting at, or will they not be included in the development of the OBPS?</p>
      </speech>
      <proceedings fk="202304271000-house">Orders of the Day</proceedings>
      <speech>
         <p>Within Bill 10, or, I guess, by extension, flowing over to the budgets…. Under the current system, there has always been a dollar figure somewhat attached to the expected dollars associated with the carbon tax offset for industry. Is there anything in Bill 10 that would cap the dollars available for industry under the new OBP system, or will it just be if you meet the standard, you qualify, and the dollar figure is somewhat irrelevant?</p>
         <p>As I say, based on current emission profiles, at $170 a tonne, it will be somewhere in the neighbourhood of $8 billion or $10 billion of carbon tax technically being collected in British Columbia. But under OBPS, that’s obviously going to remove a large portion of those dollars.</p>
         <p>Is there a cap? Is it going to be capped at $5 billion, $4 billion, that could be returned back to industry, or is it just if industry qualifies, they qualify, and the dollar figure is somewhat irrelevant in that equation?</p>
      </speech>
      <proceedings fk="202304271000-house">Orders of the Day</proceedings>
      <speech>
         <p>I’ll take it from that, then, there’s no cap on the dollars, which makes sense.</p>
         <p>In terms of the overall…. Sorry, I was jumping ahead. You weren’t answering that question.</p>
         <p>Actually, you know what? That’s probably good through clause 47. I’ll pick things up on clause 48 with a different section.</p>
      </speech>
      <proceedings fk="202304271000-house">Orders of the Day</proceedings>
      <speech>
         <p>Again, I’ve covered off most of the information-sharing types of questions that are in this bill en masse with the previous questions I was asking.</p>
         <p>The only…. On this specific one, with the homeowner grant, is there anything within these clauses in Bill 10 that is designed to interface with, or has been created to expressly do that with, the federal government, given that their change to federal tax forms, income tax forms, now requires you to start stating information about your primary residence in terms of date of ownership and things of that…? Is there anything that starts to interconnect based on the changes in Bill 10?</p>
      </speech>
      <proceedings fk="202304271000-house">Orders of the Day</proceedings>
      <speech>
         <p>Okay. To be clear, then, the ability to interface with that new piece of information that the federal government is collecting…. The provincial government has access to that information and can start trying to link it in with homeowner grants and other things to do with people’s home ownership, then?</p>
         <p>The homeowner grant…. We’ll be coming up on renters rebate questions shortly. There has obviously been a concern in communities around the homeowner grant potentially disappearing, or not. Is there anything in…? I don’t see it in Bill 10. There’s nothing in Bill 10 that sets the stage for regulatory change or something that can be done in an OIC that doesn’t currently exist in terms of the removal of the homeowner grant.</p>
      </speech>
      <proceedings fk="202304271000-house">Orders of the Day</proceedings>
      <speech>
         <p>Well, I’m glad it’s not just me furiously trying to move through the sections here in the papers. I see the minister and her staff doing the same, so that’s good. It keeps us on equal footing, I think.</p>
         <p>So 63 — this is the renters tax credit section. A few questions in this area. In 8.31, there’s the adjusted income, which, it says: “In relation to an eligible individual for a taxation year, means the total of all amounts each of which would be the income for the year of the individual or the individual’s cohabitating spouse or common-law partner if, in computing that income….”</p>
         <p>I take this to mean, then, that the threshold to qualify for the renters rebate is a household income. So it’s a combined income. Can the minister refresh all of our memories in terms of what those thresholds are and if it is indeed an actual household income versus an individual’s income?</p>
      </speech>
      <proceedings fk="202304271000-house">Orders of the Day</proceedings>
      <speech>
         <p>Thank you. So this would be, well, first off, trust-based, I guess. So as people file their federal income tax, if they check off “common law”, they’re bound by those. If they’re just dating but haven’t really declared themselves common-law, if they’re just roommates, does that count as…? If I and my girlfriend — to my wife at home, I don’t have a girlfriend; this is just an example — declare ourselves common law, we would only qualify for the $400. Myself and my roommate don’t, and we would qualify for $800. Is that what the minister is saying, if we were under $60,000 each in income?</p>
      </speech>
      <proceedings fk="202304271000-house">Orders of the Day</proceedings>
      <speech>
         <p>Okay. I guess I can see all sorts of angst. There’s still only one landlord and one rent to be paid. So you could be renting with a friend and have a combined income of $120,000 and get $800 back. If you’re common-law, paying the same landlord on the same type of a unit and the same rent, with a combined income of $120,000, you get zero. Am I stating that accurately?</p>
      </speech>
      <proceedings fk="202304271000-house">Orders of the Day</proceedings>
      <speech>
         <p>Well, there are economies of scale, but a landlord is still the landlord, and the rent paid is still the rent paid. As I said to my daughter when she wanted to move out when she was 19, I’m not worried about whether you have your rent. But if you’re with three roommates, a landlord doesn’t say: “Well, thanks. You paid your quarter. I’m only kicking the other three people out that didn’t pay.” They want 100 percent of the rent, regardless of which of the four may or may not be able to pay that month. That’s how the system works.</p>
         <p>Would it be, then, accurate that the intent and the design of this is meant for low-income people that typically, by virtue of being low-income, would only be able to afford lower-cost housing in the first place?</p>
      </speech>
      <proceedings fk="202304271000-house">Orders of the Day</proceedings>
      <speech>
         <p>Well, I get that, but at a $60,000 threshold before you start having it scaled back and only a $20,000 window of income before it goes to zero, in this day and age, it’s very much — especially household income — geared to lower-income workers. This is understandable, but by virtue of the threshold at $60,000, that would mean that they would only be able to afford lower-cost housing options in the first place.</p>
         <p>I guess that leads to my question as to why the definition of “‘rent,’ does not include the following payments,” includes “(d) a payment in respect of a campsite, moorage or a manufactured home site as defined in the Manufactured Home Park Tenancy Act.”</p>
         <p>You could have somebody that has bought an older-model trailer but still has to pay pad rent. They were able to afford the older-model trailer; it’s in an older mobile home park. They’re low-income. They have monthly pad rents. They qualify for everything because they’re a renter at that point, yet under this bill, all of those people, which would be a large portion of the lower-income people that this bill is purporting to help, do not qualify.</p>
         <p>Can the minister explain the rationale for not allowing pad rents in mobile home parks if you’re meeting all the other requirements? It’s not family-owned; it’s not a family member that’s renting you the pad rent. Why the differentiation from someone living in a basement suite, or someone living in a one-bedroom apartment, to somebody that has to pay rent for a pad for their mobile home to be on?</p>
      </speech>
   </speeches>
</member>
