<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<member>
   <header level="main">
      <name>S. Bond</name>
      <speechCount n="6"/>
   </header>
   <speeches>
      <proceedings fk="202304271000-dougfir">Proceedings in the Douglas Fir Room</proceedings>
      <speech>
         <p>I appreciate those updates from the minister. I appreciate the arrangement to allow us to deal with emergency health this morning. I’m really encouraging the minister to help us get through as much material as possible. The hours are limited, and all of these topics matter to me and to people in British Columbia.</p>
         <p>Before we move to emergency health, I’d like to follow up on a line of questioning that was actually started by the member for Saanich North and the Islands. It began last month, in the estimates with the Minister of Children and Family Development.</p>
         <p>I have met, as have a number of people in our caucus, with a number of people who are advocating on behalf of the Vancouver Island eating disorder program. There is significant concern about the fact that services have been impacted.</p>
         <p>I went back and looked at the discussion that took place in estimates. The fact of the matter is that there are not enough services. People, particularly adults, who have an eating disorder need help. In fact, what we’ve seen is adults on Vancouver Island who are facing significant barriers to treatment and care. We know that would be the case in many other places in B.C., and we simply need to do better.</p>
         <p>When the debate took place…. I appreciate my colleague from the Green Party raising these issues. When speaking to the Minister of Children and Families, she responded: “There’s work going on to align this particular clinic with other models in other health authorities. We’re working with the Mental Health and Addictions Ministry, Health and with Island Health to have a look at the future for the clinic.”</p>
         <p>Can the minister tell me today exactly what work has been done? What resources will be provided for people who are desperately in need of help? They have been here to the Legislature. They have met with us individually. Health, apparently, has a role to play in that. Is there funding being provided to ensure that there are services and supports in place, not just on Vancouver Island but across the province, for those people with eating disorders?</p>
      </speech>
      <proceedings fk="202304271000-dougfir">Proceedings in the Douglas Fir Room</proceedings>
      <speech>
         <p>Thank you to the minister. I would appreciate, certainly, follow-up information. It is incredibly devastating to hear people’s personal stories of distress and their inability to get the service that they need. They want to go on and be able to live productive, healthier lives, so we are deeply concerned about that.</p>
         <p>I will look forward to a further update from the minister about what’s being done on Vancouver Island. I’m very concerned about the fact that multiple ministries are involved and it’s: “Okay, it’s over to Health; it’s Mental Health. People just want the issue resolved on Vancouver Island.”</p>
         <p>I’m going to ask my colleague to ask his question about emergency health.</p>
      </speech>
      <proceedings fk="202304271000-dougfir">Proceedings in the Douglas Fir Room</proceedings>
      <speech>
         <p>Thank you to my colleague for that question and his concern, always, for his residents, the people he represents.</p>
         <p>I want to spend a few minutes…. Thank you to representatives from BCEHS who are here today. I think all of us agree that it’s a pretty straightforward principle that if you dial 911, you should expect you’re going to get some help in British Columbia.</p>
         <p>Earlier this week there was a story that a father called an ambulance for his daughter, who had suddenly lost her hearing and vision and began sweating. I would imagine that most families would feel pretty concerned about that. The father called 911, and he got a message the first time, “Hang up and call again,” which he did. Ten minutes later, he was passed through to a dispatcher. Even still, they had to take her to the hospital themselves.</p>
         <p>Does the minister agree that perhaps the first time someone calls 911, they should actually get an answer?</p>
      </speech>
      <proceedings fk="202304271000-dougfir">Proceedings in the Douglas Fir Room</proceedings>
      <speech>
         <p>Again, I want to thank the representatives that are here today for the work that they do, and all of their members. It’s not about them. It’s about a system that is under extraordinary pressure in British Columbia. Whether it’s ambulances or it’s nurses, doctors and all of the health care professionals, it takes an enormous toll.</p>
         <p>I will just remind the minister that this person got a recorded message. They believed they were having a health emergency of a daughter. The message was: “If this is an emergency, please hang up and dial 911 again.” I would assume that if you dial 911 in the first place, you would be thinking that it is an emergency. I just want to remind the minister that this particular family talked about what an absolutely terrible experience it was.</p>
         <p>I understand that additional resources have been added, but there’s still work to be done. Let’s take a look, for example, at what we have seen. On March 22, 2023, paramedics in this province responded to 205 overdose calls. That is the single highest number that has ever been recorded in a single day. The previous record was in January of 2022.</p>
         <p>My question to the minister: in light of the overdose incidents that are increasing — we know that the numbers are absolutely horrific and tragic — are there specific additional resources being provided to ensure that front-line staff are able to take care of their own mental health as well? We have increasing call numbers. The pressure on paramedics in this province is extraordinary. That continues to climb. Could the minister speak to us about what we’re doing to ensure that front-line staff are being properly cared for?</p>
      </speech>
      <proceedings fk="202304271000-dougfir">Proceedings in the Douglas Fir Room</proceedings>
      <speech>
         <p>Under the recruitment strategy that was announced, were there specific targets put in place for 2022-23, ’23-24 in terms of paramedics, dispatchers, all of the personnel that are covered under that recruitment strategy? Can the minister tell me: were there targets put in place? And can he provide me with an update on current vacancies?</p>
      </speech>
      <proceedings fk="202304271000-dougfir">Proceedings in the Douglas Fir Room</proceedings>
      <speech>
         <p>Thank you to the minister. I’m a bit concerned about time here. I will lay out several questions and perhaps the minister can come back after the break and answer them for me.</p>
         <p>I appreciate the update on the work that has been done, but it’s clear there’s more work to be done. I am deeply concerned about, as I have expressed continuously through the last four days now, the sense of moral distress that people in the health care system are feeling about not being able to actually manage the jobs that they care about and that they are called to do.</p>
         <p>I want to raise this point. Certainly, adding additional paramedics are one thing, but as importantly is how many additional cars are on the road. I’m wondering if the minister can provide what regions and stations have net new cars and shifts been added to. That actually is as important as having additional paramedics.</p>
         <p>I want to also…. I’ll just lay these questions out before Mr. Chair hands the note over.</p>
         <p>We also, yesterday…. I want to, obviously, make sure the context is correct. The Ambulance Paramedics and Dispatchers of B.C. have been clear that they’ve appreciated the investments that have been made, but yesterday they made several, what I think are, very important and relevant points that need to be pursued. One of them is the fact that hey talked about recruitment and actually getting people on the ground. Their spokesperson said: “Despite recruitment efforts that have drawn more applicants, there are bottlenecks in training and hiring. A lot of the delay is in the human resources system within BCEHS.”</p>
         <p>I’d like the minister to respond to that at some point, about what we’re doing to. It’s great if we can recruit more people. The most important thing is to train them and get them out into the system.</p>
         <p>The other issue that was raised, and I certainly continue to hear this across the province…. Progress, yes, but we want to make sure that we are reducing the delay in ambulance response times, especially in rural and remote communities. The minister and I have probably not often been in the position of having to dial 911. But I can assure you that the feeling of helplessness and frustration when there is not an appropriate response time….</p>
         <p>The concern that was expressed was the need for a review in terms of how many resources are needed in larger centres, because the point that was made is that resources are being taken from surrounding smaller communities. The example that was used was Victoria. Staff is being pulled in from places like Sooke, because we need more ambulances just to meet the demand and the pressures that have built up over the years.</p>
         <p>Again, what that does is put other communities at risk, when we’re madly trying to staff up in larger urban centres. Is the minister prepared to agree to a review that actually looks at how resources are deployed and what happens when we have to pull those resources out of smaller communities? I’m wondering if he could respond to that.</p>
         <p>Maybe that review is underway, but it certainly, as I understand it, hasn’t been completed, or we’re not even sure what the schedule is and if the report would be released to the public. I think those are critically important questions as we try to sort out how we are going to ensure that people have appropriate response times.</p>
         <p>This is the statement that concerned me. He says: “I think back to what happened during the heat dome in British Columbia, where over 600 frail elderly British Columbians died.” One of the concerns…. You can imagine how personnel feel when they can’t get there, when ambulances were simply overwhelmed and couldn’t respond.</p>
         <p>I remember the story of the family that was desperate for help, and what did they do? They drove their loved one to the driveway of a fire hall, just trying to find somebody who would help them. That person died in the driveway of the fire hall.</p>
         <p>So here’s the quote: “It’s not all wonderful as described and we’re seeing significant delays, and unless we get a handle on this, we’ll keep seeing those delays.” Here’s the concern as we get into the busy season.</p>
         <p>I’m wondering if the minister and EHS representatives can talk about what we are doing to be prepared for the busy season. We’ve already seen the highest number of overdose calls on a single day. That was in March. I’m assuming the busy season refers to wildfire, heat domes and all of the things that extreme weather relates to. So if we’re not managing now — not my words but the words of the representative from paramedics and dispatchers — are we ready for the busy season?</p>
      </speech>
   </speeches>
</member>
