<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9 http://www.loc.gov/ead/ead.xsd">
  <eadheader langencoding="iso639-2b" scriptencoding="iso15924" relatedencoding="dc" repositoryencoding="iso15511" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-uuml" publicid="-//University of Utah::Special Collections and Archives//TEXT (US::UUML::UUM_A0090::James Taylor Harwood oral history video collection)//EN" encodinganalog="identifier" identifier="80444/xv13973" url="http://archiveswest.orbiscascade.org/ark:/80444/xv13973">UUM_A0090</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper encodinganalog="title">Guide to the James Taylor Harwood oral history video collection
				<date era="ce" calendar="gregorian" normal="1991" encodinganalog="date">1991</date></titleproper>
        <titleproper type="filing" altrender="nodisplay">Harwood (James Taylor) oral history video collection</titleproper>
        <author encodinganalog="creator">Finding aid created by Molly Creel</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher encodinganalog="publisher">Multimedia Archives, J. Willard Marriott Library, University of Utah</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>295 South 1500 East</addressline>
          <addressline>Salt Lake City, Utah 84112-0860</addressline>
          <addressline>801-581-8864</addressline>
          <addressline>http://www.lib.utah.edu/collections/multimedia-archives/</addressline>
        </address>
        <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian" normal="2012" encodinganalog="date">© 2012</date>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Encoded in Adobe Dreamweaver by Molly Creel
			<date era="ce" calendar="gregorian" normal="2012">2012</date>.
			</creation>
      <langusage>Finding aid encoded in 
			<language encodinganalog="language" langcode="eng" scriptcode="Latn">English</language> in Latin script.
			</langusage>
      <descrules>Finding aid based on DACS (<title render="italic">Describing Archives: A Content Standard</title>).</descrules>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <archdesc level="collection" type="inventory" relatedencoding="dc">
    <did>
      <repository>
        <corpname encodinganalog="publisher">University of Utah Libraries, Special Collections</corpname>
        <subarea encodinganalog="publisher">Audio Visual Archives</subarea>
        <address>
          <addressline>Special Collections</addressline>
          <addressline>295 South 1500 East</addressline>
          <addressline>Salt Lake City, Utah 84112-0860</addressline>
          <addressline>801-581-8864</addressline>
          <addressline>http://www.lib.utah.edu/collections/multimedia-archives/</addressline>
        </address>
      </repository>
      <unitid encodinganalog="identifier" countrycode="US" repositorycode="US-uuml">A0090</unitid>
      <origination>
        <persname source="local" rules="dacs" encodinganalog="creator" role="creator">Harwood, Jim</persname>
      </origination>
      <unittitle encodinganalog="title">James Taylor Harwood oral history video collection</unittitle>
      <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian" normal="1991" encodinganalog="date">1991</unitdate>
      <physdesc>
        <extent encodinganalog="format">2 DVDs</extent>
      </physdesc>
      <abstract encodinganalog="description">The James Taylor Harwood oral history video collection (1991) consists of interviews with Harwood's widow, Ione, and daughter, Lark, about Harwood's artwork and the process and circumstances of its creation.  The video was taken by Harwood's son, Jim, in Ione Harwood's Honolulu, Hawaii home and features shots of her husband's artwork as displayed in the home.  Born in Lehi, Utah, J.T. Harwood (1860-1940) was the first of the late-nineteenth-century Utah artists to study in Paris. As a painter, he his work shows the beginning of Utah impressionism.</abstract>
      <langmaterial>Collection material in 
			<language langcode="eng" encodinganalog="language">English</language>.
            </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="description">
      <head>Biographical Note</head>
      <p>James Taylor Harwood (1860-1940) was born in Lehi, Utah. His father was a saddle and harness maker. Harwood began drawing as a child, making pictures of animals and portraits of his schoolmates. In his boyhood, he formed lifelong friendships with artists John Hafen and Cyrus E. Dallin. In his teens, Harwood carried mail and worked in his father's shop to earn enough money to go to art school.</p>
      <p>At the age of 25, he entered the San Francisco School of Design. At the end of one year, he won a gold medal for the best painting of the year. In 1886, he returned to Utah, opened a studio, and taught art. Two years later he had saved enough money to go to France and enter the Ecole des Beaux Arts. From 1891 to 1893 he studied at the Academie Julian in Paris where he won a medal for painting.</p>
      <p>In 1891, Harwood married one of his art students, Harriet Richards. They settled in Salt Lake City, after their sojourn in France, where he taught at East and West high schools. They had five children.  During the next twenty-five years, the Harwoods divided their time between France and Utah. In 1920, the family moved to California due to Harriet's poor health. She died in 1922 and the family returned to Salt Lake City.</p>
      <p>Harwood became head of the art department at the University of Utah in 1922. He held that position until 1931, when he resigned in order to devote more time to his painting. At the university, he taught the first class in color etching ever given in the United States. In 1929, Harwood married Ione Godwin. They traveled to Europe for two years where Harwood developed his impressionist painting technique. He became famous in Europe as well as in the United States and won many honors for his works. The Harwoods returned to California in 1939 with their two children, Jim and Lark. In 1940, the University of Utah assembled the James Taylor Harwood art exhibition. This exhibit was in honor of his 80th birthday and represented his life's work. He died in Salt Lake City on 16 October 1940.  Ione Harwood passed away at the age of 96 in November 2003.  Lark succumbed to cancer in October 1998.</p>
      <p>From Jim Harwood: During the period of their marriage, "Ione was usually with [her husband] on his excursions searching for subject matter and would be nearby as he worked at his easel or drawing pad.  Some of his works included Ione in the distance relaxing on a blanket or just on the grass within the scene, usually reading a book while he worked . . . children were sometimes there also."</p>
      <p>Harwood "didn't creat the finished work in the field.  He would make sketches, notes, and sometimes take photos for use back in the studio, where conditions were controllable and amenable for hours spent at the easel."</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
      <p>The James Taylor Harwood oral history video collection (1991) consists of interviews with Harwood's widow, Ione, and daughter, Lark, about Harwood's artwork and the process and circumstances of its creation.  The video was taken by Harwood's son, Jim, in Ione Harwood's Honolulu, Hawaii home and features shots of her husband's artwork as displayed in the home.  All materials have been digitized and are available to view on the DVDs described in this finding aid.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <accessrestrict encodinganalog="rights">
      <p>Materials must be used on-site; no use of original material, access copies will be made available for viewing. Five business days advanced notice required. Access to parts of this collection may be restricted under provisions of state or federal law, condition of the material, or by donor.</p>
    </accessrestrict>
    <userestrict encodinganalog="rights">
      <p>It is the responsibility of the researcher to obtain any necessary copyright clearances.</p>
      <p>Permission to publish material from the James Taylor Harwood oral history video collection must be obtained from the Special Collections Multimedia Archivist.</p>
    </userestrict>
    <prefercite>
      <p>
        <emph render="italic">Initial Citation:</emph>
                James Taylor Harwood oral history video collection A0090,
                Special Collections and Archives. University of Utah, J. Willard Marriott. Salt Lake City, Utah.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="italic">Following Citations:</emph>A0090.</p>
    </prefercite>
    <acqinfo>
      <p>Donated by Jim Harwood in 2011.</p>
    </acqinfo>
    <processinfo>
      <p>Processed by Molly Creel in 2012.</p>
    </processinfo>
    <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="relation">
      <p>See also the James Taylor Harwood papers (Ms 507) and photograph collection (P0117) and the William R. Harwood oral history audio recordings (A0180).</p>
    </relatedmaterial>
    <controlaccess>
      <persname encodinganalog="subject" source="lcnaf" role="subject">Godwin, Ione</persname>
      <subject encodinganalog="subject" source="lcsh">Artists - Utah</subject>
      <subject encodinganalog="subject" source="lcsh">Painters - Utah</subject>
      <subject altrender="nodisplay" source="archiveswest">Fine Arts</subject>
      <subject altrender="nodisplay" source="archiveswest">Moving Images</subject>
      <subject altrender="nodisplay" source="archiveswest">Oral Histories</subject>
      <genreform encodinganalog="type" source="aat">Moving images</genreform>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc type="in-depth">
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="disc">1-2</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Ione Harwood personal video raw footage</unittitle>
          <unitdate>1991</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>DVD</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Raw footage from a series of interviews with James Taylor Harwood's widow, Ione, at her Honolulu, Hawaii home where she had her late husband's artwork displayed on the walls. Son Jim Harwood conducts the interview, asking his mother questions about the circumstances leading to the creation of the work displayed on camera.  Daughter Lark appears near the end of the recordings duscussing a colored pencil drawing of herself at the age of five in the garden of the family's Salt Lake City home.  Material spread over two DVDs.  Chapter breaks every two minutes.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
