<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9 http://www.loc.gov/ead/ead.xsd">
  <eadheader langencoding="iso639-2b" scriptencoding="iso15924" relatedencoding="dc" repositoryencoding="iso15511" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-uuml" publicid="-//University of Utah::Special Collections and Archives//TEXT (US::UUML::UUM_A0997::Tina Gonzales Garcia family video collection)//EN" encodinganalog="identifier" identifier="80444/xv50473" url="http://archiveswest.orbiscascade.org/ark:/80444/xv50473">UUM_A0997</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper encodinganalog="title">Guide to the Tina Gonzales Garcia family video collection.
				<date era="ce" calendar="gregorian" normal="1986/1991" encodinganalog="date">1986-1991</date></titleproper>
        <titleproper type="filing" altrender="nodisplay">Garcia (Tina Gonzales) family video collection</titleproper>
        <author encodinganalog="creator">Finding aid created by Michael Hinderaker</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher encodinganalog="publisher">Multimedia Archives, J. Willard Marriott Library, University of Utah</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>295 South 1500 East</addressline>
          <addressline>Salt Lake City, Utah 84112-0860</addressline>
          <addressline>801-581-8864</addressline>
          <addressline>http://www.lib.utah.edu/collections/multimedia-archives/</addressline>
        </address>
        <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian" normal="2013" encodinganalog="date">© 2013</date>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Encoded in Adobe Dreamweaver by Michael Hinderaker
			<date era="ce" calendar="gregorian" normal="2013">2013</date>.
			</creation>
      <langusage>Finding aid encoded in 
			<language encodinganalog="language" langcode="eng" scriptcode="Latn">English</language> in Latin script.
			</langusage>
      <descrules>Finding aid based on DACS (<title render="italic">Describing Archives: A Content Standard</title>).</descrules>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <archdesc level="collection" type="inventory" relatedencoding="dc">
    <did>
      <repository>
        <corpname encodinganalog="publisher">University of Utah Libraries, Special Collections</corpname>
        <subarea encodinganalog="publisher">Audio Visual Archives</subarea>
        <address>
          <addressline>Special Collections</addressline>
          <addressline>295 South 1500 East</addressline>
          <addressline>Salt Lake City, Utah 84112-0860</addressline>
          <addressline>801-581-8864</addressline>
          <addressline>http://www.lib.utah.edu/collections/multimedia-archives/</addressline>
        </address>
      </repository>
      <unitid encodinganalog="identifier" countrycode="US" repositorycode="US-uuml">A0997</unitid>
      <origination>
        <persname source="local" rules="dacs" encodinganalog="creator" role="creator">Garcia, Tina Gonzales</persname>
      </origination>
      <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Tina Gonzales Garcia family video collection</unittitle>
      <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian" normal="1986/1991" encodinganalog="date">1986-1991</unitdate>
      <physdesc>
        <extent encodinganalog="format">1 DVD.</extent>
      </physdesc>
      <abstract encodinganalog="description">The Tina Gonzales Garcia family video collection (1986-1991) consists of digital copies of two documentaries relating to issues Garcia espoused as an activist for the Hispanic communit: "A Rising Voice" describes the situation of the Hispanic community and their struggle for prosperity. "Wrath of Grapes" is a film about pesticide contamination in grape farming in California.</abstract>
      <langmaterial>Collection material in 
			<language langcode="eng" encodinganalog="language">English</language>.
            </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="description">
      <head>Biographical Note</head>
      <p>Tina Gonzales Garcia (1934-1992) was born in Ojo Caliente, New Mexico.  She worked as a federal investigator and received several recognition awards for her involvement in issues related to the Hispanic Community including "Hispanic Woman of the Year" in 1989.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
      <p>The Tina Gonzales Garcia family video collection (1986-1991) consists of digital copies of two documentaries relating to issues Garcia espoused as an activist for the Hispanic communit: "A Rising Voice" describes the situation of the Hispanic community and their struggle for prosperity. "Wrath of Grapes" is a film about pesticide contamination in grape farming in California.  Both videos are available to view on a single DVD.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement encodinganalog="description">
      <p>Materials are arranged alphabetically.</p>
    </arrangement>
    <accessrestrict encodinganalog="rights">
      <p>Materials must be used on-site; no use of original material, access copies will be made available for viewing. Five business days advanced notice required. Access to parts of this collection may be restricted under provisions of state or federal law, condition of the material, or by donor.</p>
    </accessrestrict>
    <userestrict encodinganalog="rights">
      <p>It is the responsibility of the researcher to obtain any necessary copyright clearances.</p>
      <p>Permission to publish material from the Tina Gonzales Garcia family video collection must be obtained from the Special Collections Multimedia Archivist.</p>
    </userestrict>
    <prefercite>
      <p>
        <emph render="italic">Initial Citation:</emph>
                Tina Gonzales Garcia family video collection A0997,
                Special Collections and Archives. University of Utah, J. Willard Marriott. Salt Lake City, Utah.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="italic">Following Citations:</emph>A0997.</p>
    </prefercite>
    <acqinfo>
      <p>Donated by Ernest Garcia in 2012.</p>
    </acqinfo>
    <processinfo>
      <p>Processed by Michael Hinderaker in 2013.</p>
    </processinfo>
    <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="relation">
      <p>See also the Tina Gonzales Garcia family photograph collection (P1810).</p>
    </relatedmaterial>
    <controlaccess>
      <subject encodinganalog="subject" source="lcsh">Hispanic American agricultural laborers</subject>
      <subject encodinganalog="subject" source="lcsh">Hispanic American pioneers</subject>
      <subject encodinganalog="subject" source="lcsh">Hispanic American families</subject>
      <subject altrender="nodisplay" source="archiveswest">Civic Activism</subject>
      <subject altrender="nodisplay" source="archiveswest">Agriculture</subject>
      <subject altrender="nodisplay" source="archiveswest">Moving Images</subject>
      <genreform encodinganalog="type" source="aat">Moving images</genreform>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="disc">1</container>
          <unitdate>1986-1991</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>DVD</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <container type="video">1</container>
            <unittitle encodinganalog="title">A Rising Voice</unittitle>
            <unitdate>1991</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
            <p>A documentary chronocling the history of the Hispanic community in the United States and challenges facing its members:
										<list type="simple"><item>Spanish conquistadors were first to map and colonize many parts of the United States.</item><item>In 1598 Spanish established government in New Mexico.</item><item>In 1776 the Dominguez-Escalante expedition explored and mapped what would later become known as Utah.</item><item>Film of a small stage with costumed men doing a dance called the "Tonantzin", an Aztec dance.</item><item>Gonzales family was one of the early Hispanic families in Utah and they settled in Monticello.</item><item>At the time they were one of seven families in Monticello and the only Hispanic family.</item><item>In 1910, there was an influx of Hispanic people due to the Mexican revolution.</item><item>A family of Mexican migrant workers talk about their experience in Utah compared to Mexico, specifically how their work pay is better.</item><item>There was another influx of Hispanics during World War 2 to fill labor jobs.</item><item>Hispanic peoples have a diverse set of backgrounds.  The film focuses on a family from Uruguay and the differences in their cultures.</item><item>A man talks about the importance of maintaining and understanding of your own cultural background for immigrants.</item><item>A band of men play and sing a traditional Bolivian love song.</item><item>People talk about the connotations of the terms Hispanic, chicana, and la raza.</item><item>Discussion of low graduation rate for Hispanic students.</item><item>How does cultural heritage play into this?</item><item>How does MESA help to encourage students, particularly minority students, develop a love of learning and school?</item><item>Multicultural education can help Hispanic students to have a greater sense of self-worth.</item><item>Men and women in costume dancing to "Jarabe Tapatio".</item><item>Man discusses how stereotypes of youth can lead to young people actually becoming gang members.</item><item>Discussion of how various programs can contribute to a child's sense of belonging.</item><item>IHRC emphasizes the ability of the family to strengthen individuals and tries to provide structure for those who don't have extended families.</item><item>Men and women in costume perform a Chilean dance called "Cueca", the national dance of Chile.</item><item>Discussion of stereotypes of Hispanic women and how the community should work to empower them.</item><item>Discussion of the growth of business owned by minorities.</item><item>Women in costume dancing "El Nino Dormido".</item><item>Discussion of need for advocacy in government for Hispanic population.</item><item>Man and women dancing a "Tango".</item></list></p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <container type="video">2</container>
            <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Wrath of Grapes</unittitle>
            <unitdate>1986</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
            <p>A documentary about pesticide contamination and its effects on workers as well as consumers:
										  <list type="simple"><item>Discussion of practices by companies that don't follow regulations and go as far as hiring thugs to break up unions.</item><item>300,000 farmworkers poisoned annually, no warnings are posted after pesticides are used.</item><item>Children of farm workers are often affected through birth defects or poisoning if their mothers were working while pregnant.</item><item>Residue of the pesticides is still sometimes on produce in supermarkets.</item><item>Pesticide also gets into water supplies as well as the air, hurting neighboring communities.</item><item>11 children in the small town of McFarland have cancer, another small town, Fowler, has a population of only 3000 and 7 children have cancer.</item></list></p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
