<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9 http://www.loc.gov/ead/ead.xsd">
  <!--Last Edited: 2008/12/08 10:10:45 by xEAD vBETA 07-14-2008-->
  <eadheader langencoding="iso639-2b" scriptencoding="iso15924" relatedencoding="dc" repositoryencoding="iso15511" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-uuml" publicid="-//:://TEXT(US::UUML::UUM_A0664::Park City Mountain Resort audio-visual collection)//EN" encodinganalog="identifier" identifier="80444/xv99234" url="http://archiveswest.orbiscascade.org/ark:/80444/xv99234">UUM_A0664</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper encodinganalog="title">
          Guide to the Park City Mountain Resort audio-visual collection
          <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian" normal="1961/2002" encodinganalog="date">1961-2002</date></titleproper>
        <titleproper type="filing" altrender="nodisplay">Park City Mountain Resort audio-visual collection</titleproper>
        <author encodinganalog="creator">Finding aid prepared by Elizabeth Shuput and Tawnya Mosier.</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher encodinganalog="publisher">Multimedia Archives, J. Willard Marriott Library, University of Utah</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>295 South 1500 East</addressline>
          <addressline>Salt Lake City, Utah 84112</addressline>
          <addressline>(801) 581-8864</addressline>
        </address>
        <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian" normal="2003" encodinganalog="date">© 2003</date>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>
        Encoded by Manish Singh
        <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian" normal="2004">2004</date></creation>
      <langusage>
        <language encodinganalog="language" langcode="eng" scriptcode="Latn">English</language>
      </langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <archdesc type="inventory" level="collection" relatedencoding="dc">
    <did>
      <repository>
        <corpname encodinganalog="publisher">University of Utah Libraries, Special Collections</corpname>
        <subarea encodinganalog="publisher">Audio Visual Archives</subarea>
        <address>
          <addressline>Special Collections</addressline>
          <addressline>295 South 1500 East</addressline>
          <addressline>Salt Lake City, Utah 84112-0860</addressline>
          <addressline>(801) 581-8864</addressline>
        </address>
      </repository>
      <unitid encodinganalog="identifier" countrycode="US" repositorycode="US-uuml">A0664</unitid>
      <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Park City Mountain Resort audio-visual collection</unittitle>
      <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian" normal="1961/2002" encodinganalog="date">1961-2002</unitdate>
      <origination>
        <corpname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="creator" role="creator">Park City Mountain Resort</corpname>
      </origination>
      <physdesc>
        <extent encodinganalog="format">Approximatley 210 VHS videocassettes, 33 U-matic videocassettes, 23 Betacam videocassettes, 3 Hi-8 videocassettes, 5 1-inch videotapes, 27 16mm films, 2 8mm films, 22 audiocassettes, 6 reel-to-reel audiotapes, 1 CD-ROM and 3 1/4-inch tape data cartridges.</extent>
      </physdesc>
      <abstract encodinganalog="description">The Park City Mountain Resort audio-visual collection (1961-2002) contains film, video and audio recordings, almost all of which are directly related to Park City Mountain Resort's role in Utah's winter sports industry and international competative ski ciruit.  The colleciton includes promotional materials for the ski area, Utah's ski industry at large and the United States Ski Team, footage of the World Cup and other competitions held at the resort, ski films by Stein Ericksen and Warren Miller, and many other materials relating to the ski and snowboard industry in Utah and beyond.  Founded in 1963, Park City Mountain Resort is one of three ski areas in the vicinity of Park City, Utah.</abstract>
      <langmaterial>
        <language encodinganalog="language" langcode="eng">English</language>
        <language encodinganalog="language" langcode="fra">French</language>
        <language encodinganalog="language" langcode="jpn">Japanese</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="description">
      <head>Organizational History</head>
      <p>The town of Park City sprung up in Utah's Wasatch Mountains after army prospectors discovered silver in the area in 1868.  Early miners used primitive skis and snowshoes as transporation to the mines, and skiing emerged a recreational activity by the 1920s.  Scandinavian miners held jumping tournaments on the Creole Mine dump (now the Creole ski run to the Town Lift), and the newly formed Park City Ski Club conducted guided ski tours on the hills that make up the modern resort.</p>
      <p>As the area's silver mining industry faded away in the mid 20th century, the town's last surviving mining company, United Park City Mines, received a federal loan to help revive conomically depressed rural towns and opened the city's first ski area, Treasure Mountain Resort, in 1963.</p>
      <p>For its first four years of operation the resort featured the Skier's Subway lift, which carried skiers in modified mining trolleys two and a half miles through the pitch dark Spiro Tunnel to the Thaynes Hoist, where they boarded the old mine elevator and were lifted 1,750 feet to the surface near the Thaynes chair lift.</p>
      <p>Treasure Mountain changed its name to Park City Ski Area in 1966 and to Park City Mountain Resort in 1996.  Its sister ski resort, Park City West (later Wolf Mountain; now The Canyons) opened in 1968, and nearby Deer Valley opened in 1981.</p>
      <p>Park City hosted its first World Cup ski race in 1986.  During the 2002 Winter Olympic Games hosted by Salt Lake City, Park City Mountain Resort hosted the men's and women's giant slalom, men's and women's snowboarding parallel giant slalom, and both men's and women's snowboarding halfpipe events.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
      <p>The Park City Mountain Resort audio-visual collection (1961-2002) contains film, video and audio recordings, almost all of which are directly related to Park City Mountain Resort's role in Utah's winter sports industry and international competative ski ciruit.  The colleciton includes promotional materials for the ski area, Utah's ski industry at large and the United States Ski Team, footage of the World Cup and other competitions held at the resort, ski films by Stein Ericksen and Warren Miller, and many other materials relating to the ski and snowboard industry in Utah and beyond.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement encodinganalog="description">
      <p>The majory of the materials are arranged chronologically.  Undated material is located at the end of the register beginning with item 224.  Some items are available on more than one format.</p>
    </arrangement>
    <accessrestrict encodinganalog="rights">
      <p>Materials must be used on-site; no use of original material, access copies will be made available for viewing. Five business days advanced notice required. Access to parts of this collection may be restricted under provisions of state or federal law, condition of the material, or by donor.</p>
    </accessrestrict>
    <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="relation">
      <p>See also the Park City Mountain Resort photograph collection (P0949), the Park City Ski Area photograph collection (P0384), the Park City, Utah photograph collection (P0228) and the Park City Ski Corporation records (Accn 1218).  For additional promotional audio-visual materials related to Utah ski resorts see the Ski Utah tourism audio-visual collection (A0590) and the Utah Travel Council tourism video collection (A0544).</p>
    </relatedmaterial>
    <processinfo>
      <p>Processed by Elizabeth Shuput and Tawnya Mosier in 2003.</p>
    </processinfo>
    <controlaccess>
      <geogname encodinganalog="coverage" source="lcsh" role="subject">Park City (Utah)--History</geogname>
      <subject encodinganalog="subject" source="lcsh">Skis and skiing--Utah--Park City--History--Sources</subject>
      <subject encodinganalog="subject" source="lcsh">Ski resorts--Utah--Park City--History--Sources</subject>
      <subject encodinganalog="subject" source="lcsh">Skiing--Utah--History</subject>
      <subject encodinganalog="subject" source="lcsh">Snowboarding</subject>
      <subject encodinganalog="subject" source="lcsh">Tourism</subject>
      <subject altrender="nodisplay" source="archiveswest">Advertising and Marketing</subject>
      <subject altrender="nodisplay" source="archiveswest">Sports and Recreation</subject>
      <subject altrender="nodisplay" source="archiveswest">Moving Images</subject>
      <subject altrender="nodisplay" source="archiveswest">Sound Recordings</subject>
      <genreform encodinganalog="type" source="aat">Moving images</genreform>
      <genreform encodinganalog="type" source="aat">Sound recordings</genreform>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc type="in-depth">
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">1</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Three Kings grand opening</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1961</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>16mm film</genreform>
            <physfacet>
              Color, magnetic soundtrack
            </physfacet>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This film contains images of two men getting onto a helicopter and a scene of the outdoors from the helicopter. It shows a few shots of the state capital and then shows the grand opening of the Three Kings chair lift where one of the men from the first scene cuts a red ribbon at Treasure Mountain Resort, which will open in 1963.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">2</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Treasure Mountain raw footage 1</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1964</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>16mm film</genreform>
            <physfacet>
              Black and white, silent
            </physfacet>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This film contains raw footage of downtown Park City and of a family purchasing ski passes at the ticket booth, getting on the gondola and then skiing at Treasure Mountain Resort.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">3</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Treasure Mountain raw footage 2</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1964</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>16mm film</genreform>
            <physfacet>
              Black and white, silent
            </physfacet>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This film contains raw footage of ski lessons at Treasure Mountain Resort and of the ski class's lunch break at the lodge.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">4</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Treasure Mountain raw footage 3</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1964</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>16mm film</genreform>
            <physfacet>
              Black and white, silent
            </physfacet>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This film contains raw footage of a giant slalom ski race and of a hot dog ski competition held at Treasure Mountain Resort.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">5</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Treasure Mountain raw footage 4</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1964</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>16mm film</genreform>
            <physfacet>
              Black and white, silent
            </physfacet>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This film contains raw footage of ski lessons for beginner, intermediate and advanced skiers. It also shows footage of a woman sitting in front of a fire and then shopping while her young children wait at the daycare facility at Treasure Mountain Resort.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">6</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Untitled Park City promotional skiing film</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1966</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>16mm film</genreform>
            <physfacet>
              Color, sound
            </physfacet>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This film compares Park City in 1966 to Park City during it's silver mining era. It shows images of Civil War soldiers and Park City's mountains and the mineshafts. It then shows footage of a man being taken to a jail cell where he spends his time playing a banjo and singing. Other historical images include drawings of trains, the miners and the actual mining process, and of several men burning a certificate.</p>
          <p>When the images switch to 1966 several people prepare to go skiing outside of the Treasure Mountain Inn. They get onto a gondola and get off at the summit house area. There are images of the skiers and then images of evening entertainment in the town.</p>
          <p>At the end of the film the man in the jail is shackled to the cell wall.  We see a man skiing, and finally the man form the jail steps out of the gondola and skis away.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">7</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">Utah! On My Mind</title>
          </unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1969</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>16mm film</genreform>
            <physfacet>
              Color, optical soundtrack
            </physfacet>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This promotional film for Utah's ski industry was presented by Telescene Inc. It includes footage of the mountains at Park City, people traveling with their skis and then skiing, and footage from the hot dog ski competition at Alta.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">8</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">Stein Turned On</title>
          </unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1969</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>16mm film</genreform>
            <physfacet>
              Color, sound
            </physfacet>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This film about Olympian Stein Ericksen's career at Park City begins with footage of Ericksen organizing and teaching ski classes for beginning and advanced students.  Footage of Ericksen setting up a picnic on the snow is followed by more ski lessons, Ericksen helicopter skiing, and Ericksen teaching slalom ski racing.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">9</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">The Ski Scene</title>
          </unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1969</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>16mm film</genreform>
            <physfacet>
              Color, sound
            </physfacet>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This film is a Warren Miller production and presented by Terracor. It features backcountry powder skiing, ballet skiing, the Sun Valley Farriman Cup Race, ski crashes and stunts, and a ski trip to Japan.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">10</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">Park City Swings</title>
          </unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1970</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>16mm film</genreform>
            <physfacet>
              Color, optical soundtrack
            </physfacet>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This film is a Warren Miller production. It begins with various shots of Park City and its surrounding ski areas. Several skiers go into the Park City mines on a small train (probably Treasure Mountain Resort's early Skier's Subway lift).  The following scenes are of these men extreme skiing at Park City.</p>
          <p>2 reels</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">11</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">De L'acier a la Neige</title>
          </unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1970</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>16mm film</genreform>
            <physfacet>
              Color, optical soundtrack, French subtitles
            </physfacet>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This advertisement for Solomon ski equipment begins with images of ski racers and a woman's hand turning a ski boot attachment. Then you see the Solomon building where men are designing ski parts and machines are making the parts. The film ends with a short summary of the film interspersed with the Solomon logo.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">12</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">Ski America</title>
          </unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1971</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>16mm film</genreform>
            <physfacet>
              Color, sound
            </physfacet>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This film showcases nine Rocky Mountain ski resorts including Aspen, Jackson Hole, Steamboat, Taos, Breckenridge, Park City, Sun Valley, Vail, and Winter Park. The featured skiers are Billy Kidd, Roger Staub, Jeff Jobe, Tom Leroi, Paul Pfosi, Arthur Furrer, Bill Peterson, Herman Gollner, Jean Claude Killy, Stein Eriksen, Ruedi Wyrsch, Pepi Stiegler, Corky Fowler, and Suzy Chaffee.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">13</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Stein ski touring</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1972</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>16mm film</genreform>
            <physfacet>
              Color, sound
            </physfacet>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This film features Stein Eriksen leading a group of five people into the backcountry on cross-country skis.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">14</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Hot dog contest skiing at Park City</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1972</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>16mm film</genreform>
            <physfacet>
              Color, sound
            </physfacet>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This film contains footage from a hot dog skiing competition held at Park City. The contest includes skiers doing back flips and skiing moguls.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">15</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Leo Kottke concert</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1972 September 19</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>16mm film</genreform>
            <physfacet>
              Color, black and white, silent, magnetic soundtrack
            </physfacet>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>a) This is the original film of the Leo Kottke Concert in an outdoor amphitheater in Park City Utah filmed by the Park City Film Group (silent).</p>
          <p>b)	The same concert footage in black and white (work print, silent).</p>
          <p>c)	Magnetic soundtracks for films a and b.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">16</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Barf-O-Rama</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1972-1973</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>8mm film</genreform>
            <physfacet>
              Color, silent
            </physfacet>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This film contains footage of skiers skiing in a single file line, playing leapfrog on skis, and bunny hopping in place.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">17</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">Deep Duck</title>
          </unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1973</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>8mm film</genreform>
            <physfacet>
              Color, silent
            </physfacet>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This film contains footage of an amateur play preformed on skis. The play begins with a classroom full of people. The villain of the play disrupts the class by running out. The next image is of a rubber ducky floating in swampy grass. The villain skis by the rubber ducky and stops to give some children a snack. Then you see the villain in the locker room stealing lunches. Next the villain kidnaps a young women and skis away with her. A young man sees the villain and starts to chase him; the villain knocks the girl out and skis away. The girl is rescued, but the villain later catches up to the rescuer and attacks him. This leads into a high-speed chase that ends with the villain being caught.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">18</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">Ski the Sky</title>
          </unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1974</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>16mm film</genreform>
            <physfacet>
              Color, optical soundtrack
            </physfacet>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This film was produced for Big Sky of Montana and Hart Ski Company by The Film Factory.</p>
          <p>Director: Jim Cotter</p>
          <p>Writer: Duane Johnson</p>
          <p>Music: Dale Mentea</p>
          <p>The film begins with shots of skiers interspersed with shots of a red hot air balloon with "Ski the Sky" written on it. After some scenic shots from the sky, the balloon lands and there are more images of skiers. The scene shifts to the lodge restaurant and bar where tired skiers eat sandwiches, have a few drinks and dance. Next there are images of cross-country skiers, a horse-drawn sled, and people of all ages getting ready to go alpine skiing. The closing image is of the red hot air balloon leaving the ski area.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">19</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">Skiing Park City</title>
          </unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1976 December 14</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>16mm film</genreform>
            <physfacet>
              Black and white, color, sound
            </physfacet>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>a-c) Olympic Medal winner Stein Eriksen takes you powder skiing through winter beauty, down a slalom course, over a summersault jump and through a few moguls. Then he leads you to the resort lobby where food and entertainment take over. Produced by Dick Barrymore Productions Inc.</p>
          <p>d) This same film, this time introduced by a short black and white clip from the 1960's and 1970's which contains free skiing, downhill racing and footage of the torch run which is when several skiers organize a night skiing event in which each individual attaches road flares to the ends of their poles, hold them out at a ninety degree angle and ski down the hill.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">20</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">The Spirit Of The West</title>
          </unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1978 November 28</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>16mm film</genreform>
            <physfacet>
              Color, sound
            </physfacet>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>a-c) This film is a Warren Miller production in which the spirit of an 'old timer' takes the viewer on a journey through time from the Old West to the modern ski resorts.  It features skiing on the slopes and other resort activities.</p>
          <p>d) The same film narrated in Japanese.</p>
          <p>e) A very similar film used as a promotional video by United Airlines.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">21</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Randy's film</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1978</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>16mm film</genreform>
            <physfacet>
              Color, sound
            </physfacet>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This film contains raw footage of ski jumping, dog sled racing, a torch run, and downhill skiing.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">22</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">Ski and Ski Better</title>
          </unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1982</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>16mm film</genreform>
            <physfacet>
              Color, sound
            </physfacet>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>a-c) A detailed how-to film for the novice skier.  Ski instructors conduct classes on skiin techniques at Utah ski resorts.</p>
          <p>d-e) Revised versions of the film.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">23</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">Utah: The Greatest Snow on Earth</title> short version</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1983</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>16mm film</genreform>
            <physfacet>
              Color, optical sound
            </physfacet>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>A promotional film for Utah's ski industry.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">24</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">Skiercise</title>
          </unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1983</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video was produced by Dean Stephen Lyras. It is an exercise film that gets you in shape for skiing. There are seven 10-minute segments and each segment contains a workout designed specifically to strengthen one type of skiing: freestyle, helicopter skiing, ballet, telemark, and cross-country. Each segment is started out by a group of girls demonstrating each move. After this, there is footage of the type of skiing that corresponds to that particular workout.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">25</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">Park City Ski</title>
          </unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1984 April 12</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Produced by Rocky Mountain Motion Pictures.  This is footage of a womens giant slalom ski race. It shows the women at the starting gate, in the middle of the course, the scoring returns and the awards ceremony. There are interviews with the top two racers at the end of the film.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">26</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Channel 5/Coca Cola Cup</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1985 February 03</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video shows highlights from the fifth week of the 1985 Channel Five/Coca Cola Cup Race event at Park City Utah. This event is a giant slalom race on a course that drops 400 vertical feet and has 27 gates. The event is open to amateur skiers of all ages.</p>
          <p>KSL's Jim Derkir narrates the video and reviews slope conditions and the history of Park City Ski Area.  Before the races, Stein Eriksen gives a few racing tips.  The results from the various age groups are reviewed, as are the results of all of the first place winners are reviewed.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">27</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">Park City Ski Area</title> rough cut</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1985 July 11</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Rough cut of an advertising film in which a family decides to travel to Park City, Utah to ski. It includes footage of Park City's facilities, restaurants, bars, and ski slopes. Featured terrain includes backcountry powder, moguls, groomed hills, and trees. The film also advertises Celebrity Ski Classics, which take place on the Park City race hills.</p>
          <p>2 cassettes.  The same footage repeated eight times.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">28</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">U.S. Ski Team Celebrity Ski Classic</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1985 October 15</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>The Celebrity Classic is a ski-racing event that is held yearly to raise funds for the United States (U.S.) Ski Team. The teams consist of athletes, celebrities, and sponsors. The races include head to head competition on parallel racecourses and individual "grudge" races. The individual "grudge" races consist of racing down the course with one ski, going down the course skiing backwards, having to tow a person in a toboggan behind you, or sliding down the course with two people on one piece of plastic. To wrap the event up, participants head indoors to hear Michel Martin Murphy perform followed by a few words from many loyal sponsors of the U.S. Ski Team.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">29</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">"Ski Park City", "Ski Vacation"</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1985 December 11</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>U-matic videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains two thirty-second advertisements. The first advertises a contest in which you could win a ski vacation to Park City, Utah. The second advertises Park City Ski Area's vast terrain and the resort's facilities.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">30</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">Heli-High</title>
          </unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1985 December 26</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>16mm film</genreform>
            <physfacet>
              Color, sound
            </physfacet>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Canadian Mountain Holidays (CMH) Heli-skiing presents "Heli-High," produced and directed by Dick Barrymore. This film is shot at Estar Base, which includes the Pucells, Selkirks, Monashees and Cariboos mountains. There is also footage from Val D'Isere, Zermatt, Chamonix, Aspen and Snowbird. The footage consists of skiers being dropped off at the top of a mountain by a helicopter and skiing down. It also shows how it is determined which mountains are the safest to heli-ski on by means of examining various snow layers.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">31</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Special Olympics</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1985</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This is a sixteen-minute coverage of the 1985 Special Olympics by Turner Broadcasting System (TBS) Sports. The footage includes the opening ceremonies, the giant slalom event, the downhill event, speed skating, figure skating, celebrity racing, and the closing ceremonies.</p>
          <p>3 cassettes</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">32</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">Park City Ski Area: Of All the Places in the World</title>
          </unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1985</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Promotional video for Park City Ski Area.</p>
          <p>3 cassettes</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">33</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">Summerside</title>
          </unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1985</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This is a promotional video for Park City's summer activities. Activities include golfing, tennis, hiking, horseback riding, hot air ballooning, water skiing, arts festivals, and live music indoors and out.</p>
          <p>2 cassettes</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">34</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">Winter in Park City, Utah</title>
          </unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1985</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This is a promotional video for Park City's winter activities. A few of the activities included are alpine skiing at one of the three surrounding resorts, cross country skiing at Jeremy Ranch, backcounty dog sled tours, snowshoeing, and hot air ballooning.</p>
          <p>2 cassettes</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">35</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">America's Opening World Cup</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1986 January 26</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette, U-matic videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This World Cup, held at Park City Ski Area, was the first World Cup in North America ever. This video contains footage of the Opening Ceremonies held at the University of Utah followed by the Salt Lake City Ski Ball at the Westin Hotel Utah. The featured races are the women's slalom and the women's giant slalom. After the races, a few words are said at the World Cup Closing Dinner.</p>
          <p>3 cassettes</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">36</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">America's Opening World Cup advertisements - "The Festival" and "The Flag Racing"</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1986 February 12</unitdate>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1986 March 11</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette, U-matic videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains two promotional clips: one is for the U.S. Womens ski team and the other is for an event called the U.S. Ski Team Versus the World. Each promotional clip is 30 seconds long and gives dates, times, locations and ticket information.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">37</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">America's Opening World Cup advertisements</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1986 November 03</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video has two promotional clips for Americas Opening World Cup ski races. The first one is a ten second version which gives the date, time and location. The second one is thirty seconds long and it gives a few facts, the date, time, location and ticket information.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">38</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">America's Opening World Cup - Birney revised</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1986 November</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>1-inch videotape</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>No description is provided because 1-inch videotape could not be played at our facility at the time this collection was processed.  However, our capabilities are constantly changing.  Please contact a multimedia archivist about the current possibility of viewing this material.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">39</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Hyrum W. Smith seminar review tape</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1986</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>Audiocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Hyrum W. Smith, one of the founders of the Franklin Institute Inc. and senior vice president of marketing, conducts a seminar on time management and organizational skills.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">40</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Park City World Cup invitation raw footage</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1986</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>U-matic videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains raw footage of Craig Badami, the vice president of Park City Ski Area, inviting everyone to welcome home the U.S. Women's Ski Team as they take on the world at the Park City World Cup ladies slalom event.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">41</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">Park City Travelview</title>
          </unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1987 March 05</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This is a promotional video for Park City Ski Area. It promotes both the town and the terrain with clips of city and ski slop activities.  The advertised terrain includes groomed hills, backcountry powder, moguls, race hills and trees.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">42</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">KPCW - Utah Symphony announcement 41</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1987 May 05</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>Reel-to-reel audiotape</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Radio advertisement for the Utah Symphony.  30 seconds.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">43</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Park City Ski Area television news coverage</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1987 September 03</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>The first story covered on this video is about the Park City Midmountain Lodge, a historical building in Park City Utah, which was moved five hundred feet up the mountain and turned into a restaurant.</p>
          <p>The second story is about the upcoming Pro Cup Ski Race at Park City Ski Resort. News reporters interview Mark Menlove, Holly Flanders and Scott Hofmann.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">44</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">Ski In: Snowbird, Utah</title>
          </unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1987 October 08</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Jack Eddies <title render="italic">Ski In</title> honors the best skiing in North America and offers information on what is happening in the Western ski areas. In this episode Eddie visits Snowbird, Utah where he features the terrain, the Cliff Lodge, the racing competition, the friendly atmosphere and the beautiful scenery.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">45</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Park City Pro Cup</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1987 November 09</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>1-inch videotape</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>No description is provided because 1-inch videotape could not be played at our facility at the time this collection was processed.  However, our capabilities are constantly changing.  Please contact a multimedia archivist about the current possibility of viewing this material.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">46</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">Ski Utah</title>
          </unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1987</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Promotional film produced by Travelview International.  The video contains a 22-minute feature about Utah's ski areas, a reference guide providing information on Utah's ski resorts in Utah, lodging and accommodation tips, dining and tourist oriented services, and a Travel Tips segment.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">47</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">Deer Valley Resort</title>
          </unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1987-1988</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This promotional video showcases Deer Valley's ski terrain, lodging, food, services, and summer season events.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">48</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Park City Senators Ski Cup</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1988 January 13-14</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>The Senators Ski Cup is a race that is held annually at the Park City Resort. This event was organized by former Senator Jake Garn to benefit the Primary Childrens Hospital and raises around 100,000 dollars through friendly head to head slalom races.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">49</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Park City Senators Ski Cup</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1988 January 21</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>More detailed footage of the Senators Ski race that is held annually to raise money for the Primary Childrens Hospital. The event was organized by former Senator Jake Garn and consists of a head to head competition slalom course.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">50</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">Ski Scene: Sun Valley, Idaho</title>
          </unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1988 January 29</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>
            <title render="italic">Ski Scene</title> is a television-program that tours various ski areas to show what they have to offer. In this episode, they travel to Sun Valley, Idaho. They review the history of Sun Valley, explore the modern site and pursue recreational adventures such as downhill skiing, cross country skiing, sleigh riding, and ice skating. They also rate the accommodations, restaurants and shops.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">51</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Canyon master plan</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1988 July 31</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This news report documents a heated controversy of developing a ski interconnect in the Wasatch Mountains. The reporter introduces the four scenarios of development followed by a discussion between Gale Dick with Save Our Canyons and Craig Badami with the Utah Ski Association. They discuss many pros and cons for each scenario.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">52</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Park City Pro Cup revised</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1988 October 31</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>1-inch videotape</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>No description is provided because 1-inch videotape could not be played at our facility at the time this collection was processed.  However, our capabilities are constantly changing.  Please contact a multimedia archivist about the current possibility of viewing this material.</p>
          <p>2 reels</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">53</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Park City Pro Cup television news coverage</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1988 November 18-28</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>These news reports discuss the planned events for the weekend of the Pro Cup Skiing race in Park City Utah. They showcase the Mahre brothers who are returning to competitive ski racing after a four-year hiatus after winning Olympic medals in Sarajevo. They show action shots of past Pro Cup winners and discuss dates, times, locations, and ticket information.</p>
          <p>2 cassettes</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">54</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Park City Pro Cup awards footage</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1988 November 23</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>Betacam videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Footage of the awards ceremony for the 1988 Pro Cup held in Park City, Utah.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">55</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Park City Pro Cup</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1988 November 30</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This is footage from the Pro Cup skiing event held at Park City, Utah. Featured are the men's and women's qualifying races, the men's slalom and giant slalom as well as the women's slalom and giant slalom.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">56</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Utah Connections - Americas Opening in Park City</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1988 December 02</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Images of professional skiers, judges, ski lifts, hot air balloons, spectators, etcaccompanied by music. This video appears to be a background piece intended to be used as visual filler during a newscast or similar type of television program.  Running time: Approximately 4 minutes.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">57</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Television news coverage</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1988 December 05-21</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
            &gt;
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>12/5/88 KSTU Utah Connections Ski Trips with Scott Cross Pt. 1</p>
          <p>12/6/88 KSTU Utah Connections Ski Trips with Scott Cross Pt. 2</p>
          <p>12/7/88 KSTU Utah Connections Ski Trips with Scott Cross Pt. 3</p>
          <p>12/8/88 KSTU Utah Connections Ski Trips with Scott Cross Pt. 4</p>
          <p>12/9/88 KSTU Utah Connections Ski Trips with Scott Cross Pt. 5</p>
          <p>12/8/88 KTVX 5:30 pm Japanese Skiing in Utah (Menlove).</p>
          <p>12/8/88 KTVX 10:00 pm (Voice Over)</p>
          <p>12/11/88 KTVX 10:00 pm Handicapped Ski Program.</p>
          <p>12/12/88 KUTV 6:00 pm Park City, etc. prepare for Japanese skiers.</p>
          <p>12/20/88 KTVX 5:30 pm Park City, etc. are booked.</p>
          <p>12/21/88 KUTV 6:00 pm Ski Resorts want to keep sales tax.</p>
          <p>Park City's 25th Anniversary (one clip).</p>
          <p>12/21/88  KTVX  5:30 pm Ski resorts want to keep sales tax.</p>
          <p>Park City's 25th Anniversary (one clip).</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">58</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">PM Magazine</title> in Orlando</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1988</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This tape consists of a television news story concerning Park City ski resort.  The story is about the Utah ski industry as a whole and hosts Beth Wood and Bob Gossler discuss Park City Ski Area in particular.</p>
          <p>Other news stories included in the same episode feature Donald Trump and the disc jockey who inspired the film, <title render="italic">Good Morning, Vietnam</title> (Barry Levinson 1987).</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">59</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">America's Opening: Park City Pro Cup</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1988 Fall</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This is a 30 second advertisement for the America's Opening Pro Cup in Park City, Utah, Thanksgiving, 1988.  There are various shots of ski competitions and sights around Park City set to instrumental music.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">60</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">TV 45 marketing promotional video, winter season</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1988-1989</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Poor quality VHS copy of local Park City television station TV 45's yearly marketing promotional video.  The tape shows television and community highlights from the previous year in Park City, Utah.  Marketing Director: Kim Steit.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">61</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Utah Ski Ball</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1988</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>U-matic videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>A dress rehearsal of a dance troupe preparing for a performance at the 1988 Utah Ski Ball.  The camera is in a fixed position throughout the duration of the tape's length while dancers perform on a recently constructed stage.  There is also footage of electricians, etc.working on the last-minute preparations for the performance.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">62</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Utah Ski Ball</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1988</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>U-matic videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This tape contains images from the Utah Ski Ball in 1988.  A man, who seems to be the evening's master of ceremonies, speaks about the silent auction.  He then introduces the following people: Spence Eccles, Craig Badami, the CEO of the U.S. Ski Association (Howard Peterson), the director of the U.S. Ski Education fund (John Wilson), and a few other names including two female athletes who join the M.C. on stage.  The camera remains on the M.C. throughout this presentation.  Suzy Harris Rytting addresses the audience.  Next, the dance troupe from cassette 37 performs for the audience at the Ski Ball.  The M.C., who introduces Merrill Osmond of the Osmond Family, follows them.  Mr. Osmond sings a number of songs and interacts with the audience.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">63</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Utah Ski Ball (continued)</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1988</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>U-matic videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This tape contains more images of Merrill Osmond singing.  During his performance, Craig Badami gets onstage with him and together they sing, clap and try to get the audience to join in with the clapping.  There are shots of the audience dancing and clapping in time.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">64</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Senators Ski Cup</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1989 January 14</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>The Senators Ski Cup is a race that is held annually at the Park City Resort. This event was organized by former Senator Jake Garn to benefit the Primary Children's Hospital and raises around 100,000 dollars through friendly head to head slalom races. After showing footage of various senators racing, the sponsors are interviewed. These sponsors include American Express, Park City Ski Area, Delta Airlines, U.S. West, BMI, First Security, Lucas Aerospace, and Textron.</p>
          <p>2 cassettes</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">65</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">News Travel Network: Park City Ski Area</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1989 January 16</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This promotional tape for Park City Ski Area aired on the News Travel Network as a five part series. The episodes highlight Park City's mining history, the various recreational activities in and around Park City, the convenience of traveling to the ski area and lodging and dining in Park City.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">66</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Television news coverage</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1989 January 25-30</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>1/25/89 "Salt Lake City hopes for 1998 Olympics". This news report covers the Olympic Committee selecting their favorite sites for the Olympics and the four venue plans that they are considering. In all of these plans, the cottonwood canyons are excluded due to environmental concerns.</p>
          <p>1/27/89 "Ski Tax Bill". In this edition the pros and cons of the Ski Tax Bill are discussed.</p>
          <p>1/28/89 "U.S. Journalists Visit The Wasatch Front". Nine U. S journalists visit Park City Ski Area, Snowbird, Sundance, and Snow Basin. After their visit, they give their brief thoughts on the Wasatch Front.</p>
          <p>1/29/89 "Disabled Ski Championships". In this report various disabled skiers are interviewed and clips from the race are aired.</p>
          <p>1/30/89 "Ski Resort Operators Convention at Park City Ski Area" This is a report on a convention that was designed to bring business to various manufacturers of mechanical parts for ski resorts.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">67</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Skiing on the rocks</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1989 February 05-09</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This five part series on the struggles of the Utah ski industry was produced by KUTV news. Reporters claim that Utah resorts are falling behind the industry and cannot afford to catch up due to the Utah sales tax burden. As a consequence, several ski resorts are sold and some claim bankruptcy. In an interview with Snowbird's manager he discusses how the competition is beating Utah resorts and what Utah resorts plan to do to reach the top of the industry.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">68</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Koalafier</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1989 February 28</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This is a 30 second advertisement for a ski competition. The competition is sponsored by 7-11, KJQFM, Koala springs, and MTV. The two dual slalom skiers who win the race will win a trip to Australia.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">69</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Ski It to Believe It</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1989 September 07</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>Audiocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This tape contains four promotional songs for the skiing industry. Each of them encourages inexperienced skiers to get up to the slopes because you 'have to ski it to believe it'.</p>
          <p>60 Second - Regional / Call Outs</p>
          <p>60 Second - Ski Area / Call Outs</p>
          <p>60 Second - Ski Shop / Call Outs</p>
          <p>30 Second - Instruments With Singer Tag</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">70</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Park City Ski Area: pre-season</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1989</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>Audiocassette, reel-to-reel audiotape</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This tape contains three sixty-second advertisements for Park City Ski Area's season passes and other discount tickets: "Ski Party" and "Ski the Best For Less."  The advertisements follow the format of the game show <title render="italic">Jeopardy</title>.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">71</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">America's Opening World Cup advertisement</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1989 October 25</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This tape contains an advertisement for America's Opening World Cup event held at Park City, Utah over Thanksgiving weekend 1989. The advertisement highlights times, dates, event locations and ticket information and is narrated by a woman.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">72</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">America's Opening World Cup advertisement</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1989 October 25</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This tape contains an advertisement for America's Opening World Cup event held at Park City Utah over Thanksgiving weekend 1989. The advertisement highlights times, dates, event locations and ticket information and is narrated by a man.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">73</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">America's Opening World Cup advertisement</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1989 October 26</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette, Betacam videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This tape contains an advertisement for America's Opening World Cup event held the Park City Ski Resort over the Thanksgiving weekend in 1989. The advertisement highlights times, dates, event locations and ticket information and is narrated by both a man and a woman.</p>
          <p>3 cassettes</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">74</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">America's Opening World Cup advertisement</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1989 October</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This tape contains an advertisement for America's Opening World Cup event held at the Park City Ski Resort over the Thanksgiving weekend in 1989. The add highlights times, dates, event locations and ticket information and is not narrated.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">75</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">CNN Travel Guide - Park City Utah</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1989 November 06-10</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains the same footage as cassette 65 but was aired on CNN's travel program. The program highlights the history of Park City and how it evolved from an old silver mining town into a booming ski haven, how Park City is developing in order to become the ultimate Olympic venue, how to avoid long lift lines and where to ski and what types of recreation Park City has to offer in addition to the great downhill skiing.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">76</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">America's Opening World Cup</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1989 November 22</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>Betacam videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This videocassette contains the opening ceremonies held at the University of Utah where senator Jake garner offers a warm welcome and congratulations to the athletes competing in the world cup. Following this, the U.S. Alpine Ski Team director speaks. Next they show clips from the actual races and the awards ceremony. Continued on 77.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">77</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">America's Opening World Cup</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1989 November 22</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>Betacam videocassette, VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Continued from 76.  This tape contains footage from the Utah Ski Ball, dancing, and entertainment from musicians such as Ed Ames. This is followed by clips from the women's slalom and giant slalom races along with the official results from the two races.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">78</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Park City street dance</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1989 November 22</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>Betacam videocassette, U-matic videocassette, VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>The Park City Street Dance accompanies the coming of the America's Opening event each year. It is a celebration of the love for skiing as well as an event to congratulate the athletes who compete in an America's Opening event. The street dance includes live outdoor music and dancing.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">79</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">U.S. Pro Cup camera footage</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1989 November 22</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains raw footage of the street dance and fireworks, the 1989 U.S. Pro Cup women's and men's giant slalom race, the crowds dancing and cheering and the flag parade.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">80</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">U.S. Pro Cup camera footage</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1989 November 22</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains raw footage of the women's giant slalom race, the men's giant slalom race, and the awards ceremonies.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">81</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Aerials and mineshafts</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1989 November 22</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>U-matic videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains an aerial view of Park City's mountains, ski runs, and mineshafts during the winter season.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">82</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Park City death</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1989 November 28</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This tape contains a 30 second news clip covering a helicopter crash in Park City, Utah.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">83</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">America's Opening World Cup: women's slalom</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1989 November</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video features the first and second runs of the women's World Cup slalom event. In addition to showing each competitor in the course, the film reviews the racers past accomplishments, current standings and future goals and reports on course conditions, weather conditions, and wins by course.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">84</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Utah Ski Ball</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1989</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>U-matic videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains footage of the auctioning of trips and cars from which all proceeds go to the U.S. Ski Team. After the auction, there is live music from Ted Miller and the High Rollers and Bobby Freeman. The live music and entertainment is continued on cassette 85.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">85</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Utah Ski Ball</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1989</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>U-matic videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Continued from 84.  More footage of live music and entertainment. The artists featured include Leon Use and the Coasters and Joe Muscalini.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">86</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Television news coverage</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1989 November 16</unitdate>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1989 November 22</unitdate>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1989 November 30</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains reports on the importance of the World Cup. The reporters emphasize the fact that the World Cup acts as a tourist attraction, which in turn raises ski revenues. They emphasize the importance of improving Park City Ski Area's snow making technology so that they can always supply a reliable course for the World Cup events regardless of the weather.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">87</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">America's Opening World Cup television news coverage</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1989 November 19-25</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>11/19/89 KUTV 10 pm "Lack of snow may cause difficulties"</p>
          <p>11/21/89 KTVX 5:30 pm "Women's ski team trains in karate"</p>
          <p>11/22/89 KUTV 5 pm	"World Cup in Park City"</p>
          <p>6 pm "World Cup begins and Park City spends the most to help the Olympic Bid"</p>
          <p>KTVX 10 pm	"preparations for the World Cup include making snow"</p>
          <p>11/23/89 KSL 6 pm "World Cup is an important event for Utah's ski future and World Cup is underway"</p>
          <p>10 pm "World Cup Opens and World Cup underway"</p>
          <p>KUTV 5 pm "Snow machines save World Cup"</p>
          <p>6 pm "Ski industry suffers this thanksgiving except Park City, who is hosting World Cup and World Cup Coverage"</p>
          <p>10 pm "World Cup action"</p>
          <p>KTVX 5:30 pm "World Cup"</p>
          <p>6 pm "World Cup could influence the Olympic bid and a look at the World Cup and a look at preparations for the World Cup"</p>
          <p>11/24/89 KSL 6 pm "women's events at the World Cup"</p>
          <p>10 pm "women's events"</p>
          <p>KUTV 5 pm "women's day at the World Cup"</p>
          <p>6 pm "World Cup and the Olympic bid"</p>
          <p>10 pm "World Cup and Olympic Bid and</p>
          <p>World Cup highlights"</p>
          <p>KTVX 5:30 pm "World Cup successful and international attention, World Cup day for Women"</p>
          <p>10 pm	"international media and women's races highlighted"</p>
          <p>KUTV 6 pm "Profile of the media coverage"</p>
          <p>KUTV 6 pm "Today's Action"</p>
          <p>KTVX 10 pm "Snow fall helps course"</p>
          <p>KTVX 10 pm "Today's action"</p>
          <p>KSL 5:30 pm "Cancellation"</p>
          <p>KSL 10 pm</p>
          <p>Sports Beat "Wrap up report"</p>
          <p>11/26/89 KUTV 5:30 pm "Cancellation"</p>
          <p>KUTV 10 pm</p>
          <p>KTVX 10 pm</p>
          <p>KTVX 10 pm "Wrap up on results"</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">88</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">America's Opening World Cup</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1989 November</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This is an overview of the four-day Thanksgiving weekend World Cup event. The film casts the event as a celebration of accomplishments and a time to share an international love for skiing and features footage of the races, the crowds going wild, and the street dance held in Park City, Utah with live music and dancing.</p>
          <p>2 cassettes</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">89</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">"Park City Ski", "America's Opening"</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1989 November</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>Audiocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This tape contains two sixty-second advertisements for the America's Opening World Cup event held at the Park City Ski Resort over the Thanksgiving weekend in 1989. The add highlights times, dates, the event schedule and special events such as live music and dancing as well as ticket information. Danny Jessop on the radio station Magic 107.5 aired these advertisements.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">90</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Craig Badami memorial parts 1-2</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1989 December 2</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>Reel-to-reel audiotape</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This audiotape contains the memorial services for Craig Badami who was the Vice President of Park City Ski Area. C.B., as he liked to be called, handled the promoting and marketing for Park City Ski Area in addition to bringing the America's Opening World Cup Event to Park City. The services where broadcasted live over the radio station KPCW. While waiting for services to begin, the radio announcer reads through the program, announces the pasture as well as the speakers and the musical interlude. The services then begin with an opening invocation and prayer. Then the pasture reads several letters from various members of the Men's and Women's U.S. Ski Team, all honoring Craig's hard work. Following this, five of C.B's close friends share their own memories of his hard work and fun personality. The musical interlude was offered by C.B's very own band, Johnny and the P.C Rockers.  The band then presents Nicholas Badami, Craig's son, with his harmonica. Five more friends share their loving memories and the service is brought to a close with a benediction.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">91</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">TV 45 avalanche story, Warren Miller feature, Al's Hill feature</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1989</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains three news reports:</p>
          <p>The first is a story on avalanches. It includes avalanche statistics, the definition of the three different types of avalanches along with footage of each type, and information on what to do if you are ever caught in an avalanche.</p>
          <p>The second report is a story on the upcoming Warren Miller production, <title render="italic">Extreme Winter</title>.</p>
          <p>The third is a news report on a ski event named Al's Challenge. This ski event is a relay race that takes place during spring skiing. This coverage ends abruptly.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">92</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">On The Move</title>
          </unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1989</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This is a promotional video for the U.S. Ski Team. It contains comments from the coaches and racers concerning the development of the team as well as comments from the sponsors on why they have chosen to support the team. There is also a brief explanation of each U.S. Ski Team event, what is required of the athletes as far as training, and why it is so important that the World Championships has finally opened in America.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">93</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">"Higher Ground" three minute version</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1989</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>Audiocasette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This is a three-minute promotional song for the Utah Winter Games. Written by Judd Maher and Sam Cardon.</p>
          <p>2 cassettes</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">94</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Jimmie Heuga Center</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1989</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video is a John Sandy production and portrays the life story of Jimmie Heuga.  The Jimmie Heuga Center was created to give physically challenged people a second chance by focusing on what they can do rather than on what they cannot.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">95</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">Salomon Bindings</title>
          </unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">circa 1989-1990</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Promotional video about Salomon bindings.  The film explains the mechanics behind the bindings and the materials used in developing safer and lighter bindings and shows the various bindings produced by Salomon for different levels and types of skiers.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">96</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Holly Flanders news special</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1990 January 06</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>In this news special they discuss Flanders' past skiing accomplishments, current endeavors and future goals.  Flanders also discusses her transition from world wide competitive skier to public relations employee at Park City Ski Area.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">97</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Rossignol advertisement</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1990 January 10</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This tape contains a thirty-second advertisement for Rossignol skis and boots.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">98</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Subaru's fanfare to U.S. Skiing</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1990 October 02</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Promotional video for the U.S. Ski Team and Subaru's sponsorship of them. It reviews the history of Subaru's sponsorship of the team and the history and future of U.S. Ski racing. 12:31.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">99</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Park City Pro Cup advertisement</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1990 November 05</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains thirty-seconds of an advertisement for the Pro Cup event held at Park City Ski Area. It shows the beautiful mountains of Park City and a Pro Cup racer skiing the gates.  The video ends abruptly.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">100</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">U.S. Pro Cup races advertisement</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1990 November 07</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>Betacam videocassette, VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This is a thirty-second advertisement for the fifth annual Pro Cup Ski Tour held at Park City Ski Area. The add includes information on times, dates and ticket information.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">101</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">America's Opening World Cup: women's slalom</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1990 November 24</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains ESPN's coverage of the 1990 World Cup women's slalom event. It begins with highlights from the first run and the corresponding results. Then VISA sponsors a profile of Eva Twardokens that includes a short interview. Next Nordica sponsors a ski fact, in this case, the difference between slalom and giant slalom skis. The second run of the women's slalom event is broadcasted live followed by a report of the final standings.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">102</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">U.S. Pro Cup raw race footage from Extreme Novo</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1990 November 24-25</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains footage of the street dance and fireworks held in the streets of Park City Utah along with the flag parade, balloon release, and the men's 1990 U.S. Pro Cup awards ceremony.</p>
          <p>The next footage is of the 1990 U.S. Pro Cup Women's giant slalom race followed by the awards ceremony.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">103</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Soldier honored at Park City</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1990 November 25</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains a report on a marine named William Thompson who saved six other marines during the Vietnam War. He is honored at Park City Ski Area with a bronze star metal.</p>
          <p>This story is followed by a memorial for Craig Badami (1952-1989). In the memorial Mark Menlove offers memories of his friend and co-worker, they honor his accomplishments, and show past clips of various interviews with Craig himself.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">104</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">U.S. Pro Cup raw race footage</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1990 November 25</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains raw footage of the 1990 U.S. Pro Cup race held at Park City Ski Area. The footage includes a view of the race course and the crowds, a ceremony in which Captain William Thompson is honored with a bronze star metal (see 103 for more details), the women's giant slalom race, and the awards ceremony.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">105</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">U.S. Pro Cup Ski Tour, America's Opening slalom event</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1990 November 25</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video features the U.S. Pro Cup race at Park City Ski Area. The announcers give a brief history of America's Opening Pro Cup then they review the course conditions, the fastest qualifiers, the American qualifiers, and explain how a Pro Cup race is put on.</p>
          <p>The video features runs from the rounds of 32 and 16, the quarterfinals, semifinals and the finals. Race results are reported throughout.</p>
          <p>2 cassettes</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">106</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">U.S. Pro Cup Ski Tour, America's Opening giant slalom event</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1990 November</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video features the U.S. Pro Cup race at Park City Ski Area. The announcers list the locations that the Pro Cup races visit on tour, they give a brief ski history on the top two racers and give a course description.</p>
          <p>The video features runs from the rounds of 32 and 16, the quarterfinals, semifinals and the finals.  Throughout the race the announcers report the race results and host brief interviews with various racers.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">107</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">America's Opening Pro Cup days 1-2</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1990 November</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>Hi-8 videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Starts, bumps, finish, flag parade and balloons, awards, races and announcers.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">108</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">Extreme Winter</title>
          </unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1990</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video is a Warren Miller production and is a screening copy only. It highlights the extreme side of skiing with cliff jumping, snowboarding, deep powder skiing, and mogul skiing. The world's best freestyle riders travel with Warren Miller to Grand Targee, Blackcomb British Columbia, Breckenridge Colorado, to Vermont for the freestyle legends competition, the Colorado Rockies, to an untracked and unnamed mountain in Antarctica, Mammoth, France and to Moscow to find the greatest thrills on skis and snowboards. The U.S. Men's Ski Team and the junior race team are also highlighted in this production.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">109</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Corporate ski challenge</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1990</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>The corporate ski challenge is based on the idea of leaving the stresses of a corporate lifestyle behind and heading to the mountains to get some fresh air and to have fun. Each major corporation races against another in a relay race where the competitors play tug-a-war on skis and ski the course with only one ski. The race takes place at the Alpine Meadows ski area and is followed by live music and dancing.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">110</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">"The World According To Spyder", "Dress To Thrill", "Push It to the Limit"</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1990</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>"The World According To Spyder" and "Dress To Thrill" are advertisements for Spyder ski gear featuring the United States Ski Team, Team Michelob Light/ Spyder, Team Memorex/ Spyder, Scott Kauf , Nelson Carmichael, Robert Aguirre, Roger Aguirre, Scott Kennett, Torjus Berge, Ove Nygren, Niklas Lindqvist, Joel Gaspoz, Christian Orlainsky, Scott Rawles, Hansi Standteiner, Kent Kreitler, Bart Tuttle, Joe Vranka, Ski Club Vail Kyds, Jeff Temple, David Jacobs, Kevin Kaneda, Tom Arnstein, Rianne Aguirre, and Katherine Knowlton.</p>
          <p>"Push It to the Limit" promotes extreme sports. It features extreme snow skiing, barefoot water skiing, motorcycling, skate boarding, climbing and kayaking.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">111</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Ski Demo</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1990</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>Audiocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This tape contains an advertisement for three interconnected mountains on the east coast: Killington, Smugglers Notch, and Piko. The advertisement highlights the snow conditions, ticket prices and short lift lines.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">112</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Park City Ski Area advertisements</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1990</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>Audiocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This tape contains two thirty-second advertisements for Park City Ski Area.</p>
          <p>The first advertises Park City as a leading ski area due to it's large lift capacity, vast terrain, and low ticket prices.</p>
          <p>The second advertises the resident coupon book offered by Park City Ski Area as well as other cheap ticket options for residents.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">113</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Park City Ski Area advertisements revised</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1990</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>Audiocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This tape contains three thirty-second advertisements for Park City Ski Area. All three advertise money saving options on season passes and day tickets.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">114</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Television news coverage</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1990 November 05-1991 April 30</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>11/5 KSL Noon "Park City is opening tomorrow"</p>
          <p>6 pm "Ski resorts will begin opening"</p>
          <p>KUTV 6 pm "Snow storm makes ski resorts happy"</p>
          <p>11/6 KSL 6:30 pm "Park City will open some lifts today"</p>
          <p>KUTV 10 pm	 "Park City will open some lifts today"</p>
          <p>KTVX 5:30 pm "Park City will open some lifts today"</p>
          <p>11/19 KSL 10 pm "America's Cup at Park City"</p>
          <p>11/20 KTVX	5:30 pm	"Lonnie Ivey disabled skier"</p>
          <p>10 pm "Cutting edge series part one"</p>
          <p>11/21 KUTV 5 pm "Park City prepares for big thanksgiving"</p>
          <p>6 pm "snow making machines at Park City"</p>
          <p>KTVX 10 pm "Cutting edge series part two"</p>
          <p>11/22 KTVX	5:30 pm	"Phil and Steve Maher / America's Cup"</p>
          <p>11/23 KSL 10 pm "America's Cup"</p>
          <p>KUTV 10 pm	 "America's Cup"</p>
          <p>KTVX 10 pm "America's Cup"</p>
          <p>11/24 KUTV	6 pm "America's Cup"</p>
          <p>KTVX 5 pm "America's Cup"</p>
          <p>10 pm "America's Cup"</p>
          <p>10 pm "America's Cup"</p>
          <p>10 pm "Closing ftg. Of the America's Cup"</p>
          <p>11/25 KSL	5:30 pm	"America's Cup"</p>
          <p>Sports beat "America's Cup"</p>
          <p>KUTV 5:30 pm "America's Cup"</p>
          <p>10 pm "America's Cup"</p>
          <p>KTVX 5:30 pm	"America's Cup"</p>
          <p>10 pm "America's Cup"</p>
          <p>11/24 KSL 10 pm "Pet Olympics"</p>
          <p>11/25 KUTV	10 pm "Park City veteran honored"</p>
          <p>No December</p>
          <p>1/3/91	KUTV 6 pm "Liquor license at summit house and Snow Hut"</p>
          <p>1/7/91	KTVX 10 pm "U of U Air-med"</p>
          <p>1/9 KSL 6 pm "Handicapped skiers"</p>
          <p>1/15 KUTV 6 pm "IOC visits Park City"</p>
          <p>KTVX 5:30 "War and the Senators Cup"</p>
          <p>KTVX 5:30 pm "IOC visits"</p>
          <p>1/28 KUTV 6 pm "NBS"</p>
          <p>1/30 KSL 10 pm "NBS"</p>
          <p>1/31 KTVX 5:30 pm "NBS"</p>
          <p>2/17 KUTV 5:30 pm "NBS"</p>
          <p>2/23 KSL 6 pm "Jans handicapped ski race"</p>
          <p>KTVX 5 pm "Jans handicapped ski race"</p>
          <p>2/27 KSL 6 pm "NCAA"</p>
          <p>KUTV 10 pm	 "NCAA"</p>
          <p>KTVX 10 pm	"NCAA"</p>
          <p>3/01 KSL 10 pm "NCAA"</p>
          <p>KUTV 10 pm "NCAA"</p>
          <p>KTVX 10 pm	 "NCAA"</p>
          <p>3/03 KSL Sports beat "NCAA"</p>
          <p>KTVX 5:30 pm "High Winds"</p>
          <p>3/04 KUTV 5 pm "High Winds"</p>
          <p>3/05 KUTV Noon "Jimmie Heuga Ski Express"</p>
          <p>3/09 KTVX 5 pm "Handicapped skiing"</p>
          <p>3/19 KTVX 5:30pm "Huntsman Games"</p>
          <p>3/23 KUTV 10 pm "Jimmie Heuga MS Ski Express"</p>
          <p>3/29 KTVX 5:30 pm "Spring Skiing"</p>
          <p>4/22 KTVX 5:30 pm "Writers Fam tour"</p>
          <p>4/05 KTVX 5:30 pm "Military appreciation day"</p>
          <p>4/24 KUTV 6 pm "Development project"</p>
          <p>KUTV 10 pm "Development project"</p>
          <p>KTVX 10 pm "Development project"</p>
          <p>4/30 KTVX 10 pm "Delicate Balance part one"</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">115</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Ski demo</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1990-1991</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>Audiocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This tape contains four separate advertisements. The first one is for the Killington ski area and advertises the improved technology of their snow making equipment, the great terrain, short lift lines, and low-ticket prices. The second one is for Smugglers Notch in Vermont and advertises the great terrain, the short lift lines, and low ticket and season pass prices. The third is for Ski Blue and advertises the great powder and tree runs as well as low season pass prices. The fourth advertisement is for the Piko ski area and is in the format of a radio show. It highlights the high-speed quad lifts, the high elevation of their peaks, their long runs, and their plentiful expert terrain.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">116</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Steamboat Weather Summit</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1991 January 14-18</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains footage from a ski event held at Steamboat Colorado. The event includes driving four-wheel-drive vehicles on a snow and ice course followed by tips for driving in icy conditions, and a southwestern ski race. The ski race is not a typical race but more of a relay race on snow. The relay race includes tasks such as skiing through a patch of heavy brush, then through gates and putting a saddle on a horse with skis still on.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">117</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">Ski Tips</title>
          </unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1991 February 13</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>U-matic videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains an episode from the British television show <title render="italic">Ski Tips</title> featuring Park City Ski Area. The show starts out with a brief history of Salt Lake City, and an interview with Merrile Osmond. It then turns to Park City to highlight the America's Opening races and the street dance, live music, and the Wasatch Brewery. After giving a brief history of Park City, the hosts hit the slopes and give some tips on carving turns. They tour Park City Ski Area and explain how the hostess program operates. They show the costs of traveling to Utah including airfare, car and equipment rentals, and accommodations.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">118</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Ski host</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1991 March 25</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains a news report on a skier who was charged with trespassing because he was giving ski lesson at Park City Ski Area but was not an employee of the ski area. He entered a plea of Not Guilty due to his claims of receiving nothing in return for giving people a few ski tips.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">119</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Park City Ski Area advertisement</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1991 September</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>Audiocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This tape contains a thirty-second advertisement for Park City Ski Area's discounted season pass rates.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">120</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">"Introduction to the Gift of Skiing" commercials</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">October 1991</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains two commercials and a promotional video:</p>
          <p>The first commercial is a thirty-second commercial titled "Ski it to believe it" which encourages people to try skiing.  The second commercial is sixty-seconds also encouraging people to learn to ski.</p>
          <p>The promotional video "Getting Started" encourages people to learn to ski through correcting the preconceived notions that it is too cold or too difficult or too expensive. It provides information on renting equipment, accommodations, ski club programs, ticket prices, clothing requirements, and slope ratings and introduces skiing as a family sport and as a sport for people of all ages.  22 minutes.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">121</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Park City media</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1991 November 13</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>Betacam videocassette, VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains aerial footage of  Park City Ski Area and Park City's mine shafts as well as footage of the high speed quad lifts, clips from the Pro Cup Ski races, the weekend events from America's Opening World Cup races, and the main street in Park City, Utah.</p>
          <p>3 cassettes</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">122</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Park City World Cup farewell</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1991 November 24</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video summarizes the 1991 America's Opening World Cup at Park City Ski Area. It contains clips from the 1991 World Cup races, the street dance and live music in Park City, junior races and the award ceremonies.</p>
          <p>2 cassettes</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">123</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">America's Opening World Cup: men's slalom</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1991 November</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains highlights from the first run of the men's slalom event and a full live coverage of the second run. It also includes a VISA sponsored skier profile of Matt Grosjean and an interview with Alberto Tomba.</p>
          <p>The second portion of the Iron Man triathlon is attached at the end of this tape.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">124</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">America's Opening World Cup advertisement</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1991 November 24</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>Betacam videocassette, U-matic videocassette, VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains a thirty-second advertisement for the America's Opening World Cup event held at Park City Ski Area over Thanksgiving weekend. It highlights the times, dates, events and ticket information.</p>
          <p>3 cassettes</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">125-126</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Park City Ski Area national and local advertisement</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1991 December 10</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette, Betacam videocassette, U-matic videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains a thirty-second national and a thirty-second local advertisement for Park City Ski Area. It advertises Park City as the largest ski area in Utah with the fastest and greatest number of chair lifts and the most variation in terrain.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">127</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">America's Opening World Cup</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1991 December 19</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains footage of the ski racers preparing for races, the men's giant slalom and the first run of the men's slalom race.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">128</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">America's Opening World Cup sponsorship</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1991</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video captures the excitement and enthusiasm of the America's Opening World Cup event. It features clips from the 1991 races, the live music at the Park City street dance, the fireworks, and the flag parade. It portrays the weekend as a celebration of ski racing and a time for all to share their love for skiing. After these clips, the sponsors explain the benefits of supporting the team. The sponsors include VISA, Subaru, Park City Ski Area, and Coca Cola.  6:40</p>
          <p>2 cassettes</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">129</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">America's Opening original billboard cereal boxes</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1991</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains a still picture of a list of all of the sponsors for the America's Opening World Cup race on the original billboard.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">130</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">Park City Legends</title>
          </unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1991</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>"Filmed at Park City using all local talent. Marvel At the skill and endurance of Park City's nationally ranked young freestylers as they ski the grueling bumps. Be amazed as Bob Theobald soars over an incredible one-hundred-and-ten foot cliff. Learn what to do and see in all of Park City's seasons in the video visitors guide at the end of the film." Featured skiers include Stein Eriksen, Bob Theobald, Bob Salerno, Bobbie Burns, Beau Brinkerhoff, Mick Berry, Mark Verrone, Craig Rodman, Dave Berry, and David Dunn.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">131</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">A Fanfare To U.S. Skiing: Commitment</title>
          </unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1991</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Promotional video for the U.S. Ski Team and Subaru's sponsorship of them. It reviews the history of Subaru's sponsorship of the team and the history and future of U.S. Ski racing.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">132</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Television news coverage</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1991 October 03-1992 April 03</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>10/03 KUTV 10 pm "Predictions and making snow"</p>
          <p>10/28 KSL 6 pm</p>
          <p>KUTV Noon</p>
          <p>11/3 KTVX 10 pm "Predictions of banner year"</p>
          <p>11/11 KUTV	5 pm "Preparing for the World Cup"</p>
          <p>11/18 KUTV	11 pm "Much needed snow comes"</p>
          <p>11/21 KSL 9 pm</p>
          <p>KUTV 6 pm "Jeremy Nobis profile"</p>
          <p>KTVX 10 pm</p>
          <p>11/22 KUTV	6 pm "America's Cup opening, concert prep"</p>
          <p>KUTV 10 pm</p>
          <p>KTVX 5:30 "Prize money"</p>
          <p>KTVX 10 pm "Prize money and concert"</p>
          <p>11/23 KSL 6 pm "America's Cup results"</p>
          <p>KUTV 6 pm "Travel and tourism and results"</p>
          <p>KTVX 5:30 pm "Race results"</p>
          <p>KTVX 10 pm "Handling major events and results"</p>
          <p>11/24 KSL 5:30 pm "Results"</p>
          <p>KUTV 10 pm "Concert closing"</p>
          <p>KUTV Sports Den "Results"</p>
          <p>KTVX 10 pm "Results and highlights"</p>
          <p>11/25 KTVX	10 pm "Lifts open"</p>
          <p>11/30 KTVX	Images "Injuries"</p>
          <p>12/3 KTVX	5:30 pm	"Out of state skiers, marketing"</p>
          <p>12/20 KTVX	5:30 pm	"Ski Team profile - Kristi Terzian"</p>
          <p>12/26 KTVX	Home Show "Ski Fitness"</p>
          <p>12/27 KTVX	5:30 "Escaping the inversion"</p>
          <p>1/2/92 KTVX 5:30 "Lift Operator profile"</p>
          <p>KTVX 10 pm "Senior citizen instructor"</p>
          <p>1/07 KTVX 10 pm "Utah Winter Games"</p>
          <p>1/08 KTVX 10 pm</p>
          <p>1/09 KTVX 10 pm</p>
          <p>1/11 KSL 6 pm "Ski survey"</p>
          <p>1/17 KTVX 5:30 pm "Profile of junior ski team"</p>
          <p>1/18 KTVX 5 pm "Senators Cup / Protests"</p>
          <p>1/27 KTVX 10 pm "Ski clinic for women"</p>
          <p>2/11 KTVX 10 pm "Nemeth skiing at Park City and night skiing at Park City Ski Resort"</p>
          <p>2/12 KSL 6:30 pm "Live from Park City: Freestyle skiing"</p>
          <p>2/13 KSL Focus "Handicapped Assoc. programs"</p>
          <p>2/16 KTVX 5:30 pm "New snow storms"</p>
          <p>2/17 KTVX 5:30 pm "Nobis recovering"</p>
          <p>2/20 KSL 6:30 pm "Live from ice rink: Utah Olympic team watches Albertville"</p>
          <p>2/22 KSL 5:30 pm "Jans Handicap Challenge and Snow sculpture"</p>
          <p>KTVX 5 pm</p>
          <p>KTVX Images Instructions for Olympic hopefuls"</p>
          <p>2/24 KTVX 10 pm "Jans Handicap Challenge"</p>
          <p>3/07 KTVX Images "Kids with cancer ski"</p>
          <p>3/16 KTVX 5:30 pm "Ski testing"</p>
          <p>3/17 KUTV 6 pm "New snow falls"</p>
          <p>3/21 KTVX 5 pm "Telemark championships"</p>
          <p>KTVX Images "Disabled / Huntsman Cup"</p>
          <p>KTVX 10 pm	"Fundraiser for Nobis"</p>
          <p>KTVX 10 pm	"Telemark competition"</p>
          <p>KTVX 10 pm	(video close)</p>
          <p>3/28 KTVX Images</p>
          <p>4/03 KUTV 10 pm "Skaters perform"</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">133</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Mount Beagle</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1991</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>Audiocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This tape contains an advertisement for Park City Ski Area. It advertises Park City's high-speed lifts, short lift lines, great terrain, dependable snow conditions, and low-ticket prices by comparing Park City Ski Area to a fictional ski area called Mount Beagle.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">134</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">Etc. Etc.</title> - Utah and Park City special</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1992 February 06</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>
            <title render="italic">Etc.</title> was a television series on the Travel Channel.  This episode highlights Park City Ski Area in Utah. The show starts out with a special on the Utah ski patrol teams. They explain how they keep the slopes safe from avalanche danger and give some backcountry safety ski tips.</p>
          <p>The episode then travels to Albuquerque, New Mexico to spotlight mechanics who restore Chevrolets and to Massillon, Mexico for great fishing tips. Next they spotlight Washington State for their delicious apples, Bahamas for the intense tourism attraction, and then back to Park City for a brief history review. They also spotlight the relationship between Park City Ski Area and the U.S. Ski Team.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">135</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">Etc. Etc.</title> - Utah skiing</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1992 February 07</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>
            <title render="italic">Etc.</title> was a television series on the Travel Channel. This episode highlights the Deer Valley and Snowbird ski resorts. They show how Utah ski resorts help to protect the environment during the ski season as well as the off-season.</p>
          <p>The episode also spotlights unknown Mexico vacation destinations, learning to fly, and Eco tourism on the Bahamas peninsula.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">136</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">Etc. Etc.</title> - Utah skiing</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1992 February 07</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>
            <title render="italic">Etc. Etc.</title> was a television series on the Travel Channel. This episode gives a brief history of Park City's silver mining boom and why it became a bust. It introduces snowboarding as a new and exciting sport and spotlights a mountain that was built in Keystone Colorado.</p>
          <p>They also travel to Australia to introduce a man who captures the land down under unlike any other man can, to North Carolina for the history of the Grove Park Inn, and to the Bahamas to introduce the family islands.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cartridge">137</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Park City marketing department</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1992 March 04</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>1/4-inch tape data cartridge</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>No description is provided because 1/4-inch tape data cartridges could not be played at our facility at the time this collection was processed.  However, our capabilities are constantly changing.  Please contact a multimedia archivist about the current possibility of viewing this material.</p>
          <p>3 cartridges</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">138</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">America's Opening World Cup advertisement</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1992 November 02</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette, U-matic videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains a thirty-second advertisement for the America's Opening World Cup even held at Park City Ski Area over the Thanksgiving weekend of 1992. It highlights times, dates, event schedule information and ticket information.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">139</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">America's Opening World Cup advertisement, event video, closing video</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1992 November</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains three segments:</p>
          <p>The first is the same advertisement for the America's Opening World cup as cassette 138.</p>
          <p>The second is an event video of the America's Opening World Cup. In this segment, the Giant Slalom and Slalom courses are defined by the amount of time spent in each course and by the number of gates. It also gives a brief history of various U.S. Ski Team members.</p>
          <p>The third segment is a closing video of the America's Opening World Cup. It shows the top three athletes in the racecourse and then receiving their awards.</p>
          <p>3 cassettes</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">140</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">America's Opening event video</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1992 November</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>U-matic videocassette, VHS videocasstte</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains the same footage as the second segment of cassette 139 along with some Olympic footage and a few interviews with women from the U.S. Ski Team who discuss what they get out of skiing.</p>
          <p>4 cassettes</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">141</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">America's Opening World Cup footage</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1992 November</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains footage from the 1992 World Cup women's giant slalom and slalom races.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">142</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">America's Opening World Cup closing video</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1992 November</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette, U-matic videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video summarizes the America's Opening World Cup event. It also highlights the awards ceremony by showing the top three athletes racing and then receiving their awards.</p>
          <p>4 cassettes</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">143</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">Adventures on Jupiter</title>
          </unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1992 October 19</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video features extreme skiing at Park City Ski Area. It starts out with a geographical description of Jupiter Peak and Jupiter Bowl. These areas are then described by various extreme skiers while the footage of them skiing their plays in the background. Some of the skiers jump cliffs, some ski freestyle, others ski moguls or powder.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">144</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Park City's America's Opening World Cup special</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1992 November 05</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassettes</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains a fifteen minute special on the America's Opening 1986 World Cup event held at Park City Ski Area which was the first World Cup event hosted in North America. It shows footage of the opening ceremonies held at the University of Utah, highlights from the women's giant slalom event, and the official results and awards ceremony. It also shows clips from the Salt Lake City Ski Ball and the World Cup closing ceremonies.</p>
          <p>2 cassettes</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">145</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">America's Opening World Cup: Subaru women's giant slalom</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1992 November 28</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains ESPN's coverage of the 1992 World Cup Women's Giant Slalom event. It shows highlights from the first run and a full live coverage of the second run. It also contains a skier profile on Diann Roffe and reviews the course and weather conditions.</p>
          <p>4 cassettes</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">146</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">America's Opening World Cup: Subaru women's slalom</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1992 November 29</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains ESPN's coverage of the 1992 World Cup women's slalom event. It shows highlights from the first run and a full live coverage of the second run. It also contains a skier profile on Kristina Koznick and reviews the course and weather conditions.</p>
          <p>3 cassettes</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">147</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">America's Opening World Cup: Subaru women's slalom world feed</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1992 November 29</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video starts out with a shot of the racecourse from across the valley then shows the women's first and second runs in the slalom event. Throughout these runs, the camera periodically shows the current standings. After the race, there is footage of the awards ceremony and a few replays.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">148</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">"Ski The West" promotional summary</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1992 December 05-19</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>"Ski The West" is a series from a television program called <title render="italic">Weekend Travel Update</title>. This video compiles several episodes. "Ski The West" shows people how and where to ski in the Western United States, where to stay and what to do with any free time. They feature Park City Ski Area and Deer Valley for their dry, airy powder and their vast terrain, Steamboat, Colorado for their Cowboy downhill race and great terrain, and Squaw Valley for their terrain and surrounding attractions.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">149-150</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Greg and Sarah Snow's wedding at Park City Ski Area (edited)</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1992 December 11</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette, Betacam videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video starts out with a view of Parley's Canyon and the surrounding mountains. Then it shows Greg and Sarah skiing together followed by the marriage ceremony which took place on the ski slopes at Park City Ski Area. Next it shows the signing of the marriage license and the newly wed couple says a few words into the camera.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">151</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">Subaru Ski World with Bob Beattie</title>
          </unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1992 December 12</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>
            <title render="italic">Subaru Ski World</title> is an ESPN program hosted by Bob Beattie. It contains various skiers' opinions of Park City Ski Area, an interview with Kristen Ulmer, an extreme skier, and a clip of her skiing from "Skiing Extreme V". Bob also interviews members of the U.S. Disabled Ski Team who offer advice to other disabled people who have never skied before. Next they show a clip about Colorado avalanche rescue dogs.  Then Bob interviews Jeremy Nobis, a member of the U.S. Ski Team who had just had knee surgery. After this they show clips of horrendous ski racing falls and finally go for a tour of Park City, Utah.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">152</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">U.S. Pro Cup Ski Tour: men's slalom</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1992 December 17</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains ESPN's coverage of the U.S. Pro Cup men's slalom event. It starts with a description of the course from ESPN's course analyzer then shows highlights from the round of thirty-two followed by a full live coverage of the round of sixteen, the quarterfinals, the semifinals and the finals. Throughout the race, ESPN's announcers interview various competitors.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">153</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Park City Ski Area advertisement</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1992 December 10</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>U-matic videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains an advertisement for Park City Ski Area's 1992 winter season. It advertises the vast terrain that is perfect for skiers of all levels as well as the town of Park City.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">154</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">News: Blue Mountain</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1992</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains a news report on the Jimmy Heuga Ski Express, a fundraiser for disabled skiers. Holly Flanders, who skied for the U.S. Ski Team for four years, helps promote this event along with the help of Park City Ski Area.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">155</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Television news coverage</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1992 September 22-1993 April 25</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>9/22/92 KUTV 5 pm "LIVE Weather with Mark Menlove"</p>
          <p>KUTV 6 pm "LIVE Weather"</p>
          <p>11/04 KSL 10 pm "Park City Opens Friday"</p>
          <p>11/06 KSL 6 pm "Pay day run open"</p>
          <p>11/06 KUTV 12 pm "Pay day run open"</p>
          <p>11/06 KUTV	6 pm "Pay day run open"</p>
          <p>11/06 KTVX	5:30 pm	"Park City Opens"</p>
          <p>11/07 KSL 9 am "Park City opened Friday"</p>
          <p>11/06 KBYU	6:30 pm	"Park City opens"</p>
          <p>11/17 KUTV	5 pm "Sterling learns to ski at Park City"</p>
          <p>11/18 KUTV	5 pm "Sterling learns to ski at Park City"</p>
          <p>11/19 KUTV	5 pm "Sterling learns to ski at Park City"</p>
          <p>11/23 KUTV	5 pm "Sterling learns to ski at Park City"</p>
          <p>11/23 KSTU	9 pm "Record snowfall"</p>
          <p>11/24 KTVX	5:30 pm	"World Cup skiing: Terzian"</p>
          <p>11/27 KUTV	5 pm "Weather from Park City"</p>
          <p>11/27 KUTV	6 pm "Ski technicians / snow quality"</p>
          <p>11/27 KUTV	6 pm "World Cup skiing"</p>
          <p>11/27 KUTV	10 pm "World Cup skiing / celebration"</p>
          <p>11/27 KUTV	10 pm "World Cup skiing"</p>
          <p>11/27 KTVX	5:30 pm	"World Cup skiing"</p>
          <p>11/28 KSL 10 pm "World Cup skiing"</p>
          <p>11/28 KUTV	9 am "World Cup skiing"</p>
          <p>11/28 KUTV	6 pm "World Cup skiing"</p>
          <p>11/28 KTVX	5 pm "World Cup skiing"</p>
          <p>11/29 KSL	5:30 pm	"World Cup skiing"</p>
          <p>11/29 KUTV	8:30 am	"World Cup skiing"</p>
          <p>11/29 KUTV 5:30 pm	"Park City retailers / great skiing"</p>
          <p>11/29 KUTV	5:30 pm	"World Cup skiing"</p>
          <p>11/29 KTVX	5:30 pm	"World Cup skiing"</p>
          <p>12/01 KTVX	5:30 pm	"Good ski deals"</p>
          <p>12/05 KUTV	6 pm "Julie Parisien is World Cup winner"</p>
          <p>KTVX Images "Behind the scenes at World Cup"</p>
          <p>12/11 KUTV	10 pm "Pioneer ski instructors visit"</p>
          <p>KTVX 5:30 pm "Pro Racing"</p>
          <p>12/12 KSL	10 pm "Pro Racing"</p>
          <p>KUTV 10 pm "Pro Racing"</p>
          <p>KTVX 5 pm "Pro Racing"</p>
          <p>KTVX 10 pm "Employee killed"</p>
          <p>12/13 KSL 10 pm "Employee killed"</p>
          <p>KUTV 8:30 am "Pro Racing"</p>
          <p>KUTV 5:30 pm "Pro Racing"</p>
          <p>KTVX 5:30 pm "Pro Racing"</p>
          <p>KSTU 10 pm "Employee killed"</p>
          <p>12/14 KUTV	Noon "Employee killed"</p>
          <p>12/19 KTVX	5 pm "Winter Games activities"</p>
          <p>KTVX 10 pm "Winter Games activities"</p>
          <p>12/25 KTVX	5:30 pm	"Mr. and Mrs. Claus go skiing"</p>
          <p>1/9/93 KTVX 5:30 pm "FIS Women's Slalom"</p>
          <p>1/16 KSL 9 am "Senator's Ski Cup"</p>
          <p>1/16 KSL 6 pm "Senator's Ski Cup"</p>
          <p>1/22 KTVX 5:30 pm "Huntsman Cup Ski Race"</p>
          <p>1/23 KTVX 5:30 pm "Skiing deals / discounts"</p>
          <p>1/24 KTVX 5:30 pm "Huntsman Cup Ski Race"</p>
          <p>2/01 KSL 8 am "USWest / Boys &amp; Girls Club ski"</p>
          <p>2/03 KUTV 12 pm "USWest / Boys &amp; Girls Club ski"</p>
          <p>2/05 KUTV 6 pm "Weather/Park City Ski Resort"</p>
          <p>2/06 KUTV 9 am "Mademoiselle on the mountain"</p>
          <p>2/20 KUTV 12:30 pm	"Inside Stuff: Lou Hudson ski instructor"</p>
          <p>2/20 KTVX 5:30 pm "Park City handicap ski race"</p>
          <p>2/20 KTVX 10 pm "US Alpine races"</p>
          <p>2/20 KTVX 10 pm "Jans slalom handicapped ski race"</p>
          <p>2/26 KTVX 5:30 pm "Ski season extended"</p>
          <p>4/14 KTVX 5:30 pm "Ski season extended"</p>
          <p>4/17 KTVX 5:30 pm "Historical tours / Al's Hill"</p>
          <p>4/22 KTVX 10 pm "Ski magazine at Park City Ski Resort"</p>
          <p>4/25 KSL 5:30 pm "Park City Ski Resort closes"</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">156</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">KTVX new stories - Park City Ski Area ski season</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1992-1993</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video is a compilation of all of KTVX's news reports that have any correlation to Park City Ski Area. These reports contain information on Park City Ski Area's opening dates, what goes into hosting a World Cup event and the differences between the World Cup circuit and the Pro Cup circuit, fundraisers and races for disabled skiers, and the instillation of chair lifts at Park City Ski Area.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">157</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">U.S. Pro Cup Ski Tour: men's giant slalom</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1993 January 01</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains ESPN's coverage of the 1992/1993 U.S. Pro Cup ski race. It shows highlights from the round of thirty-two and a full live coverage of the round of sixteen, the quarterfinals, semifinals, and the finals. Throughout the race ESPN plays clips from past Pro Cup races that mainly feature Bernard Knauss. After the race the announcers interview Ove Nygren who took first place.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">158</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">Utah Fest</title>
          </unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1993 January 21</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>&gt;<title render="italic">Utah Fest</title> is a television program on the Weather Channel that features Utah's winter weather. In this episode, the forecaster explains what makes Utah's snow the greatest snow on earth. Then he gives the local weather forecast for Park City and Salt Lake City followed by the extended forecast. Lastly he reviews the ski conditions and shows satellite pictures of the West Coast and discusses the potential snowfall.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">159</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">NBC Inside Stuff</title>: Park City ski instructor</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1993 February 20</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains a news report on a ski instructor at Park City Ski Area named Lou Hudson who is a former NBA (National Basketball Association) All Star basketball player. The news reporter interviews Lou on the chairlift at Park City Ski Area. In this interview, Lou discusses his experiences as a ski instructor and his new program for teaching local Park City children how to play basketball.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">160</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">America's Opening World Cup footage</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1993 October 27</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains footage from the 1993 World Cup men's giant slalom and slalom events. Most of the footage is shot from the starting gate and the middle of the course.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">161</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">America's Opening World Cup advertisement</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1993 October 27</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>U-matic videocassette, VHS videocassette, Betacam videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains a thirty-second advertisement for the America's Opening World Cup event held at Park City Ski Area over the Thanksgiving weekend of 1993. It highlights times, dates, event schedule information and ticket information.</p>
          <p>5 cassettes</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">162</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Park City ski story</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1993 November 19</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains a news report on the concern that Utah ski areas had due to the lack of snow in the early ski season of 1993. They report that a recent snowfall helps attract local skiers but that the tourists are not likely to spend their thanksgiving ski vacation in Utah. The report is followed by Utah's extended forecast.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">163</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">America's Opening World Cup event video</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1993 October</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>U-matic videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This is a promotional video for the America's Opening 1993 World Cup event. It shows what it takes to become a member of the U.S. Ski Team along with the top racers' accomplishments.</p>
          <p>2 cassettes</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">164</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Television news coverage</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1993 December 03-29</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>12/03 KSTU	9 pm "Drug testing at Ski Resorts"</p>
          <p>12/10 KUTV	6 pm "Elder hostel"</p>
          <p>12/11 KSL 10 pm "Live with Mark Menlove on ski industry"</p>
          <p>12/12 KSL 5:30 pm "Big snowfall helps resorts"</p>
          <p>12/24 KSL 6 pm "Resorts report big bookings"</p>
          <p>12/26 KTVX	5:30 pm	"Skimpy snow but big bookings"</p>
          <p>12/29 KSTU	9 pm"Ski magazine and snow country ratings"</p>
          <p>12/03 KSTU	9 pm "Drug testing at Ski Resorts"</p>
          <p>12/10 KUTV	6 pm "Elder hostel"</p>
          <p>12/11 KSL 10 pm "Live with Mark Menlove on ski industry"</p>
          <p>12/12 KSL 5:30 pm "Big snowfall helps resorts"</p>
          <p>12/24 KSL 6 pm "Resorts report big bookings"</p>
          <p>12/26 KTVX	5:30 pm	"Skimpy snow but big bookings"</p>
          <p>12/29 KSTU	9 pm "Ski magazine and snow country ratings"</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">165</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Television news coverage</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1993 August 26-November 30</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>The August news coverage in this video contains a report on the instillation of the King Kong chairlift at Park City Ski Area.</p>
          <p>The October news coverage contains information on Park City Ski Area's new policy of random drug testing for the employees, Olympic construction to raise the bid for Utah being the Olympic venue for the 2002 Winter Olympics, and on Salt Lake City being ranked one of the top ten places to live.</p>
          <p>The November news coverage contains information on Park City Ski Area's opening dates, Park City's preparation for the America's Opening World Cup event, holiday bookings at Utah ski resorts, tips for physically preparing for the ski season, and on the first installment of $30,000,000 out of $75,000,000 given to the Salt Lake City Olympic bid committee by Park City Ski Area to help increase the chances of having the 2002 Winter Olympics in Utah.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">166</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">KTVX new stories - Park City Ski Area ski season</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1993-1994</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video is a compilation of all of KTVX's news reports that have any correlation to Park City Ski Area. These reports contain information on the instillation of chair lifts, the importance of preparing your body for the ski season and how to do so, Holly Flanders' ski clinic for women, and the sponsored junior racing program at Park City Ski Area that offers underprivileged kids an experience that they would not have otherwise had.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">167</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Television news coverage</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1994 January 06-22</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocasette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>1/06 KUTV 5 pm "Weather: skiing at Park City"</p>
          <p>1/06 KSTU 9 pm "Weather: skiing at Park City"</p>
          <p>1/07 KSTU 9 pm "Disabled skiers at Park City"</p>
          <p>1/09 KSL 10 pm "Road to Gold: Erik Schlopy"</p>
          <p>1/11 KSL 6 pm "Road to Gold: Kristi Terzian"</p>
          <p>1/14 KTVX 6 am "Live phone interview: Gay and lesbian ski week"</p>
          <p>1/14 KSTU 9 pm "U.S. Senators ski Cup"</p>
          <p>1/16 KSL 5:30 pm "Road to Gold: Jeremy Nobis"</p>
          <p>1/16 KUTV 10 pm "Gay winter fest ski week"</p>
          <p>1/20 KSL 7 pm "Road to Gold: Utah Olympic athletes (1/2 hour)"</p>
          <p>1/20 KSL 7:30 pm "Winter fest: preparations for Olympics"</p>
          <p>1/21 KSL 6 pm "Handicapped ski races"</p>
          <p>1/22 KSTU 9 pm "Huntsman Cup Trials"</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">168</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Television news coverage</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1994 February 05-26</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>2/5 KTVX Images (3 stories)</p>
          <p>2/6 KSL 10 pm "Skiers qualify for Olympics"</p>
          <p>2/7 KSL Noon "Skiers head for Olympics"</p>
          <p>2/8 KSL Noon "Send off party"</p>
          <p>2/10 KTVX Inside Edition "Senators Cup"</p>
          <p>2/12 KSTU 9 pm "Utahans are optimistic for Olympics"</p>
          <p>KSTU 9 pm "Skiers head for Park City"</p>
          <p>2/13 KTVX 10 pm "Tommy Moe wins"</p>
          <p>2/14 KSL Noon "Experts head to Norway to learn"</p>
          <p>2/18 KSL 6 pm "U.S. Ski Team celebrates"</p>
          <p>2/21 KSTU 9 pm "Presidents day weekend"</p>
          <p>2/22 KTVX 10 pm "Olympic update"</p>
          <p>2/23 KSL 6:30 pm "Jeremy Nobis Road to Gold"</p>
          <p>KTVX 5:30 pm "Jeremy Nobis in Giant Slalom"</p>
          <p>2/26 KSL 10 pm "Jeremy Nobis Olympic update"</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">169</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Television news coverage</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1994 March 12-31</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>3/12 KTVX 5 pm "Jans Rossignol Challenge"</p>
          <p>3/13 KSL 5:30 pm "Winter sports in Utah"</p>
          <p>3/18 KTVX 5:30 pm "Women's ski lessons"</p>
          <p>3/30 KTVX 5:30 pm "Spring Skiing"</p>
          <p>3/31 KTVX 5:30 pm "Park West sold - Park City rumors"</p>
          <p>3/31 KSTU 9 pm "Spring Skiing"</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">170</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Television news coverage</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1994 April 02-14</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>4/02 KUTV 9 am "Easter egg hunt"</p>
          <p>4/04 KSL 6 pm "Park City Ski Resort sold to Powder Corp."</p>
          <p>4/04 KTVX 5:30 pm "Park City Ski Area sold to Ian Cummings"</p>
          <p>4/04 KTVX 10 pm "Park City Ski Area sold to Ian Cummings"</p>
          <p>4/14 KTVX 6 am "Candy Erickson on 1993-1994 season"</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">171</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Lobbyist gifts, Senators Ski Cup</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1994 May 11</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains a news report on the cancellation of the Senators Ski Cup. The Senators Ski Cup was canceled because it was believed to have been a way for lobbyists to win over the popular vote of the senate on various political issues. Along with the cancellation of the Senators Ski Cup, restrictions were placed on what the senators could and could not accept. The restrictions include the termination of free trips and lunches, and the senators are no longer able to accept gifts from anyone but family and close friends.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">172</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Park City Ski Area local commercial</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1994 September 07</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>U-matic videocassette, Betacam videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This thirty-second commercial advertises Park City Ski Area as Utah's largest ski area where you can always find the terrain you are looking for. It also advertises discounted pass rates provided that they are purchased early in the season.</p>
          <p>5 cassettes</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">173</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">America's Opening World Cup advertisement</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1994 October 26</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>U-matic videocassette, Betacam videocassette, VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains a thirty-second advertisement for the America's Opening World Cup event hosted at Park City Ski Area over Thanksgiving weekend of 1994. It highlights times, dates, event schedule information, and ticket information.</p>
          <p>6 cassettes</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">174</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">America's Opening World Cup advertisement</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1994 November 10</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>1-inch videotape</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>No description is provided because 1-inch videotape could not be played at our facility at the time this collection was processed.  However, our capabilities are constantly changing.  Please contact a multimedia archivist about the current possibility of viewing this material.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">175</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">Reel Thrills</title>: The Après Ski Show</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1994 December 27</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>
            <title render="italic">Reel Thrills</title> is a program aired on the Resort Sports Network. It features clips from various sports films and interviews with the filmmakers. In this episode the featured sports are skiing and snowboarding.</p>
          <p>The films shown are: "2 Board With The World" by Joe Jay Jalbert, "The Hedonist" by Steve Winter and Murray Wais, "Ptex, Lies, and Duct Tape" by Greg Stumps, "Extremely Peppered" by Blake Miller, "It's The Source" by Jon Long and James Angrove, "Las Lenas '94" by Mike Ferrari and Alejandro Vayo, and "Crunch" by Sandy Santucci.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">176</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Snow slippers</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1994</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains a five-minute advertisement for Cliff Taylor's Magic Motion System and for the Cliff Taylor Ski Center. The Magic Motion System is based on Cliff Taylor's invention, Snow slippers. Snow slippers aid in the process of learning to turn on skis.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">177</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Avalanche on KPCW news with Chris Eisenberg</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1995 January 03</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>Audiocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This is an avalanche control news report by Chris Eisenberg on KPCW news. Chris Eisenberg tags along with the Park City avalanche ski patrol in order to give a detailed and accurate report.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">178</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">Spinal Snap</title> teaser</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1995 February 07</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This is an extreme skiing video produced by Rob Bruce Films. It contains footage of various extreme skiers and snowboarders each skiing through moguls, powder, off cliffs down chutes and more.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">179</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">Full Access</title> on tour with Pam Tillis</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1995 February 09</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains an interview with country singer Pam Tillis who was awarded the number one female vocalist of the year at the Country Music Awards (CMA). Throughout the interview, there are clips of her Salt Lake City concert at Capital Theatre, the CMA Awards Ceremony, and of Pam skiing at Park City Ski Area.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">180</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Park City Ski Area demo tape: Steve Carlson</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1995 August 18</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>Audiocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <phystech>
          <p>This item cannot be heard due to demagnification of the tape.</p>
        </phystech>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">181</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">KUED project funding</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1995 October 17</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains a thirty-second advertisement aired after KUED programs that lists companies who fund KUED programming. These companies include Park City Ski Area, Granite Furniture Company and O.C Tanner Jewelry.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">182</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">Teck Talk</title>: Peter Keelty and Holly Flanders</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1995 November 16</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>
            <title render="italic">Teck Talk</title> is a show that was designed to educate people on how to find the appropriate ski equipment for their style and level of skiing. Peter Keelty and Holly Flanders are the hosts of this show and they feature five of the top skis in the following categories: giant slalom, "easy carvers" or shape skis, slalom, "groomer cruisers", all mountain and extreme or three-dimensional skis.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">183</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Park City opens - Fox News</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1995 November 28</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains a report on ski areas that are making an effort to lower ticket prices for residential families through special packages and discount coupons. It also contains a report on the opening dates for Park City Ski Area and a local weather forecast.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">184</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">Subaru Ski World with Bob Beattie</title>: Utah Ski Areas</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1995 December 03</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>
            <title render="italic">Subaru Ski World</title> is an ESPN program hosted by Bob Beattie. In this episode of Ski World, Bob Beattie explains why Utah has the lightest and driest snow. He showcases several ski areas in Utah including Alta and Snowbird for the best powder and Deer Valley for being the most luxurious. Bob also hosts interviews with Stein Erikson, Tommy Moe, and Kristi Terzian.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">185</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">See For Yourself: Winter in Park City, Utah</title>
          </unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1995</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains an advertisement for Park City, Utah. "See for yourself. Discover why Park City is host to many venues for the 2002 Olympic Winter Games. It's three resorts in one great town. It's Deer Valley Resort, Park City Ski Area, and Wolf Mountain. It's the great snow conditions and abundant terrain (4700 skiable acres at the three resorts  all within a five mile radius). You can even try jumping at the Utah Winter Sports Park - from the beginning ski play area to flying off the K-18 or K-38 meter jumps. Or if you prefer, you can watch the seasoned Nordic skiers soar off the 65 or 90 meter Olympic jump. Besides skiing, there is plenty to keep you busy. This historic mining town has more shopping, dining and nightlife than you have time for. And what's really worth seeing is how easy it is to get here  just 40 minutes from Salt Lake City International Airport."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">186</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Park City spring break</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1996 February 29</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>Audiocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This is an R&amp;R Advertisement aired on Park City Radio. The advertisement is sixty-seconds long and advertises special airfare rates if flying into Salt Lake City for a spring break ski vacation at Park City Ski Area.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">187</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">All Things Considered</title>
          </unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1996 April 24</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>Audiocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>
            <title render="italic">All Things Considered</title> is a radio program in which many issues are discussed. In this particular program they discuss Park City Ski Area's decision to open the mountain to snowboarders. Charlie Lansche and Robbie Beck, both employees of Park City Ski Area, discuss this matter with the program hosts and respond to phone calls from the public.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">188</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Television news coverage</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1996 April 18-30</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>4/18/96 KUTV 12 PM	"New Lift" This is a report on a six person, high-speed chair lift installed at Park City Ski Area. The new lift replaced the prospector lift.</p>
          <p>4/23/96 KTVX 5:30 PM "Snowboarding"</p>
          <p>4/24/96 KTVX 5:30 AM "Snowboarding" This is a report on Park City Ski Area's decision to open the Mountain to snowboarders.</p>
          <p>4/30/96 KUTV 10 PM	"New Lifts" This is a report on a recall of several new chair lifts due to safety regulations.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">189</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Park City Ski Area pass rates</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1996 September 09</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>Audiocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This tape contains two sixty-second advertisements. The first advertises a savings of over $300 on Park City Ski Area season passes. The second advertises a savings of over $180 on Park City Ski Area season passes.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">190</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">America's Opening World Cup advertisement</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1996 October 30</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette, U-matic videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This is a thirty-second advertisement for the America's Opening World Cup event held at Park City Ski Area over the Thanksgiving weekend of 1996. It highlights times, dates, event schedule information and ticket information.</p>
          <p>3 cassettes</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">191</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Chevy Truck Skiing Magazine on television</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1996 November</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains clips from the 1996 World Cup flag parade, street dance, and the Men's World Cup Slalom event.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">192</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">Skier's Forecast</title>
          </unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1996 December 06</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>
            <title render="italic">Skier's Forecast</title> is a program that is aired on the weather channel. It contains a local weather forecast, ski conditions and resort reports.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">193</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">Ski World with Bob Beattie</title>
          </unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1996 December 08</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>
            <title render="italic">Ski World</title> is an ESPN program hosted by Bob Beattie. In this episode Bob Beattie hosts various interviews at Park City Ski Area. Interviewees include Dave Downing and Shannon Dunn who are two of the top snowboarders, Kristi Terzian who raced on the U.S. Ski Team, Kristen Ulmer who ranks number one for female extreme skiing, and Tommy Moe and Shannon Nobis who both ski for the U.S. Ski Team.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">194</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Park City Ski Area's official Blazer</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1996 December 09</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains a thirty-second advertisement for Chevrolet/Geo becoming Park City Ski Area's official Blazer.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">195</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Snowboarding industry conference and "Powder Quest"</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1996</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This is a video invitation to the Trans-world seventh annual snowboarding conference in Vail, Colorado. The video is formatted after the James Bond movie <title render="italic">GoldenEye</title> (Martin Campbell 1995). The mission, "Red Eye," is to pick up and hand off a red backpack. The backpack contains a video that reveals the next mission which is to attend the snowboarding conference in Vail.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">196</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">RSN.com resort-cam</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">circa 1996-1997</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains an advertisement for the Resort Sports Network's new website. The website provides various ski resorts information.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">197</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Utah ski industry</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1997 February 23</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains an interview with Deer Valley's director of skiing and Olympic gold medallist, Stein Eriksen, Snowbird's director of skiing, Junior Bonous, and the President of the Park City Ski Corporation, Phil Jones. In this interview they discuss why skiing is the greatest sport on Earth, the evolution of ski equipment, changes in Utah skiing, and the pros and cons of having the Winter Olympics in Utah.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">198</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Side cut skis, senior ski club</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1997 February 24</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains a news report on side cut skis and on a senior citizen ski club. The report on the side cut skis includes the scientific design of parabolic skis and Information on why ski resorts invested so much into the designing of these skis. The report on the senior citizens ski club includes interviews with the club members and footage from their race at Park City Ski Area.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">199</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">Ski Utah</title> volume one</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1996 November 09-30</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>
            <title render="italic">Ski Utah</title> is a television program that was aired every Saturday November 9-March 8. Each episode follows a basic pattern: the hosts spotlight various Utah Ski resorts and give skiing or snowboarding tips.</p>
          <p>"Ski Shape" tips are tips for preparing for the ski season, staying in shape for the season and exercising to prevent injury.</p>
          <p>"The Cutting Edge" is a brief introduction to new gear.</p>
          <p>"Ski Stat" is a report on ski resort statistics.</p>
          <p>"Ski Slate" is a calendar of events for ski resorts.</p>
          <p>"Steep Thrills" is an introduction to extreme runs at local Utah ski resorts.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">200</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">Ski Utah</title> volume two</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1996 December 07-1997 January 04</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>See the description for cassette 199 for an outline of the <title render="italic">Ski Utah</title> program.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">201</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">Ski Utah</title> volume three</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1997 January 11-February 08</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>See the description for cassette 199 for an outline of the <title render="italic">Ski Utah</title> program.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">202</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">Ski Utah</title> volume four</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1997 February 15-March 08</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>See the description for cassette 199 for an outline of the <title render="italic">Ski Utah</title> program.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">203</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Sniagrab - Denver version</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1997 August 19</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains twelve fifteen-second advertisements for a sale at Gart Sports. Each advertisement highlights a different item that is on sale and gives sale dates, times and locations.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">204</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Utah business show</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1997 August 19</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains a report on Ski Resorts that are no longer famous for just skiing. They report on Sundance which is famous for it's summer mountain biking, hiking, horseback riding, and arts programs as well as Park City Ski Area which, in the spirit of evolving into a summer destination as well as a winter destination, has changed it's name to Park City Mountain Resort. Park City Mountain Resort is famous for its summer alpine slide, miniature golf, hiking, shopping and much more.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">205</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Park City "EZ Access"</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1997 September 16</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>Audiocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This tape contains a sixty-second advertisement for Park City Mountain Resort's new six person, high-speed chair lift, the new snowboard park, and the easy access pass that gets you straight onto the lift without waiting in any ticket lines.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">206</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">Snowriders 2</title> trailer - Salt Lake City version</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1997 October</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains a five-minute advertisement for a Warren Miller production called <title render="italic">Snowriders 2</title>.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">207</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">America's Opening World Cup advertisement</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1997 November 13</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette, Betacam videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains a thirty-second advertisement and a ten-second revised advertisement for the America's Opening World Cup event hosted by Park City Mountain Resort over thanksgiving weekend of 1997. The add highlights times, dates, event schedule information and ticket information with clips from World Cup races in the background.</p>
          <p>6 cassettes</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">208</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">America's Opening World Cup - KTVX coverage</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1997 November</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This raw news footage of the 1997 World Cup event and contains background noise and overhead announcements but is not narrated. There are images of a Chevrolet Blazer, the America's Opening sign along with the sponsors banners, various skis being tuned before the race, the crowds, and the racers warming up. It then shows the first run of the men's giant slalom race followed by footage of sponsors entering the sponsor hospitality area where they are served hot food and drinks courtesy of Park City Mountain Resort. Next is footage of the second run of the men's giant slalom race.  The camera focuses on the crowds more than the racers during this run.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">209</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Television news coverage</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1997 November 15-23</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>11/15 KSL 11:30 PM "1997 America's Opening World Cup"</p>
          <p>11/16 KSL	5 pm</p>
          <p>11/17 KTVX	5:30 pm</p>
          <p>11/18 KTVX	5:30 am</p>
          <p>11/20 KSL	6 pm</p>
          <p>KSL 10 pm</p>
          <p>KUTV Noon</p>
          <p>KUTV 5 pm</p>
          <p>KUTV 5 pm</p>
          <p>KUTV 5 pm</p>
          <p>KTVX 5:30 pm</p>
          <p>11/21 KUTV	5 pm</p>
          <p>KUTV 5 pm</p>
          <p>KUTV 10 pm (2)</p>
          <p>KTVX 10 pm</p>
          <p>KSTU 9 pm</p>
          <p>11/22 KSL	10 pm</p>
          <p>KSL 10 pm</p>
          <p>KUTV 10 pm</p>
          <p>KTVX 5:30 pm</p>
          <p>11/23 KSL	10 pm</p>
          <p>KUTV 5 pm</p>
          <p>KUTV 5 pm</p>
          <p>KUTV 10 pm</p>
          <p>KTVX 5:30 pm</p>
          <p>KTVX 5:30 pm</p>
          <p>KTVX 10 pm</p>
          <p>KTVX 10 pm</p>
          <p>KSTU 9 pm</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">210</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Craig Badami remembered</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1997 November 21</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This is a KUTV 5 PM news report on remembering the life of Park City's Craig Badami.</p>
          <p>2 cassettes</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">211</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Manitou Productions demo</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1997</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains an advertisement for Manitou Productions. It shows their various capabilities working with film and computer graphics by compiling short clips of high-speed active images, morphing images, fading images, etc.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">212</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">Snow Power</title> trailer</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1997</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains a five-minute promotional video for <title render="italic">Snow Power</title>. "Snow Power is a skiing and snowboarding film that will keep you on the edge of your seat with unbelievable skiing and boarding, breathtaking cinematography and a great musical score.".</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">213</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">Snowriders 2</title>
          </unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1997</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This Warren Miller Production features extreme winter activities, mainly skiing and snowboarding. The extreme skiers travel to Mt. Cook in New Zealand, Blackcomb in Whistler B.C, the Republic of Kosickston on the boarder of China, Killington, Breckenridge Colorado, Alieska and Mt. McKinley in Alaska, Lake Tahoe, Snowbird in Utah, Vancouver B.C, Blue River B.C, and Vail Colorado.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">214</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Television news coverage</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1996 October 06-1997 March 22</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>10/06/96 KSL 5 pm "Silver Load lift towers"</p>
          <p>10/24 KUTV	6 pm "Weather (quick mention of Park City Mountain Resort)"</p>
          <p>KTVX 10 pm "Ski Resort opening dates"</p>
          <p>KSTU 9 pm "Weather (quick mention of Park City Mountain Resort)"</p>
          <p>10/25 KUTV	Noon "Park City opens this weekend"</p>
          <p>KSTU 7 am "Weather (quick mention of Park City Mountain Resort)"</p>
          <p>KSTU Noon "Snow stories"</p>
          <p>10/26 KSL 6 pm, 10pm	"Park City Mountain Resort opens (2)"</p>
          <p>KUTV 5 pm, 10 pm "Park City Mountain Resort opens"</p>
          <p>KUTV 10 pm "Park City Mountain Resort opens"</p>
          <p>KTVX 5:30 pm, 10 pm "Weather (video of Park City Mountain Resort)"</p>
          <p>KSTU 9 pm "Park City Mountain Resort opens"</p>
          <p>11/11 KTVX	5:30 pm	"Park City Mountain Resort opens"</p>
          <p>11/16 KSL	4 pm "Advances in ski technology"</p>
          <p>11/20 KUTV	12, 6 pm "Snowboarding in powder / Bill Bordy"</p>
          <p>KTVX 5:30 pm "World Cup circuit races"</p>
          <p>KTVX 5:30 pm "Weather live in Park City"</p>
          <p>KBYU 4:40 pm "Weather / World Cup races"</p>
          <p>11/22 KSL	12 pm "World Cup races"</p>
          <p>KSL 6 pm "Chefs prepare for thousands in Park City"</p>
          <p>KUTV 12 pm "Rain ruined racing at Park City Mountain Resort"</p>
          <p>KUTV 6 pm "Rain ruined racing at Park City Mountain Resort"</p>
          <p>KUTV 12 pm "Rain ruined racing at Park City Mountain Resort"</p>
          <p>KTVX 5:30 pm "Rain ruined racing at Park City Mountain Resort"</p>
          <p>11/23 KSL	4 pm "Modern snowmaking"</p>
          <p>KSL 4 pm "Next Week: World Cup Wrap Up"</p>
          <p>KSL 10 pm "World Cup racing returned"</p>
          <p>KUTV 10 pm "World Cup racing returned"</p>
          <p>KTVX 10 pm "Utah puts on best face for</p>
          <p>Journalists"</p>
          <p>KSTU 9 pm "Park City Mountain Resort hosts World Cup Ski Tour"</p>
          <p>11/24 KUTV	5 pm "Weather / Par City skiers"</p>
          <p>KUTV 10 pm "Weather / Par City skiers"</p>
          <p>KTVX 5:30 pm "World Cup competition / Olympic training run"</p>
          <p>11/27 KSTU	12 pm "Snow comes for holiday skiers"</p>
          <p>11/30 KSL	4 pm "Snowboarding class / Bill Bordy"</p>
          <p>KSL 4 pm "World Cup wrap up"</p>
          <p>12/05 KSL	12 pm "Reba McIntyre ski injury"</p>
          <p>12/05 KSTU	12 pm "Reba McIntyre ski injury"</p>
          <p>12/20 KSTU	7 am "Santa visits Park City Ski Resort"</p>
          <p>12/21 KTVX	5:30 pm "Ski resorts expect record year"</p>
          <p>KTVX 10 pm "Ski resorts expect record year"</p>
          <p>12/22 KSL 5:30 pm "Fresh powder at Ski Areas"</p>
          <p>KSL 10 pm "Fresh powder at Ski Areas"</p>
          <p>12/25 KTVX	10 pm "Mega-mergers in ski industry"</p>
          <p>12/28 KSL 4 pm "Steep Thrills: Park City Mountain Resort's Jupiter Bowl"</p>
          <p>1/4/97	KUTV 5 pm "Huntsman Cup"</p>
          <p>KUTV 10 pm "Huntsman Cup"</p>
          <p>1/11 KSL 8 am "Fitkids: Cancer survivors learn to ski"</p>
          <p>KSL 4 pm "Parabolic skis"</p>
          <p>1/29 KTVX 10 pm "Ski for the environment tomorrow"</p>
          <p>1/30 KTVX 5:30 pm	"Women only ski lessons"</p>
          <p>2/19 KSTU 9 pm "Park City ski area changes name"</p>
          <p>2/22 KSL 5pm "Special needs skier programs"</p>
          <p>KTVX 10 pm "This week on Utah 1997: Skiing in Utah"</p>
          <p>2/23 KSL 5pm "Ski industry shows"</p>
          <p>KTVX 5 pm "Parabolic skis"</p>
          <p>KTVX 5:30 pm "specialized programs at ski resorts"</p>
          <p>KTVX 10 pm "Specialized ski programs"</p>
          <p>2/24 KUTV 6 pm "Season health center at Park City Mountain Resort"</p>
          <p>3/11 KSL 5 pm "70 Plus skier club"</p>
          <p>KSL 6:30 pm "70 Plus skier club"</p>
          <p>KSL 6:30 pm "70 Plus skier club"</p>
          <p>KTVX 10 pm "70 Plus skier club"</p>
          <p>KSTU 9 pm "70 Plus skier club"</p>
          <p>3/12 KSTU 12 pm "70 Plus skier club"</p>
          <p>3/15 KSL 5 pm "History of Park City Mountain Resort"</p>
          <p>KTVX 5:30 pm "Ability ski challenge"</p>
          <p>3/22 KSL 5 pm "Ski slate/70 plus ski club"</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">215</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">Ski Utah</title>
          </unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1998 February 27</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>In this episode of <title render="italic">Ski Utah</title>, Park City Mountain Resort's quick carve guru Jon DeBoer talks about carving turns on a snowboard and promotes Park City Mountain Resort's quick carve classes. Also in this series, Heidi Voelker talks about her experience of competing in the Winter Olympics.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">216</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">Travel Travel</title> episode 147: Park City, Utah</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1998 October 27</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This is a promotional travel video for Park City, Utah. It includes Park City's history, its present day rustic charm and the current statistics for Park City Mountain Resort such as the number of trails, the highest elevation, yearly snowfall, ticket prices and the quality of the terrain. There is also a review of accommodations and dining in Park City as well as a brief introduction to all of the other recreational activities for those who enjoy a variation to alpine skiing.  28:30.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">217</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Global News and Entertainment</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1998 October</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This is a promotional video for Global News and Entertainment who specialize in sponsored news and image campaigns, public service announcements, video and audio news releases, electronic media kits, executive media training, corporate videos, original programming, documentaries and film.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">218</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Southwest Airlines washing machine</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1998 December 22</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains an advertisement for a special fare offered by Southwest Airlines on a vacation package. The special is that kids fly and ski free when flying on Southwest Airlines and skiing at Brighton, Alta, Snowbird or Solitude.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="disc">219</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Inside Guide to Park City</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1998 Winter</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>CD-ROM</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <phystech>
          <p>For IBM compatibles running Windows '95. System requirements: Microsoft Windows '95 OS, 16 mega bite RAM, 4x CD-ROM drive or better, 16 bit color display, 32 bit QuickTime for Windows (included on CD) and 16 bit audio. Instillation instructions are included.</p>
        </phystech>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This disc "contains comprehensive listings on all that Park City has to offer including recreation and leisure, lodging, dinning and nightlife, shopping, visitor information, calendar of events, real estate, 2002 Olympics, community and education, and services."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">220</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">Higher Ground</title>: Utah's Winter Olympics</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1998</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This is a seventeen-minute movie promoting Utah as a host city for the Winter Olympic Games. They point out the convenience and accessibility of each venue, the cleanliness and safety in the city, the plentiful accommodations, restaurants, and cultural events, and Park City's proven competence to host a world-class event. They also outline the anticipated venue locations.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">221</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Picabo Street, Park City Mountain Resort media tour</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1999 January 04</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains a television interview with two time Olympian Picabo Street.  Street discusses her serious injuries accrued while skiing in the World Championships in Switzerland and how they have forced her to make a decision of whether to start training in the spring for the 2002 Winter Olympics with a metal plate in her leg or to take the metal plate out, rehabilitate for a year, and miss the 2002 Winter Olympics in her home town.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">222</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Piabo Street - KTVX</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1999 January 21</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains an interview with two time Olympian Picabo Street. Street discuses the process of her injury rehabilitation and recovery and how it has effected her psychologically, her racing plans for 2002, which event she will specialize in, and what effects the upheaval with the Salt Lake Olympic Committee is having on the athletes.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">223</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">The Dream Comes True in 2002</title>
          </unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">circa 1999-2002</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video is a celebration of the 2002 Winter Olympics. It starts out with the International Olympic Committee announcing that the 2002 Winter Olympics will be hosted by Salt Lake City Utah. It then shows crowds of people celebrating in various locations. This is followed by an explanation of Salt Lake City's three basic objectives. Their first objective is commitment to the athletes, the second is commitment to the Olympic values, and the third is providing a unique Olympic experience.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">224</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">Victoire a Ski Sur "L'eiger"</title>
          </unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">undated</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>16mm film</genreform>
            <physfacet>
              Color, optical soundtrack
            </physfacet>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This is a French ski film that features cross-country skiing, helicopter skiing and a backcountry skiing expedition.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">225</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Ski Film - Salt Lake Attys</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">undated</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>16mm film</genreform>
            <physfacet>
              Color, sound
            </physfacet>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This film contains raw footage of a race where the competitors are skiing on 2.5 foot skis.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">226</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Barrymore's original miscellaneous footage of Park City</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">undated</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>16mm film</genreform>
            <physfacet>
              Color, silent
            </physfacet>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This film contains raw footage of downtown Park City and of skiing. The downtown footage includes images of the Poison Creek Restaurant, the mountains, and dancing and drinking at Solid Mulboons. The skiing footage includes images of a few skiers skiing a mogul field.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">227</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Park City ski</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">undated</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains a news report from WKYT Lexington, Ky. on Park City. The report includes the average snowfall at the ski area, the convenience of the location, and it's vast terrain. It also includes an interview with Charlie Lansche and various vacationing skiers.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">228</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">R and R Advertising - Park City television advertisement</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">undated</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette, U-matic videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains a thirty-second advertisement for Park City Ski Area. It features clips from America's Opening World Cup and of various people skiing and snowboarding.</p>
          <p>2 cassettes</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">229</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
          </unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">undated</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>In this episode Barry Johnson, the host of the show, reviews dining and entertainment in Park City, gives tips on skiing moguls, reviews new equipment technology, and conducts a few interviews. His interviewees include Randy Reynolds, a cinematographer for ski and snowboarding films and Bob Oniel who was the director of marketing for the Deer Valley Ski Resort. This series also includes footage from the Sprint Bumps and Jumps freestyle competition held at the Winter Sports Park in Park City.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">230</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">The Park City Guide with Barry Johnson</title>
          </unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">undated</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains a television series called The Park City Guide. This episode contains information on the Park City area contained in local shop and resort advertisements.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">231</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Park City Mountain Resort B roll footage</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">undated</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains footage of powder skiing and snowboarding, mogul skiing, snowboard jumping, the women's World Cup giant slalom event, the men's World Cup slalom event, and of the flag parade. 11 minutes.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">232</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">Robin Leach's Travel Secrets</title> promotion</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">undated</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This is a promotional video for a new television series called <title render="italic">Travel Secrets</title>. The promotion is directed toward any company who desires marketing their product on the new show.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">233</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Rob Bruce stock footage</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">undated</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Rob Bruce was the president of TCS West 16/35 mm Motion Picture Camera Rental. This video is for viewing only. It contains footage of powder skiing through trees, extreme skiing down chutes, cliff jumping, and backcountry powder skiing.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">234</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Rob Bruce snow footage</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">undated</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Rob Bruce was the president of TCS West 16/35 mm Motion Picture Camera Rental. This video contains raw footage of various people skiing in the trees and powder skiing.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">235</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">TV 45</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">undated</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains advertisements for the new programs that will be aired on a new Park City television station, channel 45.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">236</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Promotion tape</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">undated</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains thirty-second advertisements for a "watch and win" ski contest and for a free weather survival guide.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">237</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">Two of the Few in Jupiter</title>
          </unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">undated</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video is a First Chute production and contains footage of extreme skiing in Park City Ski Area's Jupiter Bowl.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">238</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Resort Cam - sports cam hand-free Video</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">undated</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This is a promotional video for the Resort Cam's hands-free video and the easy video toaster, which is used for editing film.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">239</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">"Operation Snowblast" - television, radio, and print advertising</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">undated</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains a television, a radio, and a print advertisement for a skiing and snowboarding sweepstakes.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">240</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">Travel Travel</title> episode 102: Ski Vail Colorado</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">undated</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This is a promotional video for Vail Colorado. It features facts about the Vail resort, dining, lodging and how to occupy your time off of the slopes. It also highlights Vail's sister resort, Beaver Creek.  28:30.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">241</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">America's Opening World Cup advertisement</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">undated</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>Audiocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This is a radio advertisement for the America's Opening World Cup event held at Park City Ski Area over Thanksgiving weekend. The add highlights dates, special events such as live music and dancing, the event schedule and ticket information.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">242</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Park City giant slalom world satellite feed reel 1</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">undated</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>U-matic videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains footage of the America's Opening World Cup women's giant slalom event. It begins with a view of Park City from the racecourse then the course conditions and start list are superimposed onto this image. Next is the actual race footage followed by the results list.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">243</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">S.K.I. Ltd.</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">undated</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This is a promotional video for S.K.I. Limited, a ski corporation.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">244</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">Family Skiing</title>
          </unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">undated</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This is a promotional video for Park City Ski Area based on it being a family ski area.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">245</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">News report - Ed Poquette</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1991 March 25</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains a news report on a man names Ed Poquette who was charged with trespassing by Park City Ski Area. The claim was that he was teaching ski lessons at the resort but was not a resort employee and therefore was trespassing. See item 118 for more information on this story.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">246</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Jonathan Olch</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">undated</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This is a promotional video for a man named Jonathan Olch. It highlights his history and accomplishments as a racecar driver, a professional ski racer, and a fly fisher.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">247</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Park City "800 Park" proof</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">undated</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>Audiocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This tape contains one thirty-second advertisement for Park City as a ski vacation destination.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">248</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">"Top of the Mountain" promo</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">undated</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>Audiocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This tape contains an advertisement for a listen and win program on the radio station FM 100. The prize is a holidy weekend give away of all day tickets to Park City Ski Area.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">249</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Multi Market Media Park City, Utah demo tape</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">undated</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>Audiocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This is a promotional tape for Park City, Utah and contains six advertisements:</p>
          <p>1) Say yes to Park City</p>
          <p>2) Set your sights on Park City</p>
          <p>3) You're the reason</p>
          <p>4) Star lit nights</p>
          <p>5) Ski heaven</p>
          <p>6) Ski dream</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">250</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">Destination: Park City</title>
          </unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">circa 1980s</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>U-matic videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This film by Destination Productions contains the native history of Park City, the mining history of Park City, and the current day entertainment in Park City.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">251</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Underwriting credits for KUED program fund - Park City Ski Area</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">undated</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This is a twenty-nine second commercial for Park City Ski Area aired on KUED in return for their program funding from Park City Ski Area.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">252</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">"The Heat is On: Winter Heat"</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">undated</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains an advertisement for boot heaters made by Winter Heat.  2:58.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">253</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">This Is The Place: Salt Lake</title> summer version</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">undated</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This is a promotional video for the Salt Lake Convention and Visitors Bureau. It promotes Salt Lake City as a great place to have a business meeting and to have fun. It highlights Salt Lake restaurants and clubs, summer activities, shopping facilities, business facilities and hotels and other accommodations.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">254</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">Localmotion</title>: Park City ski movie</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">undated</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This is a television production that shows various locals skiing different runs at Park City Ski Area.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">255</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Park City roll 6A</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">undated</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains footage of the America's Opening men's giant slalom event. For the first several racers, the camera is stationary at one of the first gates and the racers are in slow motion. Then the camera is positioned at the staring gate. It also includes footage of the winners on the podium receiving their awards.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">256</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">SKI USA</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">undated</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains an international travel promotion for skiing in the United Sates. It features ski areas on the East Coast and the West Coast highlighting resort facts, accommodations, dinning and entertainment. The video is concluded with a list of SKI USA resorts.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">257</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Eastern Professional River Outfitters Utah ski vacation program</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">undated</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video promotes a program run by the Eastern Professional River Outfitters where the river guides take clients to Utah to ski or they design the trip for their clients.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">258</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Heuga / Mazda Express at Park City b-roll</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">undated</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>Betacam videocassette, VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains raw footage of the Jimmie Heuga Mazda Express ski race held at Park City Ski Area. The footage includes the racers registering, interviews with some of the racers on why they compete in the race, and an explanation of what the Jimmie Heuga Mazda Ski Express is and how it came about.</p>
          <p>2 cassettes</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">259</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Utah Winter Games</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">undated</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This is a promotional video for the Utah Winter Games. It includes facts about the Winter Games, where the venues will be, and which events are included in the games. The Utah Winter Games is run by a non-profit organization and its purpose is to support athletes and to showcase Utah.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">260</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Park City racing</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">undated</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains footage from the America's Opening slalom and giant slalom events, the street dance and fireworks show, and pictures of Park City's silver mining era. The entire video is set to music and there is no narration.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">261</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">C-Race / Fun Race</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">undated</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>Hi-8 videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">262</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">The Resort Center - Park City</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">undated</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This is a promotional video for the Resort Center at the base of Park City Ski Area. It features the Resort Center's accommodations, shops, the convenience of its layout, and the ski area. It also highlights the summer activities at the Resort Center.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">263</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Craig Badami: a tribute</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">circa 1989</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains a tribute to Crag Badami, Park City Ski Area's former Vice President. The tribute reveals Craig's history through his friends and families memories of him. The tribute also includes footage from the America's Opening World Cup events 1986-1989.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">264</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">In Utah all that Glitters is not Gold: Kens Television, San Antonio, Texas</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">circa 1986</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains a news report on Utah and, more specifically, Utah's ski areas. The report covers Salt Lake City's history, Utah's plans for hosting the 1998 Winter Olympics, the history of Park City, the Park City Ski Resort's facilities, Deer Valley's facilities, the Homestead's facilities, and Park West's facilities.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">265</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Peek 'n Peak incorporation to WICU Television</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">undated</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains a news report on Holly Flanders. The report includes Flanders' skiing history and her tips for young Peek 'n Peak ski team members.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">266</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Peek 'n Peak news report</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">undated</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains both raw and edited footage of a news report on the winter recreation compared to the summer recreation at the Peek 'n Peak resort. The footage includes a race crew setting up a course, an interview with Holly Flanders, and Holly Flanders skiing the course that was set up.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">267</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Women's ski challenge - camp 2</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">undated</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains the raw footage of a women's ski clinic at Park City. The instructor skis down the hill then each woman skis down one at a time. The camera films each woman from three different vantage points; the first is from below, looking up the hill, the second is directly from the side as the woman passes the camera, and the third is from above, looking down the hill.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">268</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">ESPN: <title render="italic">Toyota Ski World with Bob Beattie</title></unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">circa 2000</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This episode of Ski World features a special on Alberto Tomba, the Winter Olympic Sports Park, scenes from Mt. Cook, Summit Of Extremes, and interviews with Kristen Ulmer, Jeremy Nobis and Shannon Nobis.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">269</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">
            <title render="italic">Ski Utah with Kenneth Cowan</title> - WHCU 870 AM / WYXL 97 FM</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">undated</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>Audiocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Side A of this tape contains a radio talk show aired on WHCU 870 Am and WYXL 97 Fm. The topic of this show is ski vacations in Utah and Kenneth Cowan is the guest. Kenneth discusses traveling to Salt Lake City with Park City being his ultimate destination. He discusses Park City's atmosphere, it's history, accommodations in and around Park City, and the ski area's facilities.</p>
          <p>Side B of this tape contains a news report on the possible instillation of a water plant at the mouth of Millcreek Canyon and the Wall Street Journal report.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">270</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Park City pass rates promotion</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1961</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>Reel-to-reel audiotape</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This tape contains an advertisement for Park City's season passes and their resident coupon book.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">271</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">New York Stock Exchange ski competition</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">undated</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This video contains a news report on a ski race held at Val Di Ser in France and on the New York Stock Exchange team who competed in this race. The footage includes the giant slalom race, the celebration held after the race, and a torch light run. After this report, there is footage from the Park City America's Opening Pro Cup Race set to music, a Pro Cup celebration party, and of live music and dancing.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">272</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Team Deer Valley mogul skiing promotion / Bud Mogul Tour</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">undated</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>In this video, Barry Johnson promotes the Deer Valley Pro Mogul team. The video also contains a news report on Park City's freestyle team which includes interviews with the team members and footage of them competing. Also included is ESPN's coverage of the Bud Mogul Tour.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">273</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Park City Resort employee orientation</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">undated</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>Reel-to-reel audiotape</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This tape contains Park City Mountain Resort's employee orientation, which focuses on customer service.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">274</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Untitled videocassette</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">undated</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>Hi-8 videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
