<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9 http://www.loc.gov/ead/ead.xsd">
  <!--Last Edited: 2008/12/08 10:10:44 by xEAD vBETA 07-14-2008-->
  <eadheader langencoding="iso639-2b" scriptencoding="iso15924" relatedencoding="dc" repositoryencoding="iso15511" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-uuml" publicid="-//:://TEXT(US::UUML::UUM_A0655::Alton Crane Melville family home movies)//EN" encodinganalog="identifier" identifier="80444/xv73236" url="http://archiveswest.orbiscascade.org/ark:/80444/xv73236">UUM_A0655</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper encodinganalog="title">
          Guide to the Alton Crane Melville family home movies
          <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian" normal="1940/1982" encodinganalog="date">1940-1968</date></titleproper>
        <titleproper type="filing" altrender="nodisplay">Melville (Alton Crane) family home movies</titleproper>
        <author encodinganalog="creator">Finding aid prepared by Elizabeth Shuput.</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher encodinganalog="publisher">Multimedia Archives, J. Willard Marriott Library, University of Utah</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>295 South 1500 East</addressline>
          <addressline>Salt Lake City, Utah 84112</addressline>
          <addressline>(801) 581-8864</addressline>
        </address>
        <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian" normal="2004" encodinganalog="date">© 2004</date>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>
        Encoded by Elizabeth Shuput
        <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian" normal="2004">2004</date></creation>
      <langusage>
        <language encodinganalog="language" langcode="eng" scriptcode="Latn">English</language>
      </langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <archdesc type="inventory" level="collection" relatedencoding="dc">
    <did>
      <repository>
        <corpname encodinganalog="publisher">University of Utah Libraries, Special Collections</corpname>
        <subarea encodinganalog="publisher">Audio Visual Archives</subarea>
        <address>
          <addressline>Special Collections</addressline>
          <addressline>295 South 1500 East</addressline>
          <addressline>Salt Lake City, Utah 84112-0860</addressline>
          <addressline>(801) 581-8864</addressline>
        </address>
      </repository>
      <unitid encodinganalog="identifier" countrycode="US" repositorycode="US-uuml">A0655</unitid>
      <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Alton Crane Melville family home movies</unittitle>
      <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian" normal="1940/1982" encodinganalog="date">1940-1968</unitdate>
      <origination>
        <persname source="local" rules="dacs" encodinganalog="creator" role="creator">Melville, Alton Crane</persname>
      </origination>
      <physdesc>
        <extent encodinganalog="format">55 8mm films, 19 16mm films</extent>
      </physdesc>
      <abstract encodinganalog="description">The Alton Crane Melville family home movies (1940-1968) consist of footage of the Melville family's vacations, home life and special events across multiple generations.  In addition to family footage of Alton and Verna Melville and their children, many of the films in this colleciton contain footage of competative or recrational skiing at resorts in Utah and around the world.  Both Alton Crane Melville and his son, Marvin Melville are prominent members of the United States ski community, and many of the films in this colleciton contain footage of competative or recrational skiing at resorts in Utah, Intermountain West, and around the world.</abstract>
      <langmaterial>Materials in 
        <language encodinganalog="language" langcode="eng">English</language>.
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="description">
      <head>Biographical Note</head>
      <p>Alton Crane Melville (1904-1966) was an avid skier who once served as president of the National Ski Association (NSA), an organization now known as the United States Ski and Snowboard Association (USSA).  His son, Marvin Melville (b. 1935), is an internationally decorated and respected skier.  He skied for the Granite High School, University of Utah, 1958 United States Olympic Alpine, and 1960 International Ski Federation (FIS) ski teams. In 1959, Marvin Melville became the National Collegiate Athletics Association (NCAA) champion in downhill, slalom and combined ski events.  After retiring from competition, he served a tour in the Army and then opened a ski school for young racers.  Melville coached the 1964 Women's Olympic Ski Team and the University of Utah Ski Team.  He was inducted into the Sports Hall of Fame in 1990.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
      <p>The Alton Crane Melville family home movies (1940-1968) consist of footage of the Melville family's vacations, home life and special events across multiple generations.  In addition to family footage of Alton and Verna Melville and their children, many of the films in this colleciton contain footage of competative or recrational skiing at resorts in Utah and the Intermountain West, and around the world, including footage of Marvin Melville's ski races and training.  All films have been digitized and are available to view on DVD.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement encodinganalog="description">
      <p>The majority of the collection is arranged chronologically.</p>
    </arrangement>
    <accessrestrict encodinganalog="rights">
      <p>Materials must be used on-site; no use of original material, access copies will be made available for viewing. Five business days advanced notice required. Access to parts of this collection may be restricted under provisions of state or federal law, condition of the material, or by donor.</p>
    </accessrestrict>
    <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="relation">
      <p>See also the Alton Crane Melville papers (Accn 723) and photograph colleciton (P0933) and the Marvin A. Melville family home movies (A1128).</p>
    </relatedmaterial>
    <processinfo>
      <p>Processed by Elizabeth Shuput in 2004.</p>
    </processinfo>
    <controlaccess>
      <subject encodinganalog="subject" source="lcsh">Skis and skiing--United States--History--Sources</subject>
      <subject encodinganalog="subject" source="lcsh">Skis and skiing--Utah--History--Sources</subject>
      <subject encodinganalog="subject" source="lcsh">Home movies</subject>
      <subject altrender="nodisplay" source="archiveswest">City and Town Life</subject>
      <subject altrender="nodisplay" source="archiveswest">Sports and Recreation</subject>
      <subject altrender="nodisplay" source="archiveswest">Moving Images</subject>
      <genreform encodinganalog="type" source="aat">Moving images</genreform>
      <genreform encodinganalog="type" source="aat">Home movies and video</genreform>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc type="in-depth">
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">1</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Parades</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1940 July 04</unitdate>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1940 July 19</unitdate>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1941 July 04</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>8mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>East Millcreek Parade (July 04, 1940)Childrens Covered Wagon Parade (July 19, 1940)Glorious 4th Parade (July 04, 1941)This film also contains footage of a young Marvin Melville (approximately age 5) riding a donkey.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">2</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Brighton, Aposhian scenic trip, Kanosh deer, Mesa Verde, Arches National Monument</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1940-1941</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>8mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Various Melville family outings 1940-1941:  Brighton on the 4th of July 1940. Here Marvin rode horseback for the first time.The next outing is an autumn scenic loop via Payson canyon and Nephi Canyon. The Melville family drives this loop with the Aposhian family in September of 1940.The next outing is a trip to Kanosh to hunt deer. After the Melville men finish hunting, they go to Aunt Ella Staples house for lunch with the rest of the family.The next outing is a trip to Mesa Verde. Alton points out on a map the rout that they will take to Mesa Verde then there are various shots of the five-car caravan that they travel in. On the way to Mesa Verde, they stop at Arches National Monument.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">3</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Christmas</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1940-1942</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>8mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>1940 Christmas memories: The Melville family decorating the Christmas tree, opening gifts, and playing with their new toys.1941 Christmas memories: The Melville children bathing the night before Christmas, decorating the Christmas tree, Mrs. Vera Melville reading "The Night Before Christmas" to her children, and the kids going to bed. On Christmas morning, the Melville family opens their presents.1942 Christmas memories: The Melville children wrapping presents, making lists of presents for Santa; the children opening their stockings and presents.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">4</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Airway parade</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1940-1942</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>8mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Footage of the old Airway Buses and of the various places that the Melville family and friends went on them. Destinations include Jackson Lake in Grand Teton National Park, Las Vegas, Nevada, and an Alligator farm.  At the end of this film there are several shots of the various transit systems in Salt Lake City including Airway Buses, Murray Cab, and the Salt Lake Trolley System (SLTS).
		</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">5</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Grandma Melville at 90 years old, Black Rock, Easter with bicycles, Knab, Zion National Park, Kanosh, Logan</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1940 July 18</unitdate>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1940 September 06</unitdate>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1942 April 05</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>8mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Various trips that the Melville family went on in 1940 and 1942:  The first of these trips is to Black Rock on July 18 1940.The second is a trip to Grandma Melville's birthday party at the Sorenson's home on September 6 1940 where four generations of this family can be seen all together.The third trip is to Kanosh where the Melville men hunt for deer.  This film also contains footage from Easter day in 1942 when the Melville children are given bicycles.
		</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">6</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Bennions, Lagoon, Grandma at 87 years old</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1940 August-1945</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>8mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>The Melville adults diving and swimming at a family friend's swimming pool while the Melville children play with their grandfather. The Melville family visits the Bennion family in Taylorsville in August of 1940. Later, Marvin visits Grandmother Bennion at the old Hyrum Bennion home.In 1945 the entire Melville family visits with Grandma Bennion. This film ends with a family trip up Millcreek Canyon where they enjoy fried steak.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">7</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Marie</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1941 January-August</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>8mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Marie Melville, Marvin's little sister, as a newborn, at six months old, eight months old, and at a year and three months.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">8</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Kids: birthdays, school, Alice in blue gown, Easter</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1941-1943</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>8mm film</genreform>
            <physfacet>
              Double exposed
            </physfacet>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Footage of the Melville children's birthdays, their first day of school, and the Melville family's Easter celebration. The first birthday celebration is on February 15 1941 for Marvin. The second birthday celebration is also in February of 1941 for Marvin's sister Marie.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">9</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Jackson Hole, Weber Park</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1942</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>8mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Melville family vacations to Jackson Hole and Weber Park:  In Jackson Hole, the family camps at the Turpin Meadow Lodge. They go on various day hikes and one afternoon they go horseback riding to the South entrance of Yellowstone National Park. There is also footage of several black bears that they encountered during their visit.The trip to Weber Park includes scenic views, footage of the Melville children playing in a river, and various shots of the Chapel of Transfiguration.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">10</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Neighborhood, zoo, Grandview Quartet, Sadie Hawkins dance, Movie Club, Mirror Lake</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1942</unitdate>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1943 August 07</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>8mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Various local activities that Alton Melville and his wife participated in. These activities include taking the children to the Zoo, playing card games with the neighbors, singing with the Grandview Quartet, going to a Sadie Hawkins dance, and playing bingo with the Movie Club.  This film also contains footage of the Melville family's trip to Mirror Lake in 1943 where they hike, go horseback riding, and have a picnic.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">11</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Farming, planting, Lu Ann, Daisy, Easter in Snake Valley, zoo, baby, Deer Creek, harvest</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1942-1944</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>8mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>A farmer farming, planting and harvesting his crops in 1944.Marvin's younger sister Lu Ann as a newborn baby.  The Melville family goes to the zoo in Salt Lake City, to a horse jumping Home Show, to the Olympus Stables where a few men build a fence, and to Deer Creek in Heber Valley where they fish and swim.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">12</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Delta, Petersens, Nebo Loop, deer hunt, winter</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1943-1944 January</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>8mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Various trips that the Melville family went on in 1943 and 1944. These trips include a drive through Nebo Loop via Nephi Canyon and Payson Canyon, a trip to Delta, a deer hunting trip to Kanosh, and a trip to see a family friend's wedding.  This film also contains footage of Thanksgiving Day in 1943 and various shots of the winter streets in January of 1944.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">13</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Mirror Lake</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1944</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>8mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>The Melville family's camping trip at Mirror Lake in 1944. The footage includes various shots of the campground and cabin that they stayed in, the hikes that they went on, and of the children playing in the lake.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">14</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Italians Pow-Cottams, Horace, Stan, fishing in American Fork Canyon</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1944</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>8mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Footage of a soccer game hosted for military veterans and of a fishing trip in American Fork Canyon. Images of the fishing trip include horseback riding to the lake, fishing on the lake, cooking the fish, and scenic views.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">15</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Airway, Denver</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1944</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>8mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>The Melville family's trip to Denver Colorado where they enjoy the natural surroundings of a lake, mountains and pine trees. There is a brief shot of the front page of a newspaper titled <emph render="italic">Hobo News</emph>. The headline, slightly cut off, reads <emph render="italic">Lets sink the rising sons of</emph> . . . The last several shots of this film are of two men walking along the train tracks.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">16</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Wedding</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1944</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>16mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Alton and Verna Melville's wedding: shots of guests and family mingling and of the receiving line.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">17</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">James A. Melville, Verna and Alton's wedding</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1926</unitdate>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1944</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>8mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>The first part of this film is a copy of another film from 1926 that contains footage concerning the Deseret National Bank. The footage includes a view of the bank from the opposite corner of the street, a few shots of the main banking room on a regular workday, and of a directors meeting held on the seventh of December. There is a shot of each man present at the meeting with their name and title preceding their image. These men include James A. Melville, Edward Rosenbaum, John G.M Barnes, James A. Eldredge, H. H. Rolapp, M. S. Eccles, and R. Q. Cannon.  The second part of this film documents Alton and Verna's marriage and consists of footage of the receiving line.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">18</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Christmas, Bennion, Alta skiing, Nate Larsen</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1944-1945</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>8mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>The Melville family's 1944 Christmas celebration: This celebration consists of singing Christmas Carols as a family, opening presents and stockings, and gathering with extended family for dinner.  Also in this film, the Melvilles go to Alta for a day of free skiing and to the Bennion's home where the two families enjoy the Holliday season together.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">19</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Marie's birthday, Lu Ann's birthday, Alta: Lu Ann</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1945</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>8mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Marie and Lu Ann Melville's birthday celebrations: The celebrations include playing games with friends, opening presents, and eating birthday cake. This film also contains footage of Lu Ann's first time going to Alta Ski Resort with the family.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">20</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Green River Lakes, Manila, July 4th: Aposhians, rain, ducks</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1945</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>8mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Various trips that the Melville family went on in 1945:  The first is the Melville's trip to Wyoming where they visit the Fort Bridger Museum, the first school house in Wyoming, the old post office in McKinnel Wyoming, and the Green River Lakes area where they fish and enjoy the view.  The second trip is to Manila Utah. This film also contains footage of the Melville's 4th of July celebration with the Aposhian family. This celebration includes a 4th of July picnic and parade.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">21</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Christmas</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1946</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>8mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>1946 Christmas memories: These celebrations include a Christmas parade, decorating the house and Christmas tree, a man dressed in a Santa suit delivering presents and filling the stockings, and opening presents Christmas morning. Towards the end of this film, there is footage of "Winter Thrills" which consists of playing in the snow and going on a horse drawn sled ride.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">22</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Lions Club, Cedar City</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1946 June 22</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>8mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Lions Club Convention in Cedar City, Utah. The footage includes several shots of two billboards; the first sign reads <emph render="italic">Convention</emph> and the second sign reads <emph render="italic">Hudson Horse Show</emph>. This film also contains footage of the elephants in the circus, and various shots of the members of the Lions Club mingling outside.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">23</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Skiing, Lu Ann's Birthday, Las Vegas, Cedar City, Yellowstone, school</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1946</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>8mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>The Melville family free skiing, celebrating Lu Ann Melville's birthday, traveling to Las Vegas, Cedar City, and Yellowstone National Park, and of the kids going to school:  The footage of Lu Ann's birthday includes several shots of Lu Ann and Marie blowing out the candles on the cake, the family eating the cake and of Lu Ann opening her presents.  The footage of the Melville's trip to Las Vegas includes several shots of the family in a boat on Lake Mohave.  The footage of the Melville's trip to Cedar City includes several shots of a parade and of Marie and Lu Ann on a swing.  The footage from Yellowstone National Park includes several shots of the Old Faithful Geyser, and of Alton, Marvin, and Marvin's friend fishing.  The footage of the Melville kids going to school includes several shots of Marvin walking to school with his friends while Marie walks to school with her friends. Lu Ann is too young to go to school yet, so she waves goodbye to her siblings from the front porch.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">24</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Air Circus, Joe Holland, Marie's birthday, Lu Ann, Utah Lake</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1946-1947</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>8mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>The Melville family's Sunday drive to see the Air Circus, of Marie's birthday, and of the Melville's trip to Utah Lake:  The footage from the Air Circus includes several shots of various airplanes on the ground and in the sky.  The footage of Marie's birthday includes several shots of Marie opening presents, blowing out the candles on her birthday cake, everyone having cake, and of Marie and her friends playing bingo.  The footage of the Melville's day spent at Utah Lake includes several shots of the family putting the boat into the water and boating around the lake.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">25</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Skiing, Jackson Hole, Wyoming</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1946 December</unitdate>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1947 February</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>8mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>The Melville family skiing at Alta in December of 1946  The Melville's family trip to Jackson Hole Wyoming in February of 1947. They attend the Cutter Races and go skiing.  At the end of this film, there are several shots of Alton Crane Melville with a broken ankle.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">26</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Lions Club,  Logan, Sorensens, USO, July 4th parade</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1947 June 20</unitdate>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1947 July 01</unitdate>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1947 July 04</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>8mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>The Melville family attending the Utah Centennial Regatta with the Lions Club. The Utah Centennial Regatta was held in Logan on June 20, 1947.  The Melville family visiting with the Sorensen family on July 1, 1947 and of the 4th of July parades in Logan and in Salt Lake City.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">27</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">This and that, Main Street, Hotel Utah</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1947</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>8mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Footage of the LDS Temple and of Main Street viewed from the roof of the Hotel Utah in 1947. There is also a shot of a street corner from an office window. This film also contains footage of Lu Ann Melville, Raymond, Bill Roger, and Eddie Schanhals.  The remaining footage of this film contains images from a bomber plane exhibit.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">28</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Millcreek Canyon, Nebo Loop, Taylorsville, Christmas, Salt Lake City Main Street, cat and dog with Spencer, Sun Valley,  Brighton skiing, Lu Ann's birthday</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1947-1948</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>8mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Various trips that the Melville family went on in 1947 and 1948. These trips include a day spent in Millcreek Canyon, a day spent driving the Nebo Loop, a trip to Taylorsville, and of the Melville's family trip to Sun Valley.  In Millcreek Canyon, the family has a picnic, Lu Ann and Marie Melville collect leaves and swing on a nearby swing, and an unknown man paints the surrounding scenery in oil paints.  The Sunday drive through Nebo Loop contains footage of the surrounding scenery and of the Melville family stopping for a picnic.  The footage of the Melville's trip to Sun Valley contains footage of the family skiing, a list of lift ticket prices, and of a snow sculpture.  This film also contains footage of Salt Lake City's Main Street in 1947, of the Melville family skiing at Brighton, and of their 1947 family Christmas celebrations. The footage of these celebrations contains images of the family Christmas shopping, visiting Temple Square to see the lights, and of Lu Ann and Marie Melville sitting on Santa's lap in downtown Salt Lake.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">29</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Lions Club, St. George</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1948 June 02</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>8mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>The Melville's trip to St. George with the Lions Club. While in St. George, the group is seen dancing and singing along to an oboe and accordion, taking jeeps off-roading followed by a short hike to a scenic viewpoint, swimming, attending a formal occasion, and visiting the scenic view area in Zions National Park.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">30</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">July 4th and 24th, Easter, West Delta</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1948</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>8mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>For July 4th and July 24th, the Melville family goes to see the local parade.  For Easter, the Melville children go on an Easter egg hunt.  This film also contains footage of the Melville family's trip to West Delta where they drive around the town.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">31</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Rosecrest groundbreaking, carnival</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1948 August 1-3</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>8mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Rosecrest Groundbreaking ceremony (August 1, 1948).  Rosecrest Ward Carnival (August 1-3, 1948).  This carnival was sponsored by the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints (LDS Church).</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">32</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Brighton, Deer Killed, Marie's Birthday, Taylorsville</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1949 January-February</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>8mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Marvin and Marie Melville free skiing at Brighton.  A deer who was killed.  Marie's birthday.  The Melville's trip to Taylorsville.  The footage of Marie's birthday contains images of Marie opening presents and of her and her friends eating birthday cake. The footage of the Melville's trip to Taylorsville contains images of the family Nordic skiing and of Lu Ann and Marie Melville being pulled on a sled by a tractor.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">33</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Brighton, Easter, Clayton, Deer Creek and Little Deer Creek, Mother's Day, Taylors in Provo, July 4th and 24th parades, trip to Monticello</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1949</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>8mm film</genreform>
            <physfacet>
              Parade footage is double exposed
            </physfacet>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>The Melville family skiing at Brighton, of the Melville family's celebration of various holidays, of their trip to Monticello, and of the various <emph render="italic">White and Melville builders</emph> sites. The holidays celebrated in this footage include Easter, Mother's Day, July 4th and July 24th. For Easter, the Melville children go on an Easter egg hunt, and for the 4th and 24th, the family goes to the local parades.  The footage of the Melville's trip to Monticello includes images of a geyser, of the surrounding scenery, and of their hike in Devils Garden.  The <emph render="italic">White and Melville Builders</emph> sites include the Deer Creek Project and the L.D.C Project. There is an image of a sign that reads <emph render="italic">Thru 700 ft. of tunnel and a mile of pipe line</emph>, and images of a backhoe moving dirt.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">34</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Yellowstone, Bears</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1949</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>8mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>The Melville family's trip to Yellowstone National Park: While in Yellowstone, the family hikes through the woods, goes fishing, visit the Old Faithful Geyser, and drives to the Upper Falls. Throughout this film, there is footage of various black bears including a mother bear and her cubs. At the very end of the film, there are a few shots of an elk in a field.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">35</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Easter, deer hunt, Sorensens at Beau Brommel, family at 1300 East, Weilers, Hollands, addition to house, Christmas at Cottams, Jim Clayton, Taylorsville</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1949</unitdate>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1955</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>8mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Footage of the Melville family's 1949 Easter and Christmas celebrations as well as footage of Marvin hunting for deer with his father.  This film also shows the Melville family leaving their home to visit their friends, the Sorensens, where all of the boys play basketball together. The Melville family then goes on a Sunday drive to Brighton where they go for a scenic ride on the ski lifts.  This film also documents the Melville's addition to their home in 1955.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">36</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Lions Convention</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1950 June 01</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>8mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Lions Convention in Old Cove Fort which was used as a stop over point between Filmore, the first state cpital, and Beaver, sixty miles to the south. This stopping point was used freaquently by early settlers and was built in 1867.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">37</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Brighton, Snake Creek, Telegram race, Snow Cup Races at Alta</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1950-1951</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>8mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>The Melville family skiing at Brighton and of Marvin racing in the Telegram races and in the Snow Cup Races at Alta. The footage of Brighton includes the family taking the "Utah Motor Tours" bus up Big Cottonwood Canyon to Brighton where they hike in single file up the hill then ski down. They also stop in the trees to cook their lunch over a small fire. The footage from the Telegram Races includes the races getting ready and skiing the course. The footage from the Snow Cup Races at Alta includes skiers getting on the chair lift, scenic views from the chair lift, the racers in the starting gate, and of the racers at the midpoint of the course.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">38</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">White and Melville, Water Tank on Wasatch Blvd., July 4th, Neffs Canyon</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1950-1952</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>8mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>The White and Melville water well on 3300 South and Wasatch Boulevard; men working on a water irrigation system.  4th of July Parade in Salt Lake City 1952.  A trip to Neffs Canyon where the Melville family goes on a boat ride, and sees a black bear and a waterfall.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">39</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Lions Vernal Convention</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1951</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>8mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>The Melville's trip to Vernal for the Lions Convention. Once in Vernal, the greetings and introduction are given and then everybody mingles with one another. After this, the group is seen feeding baby lambs from bottles.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">40</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Jackson Hole, Winter Park: Colorado</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1951-1952</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>8mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Marvin's 1951-1952 high school ski team's trip to Jackson Hole for a race. The footage from this race includes images of the racers getting ready, in the starting gate, and skiing the course. It is noted that Bonnie Jo is racer 46 and that Teniel H. is racer 48. This film also contains footage of a jumping competition held at the Winter Park in Colorado.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">41</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Knudsen Cup, American Lecidn Races, Landes Jump</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1952</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>8mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Marvin Melville skiing in the Knudsen Cup, the American Lecidn Races, and the Landes Jumping competition. The Knudsen Cup was held in Sun Valley Idaho and the footage of it includes Marie free skiing and Marvin and his fellow racers in the starting gate and in the course. The footage of the American Lecidn Races and the Landes Jumping competition includes several shots of various competitors jumping. It is noted that Marvin is competitor 2 in the Landes Jumping competition.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">42</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Alta: Mt. Superior hike, Aspen: Roach Cup, Nationals, Sun Valley: Harriman Cup, Squaw Valley</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1952</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>16mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>The Melville family hiking Mt. Superior at Alta during the winter then skiing down.  Marvin competing in the Roach Cup, Nationals, the Harriman Cup, and in a race in Squaw Valley.  The Roach Cup was held in Aspen Colorado and consists of a giant slalom course, a slalom course, and downhill course. Nationals where also held at Aspen and consists of a giant slalom course, a slalom course, and downhill course. The Harriman Cup was held in Sun Valley Idaho and consists of a downhill course and a slalom course. The race in Squaw Valley also consists of a downhill course and a slalom course.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">43</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">White and Melville, Neffs Canyon, Millcreek Canyon, El Sennito tank 4, Las Vegas, Los Angeles, Amelia</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1952-1953</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>8mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Footage of the Melville family's 1952 hike in Neffs Canyon as well as their trips to Las Vegas, and Los Angeles. In Las Vegas, they watch speed boat races and in Los Angeles, they tour the city. This film also contains images of the White and Melville water well and of men working on an irrigation system in the canyon during the winter.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">44</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Intermountain Giant Slalom,National Juniors at Brighton, jumping at Alta, Harriman Cup at Sun Valley</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1953 February</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>8mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This film contains footage of Marvin Melville racing in several races. These races include the Intermountain Giant Slalom race, the National Juniors race held at Brighton, the Landes Jumping competition at Alta, and the Harriman Cup in Sun Valley Idaho.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">45</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Skiing, State Fair, Neffs Cave, Snow Cup at Brighton,  Eccles Cup at Snow Basin</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1953-1954</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>8mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>The Melville family hiking up Neffs Canyon to Neffs Cave, which is one of the deepest caves in Utah.  Marvin racing in the January Snow Cup held at Brighton, and in the Eccles Cup held at Snow Basin. Along with the footage of Marvin competing in these two races is footage of Marvin and Marie free skiing together.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">46</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Skiing: Brighton to Homestead, Harriman Cup, Intermountain Giant Slolm, costume race</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1953-1954</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>8mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Marvin Melville competing in the eleventh annual Harriman Cup, the Intermountain Giant Slalom race, and in a costume race. This reel also contains footage of the Melville family skiing from Brighton to The Homestead.  The footage of the Harriman Cup includes a list of tentative starting times for the Slalom and Giant Slalom events, images of the crowd cheering, and of the racers getting ready and skiing the course. The Harriman Cup was held in Sun Valley Idaho on March 20-21, 1954.  The footage from the Intermountain Giant Slalom race includes images of the racers getting ready, the racers in the course, and the crowd cheering. This race was held at Brighton in March 1954.  The Costume Race was also held at Brighton but was in May of 1954. The footage from this race consists of a view of the resort from above and images of the racers in costume skiing the course.  The footage of the Melville family skiing from Brighton to the Homestead includes images of the family hiking to the top of the mountain then skiing down it's ridgeline and through some trees.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">47</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Jackson Hole, Whites, Knight, Little Cottonwood, Whites up Mineral Fork</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1954</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>8mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>The Melville's trip to Jackson Hole with the White family  A day of hiking in Little Cottonwood Canyon  The Melville and White families up Mineral Fork.  The footage of their trip to Jackson Hole includes images of the children playing, the fathers fishing, and the mothers knitting. There are also images of the surrounding scenery. The footage from the day spent up Little Cottonwood Canyon includes scenic images as well as images of the family hiking. The footage of the White and Melville families up Mineral fork consists of scenic images.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">48</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Ski pictures: College Jump (Alf Engen and Marvin), Snow Cup at Alta, Intermountain Junior Races in Ogden (Marie), Hariman Cup in Sun Valley</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1954-1955</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>8mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Marvin training with Alf Engen at the College Jump and competing in the Snow Cup at Alta and in the Harriman Cup in Sun Valley. The footage of the races includes images of the racers getting ready and skiing the course.  This film also contains footage of Marie competing in the International Junior races at Snow Basin.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">49</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Yosemite, Las Vegas Parade, Dimple Dell Farm</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1955 May-June</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>8mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>The Melville's trips to Yosemite National Park, Las Vegas, and Dimple Dell:  The footage from Yosemite includes a view of a waterfall, and the scenic view from Glacier Point and Fresno.  The footage from Las Vegas is of a street parade.  The footage from Dimple Dell is of farmland being cleared of shrubbery and the like.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">50</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Dimple Dell well</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1955 July</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>8mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Several men working on an irrigation system for a farm in Dimple Dell. The men also preform well tests.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">51</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Nevada, California, Pineview, July 4th, Fork Barker Ranch, Montana, wedding</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1955-1957</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>16mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Various trips that the Melville family went on from 1955-1957:  The footage from Nevada contains images of the Melville family swimming in a pool at a Hotel.  The footage from California contains images of the family swimming in the ocean, going to Disney Land and to the Marine Park.  The footage from Pineview contains images of the Melville family driving jeeps off road.  The footage from Montana contains images of the family visiting Fork Barker Ranch, where they feed fawns from a bottle, go horseback riding, and canoeing on a pond.  The film ends with footage of a wedding and images from before and after the ceremony. There are images of the guests mingling outdoors and of the bride, groom, bride's maids and men of honor all in a line.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">52</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Winter Olympics, Alta</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1956</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>16mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>The 1956 Winter Olympics where hosted by Cortina d'Ampezzo Italy. The featured footage of the Winter Olympics consists of the flag carrying ceremony, the opening ceremony, the torch lighting ceremony, and the various events that the Melville family attended while in Italy. These events include bobsledding, hockey, nordic skiing, giant slalom, figure skating, and downhill.  This film also includes footage of the Melville family skiing at Alta</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">53</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Dozer, Big Cottonwood Canyon</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1957</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>8mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Construction of the road going up Big Cottonwood Canyon.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">54</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Skiing at Badgastein</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1957</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>16mm film</genreform>
            <physfacet>
              Poor color quality
            </physfacet>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Marvin Melville training for giant slalom in Badgastein, Austria in the Tauern Mountain Range.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">55</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Europe</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1957</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>16mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Marvin Melville's trip to Europe where he races in both slalom and giant slalom events. At the end of this film, there is a close up of the local newspaper.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">56</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Nevada mine</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1957 November</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>8mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Two men skiing while a dog plays in the snow.  Images of the Nevada mines.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">57</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Dozer ABOC</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1957</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>8mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>A bulldozer cleraing land.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">58</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">European trip, Alta Snow Cup, A.C Melville, Salt Lake City</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1958</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>16mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>The Melville Family's trip to Europe, where Marvin competes in various ski races, as well as footage of Marvin racing in the Alta Snow Cup in Salt Lake City, Utah:  The footage from Europe contains images of the family arriving in Amsterdam where they then board a ferry and then get back onto a plane. They arrive in Germany where they go sight seeing. Later they arrive at the <emph render="italic">Munche</emph> Ski Resort where Marvin races in a slalom, giant slalom, and downhill race. Marvin's race number is 23. The next scenes from Europe are of the Melville family walking the streets of Zurich, Switzerland, Naples, Italy, and Nice, France. In Nice, the family attends a street parade, and then travels to Paris to visits the Louvre Museum. In Stockholm, Sweden, the family attends another street parade, and visit Mount Melville.  The Alta Snow Cup that Marvin competes in is composed of a slalom race under the FIS Alpine heading.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">59</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Home, Zeus Landes, Snow Cup at Ecker Hill, Steamboat, Olympic Tryouts, Squaw Valley, Sun Valley, Aspen</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1958-1959</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>16mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Footage of an older couple riding a tandem bicycle followed by footage of the Melville family playing with two dogs.  This film also contains footage of Marvin Melville competing in various races. These races include the Home Zeus Landes Long Jumping competition, the Snow Cup on Ecker Hill in Steamboat Colorado, the 1959 North American Championships, the Harriman Cup in Sun Valley, and a slalom race in Aspen.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">60</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Marti, Easter, Marvin's graduation, Yellowstone, Glacier National Park, Marie goes to Europe, airport, Whites on Yellowstone Lake, bicycles, Cody, Marti, snow</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1959-1960</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>16mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>The Melville family at home and on various trips that the Melvilles went on from 1959-1960. These trips include a trip to Yellowstone National Park where the family visits the Old Faithful Geyser and then take a tour through Glacier National Park. The Melville family returns to Yellowstone National Park with the White family. Together they go boating, feed the birds, and see a brown bear eating.  Marie Melville's boards the airplane for her trip to Europe.  The footage of the Melville family includes footage of their family Easter celebration, of Marti Melville as a baby, of Marvin's Graduation from the University of Utah, and of the family riding their bicycles.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">61</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">University of Utah dry land training, Marvin: slalom, NCAA downhill, NCAA jumping</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1959-1963</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>16mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Marvin Melville training and competing in various ski events. The beginning of the film contains footage of the University of Utah's ski team dry land training followed by footage of Marvin training for slalom in December of 1959. The races that Marvin competes in are the NCAA downhill event, held in February of 1961, and the NCAA Jumping event in 1963.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">62</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Mill D, south fork of Big Cottonwood Canyon, Frank Yanchar, Vare Frantz Road To Venus, 94 South, well test 14, Belnap Well test, White Pine Little Cottonwood Creek dam, Peruvian Road construction, Dam Mert Wensens, Albion Basin</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1959-1963</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>16mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Various construction sites and well testing:  The first construction site seen is in the South Fork of Big Cottonwood Canyon and the second site is the road construction to the Peruvian in Little Cottonwood Canyon.  The well testing is done at the Cardiff Fork where some mining is also seen.  This film also contains scenic views from White Pine and Albion Basin.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">63</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Winter Olympics, Squaw Valley</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1960</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>16mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>The 1960 Winter Olympics held in Squaw Valley, California. Having competed in the 1956 Winter Olympics in Cortina d'Ampezzo, and for the National Federation of Skiing Team in 1958 in Badgastein Austria, Marvin competes in his last international race before moving on to coaching ski teams. The event that he competed in was downhill racing.  This film begins with footage of the Melville family packing their camper and driving to California on the ninth of February 1960.  The first Olympic event that the family sees is figure skating.  The second event that is shown is the downhill race, which was held on February 14. After the race, the Melville family and a few friends go to the Squaw Valley Lodge for lunch. During lunch, Mrs. Hanna's ski are stolen.  On February 17 the Melville family attends another downhill race featuring a disabled skier named Lowell Thomas. After this, they attend an Olympic Ceremony followed by the ladies downhill, and the men's giant slalom events.  On February 20 there is yet another downhill event which is filmed with greater detail than the first two.  On February 24 the Melville family attends an ice hockey event, a cross-country skiing event, and the eighty-meter jumping event.  The last events that the Melville family attended were speed skating, pairs figure skating, and ladies slalom ski racing.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">64</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Bicycle State Championships, Liberty Park, trip to Key West</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1961</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>16mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Footage of the Mountain States Cycling Scene Race Awards and of the Melville family's trips to Key West, Florida, Miami and the Everglades.  In Key West, the family goes to the Marine Studios where they see Dolphins, Ducks, Sea Turttles, and other marine life.  In Miami, they float a river where they see a man wrestle an alligator, and then they take a train tour.  In the Everglades, the Melville family goes on a boat trip.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">65</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">County water system, well at 275 East 30 South</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1961 January</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>16mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Salt Lake County's water tanks from above.  Images if several real estate signs, possibly in consideration for developing future water tanks on.  Several men working on a well located at 275 East and 300 South.  Several scenes with images of records filling the entire frame.  The last image is of a newspaper headline that reads <emph render="italic">Residents Face 3d Waterless Days</emph>.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">66</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Training school, Aspen, Sun Valley</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1961-1962</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>16mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This film was directed by Marvin Melville, Dick Street, Bill Spencer, and Al Hansen and contains footage of the high school ski team training for Slalom and Giant Slalom in addition to dry land training. The dry land training consists of running, sprinting, sit-ups, push-ups, climbing stairs, summersaults and climbing a rope.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">67</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Christmas, Marti &amp; Shari, Easter, Bob &amp; Marie's graduation, Dick Street wedding, Cloud Rim Road on Rainbow, Little Cottonwood, Mindy &amp; Mel, Easter, Verna &amp; ladies, July 4th parade, girls &amp; dog, Sorensens Indians, girls on skis</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1961-1963</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>16mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>The Melville family celebrating various holidays as well as footage of the Melville family with various friends. The holidays celebrated in this film include Christmas 1961, Easter 1962 and 1963, and the 4th of July, which was hosted by the Sorensen family.  This film also contains footage of Marie's graduation from the University of Utah on June 11, 1962 and footage of Dick Street's wedding.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">68</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Brighton races</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1963 January</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>16mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Marvin Melville competing in the 1963 January Juniors Cup. The event featured in this footage is a giant slalom race.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">69</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Dry land, cross country skiing</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1964</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>8mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Marvin Melville's dry land training exercises and Marvin Melville cross-country skiing. The exercises included in the dry land training are soccer and water exercises.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">70</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">December</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1965</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>16mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>The Melville family's Christmas celebration: gathering with the extended family, decorating the Christmas tree, opening presents.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">71</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Draper well</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1965</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>16mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Several men working on a water well in Draper, Utah.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">72</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Slalom training session, Sun Valley Competition</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1965-1966</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>8mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Marvin Melville training for slalom skiing and competing in various races. These races include the Solitude Cup held on March 15 1965, the NCAA Downhill Competition held at Crystal Mountain on March 27, 1956, the Nationals slalom and giant slalom events held on April 2, 1965 and the 1966 Sun Valley Competition.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">73</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Landes jumping</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1965 December 10</unitdate>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1966 December</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>8mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>This film contains footage of Marvin Melville long jumping on the Landes Jump.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">74</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Finlaysen ranch, snowmobiling trip in Yellowstone</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1965 July</unitdate>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1968 March</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>8mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>The Melville family's trips to the Finlaysen Ranch and to Yellowstone National Park:  The footage of the ranch includes several shots of the animals, the land, the Finlaysen's home, and of the tractor in the fields.  The footage of their snowmobiling trip to Yellowstone National Park includes several shots of the family's picnic at Madison Junction and of various surrounding bison.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
