<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9 http://www.loc.gov/ead/ead.xsd">
  <!--Last Edited: 2008/12/08 10:10:36 by xEAD vBETA 07-14-2008-->
  <eadheader langencoding="iso639-2b" scriptencoding="iso15924" relatedencoding="dc" repositoryencoding="iso15511" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-uuml" publicid="-//:://TEXT(US::UUML::UUM_A0331::Steve Lacy collection of Herbert B. Maw audio recordings)//EN" encodinganalog="identifier" identifier="80444/xv82199" url="http://archiveswest.orbiscascade.org/ark:/80444/xv82199">UUM_A0331</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper encodinganalog="title">
          Guide to the Steve Lacy collection of Herbert B. Maw audio recordings
          <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian" normal="1941/1946" encodinganalog="date">1941-1946</date></titleproper>
        <titleproper type="filing" altrender="nodisplay">Lacy (Steve) collection of Herbert B. Maw audio recordings</titleproper>
        <author encodinganalog="creator">Finding aid prepared by Mark Jensen.</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher encodinganalog="publisher">Multimedia Archives, J. Willard Marriott Library, University of Utah</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>295 South 1500 East</addressline>
          <addressline>Salt Lake City, Utah 84112</addressline>
          <addressline>(801) 581-8864</addressline>
        </address>
        <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian" normal="1991" encodinganalog="date">© 1991</date>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>
        Encoded by Molly Creel
        <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian" normal="2008">2008</date></creation>
      <langusage>
        <language encodinganalog="language" langcode="eng" scriptcode="Latn">English</language>
      </langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <archdesc type="inventory" level="collection" relatedencoding="dc">
    <did>
      <repository>
        <corpname encodinganalog="publisher">University of Utah Libraries, Special Collections</corpname>
        <subarea encodinganalog="publisher">Audio Visual Archives</subarea>
        <address>
          <addressline>Special Collections</addressline>
          <addressline>295 South 1500 East</addressline>
          <addressline>Salt Lake City, Utah 84112-0860</addressline>
          <addressline>(801) 581-8864</addressline>
        </address>
      </repository>
      <unitid encodinganalog="identifier" countrycode="US" repositorycode="US-uuml">A0331</unitid>
      <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Steve Lacy collection of Herbert B. Maw audio recordings</unittitle>
      <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian" normal="1941/1946" encodinganalog="date">1941-1946</unitdate>
      <origination>
        <persname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="creator" role="collector">Lacy, Steve, 1951-</persname>
      </origination>
      <physdesc>
        <extent encodinganalog="format">7 audiocassettes</extent>
      </physdesc>
      <abstract encodinganalog="description">The Steve Lacy collection of Herbert B. Maw audio recordings (1941-1946) consists of several audio recordings of speeches made by or on behalf of Herbert B. Maw during his term as governor of Utah.</abstract>
      <langmaterial>Materials in 
        <language encodinganalog="language" langcode="eng">English</language>.
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="description">
      <head>Biographical Note</head>
      <p>Dr. Steve Lacy (b.1951) is a Utah historian and the author of books including <emph render="italic">Posey: The Last Indian War</emph>, <emph render="italic">Last of the Bandit Riders . . . Revisited</emph> and <emph render="italic">The Lynching of Robert Marshall, Last in the West</emph>.  His photograph collection, donated to the Utah State Historical Society (Mss C 472), includes images of the Castle Gate mine disaster, which killed over 170 miners in three explosions March 8, 1924.</p>
      <p>Utah Governor Herbert B. Maw (1893-1990, Gov. 1941-1948) was born in Ogden, Utah to Emma Brown and Ephraim Goodman Maw, who later moved their family to Salt Lake City.  After attending Latter Day Saint (LDS) High School and the University of Utah, Maw served in World War I as one of the army's first Mormon Chaplains.  He married Florence Buehler in 1921.  Having earned his J.D. degree at Northwestern University in 1927, Maw returned to the University of Utah to teach speech and political science from 1927-1940, and he served as Dean of Men from 1928-1936.</p>
      <p>In 1928, Maw was elected to the state senate where he served until 1938.  He was president of that body from 1934-1938.  One of the Utah Democratic Party's more liberal members, Maw promoted old-age assistance programs, government control of public utilities, and direct primary elections.  He won the Democratic Party's gubernatorial nomination in 1940 in the state's first primary election of that kind and went on to defeat his conservative opponent, Don B. Colton to become Utah's eighth governor.</p>
      <p>As governor of the state of Utah, Maw reorganized various commissions, bureaus and boards under the somewhat controversial Publicity Industrial Department (PID) to promote tourism and new business.  The PID built roads to scenic attractions in Southern Utah and built a natural history museum in Vernal.  Maw's administration also built the "This is the Place Monument" at the mouth of Emigration Canyon.  While governor, Maw supported a major highway building program and approved the creation of a state water and power board to oversee the use of Colorado River water within the state.  During World War II, he successfully attracted military and other war related industries to Utah, creating many jobs and reviving the state's economy.</p>
      <p>Herbert Maw was defeated in the 1948 gubernatorial election by Republican J. Bracken Lee.  After his term as governor, he ran a private law practice until well into his 90s.  He died in 1993.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
      <p>The Steve Lacy collection of Herbert B. Maw audio recordings (1941-1946) consists of several audiocassettes recorded from 16" radio transcription discs.  The recordings are of speeches made by or on behalf of Herbert B. Maw during his term as governor of Utah. The collection also includes two episodes of the 1940s Natoinal Broadcasting Company (NBC) radio program <title render="italic">We the Abbots</title>, which were recorded on the opposite sides of a Maw cassette.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement encodinganalog="description">
      <p>This collection is arranged in loose chronological order.</p>
    </arrangement>
    <accessrestrict encodinganalog="rights">
      <p>Materials must be used on-site; no use of original material, access copies will be made available for viewing. Five business days advanced notice required. Access to parts of this collection may be restricted under provisions of state or federal law, condition of the material, or by donor.</p>
    </accessrestrict>
    <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="relation">
      <p>See also the Herbert B. Maw audio-visual collection (A066) and papers (Ms 532).</p>
    </relatedmaterial>
    <processinfo>
      <p>Processed by Mark Jensen in 1991.</p>
    </processinfo>
    <controlaccess>
      <persname encodinganalog="subject" source="lcnaf" role="subject">Maw, Herbert B. (Herbert Brown), 1893-1990</persname>
      <persname encodinganalog="subject" source="lcnaf" role="subject">Garff, Royal A.</persname>
      <geogname encodinganalog="coverage" source="lcsh" role="subject">Utah--Politics and government</geogname>
      <geogname encodinganalog="coverage" source="lcsh" role="subject">Utah--History</geogname>
      <subject altrender="nodisplay" source="archiveswest">Political Campaigns</subject>
      <subject altrender="nodisplay" source="archiveswest">Sound Recordings</subject>
      <genreform encodinganalog="type" source="aat">Speeches</genreform>
      <genreform encodinganalog="type" source="aat">Sound recordings</genreform>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc type="in-depth">
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">1</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">A Challenge to Utahns speech, interview with Maw in Oklahoma, and inaugural address part 1</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1941</unitdate>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1946</unitdate>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Side A</p>
          <p>"A Challenge to Utahns," by Royal Garff.</p>
          <p>circa 1941; 13 minutes</p>
          <p>Local teacher and public speaker Royal Garff delivers a speech which beseeches Utahns who have left the state for educational or career pursuits to make a contribution back to the state.  The speech also promotes Herbert B. Maw as a candidate for governor.  An identical recording of this speech follows on the cassette.</p>
          <p>Side B</p>
          <p>1.  Interview with Governor Herbert B. Maw.</p>
          <p>1946; 14 minutes</p>
          <p>Recorded by KDYL radio at the 1946 National Conference of Governors in Oklahoma.  The governor praises Oklahoma and its oil resources; discusses topics of the conference (veteran's affairs, agriculture and labor), the 1946 presidential campaign, and the purpose of the conference.</p>
          <p>2.  Inaugural address of Governor Herbert B. Maw, part 1.</p>
          <p>January 6, 1941; 19 minutes</p>
          <p>The governor praises his predecessor, Governor Henry H. Blood, a fellow Democrat.  Topics include the need for the state to remain debt-free, control of state money, the spending power of the population and economic problems. Continued on cassette 2, side A.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">2</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Inaugural address part 2; Maw speech January 1941 part 1, and <title render="italic">We the Abbots</title></unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1941 January 6-13</unitdate>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Side A</p>
          <p>1.  Inaugural address of Herbert B. Maw, part 2.</p>
          <p>January 6, 1941; 5 minutes</p>
          <p>Continued from cassette 1, side B.  The Governor continues by praising and expressing gratitude for his wife, family and Russell L. Tracy, local banker and founder of Tracy Aviary.</p>
          <p>2.  Speech by Governor Herbert B. Maw, part 1.</p>
          <p>January 13, 1941; 13 minutes</p>
          <p>In an address before the Utah State Legislature, topics include addressing the needs of farmers and laborers, the stimulation of industry, government finances and taxation.  Continued on Item 3, Side A.</p>
          <p>Side B</p>
          <p>circa 1941; 30 minutes</p>
          <p>A recording of two episodes of the NBC radio program, <title render="italic">We The Abbots</title></p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">3</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Maw speech January 1941 parts 2-5</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">13 January 1941</unitdate>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Side A</p>
          <p>Speech by Governor Herbert B. Maw, parts 2 and 3.</p>
          <p>January 13, 1941; 26 minutes</p>
          <p>Address before the Utah State Legislature continued from cassette 2, side A.  Topics include appropriations, the state budget, and creation and operation of new government departments.</p>
          <p>Side B</p>
          <p>Speech by Governor Herbert B. Maw, parts 4 and 5.</p>
          <p>January 13, 1941; 28 minutes</p>
          <p>Topics include the restructuring of the State Liquor Commission, control of and restructuring of higher education, administration of welfare programs, stimulation of employment opportunities, reappraisal of freight rates, and development of hydroelectric power.  Continued on cassette 5, side A.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">4</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Maw speech 1943 parts 1-4</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1943</unitdate>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Side A</p>
          <p>Speech by Governor Herbert B. Maw, parts 1 and 2.</p>
          <p>1943; 30 minutes</p>
          <p>An address before the 25th Utah State Legislature.  Topics include problems of governing during wartime, praise of government's and citizen's response to demands of wartime, progress of government restructuring initiated two years earlier, and use of government funds.  Continued on cassette 4, side B.</p>
          <p>Side B</p>
          <p>Speech by Governor Herbert B. Maw, parts 3 and 4.</p>
          <p>1943; 30 minutes</p>
          <p>Topics include criticism of current welfare/relief system, proposals for alternatives for Social Services Department, state debt, and proposed legislation.  Part 4 is an incomplete recording.  Cassette 5, Side A has a complete recording of part 4.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">5</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Maw speech January 1941 part 6, Maw speech 1943 parts 4-5</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1941-1943</unitdate>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Side A</p>
          <p>1.  Speech by Governor Herbert B. Maw, part 6.</p>
          <p>January 13, 1941; 10 minutes</p>
          <p>Continued from cassette 3, side B.  Topics include development of a coal industry, as well as other mineral, agricultural and manufacturing industries around the state, promotion of tourism, revenue collection, and use of tax funds for roads.</p>
          <p>2.  Speech by Governor Herbert B. Maw, part 4.</p>
          <p>1943; 17 minutes</p>
          <p>The complete recording of part 4 of this address to the 25th Utah State Legislature, described in cassette 4, side B.</p>
          <p>Side B</p>
          <p>Speech by Governor Herbert B. Maw, part 5.</p>
          <p>1943; 15 minutes</p>
          <p>Topics include war, emergency legislation, construction of a coal processing plant, centralization of state accounting needs in Finance Department, funding of higher education and condition of state finances.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">6</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">A Challenge to Utahns speech, interview with Maw in Oklahoma, and inaugural address part 1</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1941</unitdate>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1946</unitdate>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Cassette 6 is a duplicate of cassette 1.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">7</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Inaugural address part 2; Maw speech January 1941 part 1, and <title render="italic">We the Abbots</title></unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1941 January 6-13</unitdate>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Cassette 7 is a duplicate of cassette 2.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
