<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9 http://www.loc.gov/ead/ead.xsd">
  <eadheader langencoding="iso639-2b" scriptencoding="iso15924" relatedencoding="dc" repositoryencoding="iso15511" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-uuml" publicid="-//University of Utah::Special Collections and Archives//TEXT (US::UUML::UUM_A1056::Snowbird Ski and Summer Resort audio-visual collection)//EN" encodinganalog="identifier" identifier="80444/xv42019" url="http://archiveswest.orbiscascade.org/ark:/80444/xv42019">UUM_A1056</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper encodinganalog="title">Guide to the Snowbird Ski and Summer Resort audio-visual collection
				<date era="ce" calendar="gregorian" normal="1972/1987" encodinganalog="date">1972-1987</date></titleproper>
        <titleproper type="filing" altrender="nodisplay">Snowbird Ski and Summer Resort</titleproper>
        <author encodinganalog="creator">Finding aid created by Molly Creel</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher encodinganalog="publisher">Multimedia Archives, J. Willard Marriott Library, University of Utah</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>295 South 1500 East</addressline>
          <addressline>Salt Lake City, Utah 84112-0860</addressline>
          <addressline>801-581-8864</addressline>
          <addressline>http://www.lib.utah.edu/collections/multimedia-archives/</addressline>
        </address>
        <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian" normal="2011" encodinganalog="date">© 2011</date>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Encoded in Adobe Dreamweaver by Molly Creel
			<date era="ce" calendar="gregorian" normal="2012">2012</date>.
			</creation>
      <langusage>Finding aid encoded in 
			<language encodinganalog="language" langcode="eng" scriptcode="Latn">English</language> in Latin script.
			</langusage>
      <descrules>Finding aid based on DACS (<title render="italic">Describing Archives: A Content Standard</title>).</descrules>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <archdesc level="collection" type="inventory" relatedencoding="dc">
    <did>
      <repository>
        <corpname encodinganalog="publisher">University of Utah Libraries, Special Collections</corpname>
        <subarea encodinganalog="publisher">Audio Visual Archives</subarea>
        <address>
          <addressline>Special Collections</addressline>
          <addressline>295 South 1500 East</addressline>
          <addressline>Salt Lake City, Utah 84112-0860</addressline>
          <addressline>801-581-8864</addressline>
          <addressline>http://www.lib.utah.edu/collections/multimedia-archives/</addressline>
        </address>
      </repository>
      <unitid encodinganalog="identifier" countrycode="US" repositorycode="US-uuml">A1056</unitid>
      <origination>
        <corpname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="creator" role="collector">Snowbird (Utah)</corpname>
      </origination>
      <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Snowbird Ski and Summer Resort audio-visual collection</unittitle>
      <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian" normal="1972/1987" encodinganalog="date">1972-1987</unitdate>
      <physdesc>
        <extent encodinganalog="format">6 16mm films, 1 compact disc</extent>
      </physdesc>
      <abstract encodinganalog="description">The Snowbird Ski and Summer Resort audio-visual collection (1972-1987) consists of six commercial 16mm prints about skiing.  One is a promotional film produced by Snowbird.  The other films promote other American resorts and skiers competing on the World Cup circuit.  Several of the films feature either Snowbird or its employees.  This collection also contains a compact disc copy of a 33rpm phonodisc of yodeling music recorded by Arthur Brogli, Snowbird's first tram operator.  Snowbird Ski and Summer Resort is located in Little Cottonwood Canyon near Salt Lake City, Utah.</abstract>
      <langmaterial>Collection material in 
			<language langcode="eng" encodinganalog="language">English</language>.
            </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="description">
      <head>Historical Note</head>
      <p>After the decline of silver mining in Little Cottonwood Canyon the area was repurposed for winter recreation.  After acquiring the Blackjack and Snowbird mining claims just west of Alta, Alta Lodge employee Ted Johnson partnered with Texas oilman and rancher Richard D. Bass to develop Snowbird as a year round resort.  Snowbird begain operation in December 1971.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
      <p>The Snowbird Ski and Summer Resort audio-visual collection (1972-1987) consists of six commercial 16mm prints about skiing.  One is a promotional film produced by Snowbird.  The other films promote other American resorts and skiers competing on the World Cup circuit and used to be screeneed for students at the Snowbird Ski School.  Several of the films feature either Snowbird or its employees.  All films are badly faded.  This collection also contains a compact disc copy of a 33rpm phonodisc of yodeling music recorded by Arthur Brogli, Snowbird's first tram operator.  All materials have been digitized and are available for viewing and listening on DVD and CD.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement encodinganalog="description">
      <p>The materials are arranged chronologically and by format.</p>
    </arrangement>
    <accessrestrict encodinganalog="rights">
      <p>Materials must be used on-site; no use of original material, access copies will be made available for viewing. Five business days advanced notice required. Access to parts of this collection may be restricted under provisions of state or federal law, condition of the material, or by donor.</p>
    </accessrestrict>
    <userestrict encodinganalog="rights">
      <p>It is the responsibility of the researcher to obtain any necessary copyright clearances.</p>
      <p>Permission to publish material from the Snowbird Ski and Summer Resort audio-visual collection must be obtained from the Special Collections Multimedia Archivist.</p>
    </userestrict>
    <prefercite>
      <p>
        <emph render="italic">Initial Citation:</emph>
                Snowbird Ski and Summer Resort audio-visual collection A1056.
                Special Collections and Archives. University of Utah, J. Willard Marriott. Salt Lake City, Utah.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="italic">Following Citations:</emph>A1056.</p>
    </prefercite>
    <acqinfo>
      <p>Donated by Snowbird Ski and Summer Resort in 2010-2011.</p>
    </acqinfo>
    <processinfo>
      <p>Processed by Molly Creel in 2011.</p>
    </processinfo>
    <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="relation">
      <p>See also the Snowbird Ski and Summer Resort photograph collection (P0385).</p>
    </relatedmaterial>
    <controlaccess>
      <persname encodinganalog="subject" source="lcnaf" role="subject">Brogli, Arthur</persname>
      <geogname encodinganalog="coverage" source="lcsh" role="subject">Utah</geogname>
      <subject encodinganalog="subject" source="lcsh">Ski resorts--Utah</subject>
      <subject encodinganalog="subject" source="lcsh">Yodeling</subject>
      <subject altrender="nodisplay" source="archiveswest">Sports and Recreation</subject>
      <subject altrender="nodisplay" source="archiveswest">Music</subject>
      <subject altrender="nodisplay" source="archiveswest">Moving Images</subject>
      <subject altrender="nodisplay" source="archiveswest">Sound Recordings</subject>
      <genreform encodinganalog="type" source="aat">Moving images</genreform>
      <genreform encodinganalog="type" source="aat">Sound recordings</genreform>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc type="in-depth">
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">1</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">"Skiing Generation"</unittitle>
          <unitdate>1972</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>16mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>PepsiCo sponsored film promoting the Junior NASTAR (National Standard Race) racing program.  Produced by Summit Films and the World Wide Ski Corporation.  Producers: Roger C. Brown, Charles Holmes Goresbeck.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">2</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">"The Longest Winter" ("Cronique d'un Hivar")</unittitle>
          <unitdate>1977</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>16mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Salomon sponsored French film about Spanish skier Juan Manuel Fernandez Ochoa racing on the World Cup Circuit.  The film follows Ochoa as he travels to World Cup venues throughout Europe and also provides coverage of important skiers and races in the 1977 circuit.  Dubbed with English Narration.  Produced by Dominique Dumoulin and S.N. Cinépress.  Song: "Time Wind" by Klaus Schulze.  Directed by Jean-Claude Mesana.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">3</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">"Garmisch '78"</unittitle>
          <unitdate>1978</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>16mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Salomon sponsored film about the 1978 World Cup finals in Garmisch-Partenkirchen, Bavaria, West Germany.  The film dramatically highlights the men's and women's downhill and slalom events and champions like Bernhard Russi, Ingemar Stenmark, Franz Klammer and Irene Epple.  Produced by Jalbert Productions and Trans World International.  Producer: Jay Michaels.  Produced and Directed by Joe Jay Jalbert and Kim Takal.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">4</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Snowbird promotional film</unittitle>
          <unitdate>1978</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>16mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Snowbird Ski Resort promotional film highlighting the resort's location, the opportunities offered to skiers of various levels and the other facilities offered.  Produced for Snowbird Corporation and Hart Ski Company by Ross Jurney Advertising Inc., Dick Barrymore Productions, Telescene Inc.  Song: "Sunshine on my Shoulders" by John Denver performed by Jon Holloman, music by Sound Column.  Skiers: Corky Fowler, Junior Bonous, Jeff Jobe, Kent Hoopingarner, Gerald Warren, Kid Cutter, Herman Golner, Lynn Christiansen, Harold Styles, Sherry Fowler.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">5</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">"Wintersong"</unittitle>
          <unitdate>1980</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>16mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Music video presented by Beech Mountain Ski Area in North Carolina featuring a section filmed at Snowbird showing skiers and the Tram.  Produced by Alpenglow Productions.  Songs: "Wintersong" and "Song of the Seasons" by Peggie Niemann, performed by Sharon Scott.  Skiers: Mike Russell, Tom Chesney, Bob Ash, Corky Fowler, Johanna Moose, Bobby Linderman, Mike Barrett, Ruth Picket, Mike Doobrow, Chuck Ash, Sharon Gephardt.  Directed by Larry Gebhardt.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">6</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">"American Ski Teaching System" </unittitle>
          <unitdate>1987</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>16mm film</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Japanese film featuring the PSIA (Professional Ski Instructors of America), including Snowbird's Max Lundberg, demonstrating teaching techniques.  Although the PSIA members occasionally speak in English, the film is predominantly in Japanese without subtitles.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="reel">7</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">"Spectacular: Yodeling by Arthur Brogli"</unittitle>
          <unitdate>undated</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>compact disc</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>CD copy of 33rpm phonodisc recorded by Arthur Brogli, Snowbird's first tram operator.   To view scans of the record jacket please contact the audio-visual archivist.  Tracks:</p>
          <list type="simple">
            <item>Rainbow of Yodels (yodel)</item>
            <item>Vo Luzern gege Weggis zu (yodel song)</item>
            <item>Snowbird Yodel Polka (dance yodel)</item>
            <item>Vaters Lieblings Jodel (yodel)</item>
            <item>Polka, schooner Polka (handharmonica)</item>
            <item>Der Us-Wanderer (yodel song)</item>
            <item>Fricktaler Bure-Sunntig (yodel song)</item>
            <item>Walzer-Tanz-Jodel (dance yodel)</item>
            <item>Ich, uses Chnächtli (yodel song)</item>
            <item>Schnellzug-Jodel (yodel)</item>
            <item>Klavier und Jodel (yodel)</item>
            <item>Polka-Tanz-Jodel (dance yodel)</item>
          </list>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
