<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9 http://www.loc.gov/ead/ead.xsd">
  <!--Last Edited: 2008/12/08 10:10:42 by xEAD vBETA 07-14-2008-->
  <eadheader langencoding="iso639-2b" scriptencoding="iso15924" relatedencoding="dc" repositoryencoding="iso15511" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-uuml" publicid="-//:://TEXT(US::UUML::UUM_A0402::Alan K. Engen ski video collection)//EN" encodinganalog="identifier" identifier="80444/xv01519" url="http://archiveswest.orbiscascade.org/ark:/80444/xv01519">UUM_A0402</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper encodinganalog="title">
          Guide to the Alan K. Engen ski video collection
          <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian" normal="1996/1998" encodinganalog="date">1996-1998</date></titleproper>
        <titleproper type="filing" altrender="nodisplay">Engen (Alan K.) ski video collection</titleproper>
        <author encodinganalog="creator">Finding aid prepared by Lorraine Crouse.</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher encodinganalog="publisher">Multimedia Archives, J. Willard Marriott Library, University of Utah</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>295 South 1500 East</addressline>
          <addressline>Salt Lake City, Utah 84112</addressline>
          <addressline>(801) 581-8864</addressline>
        </address>
        <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian" normal="1998" encodinganalog="date">© 1998</date>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>
        Encoded by Greg Midgley
        <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian" normal="2008">2008</date></creation>
      <langusage>
        <language encodinganalog="language" langcode="eng" scriptcode="Latn">English</language>
      </langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <archdesc type="inventory" level="collection" relatedencoding="dc">
    <did>
      <repository>
        <corpname encodinganalog="publisher">University of Utah Libraries, Special Collections</corpname>
        <subarea encodinganalog="publisher">Audio Visual Archives</subarea>
        <address>
          <addressline>Special Collections</addressline>
          <addressline>295 South 1500 East</addressline>
          <addressline>Salt Lake City, Utah 84112-0860</addressline>
          <addressline>(801) 581-8864</addressline>
        </address>
      </repository>
      <unitid encodinganalog="identifier" countrycode="US" repositorycode="US-uuml">A0402</unitid>
      <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Alan K. Engen ski video collection</unittitle>
      <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian" normal="1996/1998" encodinganalog="date">1996-1998</unitdate>
      <origination>
        <persname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="creator" role="creator">Engen, Alan K.</persname>
      </origination>
      <physdesc>
        <extent encodinganalog="format">8 Betacam videocassettes and VHS videocassette copies.</extent>
      </physdesc>
      <abstract encodinganalog="description">The Alan K. Engen ski video collection (1996-1998) contains movies produced or created by Alan Engen dealing with the legacy of his father Alf Engen (1909-1997), an internationally recognized skier and luminary in skiing education in Utah and the American West.  Alan Engen is an accomplished competitive skier, administrator and ski historian.</abstract>
      <langmaterial>Materials in 
        <language encodinganalog="language" langcode="eng">English</language>.
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="description">
      <p>Alan Engen (b.1940), the son of Alf Engen, began skiing at the age of two. He attended the University of Utah, where he was a member of the ski team from 1958 to 1962. He graduated with B.A. and B.F.A. degrees in Art History in 1963. In a lifetime of competitive skiing, he has won countless championships. Engen is currently the director of skiing at Alta and chairman/president of the Alf Engen Ski Museum.</p>
      <p>Alf Engen (1909-1997) was a Norwegian-American skier, ski instructor and owner.  His two younger brothers, Sverre (1911-2001) and Corey (1916-2006), were also both accomplished skiers, and their combined contributions to the development and popularity of skiing in the Western United States were significant.</p>
      <p>Engen was born in Mjondallen, Norway, the oldest of three boys.  As a son of the famous skier Trond Engen he was reared in skiing from a young age. In 1929,at age twenty, Engen immigrated to the United States with his younger brother, Sverre. They settled in Chicago, where the two brothers joined the American-Norwegian Athletic Club to meet fellow Norwegians. In 1931, he settled permanently in Salt Lake City. His youngest brother, Kaare, and their mother, Martha, immigrated to the United States in 1933 and the three Engen brothers traveled the United States as professional jumpers, breaking Nordic records and gaining recognition wherever they went.</p>
      <p>Engen's success as a skier is beyond compare. He began his impressive professional career by capturing the National Jumping Champion title eight times between the years of 1931 and 1946. Furthermore, at the age of 37 and on borrowed skis, he won the 1946 National Jumping title by leaping 259 feet. He was also the National Classic Champion (cross country and jumping combined) twice during these years in 1939 and 1941. After learning how to downhill ski at the age of 30, Engen became national downhill and slalom champion in 1947. Engen was also the recipient of numerous awards including the All-American Ski Trophy, 1937, Americanism Award in 1940, Helm's Hall of Fame Award in 1954; and Skier's Hall of Fame Award in 1956.  He is credited for developing the technique of powder skiing, honed at the Alta Ski Area.</p>
      <p>He established the Alf Engen Ski School at Alta, Utah, and became director of the Deseret News and Telegram Free Ski School. In 1948, Engen and Walter Prager were co-coaches for the United States Olympic ski team.  He assisted in the creation of over 30 various ski resorts in the Western United States, in a lifetime dedicated to the development of the industry.</p>
      <p>Alf Engen died in 1997, at the age of 88. His two younger brothers both lived to the age of 90.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
      <p>The Alan K. Engen ski video collection (1996-1998) contains betacam and VHS copies of movies, most of which relate to the career of skier Alf Engen, primarily produced and moderated by his son Alan Engen.  Personal interviews, documentary films, and lecture presentations deal with the history of ski instruction in Utah as well as the considerable achievements and records set by Alf Engen as a competitive skier.  Also included are personal materials documenting Alan Engen's participation in the 1996 Olympic torch relay.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement encodinganalog="description">
      <p>This collection is arranged chronologically and by subject.</p>
    </arrangement>
    <accessrestrict encodinganalog="rights">
      <p>Materials must be used on-site; no use of original material, access copies will be made available for viewing. Five business days advanced notice required. Access to parts of this collection may be restricted under provisions of state or federal law, condition of the material, or by donor.  The Olympic Torch Relay, "Alf Engen: Ski Meister" and "Sverre Engen film" may only be reproduced with permission of donor.</p>
    </accessrestrict>
    <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="relation">
      <p>See also the Alf Engen scrapbooks (Accn 1006) and ski video collection (A0391), Corey Engen scrapbooks (Accn 1401), the Ski Museum records (Accn 518) and the Alan K. Engen papers (Accn 1601).</p>
    </relatedmaterial>
    <processinfo>
      <p>Processed by Lorraine Crouse in 1997.</p>
    </processinfo>
    <controlaccess>
      <persname encodinganalog="subject" source="lcnaf" role="subject">Engen, Alf, 1909-1997</persname>
      <subject encodinganalog="subject" source="lcsh">Skis and skiing--United States--History--Sources</subject>
      <subject encodinganalog="subject" source="lcsh">Skis and skiing--Utah--History--Sources</subject>
      <subject altrender="nodisplay" source="archiveswest">Sports and Recreation</subject>
      <subject altrender="nodisplay" source="archiveswest">Moving Images</subject>
      <genreform encodinganalog="type" source="aat">Moving images</genreform>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc type="in-depth">
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">1</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Olympic torch relay</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1996 May 10</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Short video clips of the Alan Engen segment of the Olympic Torch Relay.  Family, friends and others  cheer as the Olympic torch is passed to Alan Engen.  The Olympic Torch was carried and passed from person to person across the country, culminating in the lighting of the torch to open 1996 Summer Olympic Games in Atlanta, Georgia.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <accessrestrict encodinganalog="rights">
          <p>Reproduction is restricted except by permission of donor.</p>
        </accessrestrict>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">2-3</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">History of the Deseret News Ski School</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1996 September 12</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>Betacam videocassette, VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>History of the Deseret News Ski School as told by Wilby Durham, Alf Engen and Sverre Engen at the home of Alan Engen.  Moderated by Alan Engen and Dr. Joe Arave.  46 minutes.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">4-5</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Alf Engen: Ski Meister of the 20th Century</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1997</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>Betacam videocassette, VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Spectacular film footage of ski legend, Alf Engen, as he flies, sprints, zips through gates, and shreds the powder right into the annals of American ski folklore and history.  Narrated by Alf's elder son, Alan, this presentation shows why Alf is regarded as one of the finest all around skiers ever to grace the sport.  Produced by Alan K. Engen.  Directed by Dobber Price</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <accessrestrict encodinganalog="rights">
          <p>Reproduction is restricted except by permission of donor.</p>
        </accessrestrict>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">6</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Sverre Engen film</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">undated</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <accessrestrict encodinganalog="rights">
          <p>Reproduction is restricted except by permission of donor.</p>
        </accessrestrict>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">7</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Alan Engen presentation</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1998 November 08</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Alan Engen presentats at the Marriott Library Books and Authors Series.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <container type="cassette">8</container>
          <unittitle encodinganalog="title">Thrills and spills in the North Country</unittitle>
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" encodinganalog="date">1998</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform>VHS videocassette</genreform>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="description">
          <p>Produced and Directed by Rick Moulton for the New England Ski Museum</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
