<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:id="DigEd">Typopictoromania: Digital Edition</title>
                <author>John Thelwall</author>
                <editor>Sarah Boyle and Michael Cameron</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Introduction and Notes</resp>
                    <name>Sarah Boyle and Michael Cameron</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>General Editor</resp>
                    <name>Jane Boyes</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Judith Thompson</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl xml:id="Per">
                    <title level="a" type="chapter">The Epic Poem</title> in <title level="m">The
                        Peripatetic</title>
                    <author>John Thelwall</author>
                    <editor>Judith Thompson</editor>
                    <pubPlace>Detroit, Michigan</pubPlace>
                    <publisher>Wayne State UP</publisher>
                    <date when="2001">2001</date>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="Der">
                    <title level="a">Typopictoromania</title> in <title level="u">The Derby
                        Manuscript</title>
                    <author>John Thelwall</author>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Our text is <title level="a">Typopictoromania,</title> an epic fragment that was
                    to have been part of a much longer poem. It is epic like Dryden, satirical like
                    Pope, critical like Blake; the fragment reveals the beginnings of a poem that
                    was to use a grand yet cartoonish battle, one between the types of Caslon’s
                    print house and the brushes of Boydell’s Shakespeare Gallery, as an opportunity
                    to ridicule the abuse and abasement of poetic language during the revolutionary
                    period in England. While the poem was never finished, what has survived—a
                    preface, proposition, an invocation, a first canto, part of a second, and a few
                    random fragments, together totalling close to five hundred lines of poetry—are
                    both aesthetically and historically relevant to those interested in the early
                    romanticism of the revolutionary period. While Thelwall claims that he initially
                    intended to write a complete poem, its unfinished nature puts it in the same
                    historical camp as Keats’ <title level="m">Hyperion</title> and Coleridge’s
                        <title level="a">Kubla Khan</title>, texts that are paradoxically whole in
                    their incompleteness. Furthermore, the poem is of particular import for Thelwall
                    scholars; appearing in both <title level="m">The Peripatetic</title> of 1793 and
                    in the later Derby Manuscript, the poem bookends Thelwall’s career. The two
                    copies differ in a great many minor respects, particularly in punctuation, but a
                    significant amount of major variations, where the later Thelwall has rewritten
                    entire lines, are also present; a thorough study of the differences may be
                    valuable for scholars interested in the development from the younger to older
                    Thelwall. Thus, our task is to present a complete and accessible reading copy of
                    the poem, showing a preference to the most recent and hitherto unpublished
                    version (the Derby Manuscript) and including all important variations in
                    editorial notes and additional yet important material in appendices.
                    Furthermore, our TEI coding will ensure that scholars have access to all
                    variations between the texts for the sake of comparison.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader><text><body><div xml:id="preface">
                <pb type="pdf" n="349"/>
                <head resp="editor">Preface</head>
                <p>
                    <app>
                        <lem wit="DigEd">The object of this Poem (one entire canto of which was
                            written many years ago, but of which only the following fragments which
                            appeared in <title level="m" rend="quote">the peripatetic</title> are
                            preserved) was to ridicule the rage for splendid editions of the Poets
                            etc. The fable a supposed conflict between the Types upon
                                <placeName>Caslon’s Foundry in Chiswell Street</placeName>, and the
                            Pictures in <placeName>Boydell’s Gallery</placeName>. It was designed
                            however as a vehicle for political Satyr.<note>According to the <title level="m">OED</title>, <q>satyr</q> was a common spelling for
                                    <q>satire</q> up until the early eighteenth century. Like his
                                use of <quote>camelion</quote> in the Proposition, it is likely that
                                Thelwall used this archaic spelling to evoke the writing of earlier
                                poets (see note 10). However, it is strange that he does not use the
                                same spelling in the next two paragraphs. Regardless, we have chosen
                                to retain the original spelling.</note> The following extracts from
                            the Peripatetic might serve as materials for a preface.<note>Thelwall
                                has cut out and pasted the sections <quote>You will not...the
                                    laborious and</quote> and <quote>induced me...magnanimous
                                    hero.</quote> from <title level="m">P</title>. Interestingly,
                                Thelwall chose to hand write the material in between. This is
                                strange because, apart from some seemingly insignificant changes,
                                this material is also present in <title level="m">P</title>; he
                                changes <quote>had long struck my mind</quote> to <quote>had long
                                    impressed my mind,</quote> and <quote>the proposal of the BEST
                                    OF LETTER FOUNDERS to the BEST OF KINGS</quote> becomes
                                    <quote>the proposals of Mr Caslon (letter founder to his
                                    Majesty).</quote></note>
                        </lem>
                        <rdg wit="#Der">The object of this Poem (<subst>
                                <del>two</del>
                                <add place="inline">one</add>
                            </subst> entire canto<del>s</del> of which <subst>
                                <del>were</del>
                                <add place="inline">was</add>
                            </subst> written many years ago, but of which only the following
                            fragments which appeared in <choice>
                                <orig><title level="a">the peripatetic</title></orig>
                                <reg><title level="m">The Peripatetic</title></reg>
                            </choice> are preserved) was to ridicule the rage for splendid editions
                            of the Poets &amp;c. The fable a supposed conflict between the Types
                            from Caslon’s Foundry in Chiswell Street, &amp; the Pictures in
                            Boydell’s Gallery. It was designed however as a vehicle for political
                                <sic>Satyr</sic>. The following extracts from <choice>
                                <orig>the peripatetic</orig>
                                <reg><title level="m">The Peripatetic</title></reg>
                            </choice> might serve as materials for a preface.</rdg>
                    </app>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <app>
                        <lem wit="#DigEd">You will not, I dare say, be very angry at seeing placed
                            in a ridiculous point of view, this rage for splendid editions of works,
                            however excellent in their nature: a rage so prejudicial to the solid
                            interests of literature; and, with respect to the art of Painting
                            itself, rather holding out a kind of commercial temptation to hasty and
                            copious production, than a generous and liberal patronage to the
                            laborious and scientific pursuit of excellence and sublimity. The
                            absurdity of thus reducing the noblest specimens of literary genius to
                            mere expensive pieces of furniture, to please the vacant eye of foppery,
                            had long impressed my mind as a very proper object for satire and
                            ridicule, when the proposals of <persName>Mr Caslon</persName> (letter
                            founder to his Majesty) for adding to the list of popular publications
                            in editions <hi rend="italics">all too splendid to be read,</hi> the
                                <title level="m" rend="quote">Gil Blas</title> and <title level="m" rend="quote">Devil on Two Sticks</title><note>Closing
                                quotation mark retained from <title level="m">P</title>: absent in
                                    <title level="u">DM</title>.</note> of <persName>Le
                                Sage</persName>,<note>Alain-René Lesage (1668-1747) was a French
                                novelist and playwright. <title level="m">Gil Blas</title> and
                                    <title level="m">Devil on Two Sticks</title> are two of his
                                scathingly satirical works. Thelwall’s comment here indicates his
                                displeasure that such books are being printed to be decorative, but
                                not functional.</note> induced me to form the plan of a mock heroic
                            poem, of which the mighty <hi rend="italics">Alphabeta</hi>, the Vulcan
                            of Chiswell-street, and forger of the literary thunderbolts of the
                            terrestrial <name type="mythological">Jove</name>,<note>Jove (Jupiter)
                                is the ancient Roman god of the sky and thunder. He is the king of
                                other gods, making him an appropriate substitution for George
                                III.</note> was to be the magnanimous hero.</lem>
                        <rdg wit="#Der"><span type="print">You will not, I dare say, be very angry
                                at seeing placed in a ridiculous point of view, this rage for
                                splendid editions of works, however excellent in their nature: a
                                rage so prejudicial to the solid interests of literature; and, with
                                respect to the art of Painting itself, rather holding out a kind of
                                commercial temptation to hasty and copious production, than a
                                generous and liberal patronage to the laborious and</span>
                            scientific pursuit of excellence &amp; sublimity. The absurdity of thus
                            reducing the noblest specimens of literary genius to mere expensive
                            pieces of furniture, to please the vacant eye of foppery, had long
                            impressed my mind as a very proper object for satire &amp; ridicule,
                            when the proposals of Mr Caslon (letter founder to his Majesty) for
                            adding to the list of popular publications in editions <hi rend="underline">all too splendid to be read,</hi> the “Gil Blas”
                            and “Devil on Two Sticks of Le Sage induced me to form the plan of a
                            mock heroic poem, of which the mighty <hi rend="italics">Alphabeta</hi>,
                            the Vulcan of Chiswell-street, and forger of the literary thunderbolts
                            of the terrestrial <hi rend="smallcaps">Jove</hi>, was to be the
                            magnanimous hero. <del resp="Thelwall" rend="overstrike">Of the local
                                situation of the</del></rdg>
                        <rdg wit="#Per">You will not, I dare say, be very angry at seeing placed in
                            a ridiculous point of view, this rage for splendid editions of works,
                            however excellent in their nature: a rage so prejudicial to the solid
                            interests of literature; and, with respect to the art of Painting
                            itself, rather holding out a kind of commercial temptation to hasty and
                            copious production, than a generous and liberal patronage to the
                            laborious and scientific pursuit of excellence, and sublimity of
                            composition. The absurdity of thus reducing the noblest specimens of
                            literary genius to mere expensive pieces of furniture, to please the
                            vacant eye of Foppery, had long struck my mind as a very proper object
                            for satire and ridicule, and the proposal of the <hi rend="smallcaps">Best of Letter Founders</hi> to the <hi rend="smallcaps">Best of
                                Kings</hi>, for adding to the list of <hi rend="italics">popular
                                publications, too splendid to be read</hi>, the <title level="a">Gil
                                Blas</title> and <title level="a">Devil on Two Sticks</title> of Le
                            Sage, induced me to form the plan of a mock heroic poem, of which the
                            mighty <hi rend="italics">Alphabeta</hi>, the Vulcan of Chiswell-Street,
                            and forger of the literary thunderbolts of the terrestrial <hi rend="smallcaps">Jove</hi>, was to be the magnanimous hero.</rdg>
                    </app>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <app>
                        <lem wit="#DigEd">P.S. What I had written was at first very highly commended
                            by <persName>J. Horne Tooke</persName>,<note>John Horne Tooke
                                (1736-1812) was greatly admired by Thelwall. When Tooke ran
                                (unsuccessfully) for the Westminster election in 1780, Thelwall
                                developed a close bond, acting as his assistant. Tooke had many of
                                the same radical revolutionary ideals as Thelwall. In 1794, Tooke
                                was arrested alongside Thelwall and others for sedition, and both
                                spent time in the Tower of London (see Bugg).</note> with whom I had
                            recently become acquainted; but he afterwards discouraged me from
                            proceeding, being very desirous of drawing me to some subject more
                            exclusively political. He proposed a satire on the Coalition of
                                Kings:<note>In 1793, Great Britain joined a coalition of European
                                monarchies in a war against France. Thelwall’s fear that a satirical
                                take on the subject would have put him in danger was likely
                                justified considering the anti-Jacobin sentiment that was rising at
                                the time.</note> but <choice>
                                <orig>tho</orig>
                                <reg>though</reg>
                            </choice> I dropt (unwisely I think) my own project,<note>Thelwall
                                scratches out the word <quote>satire</quote> and corrects it with
                                the word <quote>project.</quote> This correction seems to be have
                                been made immediately upon composition, since <quote>project</quote>
                                follows sequentially as opposed to being written above the crossed
                                out word.</note> I could never see his in that point of view which
                            would furnish materials for a mock heroic poem. Had I then written upon
                            such a subject I should have written with a bitterness which might have
                            been amusing to him; but would have been dangerous to me.</lem>
                        <rdg wit="#Der">P.S. <p>What I had written was at first very highly
                                commended by J. Horne Tooke, with whom I had recently become
                                acquainted; but he afterwards discouraged me from proceeding, being
                                very desirous of drawing me to some subject more exclusively
                                political. He proposed a satire on the Coalition of Kings: but tho I
                                dropt (unwisely I think) my own <unclear cert="medium"><del rend="overstrike">satire</del></unclear> project, I could
                                never see his in that point of view which would furnish materials
                                for a mock heroic poem. Had I then written upon such a subject I
                                should have written with a bitterness which might have been amusing
                                to him; but would have been dangerous to me.</p>
                        </rdg>
                    </app>
                </p>
            </div></body></text></TEI>