<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:id="DigEd">Typopictoromania: Digital Edition</title>
                <author>John Thelwall</author>
                <editor>Sarah Boyle and Michael Cameron</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Introduction and Notes</resp>
                    <name>Sarah Boyle and Michael Cameron</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>General Editor</resp>
                    <name>Jane Boyes</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Judith Thompson</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl xml:id="Per">
                    <title level="a" type="chapter">The Epic Poem</title> in <title level="m">The
                        Peripatetic</title>
                    <author>John Thelwall</author>
                    <editor>Judith Thompson</editor>
                    <pubPlace>Detroit, Michigan</pubPlace>
                    <publisher>Wayne State UP</publisher>
                    <date when="2001">2001</date>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="Der">
                    <title level="a">Typopictoromania</title> in <title level="u">The Derby
                        Manuscript</title>
                    <author>John Thelwall</author>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Our text is <title level="a">Typopictoromania,</title> an epic fragment that was
                    to have been part of a much longer poem. It is epic like Dryden, satirical like
                    Pope, critical like Blake; the fragment reveals the beginnings of a poem that
                    was to use a grand yet cartoonish battle, one between the types of Caslon’s
                    print house and the brushes of Boydell’s Shakespeare Gallery, as an opportunity
                    to ridicule the abuse and abasement of poetic language during the revolutionary
                    period in England. While the poem was never finished, what has survived—a
                    preface, proposition, an invocation, a first canto, part of a second, and a few
                    random fragments, together totalling close to five hundred lines of poetry—are
                    both aesthetically and historically relevant to those interested in the early
                    romanticism of the revolutionary period. While Thelwall claims that he initially
                    intended to write a complete poem, its unfinished nature puts it in the same
                    historical camp as Keats’ <title level="m">Hyperion</title> and Coleridge’s
                        <title level="a">Kubla Khan</title>, texts that are paradoxically whole in
                    their incompleteness. Furthermore, the poem is of particular import for Thelwall
                    scholars; appearing in both <title level="m">The Peripatetic</title> of 1793 and
                    in the later Derby Manuscript, the poem bookends Thelwall’s career. The two
                    copies differ in a great many minor respects, particularly in punctuation, but a
                    significant amount of major variations, where the later Thelwall has rewritten
                    entire lines, are also present; a thorough study of the differences may be
                    valuable for scholars interested in the development from the younger to older
                    Thelwall. Thus, our task is to present a complete and accessible reading copy of
                    the poem, showing a preference to the most recent and hitherto unpublished
                    version (the Derby Manuscript) and including all important variations in
                    editorial notes and additional yet important material in appendices.
                    Furthermore, our TEI coding will ensure that scholars have access to all
                    variations between the texts for the sake of comparison.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="introduction">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <div>
                    <head>I. General Introduction</head>
                    <p>Epic like Dryden, satirical like Pope, radical like Blake, <title level="a"
                            >Typopictoromania: An Epic Fragment</title> is an unfinished mock heroic
                        poem that was to use a grand yet cartoonish battle, one between the types of
                        Caslon’s print house and the brushes of Boydell’s Shakespeare Gallery, as an
                        opportunity to ridicule the abuse and abasement of poetic language, writing,
                        and speech during the revolutionary romantic period in England. While
                        Thelwall claims that he initially intended to write a complete poem, its
                        unfinished nature puts it in the same historical camp as Keats’ <title
                            level="m">Hyperion</title> and Coleridge’s <title level="a">Kubla
                            Khan</title>, texts that are paradoxically whole in their
                        incompleteness. The sections that have survived—a preface, a proposition, an
                        invocation, a first canto, part of a second, and a few random fragments,
                        together totalling close to five hundred lines of poetry—are both
                        aesthetically and historically relevant to those interested in the print
                        culture of the 1790s and the relationship between revolution and
                        romanticism.</p>
                    <p>The poetic fragment comes to us in two forms. It first appears in Thelwall’s
                        genre-blending <title level="m">The Peripatetic</title> [1793] as part of
                        the chapter entitled <title level="a">The Epic Poem.</title> Here, the poem
                        goes unnamed, and it is but a small section of the third volume, a chance
                        for the narrator, Sylvanus, to share some epic poetry as part of a debate
                        with his friends. The poem then appears properly titled, prefaced, and
                        individuated in the second volume of the <title level="u">Derby
                            Manuscript</title>, which dates from the early decades of the nineteenth
                        century. By bookending Thelwall’s career, the poem is of particular import
                        for Thelwall scholars. The two copies differ in a great many minor respects,
                        particularly in punctuation, and a significant number of major variations,
                        where the later Thelwall has rewritten entire lines in the manuscript, are
                        also present. A thorough study of the differences will be valuable for
                        scholars interested in Thelwall’s poetic and political development.</p>
                    <p>This introduction gives context for the poem, both in its early moment of
                        composition and in its later revision. It opens with a brief description of
                        Thelwall’s early life, and closes with a note on our edition.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>II. Thelwall’s Early Biography</head>
                    <p>Thelwall’s upbringing helps to explain his later advocacy of democratic
                        ideals against governmental and monarchical corruption. He was born in 1764
                        into the shopkeeper class. His father, a silk mercer, died in 1772, and
                        afterward the family business started to fail. As a child, Thelwall received
                            <quote>a typical, but to his mind utterly inadequate, education at
                            several day and boarding schools</quote> (Thompson, <title level="a"
                            >Introduction</title> 12). In 1777, he was forced to leave school to
                        become a tailor’s apprentice, bringing an end to his formal education.
                        Hating this work, he sought to enter many other fields. He attempted
                        painting, tried to break into the theatre, and <quote>was articled as a
                            clerk to the attorney John Impey</quote> (<title level="m"
                        >ODNB</title>). He canceled his call to the bar after three and a half years
                        of studying, possibly due to his <quote>indignation at abuses</quote> (Mee
                        170) of the law; this is reflected in <title level="a"
                            >Typopictoromania,</title> where he states the <quote>lawyer may prove
                            that black is white</quote> (Line 103 of Canto One). Ultimately, none of
                        these fields was successful or fulfilling. Instead, Thelwall found his
                        calling at the junction of literature, politics, and elocution. Having
                        overcome his own disabilities (a speech impediment and hereditary asthma),
                        he placed himself in a position to represent and advocate for those whose
                        voices would not otherwise be heard. His own impediments <quote>no doubt
                            helped to transform a young man who was once a staunch Tory, royalist,
                            and high-church man into an atheist, republican, freethinker</quote>
                        (Thompson, <title level="a">Introduction</title> 14).</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>III. Revolutionary Speech in the Romantic Period</head>
                    <p>It seems almost the work of fate that Thelwall would embark on his literary
                        and political career at the outset of the French Revolution. Although the
                            <quote>initial British reaction to French developments was
                            overwhelmingly positive</quote> (Claeys, <title level="m"
                            >Revolution</title> 8), public opinion became increasingly divisive as
                        the revolution’s early idealism gave way to the Terror. The debate in
                        England was originally spurred by Burke’s 1790 <title level="m">Reflections
                            on the Revolution in France</title>, which <quote>insisted that…the
                            Revolution posed the threat of a new form of tyranny, that of a
                            democracy fuelled, like a new religion, by its own sense of
                            infallibility</quote> (Claeys, <title level="m">Revolution</title> 13).
                        This publication inspired Thomas Paine to respond with <title level="m"
                            >Rights of Man</title> [1791-92], and from then on the debate became
                        increasingly vitriolic. Burke’s role as the conservative commentator against
                        whom the revolutionaries positioned their arguments is confirmed by a later
                        statement from Thelwall: <quote>it was not <emph>Tom Paine</emph> but
                                <emph>Edmund Burke</emph> that made me so zealous a reformer</quote>
                        (quoted in Claeys, <title level="m">Politics</title> xvi, emphasis in
                        original).</p>
                    <p>Thelwall joined the British Jacobin supporters of the revolution and
                        advocated for free speech, the abolition of slavery, and education for all
                        in Britain. He knew firsthand the unfairness of class and the systemic
                        issues that kept the lower class in its place. His entrance into politics
                        began in 1790 when he volunteered to assist the political career of John
                        Horne Tooke, a radical <quote>who sought to extend…suffrage and to purify
                            the election process</quote> (Claeys, <title level="m">Politics</title>
                        xvii). Tooke, Thelwall’s <quote><soCalled rend="single">political
                                father</soCalled></quote> (Mee 183), would remain an important
                        influence on Thelwall throughout this period, and it was Tooke who
                        encouraged Thelwall to drop <title level="a">Typopictoromania</title> before
                        completion (see <title level="a">Preface</title>). In 1793, Thelwall became
                        an active member of the London Corresponding Society, a reform group
                        composed largely of tradesmen and artisans. Thelwall lectured regularly for
                        the society Thelwall and by doing so <quote>rapidly acquired a reputation as
                            the most compelling rhetorician in the reformer’s camp</quote> (Claeys,
                            <title level="m">Politics</title> xix). Although best known as an
                        orator, and committed to the people’s voice, Thelwall also capitalized on
                        print as a revolutionary tool. He viewed the <quote>expansion of the press
                            in the last quarter of the eighteenth century as an invitation</quote>
                        (Mee 169). With the expansion of print and greater literacy, radicals like
                        Thelwall could spread their revolutionary arguments to the masses relatively
                        cheaply. Like Spence’s <title level="m">Pig’s Meat</title> and Eaton’s
                            <title level="m">Politics for the People</title>, Thelwall’s <title
                            level="j">The Tribune</title>, which ran from March 1795 until April
                        1796, helped spread democratic, reformist ideas. Furthermore, print and
                        oratory were fundamentally linked for Thelwall; he often wrote with the same
                        oratorical zeal with which he spoke, and many of his lectures were later
                        printed, either by the likes of Eaton (see Scrivener, <title level="m"
                            >Allegories</title> pp. 111-118) or himself in <title level="j">The
                            Tribune</title> (Claeys, <title level="m">Politics</title>, xxv).</p>
                    <p>As a printed piece in this period, <title level="a">The Epic Poem</title> of
                            <title level="m">The Peripatetic</title> [1793], later to be renamed
                            <title level="a">Typopictoromania,</title> is not only an example of
                        Thelwall’s mix of rhetoric, print, and politics; it is also a critical
                        commentary on the use of rhetoric and print in this era in general. Thelwall
                        claims that the purpose of the poem <quote>was to ridicule the rage for
                            splendid editions of the Poets</quote> since <quote>the noblest
                            specimens of literary genius [were being reduced] to mere expensive
                            pieces of furniture</quote> (<title level="a">Preface</title>). Hence
                        the poem’s intended subject matter: the battle between the Pictures in
                        Boydell’s gallery and the Letters in Caslon’s type foundry. William Caslon,
                        who operated a type foundry on Chiswell Street, used elaborate and decorous,
                        decorative illustrations and typefaces to create books that were, according
                        to Thelwall, <quote><hi rend="italics">all too splendid to be
                            read</hi></quote> (<title level="a">Preface,</title> emphasis in
                        original). Similarly, John Boydell’s Shakespeare Gallery was part of a
                        larger project to illustrate the works of Shakespeare as elegant accessories
                        in the homes of the gentry. By pitting the type foundry against the gallery,
                        Thelwall’s satire goes without a hero to champion the intrinsic value of
                        poetry itself; Thomspon states, <quote>as Thelwall finds no idealism in this
                            mercantile world of inflation and decay, so his mock-epic has no hero,
                            only an anti-hero, the volcanic monster Alphabeta, representing the
                            power of language and literature already corrupted and co-opted by
                            monarchs and their minions</quote> (Thompson, <title level="a"
                            >Introduction</title> 27). From the fragments that remain, it is clear
                        that the poem was to end with Jove, allegorically representing King George
                        III, declaring <quote><hi rend="italics">That Reason’s voice should
                                cease</hi></quote> (Line 43 of <title level="a">Fragments</title>),
                        and thus the satire was to end with a complete commodification of literature
                        and repression of thought, reflecting Thelwall’s transition from literary
                        ambition to political activism.</p>
                    <p>The poem’s <title level="a">Invocation</title> reveals that the satire was to
                        extend beyond a criticism of Caslon and Bydell to attack <quote>the triumph
                            of elegant luxury and verbal inflation over the language of reason and
                            genius</quote> (Thompson, <title level="a">From Forum to
                            Repository</title> 185). As one example, let us return to Burke. In the
                            <title level="a">Invocation,</title> Thelwall calls Burke a
                            <quote>pretended Patriot</quote> (<title level="a">Invocation,</title>
                        line 5) who <quote>Damn’d all the honors with a glossing Tongue</quote>
                            (<title level="a">Invocation,</title> line 17). According to Russell,
                            <quote>Theatricality has long been acknowledged as integral to Burke’s
                            concept of politics as well as to his rhetorical practise</quote> (2);
                        similarly, Scrivener points out that the style of Burke’s <title level="m"
                            >Reflections</title> is <quote>hermeneutically aggressive, figuratively
                            rich with hyperbole and hyperbation, rhetorically <soCalled
                                rend="single">wild</soCalled> and emphatically oratorical</quote>
                            (<title level="m">Allegories</title> 43). For Thelwall then, Burke
                        stands as an example of the debasement of poetic and oratorical language in
                        its use of persuasion for nefarious political purposes. Conversely, Thelwall
                        ridicules Robert Merry for his overly decorous style. Merry, a Della Cruscan
                        poet, was overly emotive and sentimental, and for Thelwall this was an
                        example of poetry being drained of all its didactic power. For this reason,
                        Thelwall parodies Merry, saying that he chases <quote>common sense from off
                            the globe</quote> (see Appendix II). <title level="a"
                            >Typopictoromania,</title> therefore, presents two equally disastrous
                        uses of poetic language: poetry as demagoguery and poetry as mere
                        decoration.</p>
                    <p>At the time of the publication of <title level="m">The Peripatetic</title>,
                        Thelwall’s fame as an orator had grown considerably, and support for Jacobin
                        ideas was still widespread. By the end of the decade, however, the reform
                        movement had been brutally suppressed. Scrivener has argued that while
                            <quote>Repression was surely a muse of sorts for Jacobin allegory…one
                            cannot be too sanguine about it; this repression largely achieved its
                            goals</quote> (<title level="m">Allegories</title> 294). In response to
                        fears that the French revolution might inspire similar violence in England,
                        a series of measures were taken by those in power; in 1792, King George
                        issued a proclamation against seditious writing (to which <title level="a"
                            >Typopictoromania</title> responds), and the Two Acts (also referred to
                        as the Gagging Acts) of 1795 prevented meetings of more than fifty people at
                        a time and reassessed the criteria for what constituted high treason. By
                        1797, when the liberal Whigs withdrew from parliament, there was <quote>a
                            retreat from political activism</quote> that wouldn’t be fully rekindled
                            <quote>until after Waterloo (1815)</quote> (Scrivener, <title level="m"
                            >Poetry and Reform</title> 13). Thelwall experienced this repression
                        first hand. In 1794, he was arrested, along with Tooke, Spence, and others,
                        had <quote>ten years’ worth of writing—including manuscript drafts and fair
                            copies—</quote> seized (Bugg 37), and was locked in the Tower of London
                        to await trial. While he was acquitted nine months later, and consequently
                        saw a boost in popularity after the trial, he was also increasingly
                        threatened at his lectures by loyalist mobs. Fearing for his safety, as well
                        as the safety of his family, he was forced to leave London in 1797 and
                        retire to the country.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>IV. Reflections on the Past</head>
                    <p>Thelwall did not return to London until 1806. At this point having
                        established a career as an itinerant elocutionist and healer of speech
                        impediments, he founded his Institution for the Cure of Impediments of
                        Speech, Instruction of Foreigners, Cultivation of Oratory, English
                        Composition and Polite Literature. As Scrivener describes, <quote>[h]e went
                            from being the most successful Jacobin orator to the most successful
                            scientific lecturer <hi rend="italics">about</hi> oratory</quote>
                        (Scrivener, <title level="m">Allegories</title> 167, emphasis in original).
                        He did make a profit from this establishment, and it was not accessible to
                        the lower class; however, to give Thelwall his due, the institute was
                        devoted to <quote>removing impediments to free speech, enfranchising the
                            disabled, and fostering rational enquiry and open debate among different
                            classes, or at least among marginal and privileged members of the
                            growing middle class, from mutes and autistic children to foreigners,
                            actresses and aspiring barristers</quote> (Thompson, <title level="a"
                            >From Forum to Repository</title>187). Having trained himself to
                        overcome speech impediments, he passed this knowledge along to others. He
                        ran his institution in one form or other until his death in 1834. Although
                        his retirement to the country in 1797 had taken him out of the public sphere
                        and reduced his active involvement in political debates, he returned to
                        politics as the reform movements started to pick up again after the battle
                        of Waterloo in 1815. In 1818, Thelwall purchased a newspaper, <title
                            level="j">The Champion</title>, with which he <quote>attempted once
                            again to intervene in public debate</quote> (<title level="a"
                            >Introduction</title> 19). He continued to push for reform, but
                            <quote>his views had moderated, and he did not regain his earlier
                            popularity</quote> (<title level="a">Introduction</title> 19). It was
                        during this later period that Thelwall began to transform the <title
                            level="u">Derby Manuscript</title>, an unpublished collection of his
                        previous poetry, into a notebook for new work. As a retrospective look at
                        his own earlier career, the <title level="u">Derby Manuscript</title> serves
                        as a poetic reflection; what he chose to include may say much about how the
                        later Thelwall felt about his earlier work. In this way, the <title
                            level="u">Derby</title> version of <title level="a"
                            >Typopictoromania,</title> with its new <title level="a">Preface</title>
                        and handwritten variations, serves as the older Thelwall’s commentary on the
                        work of his younger, more rebellious self.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>V. Note on our Edition</head>
                    <p>Our task has been to present a clear reading text of the hitherto unpublished
                        version of <title level="a">Typopictoromania</title> found in the <title
                            level="u">Derby Manuscript</title> [<title level="u">DM</title>]. At the
                        same time, we have endeavored to present an edition that highlights the
                        major variations between this version and the one found in <title level="m"
                            >The Peripatetic</title> [<title level="m">P</title>]. Thus, while the
                        body of the poem is cohesive, we have included all major variations in
                        editorial notes and comprehensive variations in the XML coding. We have also
                        included additional material in appendices: a screenshot of the <title
                            level="u">DM</title> and contextual material from the frame narrative of
                            <title level="m">P</title>. While this material is not necessary for an
                        appreciation of the poem, some may find it illuminating. Material found in
                        explanatory notes not explicitly cited has been taken from the <title
                            level="m">Oxford Dictionary of National Biography</title> and the <title
                            level="m">Encyclopedia Britannica</title>.</p>
                    <p>At times we have taken editorial liberties to alter the DM, but such changes
                        have been explained and defended in notes. Such changes include: <list
                            rend="bulleted">
                            <item>The retention of punctuation from <title level="m"
                                >P</title>.</item>
                            <item>The retention of word choice from <title level="m"
                                >P</title>.</item>
                            <item>Spelling corrections, either misspelled in <title level="u"
                                    >DM</title> but correct in <hi rend="italics">P</hi>, or
                                misspelled in both.</item>
                        </list> Furthermore, some changes are global and not mentioned in notes: <list>
                            <item>Names of sections, which are entirely absent from <title level="u"
                                    >DM</title>, have been taken from <title level="m"
                                >P</title>.</item>
                            <item>All <hi rend="underline">underlined</hi> words handwritten in
                                manuscript rendered in <hi rend="italics">italics</hi>.</item>
                            <item>Em dash standardizes dashes of various sizes.</item>
                            <item>Capitalized nouns retained, but words rendered in FULL upper case
                                rendered with first letter capitalized only.</item>
                            <item>Ampersands replaced with <q>and.</q></item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <head>Typopictoromania: An Epic Fragment</head>
            <div xml:id="preface">
                <pb type="pdf" n="349"/>
                <head resp="editor">Preface</head>
                <p>
                    <app>
                        <lem wit="DigEd">The object of this Poem (one entire canto of which was
                            written many years ago, but of which only the following fragments which
                            appeared in <title level="m" rend="quote">the peripatetic</title> are
                            preserved) was to ridicule the rage for splendid editions of the Poets
                            etc. The fable a supposed conflict between the Types upon
                                <placeName>Caslon’s Foundry in Chiswell Street</placeName>, and the
                            Pictures in <placeName>Boydell’s Gallery</placeName>. It was designed
                            however as a vehicle for political Satyr.<note>According to the <title
                                    level="m">OED</title>, <q>satyr</q> was a common spelling for
                                    <q>satire</q> up until the early eighteenth century. Like his
                                use of <quote>camelion</quote> in the Proposition, it is likely that
                                Thelwall used this archaic spelling to evoke the writing of earlier
                                poets (see note 10). However, it is strange that he does not use the
                                same spelling in the next two paragraphs. Regardless, we have chosen
                                to retain the original spelling.</note> The following extracts from
                            the Peripatetic might serve as materials for a preface.<note>Thelwall
                                has cut out and pasted the sections <quote>You will not...the
                                    laborious and</quote> and <quote>induced me...magnanimous
                                    hero.</quote> from <title level="m">P</title>. Interestingly,
                                Thelwall chose to hand write the material in between. This is
                                strange because, apart from some seemingly insignificant changes,
                                this material is also present in <title level="m">P</title>; he
                                changes <quote>had long struck my mind</quote> to <quote>had long
                                    impressed my mind,</quote> and <quote>the proposal of the BEST
                                    OF LETTER FOUNDERS to the BEST OF KINGS</quote> becomes
                                    <quote>the proposals of Mr Caslon (letter founder to his
                                    Majesty).</quote></note>
                        </lem>
                        <rdg wit="#Der">The object of this Poem (<subst>
                                <del>two</del>
                                <add place="inline">one</add>
                            </subst> entire canto<del>s</del> of which <subst>
                                <del>were</del>
                                <add place="inline">was</add>
                            </subst> written many years ago, but of which only the following
                            fragments which appeared in <choice>
                                <orig><title level="a">the peripatetic</title></orig>
                                <reg><title level="m">The Peripatetic</title></reg>
                            </choice> are preserved) was to ridicule the rage for splendid editions
                            of the Poets &amp;c. The fable a supposed conflict between the Types
                            from Caslon’s Foundry in Chiswell Street, &amp; the Pictures in
                            Boydell’s Gallery. It was designed however as a vehicle for political
                                <sic>Satyr</sic>. The following extracts from <choice>
                                <orig>the peripatetic</orig>
                                <reg><title level="m">The Peripatetic</title></reg>
                            </choice> might serve as materials for a preface.</rdg>
                    </app>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <app>
                        <lem wit="#DigEd">You will not, I dare say, be very angry at seeing placed
                            in a ridiculous point of view, this rage for splendid editions of works,
                            however excellent in their nature: a rage so prejudicial to the solid
                            interests of literature; and, with respect to the art of Painting
                            itself, rather holding out a kind of commercial temptation to hasty and
                            copious production, than a generous and liberal patronage to the
                            laborious and scientific pursuit of excellence and sublimity. The
                            absurdity of thus reducing the noblest specimens of literary genius to
                            mere expensive pieces of furniture, to please the vacant eye of foppery,
                            had long impressed my mind as a very proper object for satire and
                            ridicule, when the proposals of <persName>Mr Caslon</persName> (letter
                            founder to his Majesty) for adding to the list of popular publications
                            in editions <hi rend="italics">all too splendid to be read,</hi> the
                                <title level="m" rend="quote">Gil Blas</title> and <title
                                level="m" rend="quote">Devil on Two Sticks</title><note>Closing
                                quotation mark retained from <title level="m">P</title>: absent in
                                    <title level="u">DM</title>.</note> of <persName>Le
                                Sage</persName>,<note>Alain-René Lesage (1668-1747) was a French
                                novelist and playwright. <title level="m">Gil Blas</title> and
                                    <title level="m">Devil on Two Sticks</title> are two of his
                                scathingly satirical works. Thelwall’s comment here indicates his
                                displeasure that such books are being printed to be decorative, but
                                not functional.</note> induced me to form the plan of a mock heroic
                            poem, of which the mighty <hi rend="italics">Alphabeta</hi>, the Vulcan
                            of Chiswell-street, and forger of the literary thunderbolts of the
                            terrestrial <name type="mythological">Jove</name>,<note>Jove (Jupiter)
                                is the ancient Roman god of the sky and thunder. He is the king of
                                other gods, making him an appropriate substitution for George
                                III.</note> was to be the magnanimous hero.</lem>
                        <rdg wit="#Der"><span type="print">You will not, I dare say, be very angry
                                at seeing placed in a ridiculous point of view, this rage for
                                splendid editions of works, however excellent in their nature: a
                                rage so prejudicial to the solid interests of literature; and, with
                                respect to the art of Painting itself, rather holding out a kind of
                                commercial temptation to hasty and copious production, than a
                                generous and liberal patronage to the laborious and</span>
                            scientific pursuit of excellence &amp; sublimity. The absurdity of thus
                            reducing the noblest specimens of literary genius to mere expensive
                            pieces of furniture, to please the vacant eye of foppery, had long
                            impressed my mind as a very proper object for satire &amp; ridicule,
                            when the proposals of Mr Caslon (letter founder to his Majesty) for
                            adding to the list of popular publications in editions <hi
                                rend="underline">all too splendid to be read,</hi> the “Gil Blas”
                            and “Devil on Two Sticks of Le Sage induced me to form the plan of a
                            mock heroic poem, of which the mighty <hi rend="italics">Alphabeta</hi>,
                            the Vulcan of Chiswell-street, and forger of the literary thunderbolts
                            of the terrestrial <hi rend="smallcaps">Jove</hi>, was to be the
                            magnanimous hero. <del resp="Thelwall" rend="overstrike">Of the local
                                situation of the</del></rdg>
                        <rdg wit="#Per">You will not, I dare say, be very angry at seeing placed in
                            a ridiculous point of view, this rage for splendid editions of works,
                            however excellent in their nature: a rage so prejudicial to the solid
                            interests of literature; and, with respect to the art of Painting
                            itself, rather holding out a kind of commercial temptation to hasty and
                            copious production, than a generous and liberal patronage to the
                            laborious and scientific pursuit of excellence, and sublimity of
                            composition. The absurdity of thus reducing the noblest specimens of
                            literary genius to mere expensive pieces of furniture, to please the
                            vacant eye of Foppery, had long struck my mind as a very proper object
                            for satire and ridicule, and the proposal of the <hi rend="smallcaps"
                                >Best of Letter Founders</hi> to the <hi rend="smallcaps">Best of
                                Kings</hi>, for adding to the list of <hi rend="italics">popular
                                publications, too splendid to be read</hi>, the <title level="a">Gil
                                Blas</title> and <title level="a">Devil on Two Sticks</title> of Le
                            Sage, induced me to form the plan of a mock heroic poem, of which the
                            mighty <hi rend="italics">Alphabeta</hi>, the Vulcan of Chiswell-Street,
                            and forger of the literary thunderbolts of the terrestrial <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">Jove</hi>, was to be the magnanimous hero.</rdg>
                    </app>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <app>
                        <lem wit="#DigEd">P.S. What I had written was at first very highly commended
                            by <persName>J. Horne Tooke</persName>,<note>John Horne Tooke
                                (1736-1812) was greatly admired by Thelwall. When Tooke ran
                                (unsuccessfully) for the Westminster election in 1780, Thelwall
                                developed a close bond, acting as his assistant. Tooke had many of
                                the same radical revolutionary ideals as Thelwall. In 1794, Tooke
                                was arrested alongside Thelwall and others for sedition, and both
                                spent time in the Tower of London (see Bugg).</note> with whom I had
                            recently become acquainted; but he afterwards discouraged me from
                            proceeding, being very desirous of drawing me to some subject more
                            exclusively political. He proposed a satire on the Coalition of
                                Kings:<note>In 1793, Great Britain joined a coalition of European
                                monarchies in a war against France. Thelwall’s fear that a satirical
                                take on the subject would have put him in danger was likely
                                justified considering the anti-Jacobin sentiment that was rising at
                                the time.</note> but <choice>
                                <orig>tho</orig>
                                <reg>though</reg>
                            </choice> I dropt (unwisely I think) my own project,<note>Thelwall
                                scratches out the word <quote>satire</quote> and corrects it with
                                the word <quote>project.</quote> This correction seems to be have
                                been made immediately upon composition, since <quote>project</quote>
                                follows sequentially as opposed to being written above the crossed
                                out word.</note> I could never see his in that point of view which
                            would furnish materials for a mock heroic poem. Had I then written upon
                            such a subject I should have written with a bitterness which might have
                            been amusing to him; but would have been dangerous to me.</lem>
                        <rdg wit="#Der">P.S. <p>What I had written was at first very highly
                                commended by J. Horne Tooke, with whom I had recently become
                                acquainted; but he afterwards discouraged me from proceeding, being
                                very desirous of drawing me to some subject more exclusively
                                political. He proposed a satire on the Coalition of Kings: but tho I
                                dropt (unwisely I think) my own <unclear cert="medium"><del
                                        rend="overstrike">satire</del></unclear> project, I could
                                never see his in that point of view which would furnish materials
                                for a mock heroic poem. Had I then written upon such a subject I
                                should have written with a bitterness which might have been amusing
                                to him; but would have been dangerous to me.</p>
                        </rdg>
                    </app>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="proposition">
                <pb type="pdf" n="350"/>
                <head resp="editor">Proposition</head>
                <lg>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd"><hi rend="italics">Types and the brush</hi> I sing,
                                whose friendly aid<note>Comma retained from <title level="m"
                                        >P</title>: absent in <title level="u"
                                >DM</title>.</note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der"><hi rend="underline">Types and the brush</hi> I sing
                                whose friendly aid,</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per"><hi rend="smallcaps">Types</hi> and the <hi
                                    rend="smallcaps">Brush</hi> I sing, whose friendly aid</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Calls buried genius forth from learning’s shade—</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Calls buried genius forth from learning’s shade—</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Calls buried Genius forth from Learning’s shade—</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>That shade deserted now by every wight,</l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Save only those who feed on what they write;—</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Save only those who feed on what they write;—</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Save only those who feed on what they write,—</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Camelion like, in attic dome, on high,<note>We have
                                    retained the unusual spelling of <quote>Camelion,</quote> since
                                    Thelwall spells it thus in both the <title level="u">DM</title>
                                    and the <title level="m">P</title>. In doing so, he is probably
                                    following Dryden, whose translation of Ovid’s <title level="a"
                                        >Pythagorean Philosophy</title> the <title level="m"
                                        >OED</title> quotes with this spelling.</note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Camelion like, in attic dome, on high,</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Camelion like, in Attic dome, on high,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">On Couplets feast, and commune with the
                                    Sky!—<note>Exclamation point retained from <title level="m"
                                        >P</title>: replaces semicolon in <title level="u"
                                        rend="italics">DM</title>.</note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">On Couplets feast, and commune with the Sky;—</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">On Couplets feast, and commune with the Sky!—</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd"><hi rend="italics">That Shade</hi> (if books may
                                justify the Creed?)</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der"><hi rend="underline">That Shade</hi> (if Books may
                                justify the Creed?)</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="Per"><hi rend="italics">That Shade</hi> (if Books may justify
                                the Creed?)</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>When Bishops preach’d and mighty Lords could read,</l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Which <hi rend="italics">even Statesmen</hi> deign’d
                                with smiles to view,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der"><add place="above">Which <hi rend="underline">even
                                        Statesmen</hi> deign’d with smiles to view,</add></rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Which <hi rend="italics">even Statesmen</hi> deign’d
                                with Smiles to view,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">To Rectors dear and Reverend prebends too;—</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">To Rectors dear &amp; Reverend prebends too;—</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">To Rectors dear, and reverend Prebends too,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Ere yet (for then no sordid Avarice reign’d)</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Ere yet (for then no sordid Avarice reign’d)</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd"><hi rend="italics">Mitres</hi> they found more slowly
                                were obtained</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per"><hi rend="italics">Mitres</hi> they found more slowly
                                were obtained</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">By <hi rend="italics">gaining Crowns</hi> in Wisdom’s
                                laurel’d List</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">By <hi rend="italics">gaining Crowns</hi> in Wisdom’s
                                laurel’d List</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Than <hi rend="italics">losing Crowns</hi> with
                                gracious <hi rend="italics">Queen’s</hi> at Whist!—<note>The
                                    previous two couplets (from <quote>Ere yet</quote> to
                                        <quote>Whist!</quote>) are absent in <title level="u"
                                        >DM</title> but present in <title level="m"
                                    >P</title>.</note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Than <hi rend="italics">losing Crowns</hi> with gracious
                                    <hi rend="italics">Queen’s</hi> at Whist!—</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd"><hi rend="italics">That Shade</hi> where <hi
                                    rend="italics"><persName>Shakespeare’s</persName></hi> memory
                                might expire,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der"><hi rend="underline">That Shade</hi> where <hi
                                    rend="underline">Shakespeare’s</hi> memory might expire,</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per"><hi rend="italics">That Shade</hi> where <hi
                                    rend="smallcaps">Shakespeare</hi>’s memory might expire,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">And <persName>Milton</persName> String unheard, his
                                Epic Lyre,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">And Milton String unheard, his Epic Lyre,</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">And <hi rend="smallcaps">Milton</hi> string unheard his
                                Epic Lyre,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Did not prim <hi rend="italics">Editors</hi>, with
                                timely aid,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Did not prim <hi rend="underline">Editors</hi>, with
                                timely aid,</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Did not prim <hi rend="italics">Editors</hi>, with
                                timely aid,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Rear the long varnish’d Vista’s quaint parade,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Rear the long varnish’d Vista’s quaint parade,</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Rear the long varnish’d Vista’s quaint parade,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l><app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">With gilding gay, with flaunting picture grac’d,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">With gilding gay, with flaunting picture grac’d,</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">With gilding gay, with flaunting Picture grac’d,</rdg>
                        </app></l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">To lure the Coxcomb eye of modern <hi rend="italics"
                                    >Taste</hi>;<note>According to the <title level="m">OED</title>,
                                    a <q>coxcomb</q> is <quote>a foolish, conceited, showy person,
                                        vain of his accomplishments, appearance, or
                                    dress.</quote></note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">To lure the Coxcomb eye of modern <hi rend="underline"
                                    >Taste</hi>;</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">To lure the coxcomb eye of modern <hi rend="smallcaps"
                                    >Taste</hi>—</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd"><hi rend="italics">That Shade</hi> which now (<hi
                                    rend="italics">as Fashion bids</hi>) shall shine,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der"><hi rend="underline">That Shade</hi> which now (<hi
                                    rend="underline">as Fashion bids</hi>) shall shine,</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per"><hi rend="italics">That Shade</hi> which now (as <hi
                                    rend="smallcaps">Fashion</hi> bids) shall shine</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Throng’d like <placeName>Vauxhall</placeName>—as <hi
                                    rend="italics">courtly</hi>, and as fine!<note>Exclamation point
                                    retained from <title level="m">P</title>; replaces period in
                                        <title level="u">DM</title>.</note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Throng’d like Vauxhall—as <hi rend="underline"
                                    >courtly</hi> &amp; as fine.</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Throng’d like <hi rend="italics">Vauxhall</hi>—as
                                courtly, and as <hi rend="italics">fine!</hi>
                            </rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Yet hence what strife with dire contagion
                                spread!—</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Yet hence what strife with dire contagion spread!—</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">While printer’s ink and paint of artists
                                    shed,<note>Spelling of <quote>printer’s</quote> corrected from
                                        <quote>printers.</quote> Correct spelling found in <title
                                        level="m">P</title>: see note 17.</note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">While <sic>printers</sic> ink &amp; paint of artists
                                shed,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Heap’d <placeName>Chiswell Street</placeName> and
                                fam’d <placeName>Pall-Mall</placeName> with slain;<note>Spelling of
                                        <quote>Pall-Mall</quote> corrected from
                                        <quote>Pal-Mal.</quote> Correct spelling in <title level="m"
                                        >P</title>: see note 17.</note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Heap’d Chiswell Street &amp; fam’d <sic>Pal-Mal</sic>
                                with slain;</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Till <name type="mythological">Jove’s</name> own
                                thunder clear’d the embattled plain.<note>These final four lines do
                                    not appear in <title level="m">P</title> at this point. The
                                    middle two appear in one of Sylvanus’s explanatory interjections
                                    (as <quote>Printer’s ink, and paint of artist’s shed, heap’d
                                        Chiswell-street and fam’d Pall Mall with slain,
                                        &amp;c.</quote> [see Appendix II]), but the other two lines
                                    do not show up at all. These four lines also seem crammed into
                                    the bottom of the page, are darker in colour, and appear over
                                    smudges from an earlier erased passage. Thus, it is likely he
                                    added them later.</note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Till Jove’s own thunder clear’d the embattled
                                plain.</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                </lg>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="invocation">
                <pb type="pdf" n="352"/>
                <head resp="editor">Invocation</head>
                <lg>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Genius of <placeName type="country"
                                    >Britain</placeName>!—not that power who strung</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Genius of Britain!—not that power who strung</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per"><hi rend="smallcaps">Genius of Britain</hi>!—Not that
                                power who strung</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">A <hi><persName>Hampden’s</persName></hi> arm, and
                                urg’d his patriot tongue—</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">A <hi rend="underline">Hampden’s</hi> arm, and urg’d his
                                patriot tongue—</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">A <hi rend="smallcaps">Hampden’s</hi> arm, and urg’d his
                                patriot’s tongue—</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Not she who warm’d a <persName><hi rend="italics"
                                        >Sydney’s</hi></persName>, <persName><hi rend="italics"
                                        >Russell’s</hi></persName> soul,<note>John Hampden
                                    (1653-1696) was so admired by Thelwall that he named his second
                                    son after him. An anti-monarchist who wanted to reinstate a
                                    republic, Hampden was arrested for allegedly taking part in the
                                    Rye-house plot, but later acquitted. Algernon Sydney (1623–1683)
                                    and William, Lord Russell (1639-1683), both anti-monarchists
                                    arrested with Hampden for the Rye-house plot, were unlike him,
                                    executed. Thelwall named his eldest son after Sydney (Algernon
                                    Sydney Thelwall). That the poet does not invoke the
                                        <quote>Genius</quote> that inspired these three men, all of
                                    whom Thelwall greatly admired for their political views, makes
                                    clear the satirical nature of what is to come; the Genius of
                                        <quote>Modern Britain,</quote> as it is named in the
                                    prefatory material of <title level="m">P</title> (see Appendix
                                    II), pales in comparison to that of the past. <p>Comma after
                                            <quote>Sydney’s</quote> retained from <title level="m"
                                            >P</title>: absent in <title level="u" rend="italics"
                                            >DM</title>.</p></note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Not she <subst>
                                    <del>that</del>
                                    <add place="inline">who</add>
                                </subst> warm’d a <hi rend="underline">Sydney’s Russell’s</hi>
                                Soul,</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Not she that warmed a <hi rend="smallcaps"
                                >Sydney’s</hi>, <hi rend="smallcaps">Russel’s</hi> soul,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Corruption’s tyrant progress to control—</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Corruption’s tyrant progress to controul—</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Corruption’s tyrant progress to control—</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Ere yet <hi rend="italics">pretended Patriots</hi>,
                                bought and sold,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Ere yet <hi rend="underlined">pretended Patriots</hi>,
                                bought and sold,</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Ere yet <hi rend="italics">pretended Patriots</hi>,
                                bought and sold,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Made public barter of their votes for gold;—</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Made public barter of their votes for gold;—</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Made <hi rend="italics">public</hi> barter of their
                                Votes, for Gold;—</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Ere <hi rend="italics">Freedom’s Representatives</hi>,
                                by <hi rend="italics">name</hi>,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Ere <hi rend="underline">Freedom’s Representatives</hi>,
                                by <hi rend="underline">name</hi>
                            </rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Ere <hi rend="italics">Freedom’s representatives</hi>,
                                by <hi rend="italics">name</hi>
                            </rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Lauded despotic power, unaw’d by shame;</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Lauded despotic power, unaw’d by shame;</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Lauded Despotic Power, unaw’d by shame;</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">In public Senates (fir’d with frantic rage,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">In public Senates fir’d with frantic rage,</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">In public Senates (fired with frantic rage,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Which not the tears of friendship could
                                    assuage)<note>As with the couplet at line 15, the parentheses,
                                    despite being absent in <title level="u">DM</title>, are
                                    retained from <title level="m">P</title> for this couplet. We
                                    have chosen to retain the punctuation of <title level="m"
                                        >P</title> because there is a formal echoing that is lost
                                    without the parentheses; the mirroring of the
                                        <quote>Senates</quote> and the <quote>driveling
                                        dotards</quote> is less obvious without the
                                    parentheses.</note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Which not the tears of friendship could assuage;</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Which not the tears of Friendship could assuage)</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Blacken’d each name that, true to Freedom’s
                                cause,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Blacken’d each name that true to Freedom’s cause</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Blacken’d each Name that, true to Freedom’s cause,
                            </rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Dar’d plead for <hi rend="italics">Nature’s violated
                                    Laws</hi>;—</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Dar’d plead for <hi rend="underline">nature’s violated
                                    Laws;</hi>—</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Dar’d plead for <hi rend="italics">Nature’s violated
                                    Laws</hi>;—</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Ere yet, grown grey in party’s <hi rend="italics"
                                    >sordid train</hi></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Ere yet grown grey in party’s <hi rend="underline"
                                    >sordid train</hi></rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Ere yet, grown grey in <hi rend="italics">Party’s sordid
                                    train</hi>,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">(Where who like them the clamorous throat to
                                strain?)</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">(Where who like them the clamourous throat to
                                strain?)</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">(Where who like them the clamorous throat to
                                strain?)</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Wild driveling dotards (fir’d with sacred hate</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der"><add place="above">Wild driveling dotards, fir’d with
                                    sacred hate</add></rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Wild, driv’ling Dotards (fired with sacred hate</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Of all who held what they upheld of late)<note>In
                                    addition to the retention of parentheses (see note 19), commas
                                    have been removed from after <quote>dotards</quote> (present
                                    only in <title level="u">DM</title>) and <quote>late</quote>
                                    (present in both editions) to maintain the formal echo.</note>
                            </lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der"><add place="above">Of all who held what they upheld of
                                    late,</add></rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Of all who held what they upheld of late,)</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Damn’d all the honors which a glossing
                                    Tongue,<note>Thelwall spells <quote>honors</quote> in the <title
                                        level="u">DM</title> with the American spelling without the
                                        <q>u,</q> but in the <title level="m">P</title> the British
                                    spelling is used.</note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Damn’d all the honors <subst>
                                    <add place="orig">with</add>
                                    <add place="inspace">which</add>
                                </subst> a glossing Tongue,</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Damn’d all the Honours with a glossing Tongue,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>Practis’d in fraud, and with persuasion hung,</l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Still with the rotten heart at prudent strife,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Still with the rotten heart at prudent strife,</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Still with the rotten Heart at prudent strife,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Had purchas’d with the <hi rend="italics">lie of a
                                    whole life</hi>;</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Had purchas’d with the <hi rend="underline">lie of a
                                    whole life;</hi></rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Had purchas’d with <hi rend="underline">the Lie of a
                                    whole life;</hi></rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Renounc’d all principle, and bared the heart,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Renounc’d all principle, and bared the heart,</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per"><hi rend="italics">Renounc’d</hi> all Principle, and
                                bared the Heart,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">So long conceal’d from view with painful art:</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">So long conceal’d from view with painful art:</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">So long conceal’d from view with painful Art;</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Threw off the mask, so long with credit worn,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Threw off the mask, so long with credit worn,</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Threw off the Mask, so long with credit worn,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">And chang’d respect for pity and for scorn;</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">And chang’d respect for pity and for scorn;</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">And chang’d respect for Pity, and for Scorn;</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">To Bathos div’d for culinary wit,<note>Spelling of
                                        <quote>culinary</quote> corrected from
                                        <quote>cullinary</quote>: spelled correctly in <title
                                        level="m">P</title></note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">To Bathos div’d for <sic>cullinary</sic> wit,</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">To Bathos dived for culinary wit,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Made e’en the Stews and
                                    <placeName>Billingsgate</placeName> submit<note>London’s primary
                                    fish market located at the docks. The British Library notes that
                                    it was <quote>noted for the coarse language used by the women
                                        who worked there and their propensity for gossip.</quote>
                                    This explains the poet’s later description of the women’s voices
                                    containing the <quote>Classic graces of the vulgar
                                        tongue</quote> (line 18 of Canto Two).</note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Made e’en the Stews and Billinsgate submit</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Made e’en the Stews and Billingsgate submit</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <pb type="pdf" n="354"/>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">With sheer scurrility, and blushing own<note> Spelling
                                    of <quote>scurrility</quote> corrected from
                                        <quote>scurility</quote>: spelled correctly in <title
                                        level="m">P</title>.</note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">With sheer scurility, and blushing own</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">With sheer scurrility, and blushing own</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>Their claim to mount the Shrew’s contested Throne;</l>
                    <l>Thence soaring high, or thinking that they soar’d,</l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">The Realms of <q>Beauteous and Sublime</q>
                                    explor’d,—<note>A reference to Edmund Burke (1729-1797) and his
                                        <title level="m">A Philosophical Enquiry into the Origin and
                                        of Our Ideas of the Sublime and the Beautiful</title>
                                    (1757). Much of this stanza refers to Burke: see <title
                                        level="a">Introduction.</title></note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">The Realms of <q>Beauteous &amp; Sublime</q>
                                explor’d,—</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">The realms of <q>Beauteous and Sublime</q>
                                explor’d,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Pluck’d down the Stars, and thought those stars too
                                poor</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Pluck’d down the Stars, &amp; thought those stars too
                                poor</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Pluck’d down the <hi rend="italics">Stars</hi>, and
                                thought those stars too poor</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">(Moon-struck themselves!) to deck a Royal
                                        Whore,<note><quote>Moon-struck</quote> retained from <title
                                        level="m">P</title>. While the word is certainly not
                                        <quote>struck</quote> in the <title level="u">DM</title>,
                                    since there are many more than five letters and the final three
                                    are definitely <q>ch’d,</q> we are unable to decipher with
                                    absolute certainty what word it is. We believe it might be
                                        <quote>stretch’d,</quote> but we are unable to find any
                                    explanation of what <quote>moon stretch’d</quote> might mean.
                                    Thus, we have retained the line from <title level="m">P</title>
                                    for certainty’s sake.</note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">(Moon <unclear cert="high">stretch’d</unclear>
                                themselves!) to deck a Royal Whore,</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">(Moon-struck themselves!) to deck a Royal Whore,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>Because she chanc’d the Gallic Throne to share,</l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">For which (<hi rend="italics">to
                                        <placeName>Dorset</placeName> thanks!</hi>) she brought an
                                    Heir.<note>In <title level="m">P</title>, this line reads,
                                        <quote>To which (<hi rend="italics">to Dorset thanks!</hi>)
                                        she brought an Heir.</quote> Exclamation mark retained from
                                        <title level="m">P</title>: absent in <title level="u"
                                        >DM</title>.</note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">For which (<hi rend="underline">to Dorset thanks</hi>)
                                she brought an Heir.</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">To which (<hi rend="italics">to Dorset thanks!</hi>) she
                                brought an Heir.</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">—But why with plurals thus mankind disgrace?</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">—But why with plurals thus mankind disgrace?</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">—But why with plurals thus Mankind disgrace?</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">When even these times produce but one so
                                    base.<note>Period retained from <title level="m">P</title>;
                                    absent in <title level="u">DM</title>.</note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">When even these times produce but one so base</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">When even these times produce but one so base.</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l rend="indent">
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd"><hi rend="italics">Genius of Britain</hi> prompt my
                                Epic Theme—</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der"><hi rend="underline">Genius of Britain</hi> prompt my
                                Epic Theme—</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per"><hi rend="smallcaps">Genius</hi>
                                <hi rend="italics">of</hi>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Britain</hi>! prompt my Epic theme—</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Not thou who nurs’d by <name type="mythological"
                                    >Heliconia’s</name> stream<note>In <title level="m">P</title>,
                                    the line reads, <quote>Not thou who, nurs’d by Heliconia’s
                                        stream,</quote> (in reference to Mt. Helicon, home of the
                                    muses in Greek mythology); it is possible Thelwall removed the
                                    commas for rhythmic purposes, to ensure no punctuation broke the
                                    flow of the line.</note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Not thou who nurs’d by Heliconia’s stream</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Not thou who, nurs’d by Heliconia’s stream,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Taught one illustrious British Prince to feel</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Taught one illustrious British Prince to feel</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Taught <hi rend="smallcaps">One Illustrious British
                                    Prince</hi> to feel</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l><app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">A noble love for Learning’s sacred weal,—</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">A noble love for Learning’s sacred weal,—</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">A noble love for learning’s sacred weal,—</rdg>
                        </app></l>
                    <l>To Sage and Bard that patronage supply</l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Which pimps and black-legs now alone
                                    enjoy,—<note>Thelwall went through many possible variations
                                    before settling on <quote>black-legs.</quote> In <title
                                        level="m">P</title>, the line says <quote>pimps and
                                        fiddlers,</quote> but <quote>fiddlers</quote> is nowhere to
                                    be found in the <title level="u">DM</title>. Instead,
                                        <quote>pathics,</quote>
                                    <quote>gamblers,</quote> and <quote>panders</quote> are all
                                    written in as possible words, but are crossed out. According to
                                    the <title level="m">1811 Dictionary of the Vulgar
                                        Tongue</title>, <q>black-legs</q> is a term for <quote>a
                                        gambler or sharper on the turf or in the cockpit: so called,
                                        perhaps, from their appearing generally in boots; or else
                                        from game-cocks whose legs are always black.</quote>
                                    According to the <title level="m">OED</title>, a <q>pander</q>
                                    is a pimp, a <q>fiddler</q> is a swindler or a cheat, and a
                                        <q>pathic</q> is <quote>the passive partner in homosexual …
                                        intercourse.</quote> One can only wonder why Thelwall spent
                                    so long trying to find just the right term here.</note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Which pimps &amp; <subst>
                                    <del rend="overstrike">pathics</del>
                                    <add place="above"><del rend="overstrike">panders</del></add>
                                    <add place="above"><del rend="overstrike">gamblers</del></add>
                                    <add place="below">black-legs</add>
                                </subst> now alone enjoy,—</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Which pimps and fiddlers now alone enjoy,—</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">And having freed the Land from <hi rend="italics"
                                    >foreign foes</hi><note>In <title level="m">P</title>, the line
                                    reads, <quote>And, having freed the Land from foreign
                                        Foes,</quote>: see note 31.</note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">And having freed the Land from <hi rend="underline"
                                    >foreign foes</hi></rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">And, having freed the land from <hi rend="italics"
                                    >foreign Foes</hi>,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>Rous’d him to purge it from the darker woes</l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Of savage ignorance; and Science rear</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Of savage ignorance; and Science rear</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Of <hi rend="italics">savage Ignorance</hi>, and Science
                                rear,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">At once by his Example and his care;—</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">At once by his Example and his care;—</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">At once by his Example, and his Care—</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Not thou who urg’d the godlike
                                    <persName>Alfred’s</persName> soul</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Not thou who urg’d the godlike Alfred’s soul</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Not thou who urg’d the Godlike <hi rend="italics"
                                    >Alfred’s</hi> soul,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">(<hi rend="italics">Virtue his race, immortal fame his
                                    Goal!</hi>)<note>Spelling of <quote>immortal</quote> corrected
                                    from <quote>imortal</quote>: spelled correctly in <title
                                        level="m">P</title>. In addition, comma retained from <title
                                        level="m">P</title>; absent in <title level="u"
                                    >DM</title>.</note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">(<hi rend="underline">Virtue his race imortal fame his
                                    Goal!</hi>)</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">(<hi rend="italics">Virtue</hi> his <hi rend="italics"
                                    >Race, Immortal Fame</hi> his <hi rend="italics"
                                >Goal!</hi>)</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <pb type="pdf" n="356"/>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">With reverend Sages to devote his
                                        prime;—<note><quote>Prime</quote> retained from <title
                                        level="m">P</title>. It is unclear whether the word is
                                        <q>prime</q> or <q>time</q> in the <title level="u"
                                        >DM</title>; it looks like it reads <q>time,</q> but it
                                    could just as easily be a hastily scribbled <q>prime.</q> For
                                    certainty’s sake we retain <q>prime,</q> but one may wish to
                                    read it as <q>time.</q></note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">With reverend Sages to devote his <unclear cert="medium"
                                    >time</unclear>;—</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">With reverend Sages to devote his prime,—</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Ere Dicers Boxers Swindlers curs’d the clime;</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Ere Dicers Boxers Swindlers curs’d the clime;</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Ere <hi rend="italics">Caterers, Boxers, Swindlers</hi>,
                                curs’d the Clime—</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Ere yet the Turf alone had charms; ere yet</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Ere yet the Turf alone had charms; ere yet</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Ere yet the <hi rend="italics">Turf</hi> alone had
                                charms—Ere yet</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Rooking was Science, Jockeying was wit;</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Rooking was Science, Jockeying was wit;</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per"><hi rend="smallcaps">Rooking</hi> was <hi rend="italics"
                                    >Science</hi>, <hi rend="smallcaps">Jockeying</hi> was <hi
                                    rend="italics">Wit</hi>—</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">For <hi rend="italics">Studs ere Splendid Palaces
                                    arose</hi>,—</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">For <hi rend="underline">studs ere splendid Palaces
                                    arose</hi>,—</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">For <hi rend="italics">Studs</hi> ere <hi rend="italics"
                                    >Splendid Palaces</hi> arose,—</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Where <hi rend="italics">Steeds and Grooms</hi> in
                                idle rank repose,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Where <hi rend="underline">Steeds and Grooms</hi> in
                                idle rank repose,</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Where <hi rend="italics">Steeds</hi> and <hi
                                    rend="italics">Grooms</hi>, in idle ranks, repose,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Consuming more than <placeName>Gallia</placeName>’s
                                haughty Lord,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Consuming more than Gallia’s haughty Lord,</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Consuming <hi rend="italics">more</hi> than Gallia’s
                                haughty Lord,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Her fourteenth <persName>Louis</persName>, spent to
                                deck that board<note>Louis XIV (1643-1715), King of
                                France.</note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Her fourteenth Louis, spent to deck that board</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Her <hi rend="smallcaps">Fourteenth Louis</hi>, spent to
                                deck that board</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Where <hi rend="italics">Taste</hi> and <hi
                                    rend="italics">Science</hi> found a sure retreat,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Where <hi rend="underline">taste</hi> and <hi
                                    rend="italics">science</hi> found a sure retreat,</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Where <hi rend="italics">Taste</hi> and <hi
                                    rend="italics">Science</hi> found a sure retreat,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">And <hi rend="italics">all the Wits of
                                        <placeName>Europe</placeName> had a Seat!</hi>—</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">And <hi rend="underline">all the wits of Europe had a
                                    Seat!</hi>—</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">And <hi rend="italics">all the Wits of Europe had a
                                    Seat!</hi>—</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Not thou who taught <hi rend="italics"
                                    >mellifluous</hi>
                                <persName>Pope</persName> to sing</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Not thou who taught <hi rend="underline"
                                    >mellifluous</hi> Pope to sing</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">—Not thou who taught <hi rend="italics">mellifluous</hi>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Pope</hi> to sing,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Plum’d <persName>Shakespeare</persName>’s,
                                    <persName>Milton</persName>’s, <persName>Dryden</persName>’s
                                daring wing;</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Plum’d Shakespeare’s, Milton’s, Dryden’s daring
                                wing;</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Plum’d <hi rend="smallcaps">Shakespeare’s, Milton’s,
                                    Dryden’s</hi> daring wing,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Ere whining <persName>Pratt</persName>, the pink of
                                common place,<note>Samuel Jackson Pratt (1749-1814) was a poet whose
                                    sentimental literary persona rarely carried over into his
                                    personal life. Thelwall often criticized him. In <title
                                        level="m">P</title>, <q>Pratt</q> is spelled with only one
                                        <q>T</q>. According to the <title level="m">OED</title>, the
                                    word <q>prat</q> meant, in the late eighteenth century, <quote>A
                                        trick; a piece of trickery or fraud; a prank or practical
                                        joke,</quote> and it was also slang for <quote>the
                                        buttocks.</quote> Judith Thompson believes that by spelling
                                    it with one <q>T</q> Thelwall was making a deliberate joke at
                                    Pratt’s expense. Whether or not his choice to include the second
                                        <q>T</q> in the <title level="u">DM</title>, long after
                                    Pratt’s death, shows a change of heart on Thelwall’s part is up
                                    to the reader to decide.</note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Ere whining Pratt, the pink of common place,</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Ere whining <hi rend="smallcaps">Prat</hi>, the Pink of
                                Common Place,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Pour’d forth long nothings with so soft a grace,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Pour’d forth long nothings with so soft a grace,</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Pour’d forth long nothings with so <hi rend="italics"
                                    >soft</hi> a grace,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <pb type="pdf" n="358"/>
                    <l>Made Sentiment so languishingly creep<note>From <quote>Made Sentiment</quote>
                            (line 63 of <title level="a">Invocation</title>) until <quote>as well as
                                they</quote> (line 174 of <title level="a">Invocation</title>),
                            Thelwall has pasted in pages from the <title level="m">P</title>. Thus,
                            only minor changes are made by Thelwall. Since Thelwall clearly had
                            access to a copy of the <title level="m">P</title> from which he could
                            take pages, it is strange that he chose to handwrite some sections of
                            the poem without making major changes to them: the first twenty lines of
                            the <title level="a">Invocation,</title> for instance. One imagines he
                            could have cut and pasted the whole poem into the <title level="u"
                                >DM</title> and then made his minor changes in the margins (as he
                            does at line 130 of the <title level="a">Invocation</title>). One can
                            only speculate as to the reasons for this decision. Editorial note:
                            Words in full caps have been edited so as to only have first letter
                            capitalized, and any other major changes marked with notes.</note></l>
                    <l>To the charm’d Heart, as charm’d it quite to Sleep;</l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Made Sympathy thro’ two long Cantoes shine,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Made <hi rend="smallcaps">Sympathy</hi> thro’ two long
                                Cantoes shine,</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Made <hi rend="smallcaps">Sympathy</hi> thro’ two long
                                Cantoes shine,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>Without assistance from one feeling line,</l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">And fair Humanity—<hi rend="italics">so soft</hi>—<hi
                                    rend="italics">so sweet</hi>—</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">And <hi rend="italics">fair</hi>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Humanity</hi>—<hi rend="italics">so
                                    soft</hi>—<hi rend="italics">so sweet</hi>—</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">And <hi rend="italics">fair</hi>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Humanity</hi>—<hi rend="italics">so
                                    soft</hi>—<hi rend="italics">so sweet</hi>—</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l><app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Drawl thro’ dull pages to the hundredth sheet;</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Drawl thro’ dull pages to the hundredth sheet;</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Drawl thro dull pages to the hundredth sheet;</rdg>
                        </app></l>
                    <l><app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Drew <hi rend="italics">meek</hi> Morality with such a
                                Grace,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Drew <hi rend="italics">meek</hi>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Morality</hi> with such a Grace,</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Drew <hi rend="italics">meek</hi>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Morality</hi> with such a Grace,</rdg>
                        </app></l>
                    <l>With such a <hi rend="italics">simpering</hi>, <hi rend="italics"
                            >lack-a-daisey</hi> Face,</l>
                    <l>Such <hi rend="italics">water-gruel</hi> Sweetness, one would swear</l>
                    <l>She <quote>suckled Fools, and chronicled small beer.</quote></l>
                    <l><app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">—Ere yet quaint Fopperies from the <hi rend="italics"
                                    >Italian School</hi><note>The poetry of the Italian School was
                                        <quote>characterised in terms of its theatrical displays of
                                        emotion, overt sensuality, heavily stylised language and
                                        complex sound structure</quote> (Broadhead
                                577).</note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">—Ere yet quaint Fopperies from the <hi rend="italics"
                                    >Italian School</hi></rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">—Ere yet quaint Fopperies from the Italian School</rdg>
                        </app></l>
                    <l>Threw in forc’d Extasies each Rhyming Fool;<note>According to the <title
                                level="m">OED</title>, <q>extasy</q> was an acceptable spelling well
                            into the eighteenth century. Thus, we have retained the
                        spelling.</note></l>
                    <l>Bit, like the Gad Fly, <hi rend="italics">Widows, Wives</hi>, and <hi
                            rend="italics">Maids</hi>,</l>
                    <l>With frantic <hi rend="italics">bleat</hi> to scare the tuneful Shades,</l>
                    <l>Where <hi rend="italics">self-thought</hi> Poets, deeper bit than they,</l>
                    <l><app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">To their wild <hi rend="italics">bleat</hi>, return’d
                                as wild a <hi rend="italics">bray!</hi>—</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">To their wild <hi rend="italics">bleat</hi>, return’d as
                                wild a <hi rend="italics">bray!</hi>—</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">To their wild <hi rend="italics">bleat</hi> return’d as
                                wild a <hi rend="italics">bray</hi>!—</rdg>
                        </app></l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Ere <persName type="pseudonym">Della
                                Crusca</persName>, darling of the World!<note>Used first as a
                                    pseudonym by Robert Merry, who was involved with a romantic
                                    relationship with Hannah Cowley, the term Della Crusca was used,
                                    after 1795, to label all of the poets following the Italian
                                    school. For more see Alex Broadhead’s <title level="a">The Della
                                        Cruscans: A Survey of the Criticisms and Resources.</title>
                                    In <title level="u">DM</title>, Thelwall has written in an
                                    additional <q>L</q> to turn the <quote>DE LA</quote> of the
                                        <title level="m">P</title> to
                                <quote>DELLA.</quote></note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Ere DELLA CRUSCA, darling of the WORLD!</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Ere <hi rend="smallcaps">de la Crusca</hi>, darling of
                                the <hi rend="smallcaps">World</hi>!</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>The random Gaze of Moon-struck-madness hurl’d</l>
                    <l>Thro’ the wild <quote>Wilderness of blooming Suns,</quote><note>From Robert
                            Merry’s <title level="a">Ode to Anna Matilda.</title></note></l>
                    <l>And Scenes which Common Sense indignant shuns;</l>
                    <l>Where <hi rend="italics">Popularity</hi>, (debauch’d, and led</l>
                    <l>By that old Bawd, hight <hi rend="italics">Puffing</hi>, to his Bed,)</l>
                    <l>Brought forth a Swarm of <hi rend="italics">misshaped Monsters</hi>, more</l>
                    <l>Than ever spawn’d on <placeName type="mythological">Nilus</placeName>’ antic
                        Shore;—</l>
                    <l>Monsters, to nurture which, in happy Hour,</l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd"><hi rend="italics">Dame</hi>
                                <persName>Cowley</persName> waken’d in the Muses Bow’r—</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der"><hi rend="italics">Dame</hi> COWLEY waken’d in the Muses
                                Bow’r—</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per"><hi rend="italics">Dame</hi>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Cowley</hi> waken’d in the Muses Bow’r—</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>That <hi rend="italics">Bow’r</hi> in which, strew’d by her Angel Hand</l>
                    <l>With Poppies cull’d in <name type="mythological">Morpheus</name> happy
                        Land—</l>
                    <l><name type="mythological">Morpheus</name>! inspiring God of modern
                            Themes!<note>Morpheus is the ancient Greek god of dreams.</note></l>
                    <l>The Patron blest of Poesy and Dreams!—</l>
                    <l>That Bow’r, in which the balmy-soothing Pow’r</l>
                    <l>With <hi rend="italics">partial fondness</hi>, oft, at Evening Hour,</l>
                    <l>(<q>Attention pillowing her reclining Head</q>)</l>
                    <l>The sweetest Slumbers o’er her Senses spread;</l>
                    <pb type="pdf" n="360"/>
                    <l>While crowded Theatres, by Fate’s decree,</l>
                    <l>First clapp’d, then yawn’d, then snor’d as loud as she.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Genius <hi rend="italics">of</hi>
                                <placeName>Britain</placeName>!—by what Title grac’d—</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">GENIUS <hi rend="italics">of</hi> BRITAIN!—by what Title
                                grac’d—</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per"><hi rend="smallcaps">Genius</hi>
                                <hi rend="italics">of</hi>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Britain</hi>!—by what Title grac’d—</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Fashion or Folly, Vanity or Taste—</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der"><hi rend="smallcaps">Fashion</hi> or <hi
                                    rend="smallcaps">Folly, Vanity</hi> or <hi rend="smallcaps"
                                    >Taste</hi>—</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per"><hi rend="smallcaps">Fashion</hi> or <hi
                                    rend="smallcaps">Folly, Vanity</hi> or <hi rend="smallcaps"
                                    >Taste</hi>—</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>Thou, whose high Laws, rever’d by Courtly Dames!</l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd"><persName>Cecil’s</persName>
                                <hi rend="italics">hereditary Wisdom</hi> frames.—<note>William
                                    Cecil, Lord Burghley (1520-98) was an advisor to Elizabeth I,
                                    and his descendent, Brownlow Cecil, the ninth Earl of Exeter
                                    (1725-93), advised King George III. According to Judith
                                    Thompson, the references to fashion can be interpreted as a
                                    statement by Thelwall that the <quote>hereditary wisdom</quote>
                                    once available in the counsel offered by the Cecil family has
                                    degraded.</note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der"><hi rend="smallcaps">Cecil</hi>’s <hi rend="italics"
                                    >hereditary Wisdom</hi> frames.—</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per"><hi rend="smallcaps">Cecil</hi>’s <hi rend="italics"
                                    >hereditary Wisdom</hi> frames.—</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>Important Guardian of a Royal Court!</l>
                    <l><app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Imperial Grandeur’s <hi rend="italics">wisest;
                                    best</hi> support!</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Imperial Grandeur’s <hi rend="italics">wisest; best</hi>
                                support!</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Imperial Grandeur’s <hi rend="italics">wisest,
                                best</hi>, support!</rdg>
                        </app></l>
                    <l>Whose awful Nod prescribes the <hi rend="italics">Mantua’s grace</hi>,</l>
                    <l>And dooms, without appeal, in <hi rend="italics">Gloves</hi> and <hi
                            rend="italics">Lace</hi>,</l>
                    <l>When, Wand in Hand, on Birth-Days, he presides,</l>
                    <l><app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">And with the Best of Kings, the sway divides!—</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">And with the BEST OF KINGS, the sway divides!—</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">And with the <hi rend="smallcaps">Best of Kings</hi> the
                                sway divides!—</rdg>
                        </app></l>
                    <l><app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">—That Best of Kings, from whom what blessings
                                flow!</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">—That BEST OF KINGS, from whom what blessings
                                flow!</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">—That <hi rend="smallcaps">Best of Kings</hi>, from whom
                                what blessings flow!</rdg>
                        </app></l>
                    <l>Who for his People keeps a Raree-Show</l>
                    <l>Of Pictures fine, a Month each Year, or more:</l>
                    <l>But makes them <hi rend="italics">drop their Shillings at the Door!</hi>—</l>
                    <l><app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">That Best of Kings, who gives his Royal <hi
                                    rend="italics">Name</hi></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">That BEST OF KINGS, who gives his Royal <hi
                                    rend="italics">Name</hi></rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">That <hi rend="smallcaps">Best of kings</hi>, who gives
                                his Royal <hi rend="italics">Name</hi></rdg>
                        </app></l>
                    <l>To every Work of Charity, or Fame;</l>
                    <l>But, <hi rend="italics">liberal</hi> as he is, with <hi rend="italics"
                            >Prudence</hi> blest,</l>
                    <l>Keeps the Subscription Guinea in his Chest.—</l>
                    <l><app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">That Best of Kings, who, <hi rend="italics">Umpire of
                                    the Arts!</hi></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">That BEST OF KINGS, who, <hi rend="italics">Umpire of
                                    the Arts!</hi></rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">That <hi rend="smallcaps">Best of Kings</hi>, who, <hi
                                    rend="italics">Umpire of the Arts!</hi></rdg>
                        </app></l>
                    <l><app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">To <persName>West</persName>’s coarse outline his
                                first Smile imparts:—</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">To <hi rend="smallcaps">West</hi>’s coarse outline his
                                first Smile imparts:—</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">To <hi rend="smallcaps">West’s</hi> coarse outline his
                                first Smile imparts;—</rdg>
                        </app></l>
                    <l><app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd"><persName>West</persName>, from whose hand each Male
                                Complexion shines</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der"><hi rend="smallcaps">West</hi>, from whose hand each
                                Male Complexion shines</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per"><hi rend="smallcaps">West</hi>, from whose hand each
                                Male Complexion shines</rdg>
                        </app></l>
                    <l>Like half-wrought Copper from our Cornish Mines;</l>
                    <l>While, smooth as wax, each female Cheek is spread,</l>
                    <l>And every Lip, with the same lifeless red!—</l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd"><persName>West</persName>, whose long Groups, in
                                order’d Rows display’d,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der"><hi rend="smallcaps">West</hi>, whose long Groups, in
                                order’d Rows display’d,</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per"><hi rend="smallcaps">West</hi>, whose long Groups, in
                                order’d Rows display’d,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l><app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">(As ranks of Soldiers strut on the parade,)</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">(As ranks of Soldiers strut on the parade,)</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">(As ranks of soldiers strut on the parade,)</rdg>
                        </app></l>
                    <l>At <hi rend="italics">Knightly Installations</hi>, make us stare,</l>
                    <l><app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">And ask <hi rend="italics">What Corporal drill’d the
                                    noble Fair</hi>!—</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">And ask <hi rend="italics">What Corporal drill’d the
                                    noble Fair</hi>!—</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">And ask <hi rend="italics">What Corporal drill’d the
                                    noble Fair!</hi>—</rdg>
                        </app></l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">West, who, not only taught to husband <hi
                                    rend="italics">Time</hi>,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der"><hi rend="smallcaps">West</hi>, who, not only taught to
                                husband <hi rend="italics">Time</hi>,</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per"><hi rend="smallcaps">West</hi>, who, not only taught to
                                husband <hi rend="italics">Time</hi>,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>Maintains the loss of <hi rend="italics">Space</hi> an equal Crime,</l>
                    <l>So fills—despite of ease and simple grace—</l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Each <hi rend="italics">Inch of Canvas</hi> with a
                                varnish’d <hi rend="italics">Face</hi>,<note>Benjamin West
                                    (1738-1820) was an American painter. His art is here satirized
                                    as being flat, with the bodies of people clustered, as he
                                    attempts to cover each inch of canvas. In <title level="m"
                                        >P</title>, this line read <quote>So fills each <hi
                                            rend="italics">Scrap Of Canvas</hi> with a <hi
                                            rend="italics">Face</hi>,</quote>. Since this is a line
                                    on a pasted page in the <title level="u">DM</title>, Thelwall’s
                                    changes are scribbled in on top of the printed page.
                                        <quote>Inch</quote> is not capitalized or underlined (for
                                    italicization) in <title level="u">DM</title>, but we have
                                    edited it to match the structure of <title level="m">P</title>’s
                                            <quote><hi rend="italics">Scrap of Canvas</hi>.</quote>
                                    Since Thelwall scribbled in <quote>inch</quote> in the small
                                    margin between lines, he could not indicate how he wanted it
                                    presented. Thus, editorial liberties have been taken to maintain
                                    a uniform presentation.</note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der"><del rend="overstrike">So fills</del> each <hi
                                    rend="italics"><subst>
                                        <del rend="srikethrough">Scrap</del>
                                        <add place="above">inch</add>
                                    </subst>of <del rend="overstrike"><add place="above"><gap
                                                reason="illegible" unit="word" quantity="1"
                                        /></add></del>Canvas</hi> with a <add place="above"
                                    >varnish’d</add>
                                <hi rend="italics">Face</hi>,</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">So fills each <hi rend="italics">Scrap of Canvas</hi>
                                with a <hi rend="italics">Face</hi>,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <pb type="pdf" n="361"/>
                    <l>Which all, lest quarrels rise for shape and air,</l>
                    <l>The self-same attitude and features share—</l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd"><persName>West</persName>, who, <hi rend="italics">to
                                    Scripture rules devoutly true</hi>,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der"><hi rend="smallcaps">West</hi>, who, <hi rend="italics"
                                    >to Scripture rules devoutly true</hi>,</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per"><hi rend="smallcaps">West</hi>, who, <hi rend="italics"
                                    >to Scripture rules devoutly true</hi>,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>Thinks <hi rend="italics">Eye for Eye</hi>, and <hi rend="italics">Tooth for
                            Tooth</hi>, are due,</l>
                    <l>And painting <persName type="historical">Pharoah</persName>, and his warlike
                        host</l>
                    <l><hi rend="italics">O’erthown by <persName type="historical">Moses</persName>,
                            and in Soap Suds lost,</hi></l>
                    <l><app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">With vengeful Brush, for Justice, arms his
                                Hands,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">With vengeful Brush, for Justice, arms his Hands,</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">With vengeful Brush, for <hi rend="italics"
                                >Justice</hi>, arms his Hands,</rdg>
                        </app></l>
                    <l>And <hi rend="italics">murders <persName type="historical"
                            >Moses</persName></hi>, as the <hi rend="italics">Law</hi>
                            commands.—<note>Possibly an allusion to West’s painting <title level="m"
                                >Pharoah and his Host Lost in the Red Sea</title> (1792).</note></l>
                    <l><app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">That <persName>West</persName>, who, lest the <hi
                                    rend="italics">first sad Curse</hi> be vain,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">That <hi rend="underline">West</hi>, who, lest the <hi
                                    rend="italics">first sad Curse</hi> be vain,</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">That <hi rend="smallcaps">West</hi>, who, lest the <hi
                                    rend="italics">first sad Curse</hi> be vain,</rdg>
                        </app></l>
                    <l><hi rend="italics">Damns</hi> our fall’n Parents, o’er and o’er again;</l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Then, fired with <hi rend="italics">Zeal</hi>,
                                instructs his glorious Son</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Then, fired with <hi rend="italics">Zeal</hi>, instructs
                                his glorious SON</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Then, fired with <hi rend="italics">Zeal</hi>, instructs
                                his glorious <hi rend="smallcaps">Son</hi></rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>(By whom one Day the Sire shall be outdone)</l>
                    <l>To force grim <hi rend="italics"><persName type="mythological"
                                >Satan</persName></hi> from the depths of <placeName
                            type="mythological">Hell</placeName>,</l>
                    <l>’Midst grinning Forms of Ridicule to dwell,</l>
                    <l>Where <hi rend="italics">laughing Scorn</hi> shall more afflict his Pride</l>
                    <l>Than all the Flames for torturing Ages tried.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l><app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Genius of <placeName>Britain</placeName>!—That same
                                Nymph I mean</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">GENIUS <hi rend="italics">of</hi> BRITAIN!—That same
                                Nymph I mean</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per"><hi rend="smallcaps">Genius</hi>
                                <hi rend="italics">of</hi>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Britain</hi>!—That same Nymph I mean</rdg>
                        </app></l>
                    <l><app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Who teaches <hi rend="italics">Tambour</hi> to our
                                Gracious Queen;</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Who teaches <hi rend="italics">Tambour</hi> to our
                                GRACIOUS QUEEN;</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Who teaches <hi rend="italics">Tambour</hi> to our <hi
                                    rend="smallcaps">Gracious Queen</hi>;</rdg>
                        </app></l>
                    <l><app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Whence from her Needle (wond’rous Art!) arise</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Whence from her Needle (wond’rous Art!) arise</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Whence from her Needle (wondrous Art!) arise</rdg>
                        </app></l>
                    <l>Long Pomps of <hi rend="italics">Silken Trees</hi>, and <hi rend="italics"
                            >Worsted Skies</hi>;</l>
                    <l><hi rend="italics">Quadrupeds</hi>, <hi rend="italics">non-descript</hi>, are
                        forc’d to Fame,</l>
                    <l><app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd"><hi rend="italics">Plants with new forms</hi>, and <hi
                                    rend="italics">Flowers without a name</hi>:</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der"><hi rend="italics">Plants with new forms</hi>, and <hi
                                    rend="italics">Flowers without a name</hi>:</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per"><hi rend="italics">Plants with new forms</hi>, and <hi
                                    rend="italics">Flowers without a name</hi>;</rdg>
                        </app></l>
                    <l>Or, soaring higher, to the Human form,</l>
                    <l>Her steel-eyed Pencil, (exquisitely warm!)</l>
                    <l>Calls <hi rend="italics">faces</hi> forth—(if those who late have seen</l>
                    <l><hi rend="italics"><persName>Laurence’s</persName></hi> Portrait of that <hi
                            rend="italics">awful</hi> Mien</l>
                    <l>For such a Fact can take a Poet’s word!)<note>Sir Thomas Lawrence (1769–1830)
                            was a painter. The painting referenced here of Queen Charlotte is likely
                            the one he was commissioned to do between 1789 and 1790.</note></l>
                    <l>Still more unmeaning than her Royal Lord!</l>
                    <l>—Prudent Amusement for a married Dame</l>
                    <l>Whose <hi rend="italics">Numerous Babes</hi> her <hi rend="italics">frugal
                            Fondness</hi> claim!</l>
                    <l>Expensive Books might shrink her little Store,</l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Concerts and Treats make even the Wealthy
                                    poor:<note>In the <title level="u">DM</title>, the <q>v</q> of
                                        <quote>even</quote> is hand-written by Thelwall onto the cut
                                    and pasted page; in <title level="m">P</title>, it is spelled
                                        <quote>e’en.</quote> While we have chosen the <title
                                        level="u">DM</title> in this instance, we acknowledge that
                                    it is a strange change, since it disrupts the strict iambic
                                    pentameter of the line. The disruption of the earlier metre may
                                    reflect Thelwall’s later prosodic theories and abandonment of
                                    poetic contradictions but he does not do this
                                    consistently.</note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Concerts and Treats make e<subst>
                                    <del>’</del>
                                    <add place="above">v</add>
                                </subst>en the Wealthy poor:</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Concerts and Treats make e’en the Wealthy poor:</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>But she at home who o’er her <hi rend="italics">Needle</hi> dreams,</l>
                    <l>Or <hi rend="italics">patches Fragments</hi> up with frugal Seams,</l>
                    <pb type="pdf" n="364"/>
                    <l><app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Or works <hi rend="italics">old <choice>
                                        <orig>Sattin</orig>
                                        <reg>Satin</reg>
                                    </choice> Coats</hi> with Colours fine,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Or works <hi rend="italics">old Sattin Coats</hi> with
                                Colours fine,</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Or works <hi rend="italics">old Satin Coats</hi> with
                                Colours fine,</rdg>
                        </app></l>
                    <l>O’er no <hi rend="italics">Upholsterer’s hideous Bill</hi> shall pine;</l>
                    <l>Yet sees, blest Harvest of her Royal Cares!</l>
                    <l><hi rend="italics">Quilts for her Beds</hi>, and <hi rend="italics">Covers
                            for her Chairs</hi>.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l><app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Genius <hi rend="italics">of</hi>
                                <placeName>Britain</placeName>! who, with like control,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">GENIUS <hi rend="italics">of</hi> BRITAIN! who, with
                                like control,</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per"><hi rend="smallcaps">Genius</hi>
                                <hi rend="italics">of</hi>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Britain</hi>! who, with like control,</rdg>
                        </app></l>
                    <l><app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Sway George’s, Charlotte’s, West’s, and Warren’s
                                    Soul!—<note>The references to George and Charlotte here are
                                    obviously to King George III (1738-1820) and his wife Queen
                                    Charlotte of Mecklenburg-Strelitz (1744–1818), who ruled at the
                                    time of the poem’s composition. The earlier reference to the
                                        <quote>Gracious Queen</quote> (line 148 of Canto One) is
                                    also to Charlotte, who was known for her needle work. According
                                    to Judith Thompson, <quote>Warren</quote> refers to Dr. Richard
                                    Warren, a physician who had helped treating George III’s illness
                                    during the Regency Crisis of 1788: see <title level="m"
                                        >P</title>, note 197.</note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Sway GEORGE’s, CHARLOTTE’s, WEST’s, and WARREN’s
                                Soul!—</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Sway <hi rend="smallcaps">George</hi>’s, <hi
                                    rend="smallcaps">Charlotte</hi>’s, <hi rend="smallcaps"
                                    >West</hi>’s, and <hi rend="smallcaps">Warren</hi>’s
                                Soul!—</rdg>
                        </app></l>
                    <l><app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Make <persName>Merry’s</persName> ravings,
                                    <persName>Coleman’s</persName> stolen trash,<note>For Merry, see
                                    notes 39 and 41. Thelwall parodies one of Merry’s poems—<title
                                        level="a">The Laurel of Liberty</title>—at the end of the
                                        <title level="a">Epic Poetry</title> chapter in <title
                                        level="m">P</title>. <quote>Coleman</quote> refers to two
                                    people: Colman the elder (1732-94) and the younger (1762-1836),
                                    both playwrights and theatre managers. In the <title level="a"
                                        >Prefatory Memoir</title> of <title level="m">Poems Chiefly
                                        Written in Retirement</title>, Thelwall mentions that
                                        <quote>free use</quote> (xxi) had been made of some of his
                                    work. This suggests he may have been complaining of plagiarism
                                    in this line.</note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Make MERRY’s ravings, COLEMAN’s stolen trash,</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Make <hi rend="smallcaps">Merry</hi>’s ravings, <hi
                                    rend="smallcaps">Coleman</hi>’s stolen trash,</rdg>
                        </app></l>
                    <l><app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">His <hi rend="italics">Tragi-Comic-Pantomimic</hi>
                                hash,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">His <hi rend="italics">Tragi-Comic-Pantomimic</hi>
                                hash,</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">His <hi rend="italics">Tragi-Comic-Pantomimic
                                hash</hi>,</rdg>
                        </app></l>
                    <l><app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Pass for true Wit! assist my Epic Lay:</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Pass for true Wit! assist my EPIC LAY:</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Pass for true Wit! assist my <hi rend="smallcaps">Epic
                                    Lay</hi>:</rdg>
                        </app></l>
                    <l><app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">And I may hope to write <hi rend="italics">as well as
                                    they</hi>!<note>In <title level="m">P</title>, the last line of
                                    the <title level="a">Invocation</title> reads <quote>For hard
                                        the Task my vent’rous Lines essay.</quote> In <title
                                        level="u">DM</title>, Thelwall has crossed out the original
                                    line and written his correction underneath. His change makes
                                    absolutely clear the satiric nature of the poem.</note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der"><subst>
                                    <del rend="overstrike">For hard the Task my vent’rous Lines
                                        essay.</del>
                                    <add place="below">And I may hope to write <hi rend="underline"
                                            >as well as they</hi>!</add>
                                </subst></rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">For hard the Task my vent’rous Lines essay.</rdg>
                        </app></l>
                </lg>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="canto1">
                <head resp="Editor">Canto One</head>
                <lg>
                    <l><app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Near that blest spot, of ancient classic fame—</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Near that blest spot, of ancient classic fame—</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Near that blest Spot, of ancient Classic Fame—</rdg>
                        </app></l>
                    <l><app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Fancy’s lov’d region!—<placeName>Grub
                                    Street</placeName> is its name<note>A famous street in London,
                                    Grub Street was associated with both hack writers and the free
                                    press. It is close to Chiswell street.</note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Fancy’s lov’d region!—Grub Street is its name</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Fancy’s lov’d Region—<hi rend="smallcaps">Grub
                                    Street</hi> is its name</rdg>
                        </app></l>
                    <l><app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">With mortal men (how call’d by Gods on high</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">With mortal men (how call’d by Gods on high</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">With <hi rend="italics">Mortal Men</hi>—how call’d by
                                    <hi rend="italics">Gods</hi> on high,</rdg>
                        </app></l>
                    <l><app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Small is the import, friends, to you or I!)<note>In
                                        <title level="m">P</title>, the line reads, <quote>Small is
                                        the import, friend, to you or I—</quote>.</note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Small is the import, friends, to you or I!)</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Small is the import, friend, to you or I—</rdg>
                        </app></l>
                    <l>Where oft the Muse (while Muses were esteem’d)<note>From <quote>Where oft the
                                Muse</quote> to <quote><hi rend="italics">Brotherly</hi>
                                regard</quote> (line 20 of Canto One), Thelwall has pasted pages of
                                <title level="m">P</title> into the <title level="u">DM</title>. See
                            note 38.</note></l>
                    <l>In days of yore, with bold inventions teem’d;</l>
                    <l>With <hi rend="italics">Giants</hi>, <hi rend="italics">Spectres</hi>, and
                            <hi rend="italics">Magicians</hi> dire,</l>
                    <l><hi rend="italics">Monsters</hi> and <hi rend="italics">Dragons</hi> belching
                        Streams of Fire,</l>
                    <l><app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Which armed Heroes brav’d to Combat, drunk</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Which arm<subst>
                                    <del rend="overwritten">’</del>
                                    <add place="inspace">e</add>
                                </subst>d Heroes brav’d to Combat, drunk</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Which arm’d Heroes brav’d to Combat, drunk</rdg>
                        </app></l>
                    <l>With sacred Love of Piety and Punk!—</l>
                    <l>—Near this fam’d Spot, where <hi rend="italics">Poems</hi> once were
                        made,</l>
                    <l>And <hi rend="italics">Founders</hi> yet assist the Poet’s Trade,</l>
                    <l>For leaden <hi rend="italics">Satires</hi> leaden <hi rend="italics"
                            >Types</hi> supply,</l>
                    <l><app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">And give Ideal Nonsense to the Eye;—</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">And give Ideal Nonsense to the Eye<add place="inline"
                                    >;</add>—</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">And give Ideal Nonsense to the Eye—</rdg>
                        </app></l>
                    <l><app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Near this fam’d spot—nor far (for since, by
                                Fits,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Near this fam’d spot—nor far (for since, by Fits,</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Near this fam’d spot—nor far, (for since, by Fits,</rdg>
                        </app></l>
                    <l><hi rend="italics">Wits</hi> will be <hi rend="italics">Madmen</hi>, <hi
                            rend="italics">Madmen</hi> may be <hi rend="italics">Wits</hi>,</l>
                    <l>Our prudent Ancestors, right wisely plann’d</l>
                    <l>Their dwellings in one Neighbourhood should stand,</l>
                    <l>That due assistance might at times be shar’d,</l>
                    <l>And <hi rend="italics">Brothers</hi> held in <hi rend="italics"
                            >Brotherly</hi> regard)—</l>
                    <l><app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Nor far remote from that benignant pile—<note>In
                                        <title level="m">P</title>, the line reads, <quote>Nor far
                                        remov’d from that same noble Pile,</quote>.</note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Nor far remote from that benignant pile—</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Nor far remov’d from that same noble Pile,</rdg>
                        </app></l>
                    <l><app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">(A needful structure in <placeName>Britania’s
                                    Isle!</placeName>)<note>Capital <q>I</q> in <quote>Isle</quote>
                                    retained from <title level="m">P</title>: lower case in <title
                                        level="u">DM</title>.</note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">(A needful structure in Britania’s isle!)</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">(A needful Structure in <hi rend="italics"
                                    >Britannia</hi>’s Isle!)</rdg>
                        </app></l>
                    <l><app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Which, till some loftier dome the title claim,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Which, till some loftier dome the title claim,</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Which, <hi rend="italics">till some Royal head its
                                    shelter claim</hi>,</rdg>
                        </app></l>
                    <l><app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Of Bedlam bears the far resounding name,—<note>In
                                        <title level="m">P</title>, the couplet reads, <quote>Which,
                                            <hi rend="italics">till some Royal head its shelter
                                            claim</hi>, / Of <hi rend="smallcaps">Bedlam</hi> bears
                                        the low, plebeian Name,</quote>: As one can see, this
                                    couplet has changed significantly, most notably in its
                                    characterization of <quote>Bedlam,</quote> which changes from a
                                        <quote>low, plebeian</quote> to a <quote>far
                                        resounding</quote> name. The Priory of Saint Mary of
                                    Bethlehem (Bedlam) was an infamous hospital for the mentally
                                    ill.</note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Of Bedlam bears the far resounding name,—</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Of <hi rend="smallcaps">Bedlam</hi> bears the low,
                                plebeian Name,</rdg>
                        </app></l>
                    <l><app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">There stands a mansion, o’er whose portals
                                    shine<note>In <title level="m">P</title>, the line reads,
                                        <quote>There stands a Dome, o’er whose trim Portals
                                        shine</quote>. This change is likely to facilitate the
                                    rhythm, since the original’s placing of <quote>o’er</quote> on
                                    the unstressed pulse is awkward.</note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">There stands a mansion, o’er whose portals shine</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">There stands a Dome, o’er whose trim Portals shine</rdg>
                        </app></l>
                    <pb type="pdf" n="366"/>
                    <l><app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">(Type of Jove’s guardian care and power divine!)<note
                                    place="bottom" resp="ed">In <title level="m">P</title>, the line
                                    reads, <quote>(Type of <hi rend="smallcaps">Jove</hi>’s guardian
                                        Care and Love divine!)</quote>.</note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">(Type of Jove’s guardian care &amp; power divine!)</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Type of <hi rend="smallcaps">Jove</hi>’s guardian Care
                                and Love divine!)</rdg>
                        </app></l>
                    <l><app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Lion and Unicorn, by sculptor bold<note place="bottom"
                                    resp="ed">The lion and unicorn are symbols found on the Royal
                                    Arms of the United Kingdom.</note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Lion &amp; Unicorn, by sculptor bold</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per"><hi rend="italics">Lion</hi> and <hi rend="italics"
                                    >Unicorn</hi>, by Sculptor bold</rdg>
                        </app></l>
                    <l><app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Carv’d in Olympian Oak and gay with Gold:</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Carv’d in Olympian Oak &amp; gay with Gold:</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Carv’d in Olympian Oak, and gay with Gold.</rdg>
                        </app></l>
                    <l><app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">A mansion every bard with rapture views<note
                                    place="bottom" resp="ed">In <title level="m">P</title>, the line
                                    reads, <quote>A Dome it is each Bard with rapture views</quote>.
                                    Thelwall’s choice to replace <quote>dome</quote> with
                                        <quote>mansion</quote> here, as at line 25 of Canto One, is
                                    likely for the sake of the sonic quality of the line as opposed
                                    to a deliberate change of content.</note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">A mansion every bard with rapture views</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">A Dome it is each Bard with rapture views</rdg>
                        </app></l>
                    <l>Who in spruce Garb would deck his lofty Muse,<note place="bottom" resp="ed"
                            >From <quote>Who in spruce Garb</quote> to <quote>dear-beloved
                                Lead!—</quote> (line 64 of Canto One), Thelwall has pasted pages of
                                <title level="m">P</title> into <title level="u">DM</title>. See
                            note 38.</note></l>
                    <l>Thro’ <hi rend="italics">sheets of Snow</hi> would each <hi rend="italics"
                            >dark passage</hi> spread,</l>
                    <l>And aid his weight of <hi rend="italics">Brains</hi> with weight of <hi
                            rend="italics">Lead</hi>.</l>
                    <l>There thro’ the livelong Day, o’er many a Forge,</l>
                    <l>Doom’d leaden Bolts of Vengeance to disgorge,</l>
                    <l>The <hi rend="italics">Literary Cyclops</hi> toil and sweat</l>
                    <l>O’er the <hi rend="italics">dread Thunders of the Alphabet;</hi></l>
                    <l>Which dealt, with well-aim’d Vengeance, o’er the World,</l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Tyrants <hi rend="italics">have bow’d, and mighty</hi>
                                Statesmen <hi rend="italics">hurl’d</hi></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der"><hi rend="smallcaps">Tyrants</hi>
                                <hi rend="italics">have bow’d, and mighty</hi>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Statesmen</hi>
                                <hi rend="italics">hurl’d</hi></rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per"><hi rend="smallcaps">Tyrants</hi>
                                <hi rend="italics">have bow’d, and mighty</hi>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Statesmen</hi>
                                <hi rend="italics">hurl’d</hi></rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l><hi rend="italics">From Power’s misgotten, or polluted Seat,</hi></l>
                    <l><hi rend="italics">Villains</hi> have aw’d, and made <hi rend="italics">proud
                            Vice</hi> retreat!—</l>
                    <l>Thunders which, <hi rend="italics">pointed by a Monarch’s hand</hi>,</l>
                    <l><app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Have <hi rend="italics">spread Confusion thro a
                                    peaceful Land;</hi></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Have <hi rend="italics">spread Confusion thro a peaceful
                                    Land;</hi></rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Have <hi rend="italics">spread Confusion thro’ a
                                    peaceful Land;</hi></rdg>
                        </app></l>
                    <l><app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">With panic Awe have struck the Free-born Soul,<note
                                    place="bottom" resp="ed">In <title level="m">P</title>, the line
                                    reads, <quote>With short-liv’d Awe have struck the Free-born
                                        Soul,</quote>. Since this line occurs on a page pasted into
                                    the <title level="u">DM</title>, the replaced words are
                                    scratched out and the correction is written into the
                                    margin.</note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">With <subst>
                                    <del rend="overstrike">short-liv’d</del>
                                    <add place="margin">panic</add>
                                </subst> Awe have struck the Free-born Soul,</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">With short-liv’d Awe have struck the Free-born
                                Soul,</rdg>
                        </app></l>
                    <l><app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd"><hi rend="italics">Compell’d the use of Reason to
                                    control,</hi></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der"><hi rend="italics">Compell’d the use of Reason to
                                        control<add place="inline">;—</add></hi></rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per"><hi rend="italics">Compell’d the use of Reason to
                                    control,</hi></rdg>
                        </app></l>
                    <l>Compell’d to deem as <hi rend="italics">wicked Traitors</hi>, those</l>
                    <l><app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Not who <hi rend="italics">concert the Treason,</hi>
                                but <hi rend="italics">expose</hi>—<note place="bottom" resp="ed">In
                                    the <title level="u">DM</title>, Thelwall includes between this
                                    and the next line one of Sylvanus’ interjections into the
                                    recitation of the poem, which appears at this same place in the
                                        <title level="m">P</title>: <quote>Avarice and Vanity, the
                                        fostering parents and tetular deities of the hero, are then
                                        described, while he is enjoying the sweets of slumber, as
                                        visiting the deserted scene—</quote>. Since Thelwall does
                                    not go on to describe Avarice or Vanity, one is tempted to
                                    assume that Canto One was not finished despite Thelwall’s claims
                                    to the contrary. Nevertheless, the poem reads logically without
                                    this missing description. In the <title level="u">DM</title>,
                                    Thelwall also adds a handwritten note in the margin clarifying
                                    the identity of the <quote>hero</quote>: <quote>Mr Caslon,
                                        Letter founder to his Majesty.</quote> This is the first
                                    explicit indication Thelwall gives to indicate that Alphabeta is
                                    meant to be an allegorical stand-in for Caslon.</note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Not who <hi rend="italics">concert the Treason</hi>, but
                                    <hi rend="italics">expose</hi>—</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Not who <hi rend="italics">concert the Treason</hi>, but
                                    <hi rend="italics">expose</hi>.—</rdg>
                        </app></l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l>For now ’tis night: no more the Cyclops sweat</l>
                    <l>O’er the dread thunders of the alphabet,</l>
                    <l>Whose dubious terrors can alike control</l>
                    <l>By turns the Tyrant’s and the Patriot’s soul—</l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l rend="indent"><hi rend="italics">Here</hi>, tier o’er tier, in many an
                        order’d Row,</l>
                    <l><app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">To please the Goddess, <hi rend="italics">finish’d
                                    Letters glow;</hi></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">To please the <hi rend="smallcaps">Goddess</hi>, <hi
                                    rend="italics">finish’d Letters glow;</hi></rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">To please the Goddess, <hi rend="italics">finish’d
                                    Letters glow;</hi></rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>Not burnish’d Silver beams a brighter Ray;</l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Not prim Sir Fopling more exactly gay<note
                                    place="bottom" resp="ed">Sir Fopling is a character from the
                                    comedy <title level="m">The Man of Mode</title>, written by
                                    George Etherege in 1676. As the name suggests, Sir Fopling is a
                                        <quote>fop,</quote> overly concerned with his
                                    appearance.</note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Not prim <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir Fopling</hi> more
                                exactly gay</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Not prim Sir Fopling more exactly gay</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Glides thro’ the Ball-room, fearful lest the Air</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Glides thro the Ball-room, fearful lest the Air</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Glides thro’ the Ball-room, fearful lest the Air</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l><app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd"><hi rend="italics">Derange a Frill</hi>, or <hi
                                    rend="italics">disconcert a Hair.</hi></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der"><hi rend="italics">Derange a Frill</hi>, or <hi
                                    rend="italics">disconcert a Hair.</hi></rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per"><hi rend="italics">Derange a Frill, or disconcert a
                                    Hair.</hi></rdg>
                        </app></l>
                    <l>—<hi rend="italics">There unwrought Metal</hi> lay, heap’d pile on pile;</l>
                    <l><app>
                            <lem>There <hi rend="italics">drossy Refuse of the daily
                                Toil;</hi></lem>
                            <rdg>There <hi rend="italics">drossy Refuse of the daily
                                Toil;</hi></rdg>
                            <rdg>There <hi rend="italics">drossy refuse of the daily
                                Toil;</hi></rdg>
                        </app></l>
                    <l>There, splash’d by careless hands from out the Moulds,</l>
                    <l><app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd"><hi rend="italics">Thick spangling Drops</hi> the
                                pensive God beholds,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der"><hi rend="italics">Thick spangling Drops</hi> the
                                pensive GOD beholds,</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per"><hi rend="italics">Thick spangling Drops</hi> the
                                pensive <hi rend="smallcaps">God</hi> beholds,</rdg>
                        </app></l>
                    <l>Decking with useless Pomp, each Screen, each Wall,</l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Furnace, and Chimney, thro’ the spacious Hall.</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Furnace, and Chimney, thro the spacious Hall.</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Furnace, and Chimney, thro’ the spacious Hall.</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l><said>Oh! woeful sight!</said> the sordid <hi rend="italics">Spectre</hi>
                        said,</l>
                    <l>"Oh! impious waste of dear-beloved Lead!—</l>
                    <pb type="pdf" n="368"/>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">"Lead! which, by Alphabeta touch’d, shall own<note
                                    place="bottom" resp="ed">From line 65 to line 112, quotation
                                    marks retained from <title level="m">P</title>: absent in <title
                                        level="u">DM</title>. Furthermore, in <title level="m"
                                        >P</title>, the line reads <quote>Lead which, by <hi
                                            rend="smallcaps">Alphabeta</hi> touch’d, shall
                                        owe.</quote></note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Lead! which by Alphabeta touch’d, shall own</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">"<hi rend="italics">Lead</hi> which, by <hi
                                    rend="smallcaps">Alphabeta</hi> touch’d, shall owe</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">"Him the true master of the chemic stone:—<note
                                    place="bottom" resp="ed">In <title level="m">P</title>, the line
                                    reads, <quote>Him the true Master of the Chymic
                                    stone—</quote>.</note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Him the true master of the chemic stone:—</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">“Him the true Master of the Chymic stone—</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">"Lead! which well wrought and properly bestow’d</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Lead! which well wrought &amp; properly bestow’d</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">"<hi rend="italics">Lead</hi> which well-wrought, and
                                properly bestow’d,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">"Might print a Dying Speech, or Birthday Ode;</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Might print a Dying Speech, or Birthday Ode;</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">“Might print a <hi rend="italics">Dying Speech,</hi> or
                                    <hi rend="italics">Birth-Day Ode;</hi></rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">"Grant’s lashes publish, and for justice call;<note
                                    place="bottom" resp="ed">According to Judith Thompson, this is a
                                    reference to pamphlets that were published before and after
                                    scandalous trials: see <title level="m">P</title>, note
                                    201.</note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Grant’s lashes publish, &amp; for justice call;</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">“<hi rend="smallcaps">Grant</hi>’s <hi rend="italics"
                                    >Lashes</hi> publish, and for justice call;</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">"Or shew why Rose was never lash’d at all:—</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Or shew why Rose was never lash’d at all:—</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">“Or shew why <hi rend="smallcaps">Rose</hi> was never
                                lash’d at all.—</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">"Lead! from whose womb in order’d ranks shall
                                rise</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Lead! from whose womb in order’d ranks shall rise</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">"Lead from whose womb in order’d ranks shall rise</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">"Those letters doom’d to charm all human eyes;</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Those letters doom’d to charm all human eyes;</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">"Those letters doom’d to charm all human eyes,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">"At sight of which the dunces breast shall glow,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">At sight of which the dunces breast shall glow,</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">“At sight of which the <hi rend="italics">Dunce’s</hi>
                                Breast might glow,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">"Struck with strange passion for the
                                Criss-Cross-Row!</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Struck with strange passion for the
                                Criss-Cross-Row!</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">“Struck with strange Passion for the <hi
                                    rend="smallcaps">Criss Cross-Row</hi>!-</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">—"Letters, so neat, so trim, so smoothe, so
                                fair!</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">—Letters, so neat, so trim, so smoothe, so fair!</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">—"<hi rend="italics">Letters,</hi> so neat! so trim! so
                                smooth! so fair!</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">"Be they round <hi rend="italics">oes</hi>, strait <hi
                                    rend="italics">ies</hi>, or <hi rend="italics">vees</hi> so
                                    square,<note place="bottom" resp="ed">In <title level="m"
                                        >P</title>, Thelwall prints the letters themselves (<quote>O
                                        o</quote>) instead of the phonetic spelling used in <title
                                        level="u">DM</title> (<quote>oes</quote>).</note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Be they round <hi rend="underline">oes</hi>, strait <hi
                                    rend="underline">ies</hi>, or <hi rend="underline">vees</hi> so
                                square,</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">“Be they round O o, strait I i , or V v so square,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">"Or crooked <hi rend="italics">esses</hi>, or that <hi
                                    rend="italics">ess</hi> that swells</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Or crooked <hi rend="underline">esses</hi>, or that <hi
                                    rend="underline">ess</hi> that swells</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">“Or crooked S s, or that &#383; that swells</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">"High o’er the line, like straighter <hi
                                    rend="italics">kays</hi> and <hi rend="italics"
                                >ells</hi>,—</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">High o’er the line, like straighter <hi rend="underline"
                                    >kays</hi> and <hi rend="underline">ells</hi>,—</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">“High o’er the Line, like straighter k k and l l,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">"That lofty <hi rend="italics">ess</hi> which Bell,
                                with cruel spite,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">That lofty <hi rend="underline">ess</hi> which Bell,
                                with cruel spite,</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">“That lofty &#383;s, which <hi rend="smallcaps"
                                    >Bell</hi>, with cruel spite,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">"Would damn to dark oblivion’s endless night,<note
                                    place="bottom" resp="ed">John Bell (1745–1831), was a successful
                                    bookseller famous for producing cheap prints. He introduced a
                                    new <q>modern print,</q> which included the elimination of the
                                    long <q>s</q> (a legacy reflected in our choice to standardize
                                    the <q>s</q> in our edition).</note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Would damn to dark oblivion’s endless night,</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">“Would damn to dark Oblivion’s endless Night,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">"But which, by Alphabeta’s loyal care,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">But which, by Alphabeta’s loyal care,</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">“But which, by <hi rend="smallcaps">Alphabeta</hi>’s
                                loyal Care,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">"Still o’er the ranks the lofty crest shall
                                bear,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Still o’er the ranks the lofty crest shall bear,</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">“Still o’er the Ranks the lofty Crest shall bear,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">"By laws of ancient usage tower on high,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">By laws of ancient usage tower on high,</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">“By laws of ancient usage tower on high,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">And Innovation’s fearful rage defy."<note
                                    place="bottom" resp="ed">In <title level="m">P</title>, the line
                                    reads, <quote>And Innovation’s dangerous stride defy.</quote> In
                                    the <title level="u">DM</title>, Thelwall wrote
                                        <quote>dangerous</quote> before scratching the word out and
                                    writing <quote>fearful</quote> beside it. Since the correction
                                    is included in the line itself, as opposed to being crammed into
                                    the space between lines, the change seems to have been made
                                    immediately upon transcription. The change might mark a shift in
                                    Thelwall’s view of the dangers of <quote>innovation,</quote> or
                                    might reveal nothing more than the decision to replace the
                                    dactylic <quote>dangerous</quote> with the more iambic-friendly
                                        <quote>fearful.</quote>
                                    <p>In <title level="m">P</title>, Sylvanus interjects between
                                        this line and the next: <quote>To this I shall add another
                                            speech of the same immortal personage, upon the
                                            importance of that kind of accumulation, of which he is
                                            the patron—</quote>. In <title level="u">DM</title>,
                                        Thelwall also includes an interjection, but it differs from
                                        that in the <title level="m">P</title>: <quote>The Alchemic
                                            power of Alphabeta (Caslon) and the facility with which
                                            he transmutes his native bras &amp; molten lead to gold,
                                            gives occasion for the following rhapsody, or eulogium,
                                            or that noble metal—</quote>.</p></note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">And Inovation’s <subst>
                                    <del rend="overstrike">dangerous</del>
                                    <add place="inline">fearful</add>
                                </subst> rage defy.</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">“And Innovation’s dangerous stride defy.”</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                </lg>
                <pb type="pdf" n="370"/>
                <lg>
                    <l rend="indent">
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">"All things from this their real value claim.</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">All things from this their real value claim.</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">“All things from <hi rend="smallcaps">This</hi> their
                                real value claim.</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">"Truth, Honour, Justice, Valour, Conscience,
                                Fame</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Truth, Honour, Justice, Valour, Conscience, Fame</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">“Truth, Honour, Justice, Valour, Conscience,
                                Fame,—</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">"(In every rank, Priests, Mountebanks and Kings!)<note
                                    place="bottom" resp="ed">In <title level="m">P</title>, this
                                    line reads, <quote>(Thro’ every Rank, <hi rend="italics"
                                            >Priests, Mountebanks</hi>, and <hi rend="italics"
                                            >Kings</hi>,)</quote>.</note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">(In every rank, Priests, Mountebanks &amp; Kings!)</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">"(Thro’ every Rank, <hi rend="italics">Priests,
                                    Mountebanks</hi> and <hi rend="italics">Kings</hi>,)</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">"Have no more worth than each the pence it
                                brings.</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Have no more worth than each the pence it brings.</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">"Have no more worth than each the <hi rend="italics"
                                    >Pence</hi> it brings</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">"And tho adepts may bounce, with scruples nice,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">And tho adepts may bounce, with scruples nice,</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">“And tho’ <hi rend="italics">Adepts</hi> may bounce,
                                with Scruples nice,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">"’Tis but a bubble to encrease the price,—<note
                                    place="bottom" resp="ed">Spelling of <quote>encrease</quote>
                                    retained from <title level="u">DM</title>.</note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">’Tis but a bubble to encrease the price,—</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">“’Tis but a bubble to increase the price;</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">"Save with some fools, whom learned pride
                                    misleads;<note place="bottom" resp="ed">In <title level="u"
                                        >DM</title>, Thelwall wrote <quote>Save with some learned
                                        fools</quote> before crossing out <quote>learned</quote> and
                                    finishing the line with <quote>whom learned pride
                                        misleads,</quote> thus matching the respective line in
                                        <title level="m">P</title>. It is likely that this was a
                                    transcription mistake on Thelwall’s part, but it is possible
                                    that he temporarily flirted with the idea of changing the line
                                    before settling on the earlier construction.</note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Save with some <del rend="overstrike"
                                >learned</del>fools, whom learned pride misleads;</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">“(Save with some Fools, whom learned Pride
                                misleads)</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">—"A stale stock-jobbing trick, which no one
                                heeds.</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">—A stale stockjobbing trick, which no one heeds.</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">“A stale, stock-jobbing Trick, which no one heeds.</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">"For this the <name type="occupation"
                                >Statesman</name>, clinging to the <hi rend="italics"
                                    >Purse</hi>,<note place="bottom" resp="ed">From <quote>For this
                                        the Statesman</quote> to <quote>fee him to be mute!—</quote>
                                    (line 108 of Canto One), Thelwall has pasted pages of <title
                                        level="m">P</title> into the <title level="u">DM</title>.
                                    See note 38.</note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">For <hi rend="smallcaps">this</hi> the <hi
                                    rend="smallcaps">Statesman</hi>, clinging to the <hi
                                    rend="italics">Purse</hi>,</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">“For <hi rend="smallcaps">This</hi> the <hi
                                    rend="smallcaps">Statesman</hi>, clinging to the <hi
                                    rend="italics">Purse</hi>,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">"Endures, without Remorse, his Country’s Curse;</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Endures, without Remorse, his Country’s Curse;</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">“Endures, without Remorse, his Country’s Curse;</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">"Endures the Scourge of headlong <hi rend="italics"
                                    >Party Rage</hi>,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Endures the Scourge of headlong <hi rend="italics">Party
                                    Rage</hi>,</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">“Endures the Scourge of headlong <hi rend="italics"
                                    >Party Rage</hi>,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">"And stands the <hi rend="italics">Butt</hi> of an
                                enquiring Age;</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">And stands the <hi rend="italics">Butt</hi> of an
                                enquiring Age;</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">“And stands the <hi rend="italics">Butt</hi> of an
                                enquiring Age;</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">"Without retreating from the searching Light,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Without retreating from the searching Light,</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">“Without retreating from the searching Light,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">"Sees <hi rend="italics">blacker Vices</hi> drag’d to
                                public sight</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Sees <hi rend="italics">blacker Vices</hi> drag’d to
                                public sight</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">“Sees <hi rend="italics">blacker Vices</hi> drag’d to
                                public sight</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">"Than, had he been of <hi rend="italics">poor Plebeian
                                    Race</hi>,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Than, had he been of <hi rend="italics">poor Plebeian
                                    Race</hi>,</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">“Than, had he been of <hi rend="italics">poor Plebeian
                                    Race</hi>,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">"Had justly doom’d him to a <hi rend="italics"
                                    >Rope’s</hi> disgrace:—</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Had justly doom’d him to a <hi rend="italics"
                                    >Rope’s</hi> disgrace:—</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">“Had justly doom’d him to a <hi rend="italics"
                                    >Rope’s</hi> disgrace;—</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">"<hi rend="italics">Unblushing</hi> bears it all—for
                                    <hi rend="italics">Gold</hi>, we know,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">"<hi rend="italics">Unblushing</hi> bears it all—for <hi
                                    rend="italics">Gold</hi>, we know,</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">"<hi rend="italics">Unblushing</hi> bears it all—for <hi
                                    rend="italics">Gold</hi>, we know,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">"Outbrazening <hi rend="italics">Brass</hi>, can
                                Impudence bestow.</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Outbrazening <hi rend="italics">Brass</hi>, can
                                Impudence bestow.</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">"Outbrazening <hi rend="italics">Brass</hi>, can
                                Impudence bestow.</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">"For this the <name type="occupation">Lawyer</name>
                                proves that <hi rend="italics">Black</hi> is <hi rend="italics"
                                    >White</hi>:</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">For this the <name type="occupation"><hi
                                        rend="smallcaps">Lawyer</hi></name> proves that <hi
                                    rend="italics">Black</hi> is <hi rend="italics"
                                >White</hi>:</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">"For this the <name type="occupation"><hi
                                        rend="smallcaps">Lawyer</hi></name> proves that <hi
                                    rend="italics">Black</hi> is <hi rend="italics"
                                >White</hi>;</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">"<name type="person">Arnold</name> for this upon both
                                sides will fight,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der"><name type="person"><hi rend="smallcaps"
                                    >Arnold</hi></name> for this upon both sides will fight,</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">“<name type="person"><hi rend="smallcaps"
                                    >Arnold</hi></name> for this upon both sides will fight,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">"By <hi rend="italics">both despis’d.</hi> For this
                                the <name type="occupation">Parson</name>&#32;<hi rend="italics"
                                    >preaches</hi>,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">By <hi rend="italics">both despis’d</hi>. For this the
                                    <name type="occupation"><hi rend="smallcaps">Parson</hi></name>
                                <hi rend="italics">preaches</hi>,</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">"By <hi rend="italics">both despis’d:</hi> For this the
                                    <name type="occupation"><hi rend="smallcaps">Parson</hi></name>
                                <hi rend="italics">preaches</hi>,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">"The <name type="occupation">Doctor</name>&#32;<hi
                                    rend="italics">kills</hi>, and <name type="person">Burke</name>
                                for this <hi rend="italics">impeaches</hi>,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">The <name type="occupation"><hi rend="smallcaps"
                                        >Doctor</hi></name><hi rend="italics"> kills</hi>, and <name
                                    type="person"><hi rend="smallcaps">Burke</hi></name> for this
                                    <hi rend="italics">impeaches</hi>,</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">"The <name type="occupation"><hi rend="smallcaps"
                                        >Doctor</hi></name>
                                <hi rend="italics">kills</hi>, and <name type="person"><hi
                                        rend="smallcaps">Burke</hi></name> for this <hi
                                    rend="italics">impeaches</hi>,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">"From Year to Year draws out the tedious suit—</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">From Year to Year draws out the tedious suit—</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">“From Year to Year draws out the tedious suit—</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">"For <name type="person">Hastings</name> would not <hi
                                    rend="italics">fee him to be mute!—</hi><note place="bottom"
                                    resp="ed">Warren Hastings (1732–1818) was the governor-general
                                    of Bengal. Burke accused Hastings of misgovernance in India, and
                                    in 1786 he brought charges against him for impeachment, which
                                    were successful in 1787. Benedict Arnold (1741-1801) was an
                                    American military man during the war for American independence.
                                    In 1779, while he was the military governor of Philadelphia, he
                                    betrayed the cause and started providing information to the
                                    British side. His name became well-associated with
                                    betrayal.</note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">For <name type="person"><hi rend="smallcaps"
                                        >Hastings</hi></name> would not <hi rend="italics">fee him
                                    to be mute!—</hi></rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">"For <name type="person"><hi rend="smallcaps"
                                        >Hastings</hi></name> would not <hi rend="italics">fee him
                                    to be mute</hi>!—</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Nay, chief for these (if Fame aright declare)<note
                                    place="bottom" resp="ed">In <title level="m">P</title>, this
                                    line reads, <quote>Nay, chief for this (if Fame aright
                                        declare,)</quote>.</note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Nay, chief for these (if Fame aright declare)</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">“Nay, chief for <hi rend="smallcaps">This</hi> (if Fame
                                aright declare,)</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">"<name type="person">Charlotte</name> and <name
                                    type="person">George</name> delight the Crown to wear:<note
                                    place="bottom" resp="ed"
                                        ><quote>Charlotte,</quote>&#32;<quote>George,</quote> and
                                        <quote>Crown</quote> retained from <title level="m"
                                        >P</title>. In <title level="u">DM</title>, Thelwall leaves
                                    these names and word out, and replaces them with dashes only.
                                    Since in the <title level="a">Invocation</title> Thelwall left
                                    untouched the names of Charlotte and George despite ridiculing
                                    them, it is strange that he redacted their names
                                here.</note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">__ __ and __ delight the __ to wear:</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">“<name type="person"><hi rend="smallcaps"
                                    >Charlotte</hi></name> and <name type="person"><hi
                                        rend="smallcaps">George</hi></name> delight the <hi
                                    rend="smallcaps">Crown</hi> to wear.</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">"Blest source of wealth! which leaves small cause to
                                dread</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Blest source of wealth! which leaves small cause to
                                dread</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">“Blest source of <hi rend="italics">Wealth!</hi> which
                                leaves small Cause to dread</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Their babes (God bless them!) e’er should beg their
                                    bread."<note place="bottom" resp="ed">In <title level="m"
                                        >P</title>, Sylvanus interjects between this line and the
                                    next: <quote>If you are not already wearied, I will add to these
                                        quotations a contrasted sketch of the phenomena of morning
                                        in Town and Country.—The latter part of this quotation
                                        formed the commencement of the second—the former the
                                        conclusion of the first Canto: the only one, indeed, which I
                                        had by any means finished, when I was induced by several
                                        considerations to lay aside my design.</quote> Neither
                                    Sylvanus the character nor Thelwall the author indicate where
                                    the split between the cantos occurs. However, since the <title
                                        level="a">Typopictoromania</title> of the <title level="u"
                                        >DM</title> ends without completing this respective section
                                    of the <title level="m">P</title>, we can conclude that the
                                    final line of the <title level="u">DM</title> demarcates the
                                    split between the two cantos. In <title level="u">DM</title>,
                                    Thelwall also includes an interjection, but it differs from that
                                    in the <title level="m">P</title>: <quote>The first Canto
                                        concluded with the following descriptive contrast of the
                                        matins of a pastoral region and of Chiswell Street.</quote>
                                    This line is itself a correction of an earlier, partially
                                    crossed out line, that reads, <quote>The first Canto concluded
                                        with the following descriptive enumeration of the <hi
                                            rend="underline">matins</hi> of Chiswell Street</quote>
                                    (redacted line in italics).</note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Their babes (God bless them!) e’er should beg their
                                bread.</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">“Their Babes (God <hi rend="italics">bless them!</hi>)
                                e’er should <hi rend="italics">beg their Bread</hi>."</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <pb type="pdf" n="372"/>
                    <l rend="indent">
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">"Scarce had they finish’d, when—a vulgar bard</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Scarce had they finish’d, when—a vulgar bard</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">"Scarce had they finish’d, when—A vulgar Bard</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Would tell you by the Cock’s shrill clarion
                                    scar’d;<note place="bottom" resp="ed">The <quote>vulgar
                                        bard</quote> is potentially a reference to Thomas Gray. This
                                    section of the poem mimics aspects of Gray’s <title level="a"
                                        >Elegy Written in a Country Churchyard.</title> Gray speaks
                                    of a cock’s clarion, and the repetitive <quote>or</quote> before
                                        <quote>milkmaid</quote> and <quote>Shepherd-Lad</quote>
                                    parallels the structure of Gray’s poem.</note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Would tell you by the Cock’s shrill clarion
                                scar’d;</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Would tell you, by the Cock’s shrill Clarion
                                scar’d;</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">But we, who true description seek alone,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">But we, who true description seek alone,</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">But we, who true Description seek alone,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Know that Cocks seldom crow in London Town:—</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Know that Cocks seldom crow in London Town:—</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Know that Cocks seldom crow in London Town;—</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Unless the poet, for his time of need,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Unless the poet, for his time of need,</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Unless the Poet, for the Time of Need,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Should keep one by him of Parnassian breed,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Should keep one by him of parnassian breed,</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Should keep one by him of Parnassian breed,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Who, fed with barley from the bifork’d hill,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Who, fed with barley from the bifork’d hill,</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Which, fed with Barley from the bi-fork’d hill,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Stands with arch’d neck to chuckle at his will.</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Stands with arch’d neck to chuckle at his will.</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Stands, with arch’d Neck, to chuckle at his will.—</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Scarce had they finished—O! that now, so gay,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Scarce had they finished—O! that now, so gay,</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Scarce had they finish’d—Oh! that now, so gay,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">My Muse might, thro’ enamell’d meadows, stray<note
                                    place="bottom" resp="ed">First comma and apostrophe retained
                                    from <title level="m">P</title>: absent from <title level="u"
                                        >DM</title>. First comma made necessary, grammatically, by
                                    the second, which is present in <title level="u"
                                    >DM</title>.</note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">My Muse might thro enamell’d meadows, stray</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">My Muse might, thro’ enamell’d Meadows, stray</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">By village side, where <name type="occupation"
                                    >ploughmen</name> whistle blithe,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">By village side, where <name type="occupation"
                                    >ploughmen</name> whistle blithe,</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">By Village side, whence <name type="occupation"
                                    >Ploughmen</name> whistle blithe,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">And the rude <name type="occupation">mower</name>
                                whets the shining scythe,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">And the rude <name type="occupation">mower</name> whets
                                the shining scythe,</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">And the rude <name type="occupation">Mower</name> whets
                                his shining scythe,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Or <name type="occupation">milkmaid</name> trips, and
                                while her cleanly pails</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Or <name type="occupation">milkmaid</name> trips, &amp;
                                while her cleanly pails</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Or <name type="occupation">Milk-Maid</name> trips, and,
                                while her cleanly Pails</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Click at her side, the Morn with Carol hails;<note
                                    place="bottom" resp="ed">From this line to the end of Canto One,
                                    Thelwall has pasted pages of <title level="m">P</title> into the
                                        <title level="u">DM</title>: see note 38.</note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Click at her side, the Morn with Carol hails;</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Click at her side, the Morn with Carol hails,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Or <name type="occupation">Shepherd-Lad</name>, with
                                barking Cur beside,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Or <name type="occupation">Shepherd-Lad</name>, with
                                barking Cur beside,</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Or <name type="occupation">Shepherd Lad</name>, with
                                barking Cur beside,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>Hies to the Cot where bleat the fleecy pride!</l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">With Vernal Beauties then my Verse should shine;</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">With Vernal Beauties then my Verse should shine;</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">With Vernal Beauties then my verse should shine;</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>Some varied Landscape glow in every Line;</l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Some balmy Zephyr thro’ the waving Grove,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Some balmy Zephyr thro the waving Grove,</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Some balmy Zephyr thro’ the waving Grove,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">In every Couplet, breathe the Sigh of Love;</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">In every Couplet, breathe the Sigh of Love;</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">In every Couplet, breathe the Sigh of Love;</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>While the shrill Lark, or Horn’s inspiring sound,</l>
                    <l>Should scare the Spectres to their Haunts profound.—</l>
                    <l>But Truth would here the Lark, the Horn disclaim:</l>
                    <l>And simple Truth is all the Muse’s aim.—</l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Scarce had they finish’d, when thro’
                                    <placeName>Chiswell Street</placeName></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">Scarce had they finish’d, when thro’ <hi
                                    rend="smallcaps"><placeName>Chiswell
                                Street</placeName></hi></rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Scarce had they finish’d, when thro’ <hi
                                    rend="smallcaps"><placeName>Chiswell
                                Street</placeName></hi></rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">(The Muse’s now, and Alphabeta’s Seat)</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">(The MUSE’s now, and ALPHABETA’s Seat)</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">(The <hi rend="smallcaps">Muse</hi>’s now, and <hi
                                    rend="smallcaps">Alphabeta</hi>’s Seat)</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>A shrill loud Voice proclaim’d the scatter’d Gloom,</l>
                    <l><app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">And <q><hi rend="italics">Sweep Soot O!</hi></q>
                                resounded thro’ the dome.</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Der">And <q><hi rend="italics">Sweep Soot O!</hi></q>
                                resounded thro’ the dome.</rdg>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">And <q><hi rend="italics">Sweep soot O!</hi></q>
                                resounded thro’ the dome.</rdg>
                        </app></l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l rend="indent">The Spectres started. Straight each Shadowy Breast</l>
                    <l>The <hi rend="italics">faithful Harbinger of Morn</hi> confest.</l>
                    <l>They melt to Air, as sooty, maim’d, and slow,</l>
                    <l>Pass the sad Sons of Penury and Woe!</l>
                </lg>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="canto2">
                <pb type="#Per" n="312"/>
                <head resp="Editor">Canto Two</head>
                <lg>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd"><persName>Aurora’s</persName> rush-light melted now
                                away</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per"><persName type="myth">Aurora</persName>’s rush-light
                                melted now away</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Before the flambeau of the God of Day,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Before the flambeau of the God of Day,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Whose broad unwelcome glare o’er house tops
                                seen,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Whose broad unwelcome glare o’er house tops seen,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Tips <persName type="literary">Betty</persName>’s
                                casement with refulgent sheen,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Tips <persName type="literary">Betty</persName>’s
                                casement with refulgent sheen,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">And calls young <persName type="literary"
                                    >Barnwell</persName> from her brawny arms,<note place="bottom"
                                    resp="ed">This is potentially a reference to the play <title
                                        level="m">The London Merchant</title>, written by George
                                    Lillo and first performed in 1731. It is a tragedy that centres
                                    around the middle class; Barnwell, an apprentice, becomes
                                    involved with a prostitute, and then steals from, and eventually
                                    murders, his master. Although the prostitute in the play is not
                                    named Betty, Betty Careless was a well-known prostitute of the
                                    18th century. For more information, see the British Museum
                                    website, and the <title level="m">Encyclopedia
                                        Britannica</title>.</note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">And calls young <persName type="literary"
                                    >Barnwell</persName> from her brawny arms,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">To ‘scape, unseen, thro’ gutters from her
                                charms,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">To ‘scape, unseen, thro’ gutters from her charms,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Just time enough to let his master in,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Just time enough to let his master in,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Reeling to business from the tavern’s din.</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Reeling to business from the tavern’s din.</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">—Now bakers, on their dough-troughs yawn in
                                state,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">—Now bakers, on their dough-troughs yawn in state,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Damn the assize, and shrink the destin’d weight;</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Damn the assize, and shrink the destin’d weight;</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">The midnight robber skulking hides his head,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">The midnight robber skulking hides his head,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">And unplied trulls steal pennyless to bed;</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">And unplied trulls steal pennyless to bed;</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <pb type="#Per" n="313"/>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">While <name type="occupation">milk-maids</name> haste
                                to <name type="place">Islington</name>, whose stream</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">While <name type="occupation">milk-maids</name> haste to
                                    <name type="place">Islington</name>, whose stream</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Mingles with milk to furnish
                                    <placeName>London</placeName> cream;</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Mingles with milk to furnish
                                    <placeName>London</placeName> cream;</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">—Now sprightly <placeName>Billingsgate</placeName> is
                                just awake,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">—Now sprightly <placeName>Billingsgate</placeName> is
                                just awake,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">And the throng’d Nereids their stations take:</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">And the throng’d Nereids their stations take:</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Sweet sound their treble pipes; each accent hung</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Sweet sound their treble pipes; each accent hung</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">With Classic graces of the vulgar tongue;</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">With Classic graces of the vulgar tongue;</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">While <placeName>Covent Garden</placeName> echoes back
                                the strain;</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">While <placeName>Covent Garden</placeName> echoes back
                                the strain;</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Where throng the pastoral nymph and rural swain</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Where throng the pastoral nymph and rural swain</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">From Putney’s, Battersea’s, and Peckham’s plain;</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">From Putney’s, Battersea’s, and Peckham’s plain;</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Those Nymphs and Swains, whose rural Eclogues
                                sweet</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Those Nymphs and Swains, whose rural Eclogues
                                sweet</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Have oft made vocal <name type="occupation"
                                    >Carpenter</name>’s retreat—</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Have oft made vocal <name type="occupation"
                                    >Carpenter</name>’s retreat—</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Who knows not <name type="occupation"
                                >Carpenter</name>’s? whose early doors</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Who knows not <name type="occupation"
                                >Carpenter</name>’s? whose early doors</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Ope with the dawn for <name type="occupation"
                                    >hucksters</name>, <name type="occupation">thieves</name>, and
                                    <name type="occupation">whores</name>,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Ope with the dawn for <name type="occupation"
                                    >hucksters</name>, <name type="occupation">thieves</name>, and
                                    <name type="occupation">whores</name>,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Rooks who with E.O. chace the midnight gloom,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Rooks who with E.O. chace the midnight gloom,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">And poor gull’d Pigeons stripp’d of every plume;</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">And poor gull’d Pigeons stripp’d of every plume;</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">While jilts, culls, bullies, mingle with the
                                throng,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">While jilts, culls, bullies, mingle with the
                                throng,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Pour the loud curse, and belch the reeling song.</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Pour the loud curse, and belch the reeling song.</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">To these responsive, what blithe sounds arise!</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">To these responsive, what blithe sounds arise!</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Bid shops unfold, and house maids rub their
                                eyes!</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Bid shops unfold, and house maids rub their eyes!</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd"><q>Primroses!</q>&#32; <q>Dust O!</q>&#32;
                                    <q>Lavender!</q>&#32; <q>Old Clothes!</q></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per"><q>Primroses!</q>
                                <q>Dust O!</q>
                                <q>Lavender!</q>
                                <q>Old Clothes!</q></rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">And <q>Water Cresses!</q> banish dull repose;</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">And <q>Water Cresses!</q> banish dull repose;</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd"><q>Brick Dust!</q>&#32; <q>Sweep Soot O!</q> on the
                                breezes swim</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per"><q>Brick Dust!</q>
                                <q>Sweep Soot O!</q> on the breezes swim</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">And waft from street to street the matin hymn;</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">And waft from street to street the matin hymn;</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">While, in full chorus to the jocund lay,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">While, in full chorus to the jocund lay,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Carts rattle, <name type="occupation">drivers</name>
                                swear, and asses bray!—</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Carts rattle, <name type="occupation">drivers</name>
                                swear, and asses bray!—</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l rend="indent">
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">But dead to this blithe chorus of the morn</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">But dead to this blithe chorus of the morn</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Turns purse-proud Grandeur with an idle yawn,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Turns purse-proud Grandeur with an idle yawn,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Bent to renew once more, in flattering dreams,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Bent to renew once more, in flattering dreams,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">His Dissipations or ambitious schemes.</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">His Dissipations or ambitious schemes.</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l rend="indent">
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">New forest ‘closures sweeten Rose’s sleep,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">New forest ‘closures sweeten Rose’s sleep,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">And <persName>Smith</persName>’s damn’d verdict from
                                his memory keep,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">And <persName>Smith</persName>’s damn’d verdict from his
                                memory keep,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">In <persName>Pitt</persName>’s bright fancy bolder
                                hopes arise—</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">In <persName>Pitt</persName>’s bright fancy bolder hopes
                                arise—</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Unbounded sway, and general excise;</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Unbounded sway, and general excise;</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Confiding Senates, Camps of Observation,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Confiding Senates, Camps of Observation,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">To crush enquiry, and dragoon the nation,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">To crush enquiry, and dragoon the nation,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Navies and armaments, at
                                    <placeName>Britain</placeName>’s cost,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Navies and armaments, at
                                <placeName>Britain</placeName>’s cost,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Foredoom’d to gain—of Patronage a host;—<note
                                    place="bottom" resp="ed">William Pitt (1759-1806), a British
                                    prime minister, was one of Thelwall’s political enemies, and,
                                    along with Burke, a chief object of his satire. Thelwall
                                    references Pitt’s augmenting of troops and taxes in 1793 to
                                    support the British allies in the war against
                                France.</note></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Foredoom’d to gain—of Patronage a host;—</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Foredoom’d to crush, (if Heaven their purpose
                                aid)</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Foredoom’d to crush, (if Heaven their purpose aid)</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">The impious crew who Rights of King’s invade.</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">The impious crew who Rights of King’s invade.</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l rend="indent">
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">For Dreams like these thrice strives Dundas in
                                vain,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">For Dreams like these thrice strives Dundas in
                                vain,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">While whip-gall’d Afric clanks the lengthen’d
                                chain,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">While whip-gall’d Afric clanks the lengthen’d
                                chain,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">And with fierce rage the wretch’s bosom rends,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">And with fierce rage the wretch’s bosom rends,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Who damn’d her cause by joining with her
                                friends.</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Who damn’d her cause by joining with her friends.</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Thrice turns he round and sleeps; and thrice
                                arise</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Thrice turns he round and sleeps; and thrice arise</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <pb type="#Per" n="314"/>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Grim hedious Spectres to his haggard eyes,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Grim hedious Spectres to his haggard eyes,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Shrieking aloud “No more expect repose,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Shrieking aloud “No more expect repose,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd"><said>Till slow the guilty eighteenth Century
                                    close.</said></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per"><said>Till slow the guilty eighteenth Century
                                    close.</said></rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Again he turns. His country’s curses swell</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Again he turns. His country’s curses swell</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Thick in his ears and while the hedious swell</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Thick in his ears and while the hedious swell</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Harrows his soul, the gibbet rears elate,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Harrows his soul, the gibbet rears elate,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">And burning effigies foretel his fate,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">And burning effigies foretel his fate,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Tho’ lawless magistrates wage Civil war</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Tho’ lawless magistrates wage Civil war</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">To save with British blood the men of straw.</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">To save with British blood the men of straw.</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Great Mammon Nimrod now, as when awake,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Great Mammon Nimrod now, as when awake,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Creeps to his store, a fond, fond glance to
                                take;</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Creeps to his store, a fond, fond glance to take;</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Laughs at an o’ertax’d people’s groans, and
                                cries,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Laughs at an o’ertax’d people’s groans, and cries,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">With goat-like mouth, and idiot glaring eyes,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">With goat-like mouth, and idiot glaring eyes,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">While, pile on pile, his seventeen millions
                                swell,</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">While, pile on pile, his seventeen millions swell,</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd"><q>What—what—what—what—don’t all—all things go
                                    well;</q></lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per"><q>What—what—what—what—don’t all—all things go
                                well;</q></rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Then, (tho’ his purblind eyes, disloyal, fail</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Then, (tho’ his purblind eyes, disloyal, fail</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">To shew the difference ‘twixt the mane and tail)</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">To shew the difference ‘twixt the mane and tail)</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Calls for his horse, and with heroic grace</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Calls for his horse, and with heroic grace</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <app>
                            <lem wit="#DigEd">Braves all the pleasing dangers of the chace.</lem>
                            <rdg wit="#Per">Braves all the pleasing dangers of the chace.</rdg>
                        </app>
                    </l>
                </lg>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="fragments">
                <head resp="Editor">Fragments<note place="bottom" resp="ed">These fragments appear
                        in <title level="m">P</title> surrounded by discussion of Sylvanus’ plans
                        for the rest of the poem. While the poem itself is unfinished, the second
                        fragment is almost certainly a piece of what might have become the final
                        Canto, and thus it serves as a fitting conclusion for the poem while also
                        harkening back to the closing couplets of the Proposition.</note></head>
                <div type="I">
                    <head resp="Editor">I</head>
                    <lg>
                        <l>
                            <app>
                                <lem wit="#DigEd">By his Herculean side sweet handmaid glows,<note
                                        place="bottom" resp="ed">Spelling of
                                            <quote>Herculean</quote> corrected from
                                            <quote>herculian.</quote></note></lem>
                                <rdg wit="#Per">By his herculian side sweet handmaid glows,</rdg>
                            </app>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <app>
                                <lem wit="#DigEd">Fair <persName type="mythological"
                                    >Hebe</persName>, blushing like a full blown Rose</lem>
                                <rdg wit="#Per">Fair <persName type="mythological">Hebe</persName>,
                                    blushing like a full blown Rose</rdg>
                            </app>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <app>
                                <lem wit="#DigEd">That full blown Rose, whose shape she once
                                    assum’d,</lem>
                                <rdg wit="#Per">That full blown Rose, whose shape she once
                                    assum’d,</rdg>
                            </app>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <app>
                                <lem wit="#DigEd">And bright on <placeName>Covent Garden</placeName>
                                    Hustings bloom’d,</lem>
                                <rdg wit="#Per">And bright on <placeName>Covent Garden</placeName>
                                    Hustings bloom’d,</rdg>
                            </app>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <app>
                                <lem wit="#DigEd">Till <name type="mythological">Argos</name> eyes
                                    detect the treacherous thorn,</lem>
                                <rdg wit="#Per">Till <name type="mythological">Argos</name> eyes
                                    detect the treacherous thorn,</rdg>
                            </app>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <app>
                                <lem wit="#DigEd">To goad fair Freedom’s side malignant worn;</lem>
                                <rdg wit="#Per">To goad fair Freedom’s side malignant worn;</rdg>
                            </app>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <app>
                                <lem wit="#DigEd">At which, abash’d, she fled the light of
                                    Day,</lem>
                                <rdg wit="#Per">At which, abash’d, she fled the light of Day,</rdg>
                            </app>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <app>
                                <lem wit="#DigEd">And hid beneath <persName type="mythological"
                                        >Minerva</persName>’s buckler lay.—</lem>
                                <rdg wit="#Per">And hid beneath <persName type="mythological"
                                        >Minerva</persName>’s buckler lay.—</rdg>
                            </app>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                </div>
                <div type="II">
                    <head>II</head>
                    <lg>
                        <l>
                            <app>
                                <lem wit="#DigEd">Thus fled the types when thro’ the troubled
                                    sky</lem>
                                <rdg wit="#Per">Thus fled the types when thro’ the troubled
                                    sky</rdg>
                            </app>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <app>
                                <lem wit="#DigEd">Dread thundering <persName type="mythological"
                                        >Jove</persName> resistless beam’d on high;</lem>
                                <rdg wit="#Per">Dread thundering <persName type="mythological"
                                        >Jove</persName> resistless beam’d on high;</rdg>
                            </app>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <app>
                                <lem wit="#DigEd">His awful wig of lightest hair around</lem>
                                <rdg wit="#Per">His awful wig of lightest hair around</rdg>
                            </app>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <app>
                                <lem wit="#DigEd">A star-gem’d diadem imperial frown’d,</lem>
                                <rdg wit="#Per">A star-gem’d diadem imperial frown’d,</rdg>
                            </app>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <app>
                                <lem wit="#DigEd">In front of which bright beam’d the radiant
                                    stone,</lem>
                                <rdg wit="#Per">In front of which bright beam’d the radiant
                                    stone,</rdg>
                            </app>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <app>
                                <lem wit="#DigEd">An eastern Nabob lately call’d his own;</lem>
                                <rdg wit="#Per">An eastern Nabob lately call’d his own;</rdg>
                            </app>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <app>
                                <lem wit="#DigEd">Till at the altar of the thundering God,</lem>
                                <rdg wit="#Per">Till at the altar of the thundering God,</rdg>
                            </app>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <app>
                                <lem wit="#DigEd">In supplication of his guardian nod,</lem>
                                <rdg wit="#Per">In supplication of his guardian nod,</rdg>
                            </app>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <app>
                                <lem wit="#DigEd">Submiss ‘twas offer’d. <persName
                                        type="mythological">Jove</persName>, as Gods are us’d,</lem>
                                <rdg wit="#Per">Submiss ‘twas offer’d. <persName type="mythological"
                                        >Jove</persName>, as Gods are us’d,</rdg>
                            </app>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <app>
                                <lem wit="#DigEd">Receiv’d the offering, but the pray’r
                                    refus’d.</lem>
                                <rdg wit="#Per">Receiv’d the offering, but the pray’r refus’d.</rdg>
                            </app>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <app>
                                <lem wit="#DigEd">—Dread was his presence; in his red right
                                    hand,</lem>
                                <rdg wit="#Per">—Dread was his presence; in his red right
                                    hand,</rdg>
                            </app>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <app>
                                <lem wit="#DigEd">Prepar’d to vindicate his high command,</lem>
                                <rdg wit="#Per">Prepar’d to vindicate his high command,</rdg>
                            </app>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <app>
                                <lem wit="#DigEd">He grasps those thunders Alphabeta’s care</lem>
                                <rdg wit="#Per">He grasps those thunders Alphabeta’s care</rdg>
                            </app>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <app>
                                <lem wit="#DigEd">Had forg’d the terrors of his will to bear.</lem>
                                <rdg wit="#Per">Had forg’d the terrors of his will to bear.</rdg>
                            </app>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <app>
                                <lem wit="#DigEd">Now when the adverse conflict he espies,</lem>
                                <rdg wit="#Per">Now when the adverse conflict he espies,</rdg>
                            </app>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <app>
                                <lem wit="#DigEd">With face of scarlet and grey rolling eyes,</lem>
                                <rdg wit="#Per">With face of scarlet and grey rolling eyes,</rdg>
                            </app>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <app>
                                <lem wit="#DigEd">Sees types on types dispers’d, dismay’d, or
                                    slain,</lem>
                                <rdg wit="#Per">Sees types on types dispers’d, dismay’d, or
                                    slain,</rdg>
                            </app>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <app>
                                <lem wit="#DigEd">And <persName type="historical">Boydell</persName>
                                    raging thro’ the ensanguin’d plain:<note place="bottom"
                                        resp="ed">Spelling of <q>Boydell</q> corrected from
                                            <quote>Boydel.</quote></note></lem>
                                <rdg wit="#Per">And <persName type="historical">Boydel</persName>
                                    raging thro’ the ensanguin’d plain:</rdg>
                            </app>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <app>
                                <lem wit="#DigEd">Indignant wrath and keen resentment rise,</lem>
                                <rdg wit="#Per">Indignant wrath and keen resentment rise,</rdg>
                            </app>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <app>
                                <lem wit="#DigEd">And, What! what! what! with thick short speech, he
                                    cries;</lem>
                                <rdg wit="#Per">And, What! what! what! with thick short speech, he
                                    cries;</rdg>
                            </app>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <app>
                                <lem wit="#DigEd">But could no more, for choler choak’d his
                                    tongue,</lem>
                                <rdg wit="#Per">But could no more, for choler choak’d his
                                    tongue,</rdg>
                            </app>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <app>
                                <lem wit="#DigEd">And what! what! what! thro’ heaven’s wide concave
                                    rung.</lem>
                                <rdg wit="#Per">And what! what! what! thro’ heaven’s wide concave
                                    rung.</rdg>
                            </app>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <app>
                                <lem wit="#DigEd">Scar’d Moorfields shakes, clouds tremble as they
                                    roll,</lem>
                                <rdg wit="#Per">Scar’d Moorfields shakes, clouds tremble as they
                                    roll,</rdg>
                            </app>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <app>
                                <lem wit="#DigEd">Fork’d lightnings fly, big angry thunders
                                    growl,</lem>
                                <rdg wit="#Per">Fork’d lightnings fly, big angry thunders
                                    growl,</rdg>
                            </app>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <app>
                                <lem wit="#DigEd">And what! what! what! chills every victor’s
                                    soul.</lem>
                                <rdg wit="#Per">And what! what! what! chills every victor’s
                                    soul.</rdg>
                            </app>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <app>
                                <lem wit="#DigEd">Scar’d <persName type="historical"
                                        >Boydell</persName> flies, Woodmason’s puff expires,</lem>
                                <rdg wit="#Per">Scar’d <persName type="historical"
                                        >Boydell</persName> flies, Woodmason’s puff expires,</rdg>
                            </app>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <app>
                                <lem wit="#DigEd">And e’en thy deamon, <persName type="historical"
                                        >Opie</persName>, slow retires,<note place="bottom"
                                        resp="ed">John Opie (1761-1807) was a painter popular for
                                        his portraits and historical works.</note></lem>
                                <rdg wit="#Per">And e’en thy deamon, <persName type="historical"
                                        >Opie</persName>, slow retires,</rdg>
                            </app>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <app>
                                <lem wit="#DigEd"><persName type="mythological">Jove</persName>
                                    throws his bolts thick scatter’d o’er the ground,</lem>
                                <rdg wit="#Per"><persName type="mythological">Jove</persName> throws
                                    his bolts thick scatter’d o’er the ground,</rdg>
                            </app>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <app>
                                <lem wit="#DigEd">And brands of heavenly fury blaze around.</lem>
                                <rdg wit="#Per">And brands of heavenly fury blaze around.</rdg>
                            </app>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <app>
                                <lem wit="#DigEd">Thro’ <name type="place">Britain</name>’s empire
                                    spreads the sacred ire,</lem>
                                <rdg wit="#Per">Thro’ <name type="place">Britain</name>’s empire
                                    spreads the sacred ire,</rdg>
                            </app>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <app>
                                <lem wit="#DigEd">Prints every gate-house, post, and village
                                    spire,</lem>
                                <rdg wit="#Per">Prints every gate-house, post, and village
                                    spire,</rdg>
                            </app>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <app>
                                <lem wit="#DigEd">Whence gazing Rustics, wondering what is
                                    meant,</lem>
                                <rdg wit="#Per">Whence gazing Rustics, wondering what is
                                    meant,</rdg>
                            </app>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <app>
                                <lem wit="#DigEd">Read dreadful words of treason, discontent,</lem>
                                <rdg wit="#Per">Read dreadful words of treason, discontent,</rdg>
                            </app>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <app>
                                <lem wit="#DigEd">Sedition rumour’d, enemies to peace,</lem>
                                <rdg wit="#Per">Sedition rumour’d, enemies to peace,</rdg>
                            </app>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <app>
                                <lem wit="#DigEd">And dread commands, <hi rend="italics">that
                                        Reason’s voice should cease</hi>.</lem>
                                <rdg wit="#Per">And dread commands, <hi rend="italics">that Reason’s
                                        voice should cease</hi>.</rdg>
                            </app>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Broadhead, Alex. <title level="a">The Della Cruscans: A Survey of the
                            Criticism and Resources, 1956–2009.</title>
                        <title level="j">Literature Compass</title>, vol. 7, no. 7, 2010, pp.
                        577–585.</bibl>
                    <bibl><title level="a">Billingsgate Market from Microcosm of London.</title>
                        British Library.
                        https://www.bl.uk/collection-items/illustration-of-billingsgate-market#</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bugg, John. <title level="a">Close Confinement: John Thelwall and the
                            Romantic Prison.</title>
                        <title level="j">European Romantic Review</title>, vol. 20, no. 1, 2009, pp.
                        37-56.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Claeys, Gregory. <title level="m">The French Revolution Debate in Britain:
                            The Origins of Modern Politics</title>. Palgrave Macmillan, 2007.</bibl>
                    <bibl>---, editor. <title level="m">The Politics of English Jacobinism: Writings
                            of John Thelwall</title>. Penn State UP, 1995.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Grose, Francis. <title level="m">1811 Dictionary of the Vulgar
                            Tongue</title>. Project Gutenburg,
                        http://www.gutenberg.org/cache/epub/5402/pg5402-images.html.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Mee, Jon. <title level="m">Print, Publicity, and Popular Radicalism in the
                            1790’s: The Laurel of Liberty</title>. Cambridge University Press,
                        2016.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Roe, Nicholas. <title level="a">Thelwall, John (1764–1834), political
                            reformer and lecturer.</title>
                        <title level="m">Oxford Dictionary of National Biography</title>. October
                        04, 2012. Oxford UP. Date of access 11 Dec. 2018,
                        http://www.oxforddnb.com.ezproxy.library.dal.ca/view/10.1093/ref:odnb/9780198614128.001.0001/odnb-9780198614128-e-27167</bibl>
                    <bibl>Russell, Gillian. <title level="a">Burke’s Dagger: Theatricality, Politics
                            and Print Culture in the 1790s.</title>
                        <title level="m">British Journal for Eighteenth-Century Studies</title>,
                        vol. 20, 1997, pp. 1-16.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Scrivener, Michael. <title level="m">Poetry and Reform</title>. Wayne
                        State University Press, 1992.</bibl>
                    <bibl>---. <title level="m">Seditious Allegories: John Thelwall and Jacobin
                            Writing</title>. Penn State UP, 2001.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Thelwall, John. <title level="m">The Peripatetic</title>. Edited by Judith
                        Thompson, Wayne State UP, 2001.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Thompson, Judith. <title level="a">Introduction.</title>
                        <title level="m"> The Peripatetic</title>, Wayne State UP, 2001.</bibl>
                    <bibl>---. <title level="a">From Forum to Repository: A Case Study in Romantic
                            Cultural Geography.</title>
                        <title level="j">European Romantic Review</title>, vol. 15, no. 2, 2004, pp.
                        177–191.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
