<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><?xml-model href="http://ebeshero.github.io/MRMValidate.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title xml:id="MRM2014">Letter to <persName>Mary Webb</persName>, <date when="1819-01-10">January 10, 1819</date></title><author ref="#MRM">Mary Russell Mitford</author><editor ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</editor><sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford Project</orgName></sponsor><sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor><sponsor>Pittsburgh Supercomputing Center</sponsor><principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal><respStmt><resp>Transcription and coding by</resp><persName ref="#ncl">Natalie LoRusso</persName><persName ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Date last checked: <date when="2015-10-12">2015-10-12</date><!-- updated header, fixing tags. LMW -->
                  Proofing and corrections by</resp><persName ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</persName></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>First digital edition in TEI, date: <date when="2014-10-05">5 October 2014</date>. P5.</edition><respStmt><resp>Edition made with help from photos taken by</resp><orgName>Digital Mitford editors</orgName></respStmt><respStmt><orgName>Digital Mitford</orgName><resp> photo files: <idno>DSCF8746-4.jpg, DSCF8747-1.jpg, DSCF8748-2.jpg, DSCF8750-3.jpg,DSCF8752-5.jpg, DSCF8753-6.jpg, DSCF8754-7.jpg, DSCF8755-8.jpg</idno></resp></respStmt></editionStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority><pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace><date>2013</date><availability><p>Reproduced by courtesy of the <orgName ref="#ReadingCL">Reading Central Library</orgName>.</p><licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                  License</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Mitford Letters: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><repository ref="#ReadingCL">Reading Central Library</repository><collection>The letters of Mary Russell Mitford, vol. 4, 1819-1823</collection><idno><!--LMW/EBB: No RCL shelfmark; in folder of loose files. --></idno></msIdentifier><head>Letter from Mary Russell Mitford to Mary Webb, <date when="1819-01-10">1819 January 10</date>.</head><physDesc><objectDesc><supportDesc><support><p>Two sheets of folio <material>paper</material>, eight surfaces photographed.</p></support><condition><p>Sheet (pages seven and eight) torn on right edge where wax seal was removed.</p></condition></supportDesc></objectDesc><sealDesc><p>Black wax seal, remnants of black wax adhered elsewhere on page seven.</p></sealDesc></physDesc></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><handNotes><handNote corresp="#pencil" medium="pencil"> Someone, apparently other than Mitford, perhaps cataloging letters and describing them, who left grey pencil marks and numbered her letters now in the Reading Central Library's collection. This letter has a date attributed: [10 Jan. 1819] underneath the heading, "Bertram House Sunday."
           </handNote></handNotes></profileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><p>Mitford’s spelling and punctuation are retained, except where a word is split at the end of a line and the beginning of the next in the manuscript. Where Mitford’s spelling and hyphenation of words deviates from the standard, in order to facilitate searching we are using the TEI elements “choice," “sic," and “reg" to encode both Mitford’s spelling and the regular international standard of Oxford English spelling, following the first listed spelling in the Oxford English Dictionary. The long s and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="letter"><opener><dateline><name type="place">Bertram House</name><date when="1819-01-10">Sunday</date>. <!--lmw:  Checked perpetual calendar.  1-10 was a Sunday--><add hand="#pencil"><date when="1819-01-10">[10 Jan. 1819]</date></add></dateline></opener><p>Pray, my very dear Friends, which of us has a right to be angry for not having heard yesterday? You? or I? Or neither? Solve me this knotty point. I am sure there is cause for anger some where--&amp; I rather think that you <persName ref="#Webb_Mary_younger">Mary</persName> have reason good to be in a passion for my not coming to see you--&amp; that I have an equal right to be in a fury for not getting a note--in short that every body has cause to <metamark rend="caret" place="below" function="insertion"/><add place="above">be</add> angry--except <persName ref="#Webb_Eliza">Miss Eliza</persName>--who not being at all in the habit of using it will not mind our taking away her privilege. So <persName ref="#Webb_Mary_younger">Mary</persName>, My Dear, you &amp; I will be properly angry--a little gentle anger which serves like a glass of Champagne this cold weather to keep us warm &amp; make us laugh &amp; blush--you &amp; I will be angry &amp; then we will make it up in the customary formula of an apologizing letter <foreign xml:lang="fr">de part &amp; d'autre</foreign><note resp="#ncl">French for 'on each side.'</note>. First of all for me, I have <choice><sic>staid</sic><reg resp="#lmw">stayed</reg></choice>away much against my will I assure you--All the week till <date when="1819-01-09">Saturday</date>, I had so bad a cold that <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</persName> would not let me stir--then <date when="1819-01-09">Saturday</date>--yesterday I mean--was <date when="1819-01-09">Saturday</date> you know--&amp; the horrible Bench and so forth--&amp; today was so illnatured as to rain--&amp; tomorrow <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</persName> is going coursing--&amp; <date when="1819-01-12">Tuesday</date> the <rs type="event">Quarter Sessions</rs> deuce take them! &amp; <date when="1819-01-13">Wednesday</date> &amp; the latter end of the week he expects to be going to <placeName ref="#London_city">Town</placeName>--so <emph rend="underline">I must</emph> write to beg pardon--&amp; <emph rend="underline">you must</emph> write to forgive--write &amp; bring me your letter yourself, my own dear little <persName ref="#Sevigne_Mad">Madame de Sévigné</persName>--won't you? Can't you? It seems such an age since I have seen you--&amp; <q>since the mountain cannot come to <persName ref="#Mahomet">Mahomet</persName><persName ref="#Mahomet">Mahomet</persName> should come to the Mountain</q>--I have an infinite respect for old proverbs--especially when they make for my purpose. See that you obey this one.</p><p>I take it for granted, my dear Friend, that <persName ref="#Webb_Eliza">Eliza</persName> gave you all the particulars of the Ball--We wanted you very much indeed--which was a proof that the ball was worth going to. It had indeed great elegance, great sociability, a delightful host, an enchanting hostess--&amp; above all it had <persName ref="#Crowther_Mr">Mr. Crowther</persName>. This man kept me alive &amp; <emph rend="underline">lifelich</emph> (as old <persName ref="#Chaucer">Chaucer</persName> says) all the evening. Oh my dear <persName ref="#Webb_Mary_younger">Mary</persName> I would give a great deal that you could see him--You have never seen anything like him--never unless you have seen a wasp in a Solar Microscope (an insect turned into a monster)--or unless you can imagine a <placeName ref="#Brobdingnag">Brobdingnagian</placeName> Hourglass <note resp="#ncl">Reference to <placeName ref="#Brobdingnag">Brobdingnag</placeName>, fictional land of giants in <title ref="#GulliversTr_JS">Swift's Gulliver's Travels</title>.</note>--but neither wasp nor hourglass are small enough in the waist for this Dandy--this Exquisite--I have all my life had a great respect for the mechanical inventions of this age, but nothing that I have ever seen has given me such an idea of the power of machinery--not your <persName ref="#Webb_James">Father</persName>'s melting machine--not the <placeName ref="#Portsmouth_Blockhouses">Portsmouth Blockhouses</placeName>--not the <placeName ref="#Mint_new">new Mint</placeName>--as that wonderful effort of mechanism by which those ribs are endued in those stays. I do think he must have had one or two ribs broken on each side to make them lie closer. The compression would be incredible without some such expedient. But I am unjust in talking so much of the stays when it is the Altogether that is so perfect. <choice><sic>Trowsers,</sic><reg resp="#lmw">Trousers,</reg></choice> Coat, handkerchief, shirt collar, head inside &amp; out, all were in exact keeping--all belonged to those inimitable stays &amp; could not have belonged to <choice><sic>any thing</sic><reg resp="#lmw">anything</reg></choice> else. I never took such a fancy to <choice><sic>any thing</sic><reg resp="#lmw">anything</reg></choice>in my Life--I have seen nothing at all equal to it--Since <persName ref="#Liston_John">Liston</persName> in <persName ref="#Grizzle_Lord">Lord Grizzel</persName><note resp="#lmw"><persName ref="#Liston_John">John Liston</persName> played <persName ref="#Grizzle_Lord">Lord Grizzle</persName> in the pantomime <title ref="#TomThumb_OHaraAdpt">Tom Thumb</title> at the <placeName ref="#Haymarket_Theatre">Haymarket</placeName> in <date when="1810">1810</date>. <persName ref="#Lamb_Chas">Lamb</persName> and <persName ref="#Hazlitt_Wm">Hazlitt</persName> mention <persName ref="#Liston_John">Liston</persName> in this role. More usually spelled Grizzle. In <persName ref="#Lamb_Chas">Charles Lamb</persName>'s essay, "The New Style of Acting," he writes:  "For a piece of pure drollery, Liston's Lord Grizzle has not competitor." <persName ref="#Hazlitt_Wm">Hazlitt</persName> also mentions <persName ref="#Liston_John">Liston</persName> in this role in <title ref="#LecComic_WHaz">Lectures on the English Comic Writers</title>.</note>--It was quite the charm of the evening to me at least, such a charm as a top is to a schoolboy--or a hoop--or as my grave cat <persName ref="#Selim_pet">Selim</persName> is to my frisky puppy <persName ref="#Miranda_pet">Miranda</persName>. I am sorry to say the admiration was by no means mutual. <pb n="3"/>The Dandy was an ungrateful Dandy--&amp; <gap reason="illegible" quantity="1" unit="word"/><unclear/> away at the sound of my voice just as <persName ref="#Mossy_pet">Mossy</persName> (begging <persName ref="#Mossy_pet">Mossy</persName>'s pardon for the comparison) flies off at the sight of our dog-hating cook. He told a discreet friend who told me that he had an "idea" (a very bold assertion by the bye) "an idea that I was Blue<emph rend="underline">ish</emph>."--Mr. Dandy Good Night--Thank you for a great deal of the best thing in the world--a great deal of laughter. Tell dear <persName ref="#Webb_Eliza">Eliza</persName> that I wished for her as well as for you all <date when="1819-01-08">Friday</date> &amp; almost all <date when="1819-01-09">Saturday</date>. <date when="1819-01-08">Friday</date> was a delightful day--<persName ref="#Dickinson_Charles">Mr. D.</persName> was just as if nothing had happened--<persName ref="#Dickinson_Mrs">Mrs. Dickinson</persName> more than usually charming--languid gentle delicate tender like <name ref="#woodsorrel">wood sorrel</name>, or <name ref="#lily_valley">lilies of the valley</name> so drooping &amp; so sweet--only just enough alive to sing more sweetly than I ever heard even her that enchanting song of <persName ref="#Handel">Handel</persName>'s (which <persName ref="#Webb_Eliza">Eliza</persName><emph rend="underline">must</emph> learn) <title corresp="#Whereer_Handel">"Where'er you walk."</title>--In the evening we had a good deal of literature, English &amp; Italian. <persName ref="#Dickinson_Charles">Mr. Dickinson</persName> read me some fine Translations from <persName ref="#Dante">Dante</persName> &amp;c--with one of which I was so charmed as to beg a Copy--to my sorrow. The copy was graciously granted on condition that <emph rend="underline">I</emph> would transcribe it for the Author--to which polite request I of course acceded, quite forgetting that my accomplished friend wrote a fine rapid crabbed learned-looking hand which might pass for Greek or Persian or Arabic just as well as for English. So that I have been obliged to <emph rend="underline">copy</emph> this translation--half from recollection--half from guess--&amp; half from the original Italian. (<persName ref="#Webb_Eliza">Eliza</persName> who is so great an Arithmetician must tell you how I can be divided into three halves by any but an Irish method of Calculation) I have however done it at last &amp; some time or other I will read it you. It is the celebrated Episode of <persName ref="#Ugolino">Count Ugolino</persName> in <persName ref="#Dante">Dante</persName>'s <title ref="#Inferno_Dante">Inferno</title>. Don't imitate <pb n="4"/> the discretion of <persName ref="#Crowther_Mr">Mr. Crowther</persName>'s friend by telling <persName ref="#Dickinson_Mrs">Mrs. Dickinson</persName> when she calls, which I know she intends to do soon, that I can't read her <persName ref="#Dickinson_Charles">husband</persName>'s hand, I entreat you my dear<persName ref="#Webb_Mary_younger">Mary</persName>. On <date when="1819-01-09">Saturday</date> I went with her into <placeName ref="#Reading_city">Reading</placeName> &amp; home to dinner. This is the history of my visit. Ever since I have been at home as quiet as a mouse--reading all day long. First of all I have read <title ref="#Euro_Settlements_in_Am">6 Volumes of <persName ref="#Burke_E">Burke</persName></title>--of which I will have the compassion not to talk at present--you don't want to hear about old pamphlets, old speeches &amp; old American Wars--Then for the second time <persName ref="#Fearon_HB">Mr. Fearon</persName>'s very clever bran new <title ref="#Sketches_of_America">book</title> about <placeName ref="#USA">America</placeName>. I don't know any thing more agreeable than to have one's preconceived notions of a place or people confined by a good citable authority--a matter of fact authority who brings one in a tangible shape good reasons for old prejudices. This is the pleasure <persName ref="#Fearon_HB">Mr. Fearon</persName> has given me. I always defended <placeName ref="#USA">America</placeName> &amp; the <orgName ref="#Americans">Americans</orgName> (all but <persName ref="#Franklin_Ben">Franklin</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#Washington_Geo">Washington</persName>) without very well knowing why--except that in that fair &amp; fresh &amp; beautiful world with every thing to inspire &amp; incite them to excellence in Art &amp; Nature--they had done nothing &amp; they were nothing. <persName ref="#Fearon_HB">Mr. Fearon</persName> has now added positive to these negative proofs &amp; has fairly set them forth as the most boasting, vainglorious, ignorant, trumpery, second-hand, pawnbrokers-shop--sort of people that ever crept on the face of the earth. His book is invaluable &amp; an antidote to the poison of <persName ref="#Birkbeck_M">Mr. Birkbeck</persName>'s beautifully written but most deceitful works--an antidote the more powerful &amp; the more certain as coming from a friend to liberty &amp; an admirer of the republican form of Government. I think you would like these <title ref="#Sketches_of_America">Sketches of America</title>--&amp; I am sure you would like a book which I have just finished--<title ref="#NightmareAbbey">Nightmare Abbey</title>. By far <pb n="5"/> the best of <persName ref="#Peacock_TL">Mr. Peacock</persName>'s works--worth all his prose &amp; all his poetry <title ref="#Melincourt">Melincourt</title> &amp; <title ref="#Rhododaphne">Rhododaphne</title> included--Never was a more cheerful &amp; amicable piece of persiflage--full of laughing raillerie &amp; smiling philosophy--Notwithstanding the gloomy title <title ref="#NightmareAbbey">Nightmare Abbey</title> is the most sunshiny book I have met with this many a day. It is a very clever attack upon mystical metaphysics &amp; misanthropical poetry (Deuce take <persName ref="#Peacock_TL">Mr. Peacock</persName> for putting me to hard words!) and knocks them both completely down in the persons of my poor dear Friend <persName ref="#Coleridge_ST">Mr. Coleridge</persName> (<del rend="squiggles" quantity="1" unit="chars"><unclear/></del> alias <persName ref="#Flosky">Mr. Flosky</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#Byron">Lord Byron</persName>--not only knocks them down but dances on them being down, as his unruly subjects did on poor <persName ref="#Sancho_Panza">Sancho</persName> in the <placeName ref="#Island_Barataria">Island of Barataria</placeName>. Nothing was ever better managed than the way in which <persName ref="#Peacock_TL">Mr. Peacock</persName> contrives to put divers stanzas of <title ref="#ChildeHaroldsPil">Childe Harolde</title> done into prose, into the Mouth of <persName ref="#Cypress_Mr">Mr. Cypress</persName>, the <persName ref="#Byron">Lord Byron</persName> of the story. The book has another great merit. It is short.--Well then I have had a pretty present in the book way--a present from dear dear <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</persName>--he who gives me all that I wish for as if by intuition--for I am sure I never hinted at it to him or anyone--This present is the <title ref="#Lit_Pocket_Bk">Literary Pocket Book</title>--Have you seen one of them my dear <persName ref="#Webb_Mary_younger">Mary</persName>?  It is edited I believe by <persName ref="#Hunt">Leigh Hunt</persName>--certainly the greater part is written by him--&amp; exceedingly well written. I have never seen anything of the sort so well executed. First of all there is a Naturalist's Calendar--very graceful &amp; beautiful--though not quite extensive enough for the Title--It should rather have been called the Florist's Calendar--&amp; even then it would seem a little Suburbian--rather <placeName>Hampstead-Heath</placeName>ish--but very pretty nevertheless. Then in the common pocket book part, the blank pages with months <pb n="6"/> &amp; weeks &amp; days, there are occasional notices of birthdays of great men <persName ref="#Bacon">Bacon</persName><persName ref="#Shakespeare">Shakespeare</persName> &amp; so forth which come upon one very pleasantly--Then lists of living Artists Musicians Actors &amp; celebrated Authors--only think of their having left me out!--That Authorial list is very incomplete! Not a word about me!  And my own friends too!  Oh they have no idea that I am "Blue<emph rend="underline">ish</emph>" to borrow my friend the Dandy's phrase.--He would have stuck me at the head of the list. Well these lists in spite of this grand omission are very interesting--&amp; then there is poetry--not quite so good as I expected from <persName ref="#Hunt">Leigh Hunt</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#Keats">John Keats</persName>, but still good enough to stare &amp; wonder how it came in a pocket book. In short, My Dear Love, if your dear <persName ref="#Webb_James">Papa</persName> should be wanting to make you such a present I would recommend him--to make this.--I have lost a literary friend this last week--poor <persName ref="#Brunton_Mary">Mrs. Brunton</persName> the Authoress of <title ref="#Self_Control">Self Control</title> &amp; <title ref="#Discipline">Discipline</title>. Did I ever talk to you about her? If I did, it was probably under the name of <rs type="person" ref="#Brunton_Mary">Mrs. Discipline</rs>--the name by which <persName ref="#Rowden_Fr">Mrs. Rowden</persName> (who disliked <foreign xml:lang="fr">à l'envie</foreign> both her &amp; her works) always used to call her. You are not likely to have admired her Novels which always seemed to me to have almost all the faults that very clever writing can have--preachy--prosy--false to character, to nature, &amp; to passion--yet with occasional flashes of sense &amp; of power which rendered their merits &amp; their faults alike incomprehensible. I liked the lady much better than her books. She was exceedingly robust in mind &amp; person--perhaps in both a little coarse--large boned--dark complexioned--ruddy cheeked--of loud speech &amp; abrupt manner. But there was in all she said point &amp; strength &amp; <emph rend="underline">body</emph>. She was perfectly frank &amp; unaffected, &amp; her very awkwardness had sometimes a grace <pb n="7"/> from its natural &amp; unconscious simplicity. Now that she is dead poor thing I wish I had cultivated her acquaintance more earnestly. I used to meet her at the house of some very clever people in <placeName ref="#Sloane_St">Sloane Street</placeName> where we were both intimate--but I did not like <persName ref="#Brunton_Alexander">her husband</persName> who was exceedingly priggish &amp; parsonic that was one reason, &amp; vanity, which I suppose at the time I might call modesty, was another. She was always very kind &amp; civil to me, but it was perfectly clear that she thought me over-rated and did not care a farthing for me. Besides I never could get over those sermonizing books. You would see that she died in a very distressed way after the birth of a dead <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/><unclear/></del>child the first she had had in a twenty years marriage. She looked near fifty when I used to see her some years ago.</p><p>I was so sorry to miss seeing <persName ref="#Seward_Martha">Martha Seward</persName>--dear sweet girl--If she comes to you again to spend any time pr<gap reason="torn" quantity="2" unit="chars"/><unclear/><supplied resp="lmw">ay</supplied> bring her here.--Did <persName ref="#Webb_Eliza">Miss Eliza</persName> tell you that she met <persName ref="#Parfitt_Jos">young Parfitt (Mr. Joseph)</persName> whom we thought a very fine gentlemanly young man &amp; that he was very attentive to the aforesaid <persName ref="#Webb_Eliza">Miss Eliza</persName>? And that we liked <persName ref="#Parfitt_Sarah">Miss Sarah Parfitt</persName> very much who gave an almost equal specimen of good taste by falling in love with me? Making <persName ref="#Parfitt_Sarah">Miss Sarah</persName> laugh was my charm--I don't know what enchantment <persName ref="#Webb_Eliza">Miss Eliza</persName> put in force with <persName ref="#Parfitt_Jos">Mr. Joseph</persName>--However I have given my consent &amp; I beg my dear <persName ref="#Webb_Mary_younger">Mary</persName>, if you have a dance that <orgName ref="#Parfitt_family">the Parfitt's</orgName> may be asked. I assure you you would not be at all shamed of your brother in law. We met a <persName ref="#Coffin_Mrs">Mrs. Coffin</persName> too whom I liked much--She talked of books with taste &amp; selections <metamark rend="caret" place="below" function="insertion"/><add place="above">with something too of</add> that wide range which is my delight--old books--odd books--rare boooks--I hate <persName ref="#Homer">Homer</persName> who tread only the beaten road of literature marching one by one<metamark rend="caret" place="below" function="insertion"/><add place="above">in the same path</add>like <pb n="8"/>a great brood of full grown geese after an old gander. People should talk of <persName ref="#Walton_I">Isaac Walton</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#Taylor_Jer">Jeremy Taylor</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#Brown_Thos">Sir Thomas Brown</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#Fletcher_John"/>Fletcher &amp; <persName ref="#Froissart">Froissart</persName>&amp; <persName ref="#DeJoinville">de Joinville</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#Pulci">Pulci</persName>--&amp; talk as if they had read the books &amp; not reviews or extracts of them.</p><p>--In the mean time my dear <persName ref="#Webb_Mary_younger">Mary</persName> I am forgetting that you do not like any works that are too voluminous--&amp; that this letter is of a length to startle even partial eyes. I have the grace to pity you for being condemned to read it. Write soon--Come soon--Writing without coming will not do--nor coming without writing. Imitate me in length, my dearest, but not in dullness--A very needless caution! Dullness is not in your power.--Love to all &amp; every body--<persName ref="#Webb_James">Papa</persName>--<persName ref="#Webb_Eliza">Eliza</persName>--<persName ref="#Webb_Mary_elder">Aunt Mary</persName>--<persName ref="#Webb_John">Uncle John</persName>--<persName ref="#Wheeler_Kate">Kate Wheeler</persName>--Love to all &amp; from all.</p><closer>--Ever my very dear Friend most faithfully<choice><sic>your's</sic><reg resp="#lmw">yours</reg></choice><lb/><persName ref="#MRM">M.R. Mitford</persName>.<lb/></closer><closer><address><addrLine>To <persName ref="#Webb_Mary_younger">Miss Webb</persName></addrLine></address></closer></div></body><back><div>
        
 </div></back></text></TEI>