<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><?xml-model href="http://ebeshero.github.io/MRMValidate.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title xml:id="MRM1735">Letter to <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir William Elford</persName>, <date when="1819-02-27">February 27, 1819</date></title><author ref="#MRM">Mary Russell Mitford</author><editor ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</editor><sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford Project</orgName></sponsor><sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor><sponsor>Pittsburgh Supercomputing Center</sponsor><principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal><respStmt><resp>Transcription and coding by</resp><persName ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</persName><persName ref="#wnb">William Barr</persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Date last checked: <date when="2016-11-17">2016-11-17</date><!--Fill out and update the date here as different proofreaders work with this file. Dates inside the attribute @when take the form of a hyphen-separated four-digit year followed by two-digit month and two digit day, so May 2, 2015 comes out as 2015-05-02. -->
                  Proofing and corrections by</resp><persName ref="#ebb">Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName><!--ebb 2016-11-17: corrected representation of superscripts in the date to match ms, and simplified tagging of mentions of the Bodleian and Letters_Hearne_Aubrey for accurate rendering. MORE WORK TO BE DONE for SI here, unpacking the three separate books that are in the edited collection of Letters_Hearne_Aubrey that Mitford discusses in pieces here.--><persName ref="#mco">Molly C. O'Donnell</persName>
               <!--mco: 2015-09-27: Proofed the body and TEI headers. Added tags. Unchecked against ms other than coding deletion, addition, torn, etc. codes.-->
               <!--LMW: 2015-09-29 added SI to mine. Backlist pulled. Header and tags updated 2015-10-14--></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>First digital edition in TEI, date: <date when="2014-10-03">3 Oct. 2014</date>. P5.</edition><respStmt><resp>Edition made with help from photos taken by</resp><orgName>Digital Mitford editors</orgName></respStmt><respStmt><orgName>Digital Mitford</orgName><resp> photo files: <idno>IMG_0246.jpg, IMG_0247.jpg, IMG_0248.jpg, IMG_0249.jpg, IMG_0250.jpg, IMG_0251.jpg, IMG_0252.jpg, IMG_0253.jpg</idno></resp></respStmt></editionStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority><pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace><date>2013</date><availability><p>Reproduced by courtesy of the <orgName ref="#ReadingCL">Reading Central Library</orgName>.</p><licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                  License</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Mitford Letters: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><repository ref="#ReadingCL">Reading Central Library</repository><collection>The letters of Mary Russell Mitford, vol. 4, 1819-1823</collection><idno>qB/TU/MIT Vol. 4 Horizon No.: 1361550 ff.364</idno></msIdentifier><head>Letter from Mary Russell Mitford to Sir William Elford, <date when="1819-02-27">1819 February 27</date>.</head><physDesc><objectDesc><supportDesc><support><p>Folio sheet of <material>paper</material> folded in half to form 
                           quarto pages, with correspondence on 1-6 and address leaf on page 6,
                           then folded in thirds twice more and sealed for posting.</p><p>Address leaf bearing the following postmarks: 1) black circular
                           mileage stamp illegible.</p></support><condition><p>Sheet (pages five and six, which are the same page front and back) torn on right edge (page 5) where wax seal was removed.</p></condition></supportDesc></objectDesc></physDesc></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><handNotes><handNote corresp="#rc" medium="red_crayon"> Red crayon or thick red pencil. Probably a different hand from Mitford's that marks many of her letters, sometimes drawing diagonal lines across pages, and sometimes writing words overtop and perpendicularly across Mitford's writing. On this letter, a red line is drawn in the usual way from top left to bottom right of each of the leaves. On page four, a red line is drawn through a sentence.</handNote><handNote corresp="#penAnnot_RCL">Someone, apparently other than <persName ref="#MRM">Mitford</persName>, who occasionally left notes in a spidery thin hand to explain or document details in Mitford's letters in the margins of her pages, noted in manuscripts held at <orgName ref="#ReadingCL">Reading Central Library</orgName>. This may be William Harness or A. G. L'Estrange. This letter is labelled "To Sir William Elford" in the top left of the first leaf.</handNote><handNote corresp="#pencil" medium="pencil"> Someone, apparently other than Mitford, perhaps cataloging letters and describing them, who left grey pencil marks and numbered her letters now in the Reading Central Library's collection. This letter is numbered "6" in the top left of the first leaf, underneath the opening line, "To Sir W. Elford."
           </handNote></handNotes></profileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><p>Mitford’s spelling and punctuation are retained, except where a word is split at the end of a line and the beginning of the next in the manuscript. Where Mitford’s spelling and hyphenation of words deviates from the standard, in order to facilitate searching we are using the TEI elements “choice," “sic," and “reg" to encode both Mitford’s spelling and the regular international standard of Oxford English spelling, following the first listed spelling in the Oxford English Dictionary. The long s and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="letter"><opener><add hand="#penannot">To <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir W. Elford</persName></add><lb/><add hand="#pencil">6</add><lb/><dateline><placeName ref="#Bertram_house">Bertram House</placeName><lb/><date when="1819-02-27">Feb<hi rend="superscript">y</hi> 27<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1819</date>.
               </dateline></opener><p>No! My dear <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir William</persName>--your kind &amp; delightful letter with all its enclosures did not make me bless myself at all--Kindnesses never take me by surprise especially from you--Hoping is one of my pleasures--I always begin expecting to hear from you as soon as ever I have left off a letter. So now you know why I always write so soon, &amp; may answer me at any time by return of post with without danger of expecting my nerves by taking me unawares. </p><metamark rend="jerk"/><p>I have now to thank you most sincerely for your kindness &amp; frankness with regard to <persName ref="#James_Miss">Miss James</persName> &amp; to apologize for having troubled you with her terms--but I did not know at all that your interest was so strongly &amp; so laudably pre-engaged, &amp; could not resist the temptation of mentioning her scheme wherever there was a chance of doing her good. I am quite sure you will forgive me. It seems to me that I &amp; my friend are in a conspiracy to plague you with terms and proposals--I find by a letter from <persName ref="#Hofland_B">Mrs. Hofland</persName> that the poor dear woman, has sent you the proposals of her book--but this was none of my doing--She sends it to you not as my friend but as a Patron of Art--She has sent about a thousand to all the great men in the Kingdom--It is not a book you would have the slightest temptation to buy--<metamark place="above" function="insertion" rend="cross"/><add place="bottom of page">It consisted of Plates from <persName ref="#Hofland_TC #Hofland_B">the Hofland's</persName><title ref="#Whiteknights_Desc_TCH">Views of Whiteknights</title></add><pb n="2"/> You are a great deal too wise to deal in books printed upon drawing paper in Atlas quarto--books merely meant to make a show--but if you would have the goodness when you go into <placeName ref="#Plymouth_city">Plymouth</placeName> merely to <del rend="squiggles"><supplied resp="#mco">beg</supplied></del>leave the proposals on the table in the Reading Room it might do good--there are fools in <placeName ref="#Devonshire_county">Devonshire</placeName> I suppose as well as elsewhere &amp; some one who happened to be at once silly &amp; rich might see the proposals might buy the Volumes. The prints are beautiful.--I take the liberty to make this request because it is one that cannot give you much trouble, &amp; may do good--&amp; above all because the sale of these miserable fifty copies is all poor <persName ref="#Hofland_TC">Mr. Hofland</persName> is likely to get for the paintings drawings <del rend="squiggles" unit="char" n="3"/> journies--his wife's writing--&amp;, which is worst of all, the whole of the engravings--every one of which he was obliged to pay for--not a single engraver in <placeName ref="#London_city">London</placeName> chusing to strike a single stroke upon the <persName ref="#Geo_SpencerChurchill">Duke of Marlborough</persName>'s credit--&amp; the <persName ref="#Geo_SpencerChurchill">Duke of Marlborough</persName>, not having, to use his own elegant phrase <said>"a brass farthing"</said> to repay <persName ref="#Hofland_TC">Mr. Hofland</persName>. I can tell you when we meet some curious anecdotes of this Noble <persName ref="#Geo_SpencerChurchill">Duke</persName>--<persName ref="#Hofland_B">Mrs. Hofland</persName> came from <placeName ref="#Whiteknights">Whiteknights</placeName> here--the <persName ref="#Geo_SpencerChurchill">Duke</persName> left the house at the same time--taking with him the contents of the larder--half a cold turkey &amp; three quarters of a ham--after he had driven off he remembered that he had left behind some scraps of a loin of mutton &amp; actually came back to fetch them--the servants are not at board wages observe &amp; the Housekeeper knowing they could not get even a twopenny loaf without twopence &amp; naturally alarmed at this clearance of eatables ventured to ask him for money--after much stuttering he gave her ten pounds--which being perceived by his son <persName ref="#Chas_SpencerChurchill">Lord Charles</persName>--he lingered behind &amp; borrowed <emph rend="underline">five</emph> of it--All this time for him &amp; his Son there were three carriages <del rend="squiggles" unit="word" n="1"/><add place="above">with</add><add place="below"><metamark place="below" function="insertion" rend="caret"/>each</add>--one of them empty. Is this not stopping one hole in a <choice><sic>cullender</sic><reg>colander</reg></choice>? <persName ref="#Hofland_B">Mrs. Hofland</persName> saw the whole transaction with her own eyes--You should hear her tell the story--with the <persName ref="#Geo_SpencerChurchill">Duke</persName>'s stuttering--<persName ref="#Chas_SpencerChurchill">Lord Charles</persName>'s Dandyism--&amp; the poor Housekeeper's dismal whine--She cannot help laughing now in the midst of her troubles. You will say that <persName ref="#Hofland_TC">Mr. Hofland</persName> was mad to engage in such an undertaking--&amp; I shall say I think so too--</p><metamark rend="jerk"/><p>The lozenges are excellent. I have not got a cough, but <pb n="3"/> I must make some after your recipe &amp; then get a cough on purpose to be cured by them--I do not think though that I shall prove so neat handed a confectioner as you--truly my dear friend an universal genius--your jujubie (is that the proper name?) may vie with those cream tarts by which a certain <persName ref="#Hassan_Bedreddin">Prince</persName> in the <title ref="#Arabian_Tales">Arabian Tales</title> (the <persName ref="#Hassan_Bedreddin">Prince Bedreddin Hassan</persName> I think) recovered his birthright. I must catch cold on purpose to try them, being unluckily quite recovered (by the help of treacle posset) of the one I had when I wrote last. But catching cold will be a very easy exploit in this weather--it freezes, snows, hails &amp; rains every day regularly--demolishes my <name type="plant" ref="#primrose">primroses</name>, cuts off my <name type="plant" ref="#violet">violets</name>, rouses poor <persName ref="#Miranda_pet">Miranda</persName> &amp; dirties the <persName ref="#Selim_pet">white cat</persName>--all this tornado too is come after an absolute Spring--a fortnight ago <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</persName> found a pheasant's nest with 4 eggs in <placeName ref="#BillingbearPk"><persName ref="#Griffin_Rich">Lord Braybrooke</persName>'s park</placeName>--grass was springing--flowers were blowing &amp; the elder leaves coming out--now we have winter in its worst &amp; dreariest form--a white world every morning--a black one every night--Nothing will be easier than to catch cold. </p><metamark rend="jerk"/><p>I am happy to say the <persName ref="#whitekitten_WEpet">Persian Princess</persName> is still unkilled, though the brute <rs type="person" ref="#Selim_pet">her father</rs> has lost nothing of his legitimate fury--He is the most perfect representative of the Sultans of the old metrical romances the bloody followers of <q>"Mahound and Termagaunt"</q><note resp="#wnb #lmw">Mitford paraphrases a line from <persName ref="#Percy_Thos">Percy</persName>'s <title ref="#Percy_Reliques">Reliques</title> introducing "King Estmere," in which <persName ref="#Percy_Thos">Percy</persName> states, <quote>"The Mahometans are spoken of in ver. 49, &amp;c, just in the same terms as in all other old Romances. The author of the ancient Legend of Sir Bevis represents his hero, upon all occasions, breathing out fire against 'Mahound and Termagaunte.'"</quote> "Mahound" is another name for Mahomet; Termagaunte was believed to be a violent Islamic god. One aspect of the stereotype of evil Saracen characters was to show them swearing on "Mahound and Termagaunte."</note> who made nothing of striking off fifty heads at a blow, or eating an enemy for supper, or murdering their own daughters, or any other enormity--He is likewise a strong resemblance of the ranting Sultans of <persName ref="#Dryden">Dryden</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#Lee_Nath">Lee</persName> who dragged people about by the hair of their head--talked (or <unclear><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/></unclear>)them to death--clawed them &amp; burnt them alive. In short he is the wickedest person that ever walked on four feet. I have a vast inclination to whip this Sultan <persName ref="#Selim_pet">Selim</persName>--but the beast is too formidable when he takes these fits, that really I <pb n="4"/>am afraid. So we keep the poor dear little gentle thing in a safe quiet room &amp; only bring her out when we can make sure of her <persName ref="#Selim_pet">Papa</persName>'s prowling elsewhere. She is exceedingly pretty--much too pretty to be caged--you <emph rend="underline">must</emph> come &amp; fetch her--Do pray--And let me know when you are likely to be in <placeName ref="#London_city">Town</placeName>. I shall pass a few days there myself sometime about the end of April or the beginning of May.</p><metamark rend="jerk"/><p>You need not at all be alarmed at the too great virtue of any of <persName ref="#Owenson_S">Lady Morgan's</persName> heroes or heroines--she is not single minded enough--has not sufficient moral taste to know a really excellent man--Her virtues are all of the exaggerated melodramatic sort--grand--fine--magnanimous--all claptraps &amp; stage tricks. The want of invention is really astonishing--her three principal personages all come in under borrowed names. And yet there is a good deal of talent among all this--a <persName ref="#Miss_Crawley_fict">Miss Crawley</persName>for instance who is almost as good as <persName ref="#Mr_Dexter_fict">Mr. Dexter</persName>, &amp; some other under <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/></del><add place="above">personages</add> who show quick perception of character &amp; considerable power of humor.--I understand that the very best novel that has been published for a long time is <title ref="#Marriage_SF">"Marriage"</title>--I have not seen it--but a friend whose taste can be trusted tells me it is equal to any of <persName ref="#Austen_Jane">Miss Austen</persName>'s. This to me is the very highest recommendation that can be given, &amp; I believe it will be to you. <persName ref="#Austen_Jane">Miss Austen</persName>'s books were so true to Nature, that <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/></del> facts theselves--history or Biography looked false by the side of her fictions.--I cannot tell you whether <persName ref="#Aubrey_John">Aubrey</persName>'s Lives had ever been printed before or not--I have seen them quoted in many books--but they might have been quoted from the original M.S. in the <orgName ref="#OxfordBodleian">Bodleian Library</orgName>. The book where I read them (a borrowed book which I have returned without absolutely copying the title) is I should think not rare. It <pb n="5"/> was printed at the <orgName ref="#Clarendon_Press">Clarendon Press</orgName> in 2 Vols--but the 2nd Vol so large that it was perforce divided into two parts--&amp; the title is as I can remember to this effect--<bibl corresp="#Letters_Hearne_Aubrey"><title level="m">Letters of eminent Persons in the Bodleian Library</title>, <title level="m">Hearne's journeys to Reading &amp; Silchester</title>, &amp; <title level="m">Aubrey's Lives</title></bibl>--I should think the work rather common than scarce. With <title level="m">the Lives</title> I am sure you will be delighted--they are rather portraits than Lives--not longer than a page or two to each person--&amp; very numerous embracing almost all of the distinguished characters of <persName ref="#JamesI">James</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#ChasI">Charles the First's Days</persName> &amp; the Commonwealth--full of curious anecdotes, &amp; written in the strongest &amp; raciest English. I am sure of your liking old <persName ref="#Aubrey_John">Aubrey</persName>. I would not much recommend the letters, some of which are surely antiquarian, &amp; as dull as Antiquarians are privileged <gap quantity="2" unit="word" reason="torn"/><unclear><supplied resp="#lmw">to be</supplied></unclear>--Pray did you ever see a delightful piece of pleasantry <gap quantity="1" unit="word" reason="torn"/><persName ref="#Master_Fuller">Old Master Fuller</persName> where he makes all the shires quarrel <gap quantity="1" unit="word" reason="torn"/> the <placeName ref="#London_city">Capital</placeName>? I have just met with it in another <placeName ref="#Oxford_city">Oxford</placeName> book--the <title ref="#Collectanea">Collectanea Curiosa</title> which well deserves its name. This is a mere pleasantry so gay--so hearty--so healthy--fresh &amp; laughing like <title ref="#GammerGurton">Gammer Gurton's Needle</title>--did you never remark how superior old gaiety is to new? There is a critical &amp; comparative spirit about us moderns which dulls the sunshine--they laughed where we sneer--we cannot fire a <lang xml:lang="fr">feu de joie</lang><note resp="#lmw">A celebratory firing of rifles, normally with blanks.</note> without loading with ball cartridges. Well I will not talk any more of books lest you should say like a friend of mine <said>"My dear <persName ref="#MRM">Miss Mitford</persName> you read so much that you will finish by knowing nothing"</said>--this pretty Speech was made 5 years ago--What would he say now! But reading is my favorite mode of idleness--I like it better than any of my play-works--better than <name type="plant" ref="#fir">fir</name>topping--better than <name type="plant" ref="#violet">violet</name>ing--better than working <pb n="6"/>gown tails--better than playing with <persName ref="#Miranda_pet">Miranda</persName>--better <add place="above"><metamark place="below" function="insertion" rend="caret"/>than</add> feeding the <persName ref="#whitekitten_WEpet">white kitten</persName>--better than riding in a gig--better than any thing other than that other pet idleness talking (that is to say <emph rend="underline">writing</emph> to you.--But it is time to release you. Adieu, my dear Friend--<persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#Russell_M">Mama</persName> desire their kindest regards--write--&amp; above all--come--</p><closer><lb/>Ever most affectionately <choice><sic>your's</sic><reg>yours</reg></choice><lb/><persName ref="#MRM">Mary Russell Mitford</persName>.
           
               <address><addrLine><placeName ref="#Reading_city">Reading</placeName><date when="1819-03-02">March two</date></addrLine><addrLine><date when="1819">1819</date></addrLine><addrLine><persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir W. Elford B<emph rend="superscript">t</emph></persName></addrLine><addrLine><placeName ref="#Bickham_village">Bickham</placeName></addrLine><addrLine><placeName ref="#Plymouth_city">Plymouth</placeName></addrLine></address></closer><postscript><p>The <persName ref="#whitekitten_WEpet">white kitten</persName> sends her duty.</p></postscript></div></body><back>
<!-- backlist pulled to si-add-LMW 2015 10 07 --></back></text></TEI>