<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><!--<?xml-model href="http://ebeshero.github.io/MRMValidate.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>--><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title xml:id="MRM1734">Letter to <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir William Elford</persName>, <date when="1819-02-18">1819 February 18</date></title><author ref="#MRM">Mary Russell Mitford</author><editor ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</editor><sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford Project</orgName></sponsor><sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor><sponsor>Pittsburgh Supercomputing Center</sponsor><principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal><respStmt><resp>Transcription and coding by</resp><persName ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</persName><persName ref="#wnb">William Barr</persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Date last checked: <date when="2015-10-14">2015-10-14</date>
                        Proofing and corrections by</resp><persName ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</persName> <!-- lmw: 2015-09-27; 2015 10-14, updated header and tags. --><persName ref="#mco">Molly C. O'Donnell</persName><!--mco: 2015-09-27: Proofed the body and the TEI header. Added tags and SI entries provided by lmw at bottom to si-add-MCO. Unchecked against ms.--></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>First digital edition in TEI, date: <date when="2014-09-15">19 September 2014</date>. P5.</edition><respStmt><resp>Edition made with help from photos taken by</resp><orgName>Digital Mitford editors</orgName></respStmt><respStmt><orgName>Digital Mitford</orgName><resp> photo files: <idno>IMG_0244.jpg, IMG_0245.jpg</idno></resp></respStmt></editionStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority><pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace><date>2013</date><availability><p>Reproduced by courtesy of the <orgName ref="#ReadingCL">Reading Central Library</orgName>.</p><licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                        License</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Mitford Letters: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><repository ref="#ReadingCL">Reading Central Library</repository><collection>The letters of Mary Russell Mitford, vol. 4, 1819-1823</collection><idno>qB/TU/MIT Vol. 4 Horizon No.: 1361550 ff. 363</idno></msIdentifier><head>Letter from Mary Russell Mitford to Sir William Elford, <date when="1819-02-18">1819 February 18</date>.</head><physDesc><objectDesc><supportDesc><support><p>One half sheet of folio <material>paper</material>, two surfaces photographed.</p><p>Address leaf bearing black postmark, partially illegible, reading <stamp><lb/><placeName>READING</placeName><lb/></stamp>.</p></support><condition><p>Sheet (pages one and two) torn on right edge where wax seal was removed. Small tears in center of the sheet, at the upper right corner of the text block containing the address.</p></condition></supportDesc></objectDesc><sealDesc><p>Red wax seal, remnants of black wax adhered elsewhere on page two.</p></sealDesc></physDesc></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><handNotes><handNote corresp="#rc" medium="red_crayon"> Red crayon or thick red pencil. Probably a different hand from Mitford's that marks many of her letters, sometimes drawing diagonal lines across pages, and sometimes writing words overtop and perpendicularly across Mitford's writing. On this letter, a red line is drawn top left to bottom right on page one; page one also has four lines of text crossed out and with two diagonal lines across the same text. Page two has two diagonal lines drawn through each of the text blocks.</handNote></handNotes></profileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><p>Mitford’s spelling and punctuation are retained, except where a word is split at the end of a line and the beginning of the next in the manuscript. Where Mitford’s spelling and hyphenation of words deviates from the standard, in order to facilitate searching we are using the TEI elements “choice," “sic," and “reg" to encode both Mitford’s spelling and the regular international standard of Oxford English spelling, following the first listed spelling in the Oxford English Dictionary. The long s and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="letter"><opener><salute>To <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir W. Elford--</persName></salute><dateline><name type="place"><unclear/></name><date when="1819-02-18">Feb<hi rend="superscript">y</hi> 18 1819</date>.
                    </dateline></opener><p><date when="1819-02-12"><del rend="crossout">Friday night</del></date>--My letters always grow like snowballs when they have time to gather--Not a single member of the <orgName ref="#House_Lords">Lords</orgName> or <orgName ref="#House_Commons">Commons</orgName> was at our Music meeting today--the wiser they! I shall have a better opinion of the <orgName ref="#Parliament_UK">Legislature</orgName> as long as I live. Pray do you like Music Meetings? I never come from one without being very sure that I have no music in my soul--I am always tired to death--stupified--stultified--fit for nothing but to vent my <del rend="squiggles">stupidity</del>weariness on some luckless Correspondent such as you my dear <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir William</persName>. Not but music that <q>"Medicine of the mind"</q><note resp="#lmw">Possibly a reference to <persName ref="#LeCamus_Antoine">Antoine Le Camus</persName>'s <title ref="#Medecine_esprit">La Médecine de l'esprit</title>, sometimes translated as "Medicine of the Mind" (Paris, first edition, 1753). <!--lmw: quote: identify. "(Medicine of the Mind) (1753–69), for instance, Antoine Le Camus proposed a regimen of sensation management that he felt confident would transform middling minds into great intellectuals" (Brewer, Cambridge Companion to the French Enlightenment. There is however, no specific English translation called "Medicine of the Mind" that I can find anywhere.--></note>, as somebody called it, is a very fine thing taken in small &amp; distant doses--but a whole Oratorio--a four hours portion.--Good Lord it is pouring a whole Apothecary's shop down one's throat. Nevertheless I had my amusements. To say nothing of the feminine diversion of dress-scanning--staring at Pelisses &amp; bonnets--I happened to be in an entertaining neighborhood. A man close behind me took the <title corresp="#Te_Deum">Te Deum</title> for Italian <note resp="#lmw">Here, <persName ref="#MRM">Mitford</persName> points out the humor in the pair mistaking the well-known church Latin of the hymn for Italian.</note>--&amp; a "Miss Matilda"<note resp="#lmw">Likely not a reference to a specific young woman named Matilda; during Mitford's time, "Matilda" was becoming proverbial for silly and romantic young women, since the name was associated with the heroines of several Gothic novels as well as the poetic pseudonyms of women authors such as <persName ref="#Dacre_Charlotte">Charlotte Dacre ("Rosa Matilda")</persName> and <persName ref="Cowley_H">Hannah Cowley ("Anna Matilda")</persName>. <!--LMW: See my article on Charlotte Dacre's pseudonyms. --></note> of his party to do him the favor to translate it for him--Miss Matilda did not deny its being Italian <gap reason="torn"/><supplied resp="#lmw"><unclear>nor</unclear></supplied> disclaim the knowledge he imputed to her, but she said <said>"she could not quite make it out--she thought it must be misprinted--she would try when she got home."</said> This is quite true I assure you--&amp; I was so well bred that I did not laugh.--Another of my recreations was comparing the actual noise with a Theory of <persName ref="#Dickinson_Charles">Mr. Dickinson</persName>'s who maintains that all sounds of Art &amp; Nature are reducible to a musical scale--&amp; really when one listens to a great Chorus--analyzing &amp; taking it to pieces--it does seem as if composed of grander <metamark rend="caret" place="below" function="insertion"/><add place="above">&amp; more various Sounds</add> than mere music though our Choruses to day were not half full enough. By the bye I puzzled my <rs type="person" ref="#Dickinson_Charles">Theorist</rs> the other day--for half a minute I fairly <emph rend="underline">posed</emph> him. He was haranguing very triumphantly about this universal musical scale of his when I put the <title corresp="#EnragedMus_WH">Enraged Musician</title> before him for a text &amp; begged him to begin with arranging that according to his new System--he was really disconcerted for an instant--but nothing <pb n="2"/> can put him <metamark rend="caret" place="below" function="insertion"/><add place="above">long</add>out of his way--He flew off at a Tangent to <persName ref="#Hogarth">Hogarth</persName> &amp; gave such a character of him--with such eloquence such discrimination such delightful &amp; unwearying lightness &amp; tact that it was worth even the bodily fatigue of an Oratorio to her it. He really is a first rate man--I should like you to know him.--There is a concert &amp; Ball at <placeName ref="#Reading_city">Reading</placeName> tonight--&amp; people are expecting the <persName ref="#Wellington_Duke">Duke of Wellington</persName>. Now there is likewise a <gap reason="torn"/><supplied resp="#lmw"><unclear>ball at</unclear></supplied><placeName ref="#Basingstoke">Basingstoke</placeName> where he is also expected tonight--<del rend="squiggles">Now</del>the probable end is that he will go to neither--Good bye--God bless you!--This letter must go for two or three mind--&amp; you must write to me directly--do you hear my dear <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir William</persName>? Directly.</p><closer>--Ever <choice><sic>your's</sic><reg resp="#lmw">yours</reg></choice><persName ref="#MRM"> M.R.M.</persName></closer><closer><address><pb n="2"/><addrLine><placeName ref="#Reading_city">Reading</placeName><date when="1819-02-18"/>February eighteen</addrLine><addrLine>1819</addrLine><addrLine><persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir W. Elford</persName> B<hi rend="superscript"/>t.</addrLine><addrLine><placeName ref="#Bickham_village">Bickham</placeName></addrLine><addrLine><placeName ref="#Plymouth_city">Plymouth</placeName></addrLine><addrLine><unclear/></addrLine></address></closer></div></body><back><div>
                <!-- back list complete and removed to si-add-LMW 2015 10 04 --></div></back></text></TEI>