<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><?xml-model href="http://ebeshero.github.io/MRMValidate.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title xml:id="MRM1743">Letter to <persName ref="#Haydon">Benjamin Robert Haydon</persName>, <date when="1819-08-08">August 8, 1819</date></title><author ref="#MRM">Mary Russell Mitford</author><editor ref="#mco">Molly C. O'Donnell</editor><sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford Project</orgName></sponsor><sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor><principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal><respStmt><resp>Transcription and coding by</resp><persName ref="#mco">Molly C. O'Donnell</persName><!--mco: updated letter xml:id info.--></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Date last checked: <date when="2015-10-19">2015-10-19</date>
                  Proofing and corrections by</resp><persName ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</persName> <!--LMW: proofed against ms. 2015 09 28. --></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>First digital edition in TEI, date: <date when="2015-05-30">30 May 2015</date>. P5.</edition><respStmt><resp>Edition made with help from photos taken by</resp><orgName>Digital Mitford editors</orgName></respStmt><respStmt><orgName>Digital Mitford</orgName><resp> photo files: <idno>P1020251.jpg, P1020252.jpg, P1020253.jpg, P1020254.jpg, P1020255.jpg, P1020256.jpg</idno></resp></respStmt></editionStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority><pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace><date>2013</date><availability><p>Reproduced by courtesy of the <orgName ref="#ReadingCL">Reading Central Library</orgName>.</p><licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                  License</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Mitford Letters: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><repository ref="#ReadingCL">Reading Central Library</repository><collection>The letters of Mary Russell Mitford, vol. 4, 1819-1823</collection><idno>qB/TU/MIT Vol. 4 Horizon No.: 1361550 ff. 378</idno></msIdentifier><head>Letter from Mary Russell Mitford to Benjamin Robert Haydon, <date when="1819-08-08">1819 August 8</date>.</head><physDesc><objectDesc><supportDesc><support><p> One sheet of <material>paper</material>, four surfaces photographed. Paper 23 cm. long.</p><p>No postmarks. Page four blank.</p></support><condition><p>Some wrinkling to long edge; does not affect text.</p></condition></supportDesc></objectDesc><sealDesc><p>No seal.</p></sealDesc></physDesc></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><handNotes><handNote corresp="#rc" medium="red_crayon"> Red crayon or thick red pencil in a different hand from Mitford's marks all pages of this letter with a diagonal line beginning in the left corner of each page and striking through to bottom right corner of text.</handNote><handNote corresp="#pencil" medium="pencil">Someone other than Mitford left grey pencil marks and numbered her letters now in the Reading Central Library's collection. This letter is numbered "14" in the upper left corner of page 1, and just above this the same pencil notes "B. R. Haydon" with an underscore.</handNote></handNotes></profileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><p>Mitford’s spelling and punctuation are retained, except where a word is split at the end of a line and the beginning of the next in the manuscript. Where Mitford’s spelling and hyphenation of words deviates from the standard, in order to facilitate searching we are using the TEI elements “choice," “sic," and “reg" to encode both Mitford’s spelling and the regular international standard of Oxford English spelling, following the first listed spelling in the Oxford English Dictionary. The long s and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="letter"><opener><add hand="#pencil"><persName ref="#Haydon">B. R. Haydon Esq.</persName><lb/>14</add><dateline><name type="place" ref="#Bertram_house">Bertram House</name><date when="1819-08-08">August 8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1819</date>. 
               </dateline><salute><persName ref="#Haydon">My dear Sir</persName></salute></opener><p>I cannot defer for a moment thanking you for the pleasure you have given us in the prospect of seeing you here. Nothing I trust will or can arise to disappoint us. Your health &amp; your eyes would be so much benefitted by rest &amp; country air that your <title corresp="#ChrstEJrslm_Haydon">Picture</title> would go on the faster for the excursion--you would gain in power more than you would lose in time. <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</persName> says he can show you excellent coursing--Again I must prepare you for our homely ways, &amp; our little variety of company--We have not at any time a large society &amp; just now all our neighbours seem migrating--But this you will pardon I am sure. I can promise you a most delighted welcome in our little family circle from the two you know &amp; the one you do not know--I think you will like my dear <persName ref="#Russell_M">Mother</persName>--every body does--she is so very good--though perhaps I oughht not to say so. If not inconvenient to you let us have the pleasure of seeing you rather before than after the middle of next month--&amp; be so good to write a day or two before to fix the time that my <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Father</persName> shall meet you in <placeName ref="#Reading_city">Reading</placeName>--I have <choice><sic>exprest</sic><reg>expressed</reg></choice> myself with my usual awkwardness I see &amp; seem to limit you to the middle of the month--As early in September as you like we shall be most happy to receive you--only the beginning would suit my <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Father</persName> better than the latter end. Pray do not let anything prevent your coming.</p><p>You shall certainly have a very beautiful thoroughbred dark coloured young greyhound--of that my dear Sir be assured. My <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Father</persName>'s most intimate friend, &amp; the father of my most intimate friends is the greatest courser in this neighborhood &amp; has a breed of dogs so celebrated that <persName ref="#Rivers_Lord">Lord Rivers</persName> himself was in great part supplied<pb n="2"/> by him. This Gentleman, <persName ref="#Webb_James">Mr. Webb</persName>, has just now 8 or nine very fine young greyhounds all blue, of which he does not mean to keep more than five or six, so that there will be neither trouble nor obligation in promising one for you--&amp; if you do not like that one you shall have my little beauty from <placeName ref="#Stratford_upon_Avon_city">Stratford</placeName><note resp="#lmw">A reference to <persName ref="#MRM">Mitford</persName>'s greyhound <persName ref="#Miranda_pet">Miranda</persName>, who came from a breeder in <placeName ref="#Stratford_upon_Avon_city">Stratford</placeName>.</note><persName ref="#Webb_James">Mr. Webb</persName> is ill just now, so that I cannot very well <choice><sic>chuse</sic><reg>choose</reg></choice> one, but I shall prefer my petition &amp; am sure of getting you a very handsome one by <date when="1819-09">September</date>. <persName ref="#Webb_James">Mr. Webb</persName> will be most proud to supply <emph rend="underline">you</emph>--He is getting better, &amp; will I hope be well enough to be introduced to you when we have the happiness of your company--&amp; I am sure you will think it a pleasure to be supplied by him. He is a most excellent man--a brewer by trade &amp; a gentleman by nature--quite as thorough bred as his greyhounds.</p><p>What you say of your <title>picture</title> delights me. Is the <persName ref="#Jesus">Christ</persName> finished?--I do not wonder that you are improved in the interval that has elapsed since your illness--you must have thought so intently on that divine figure--&amp; surely after a certain degree of mechanical power is acquired the mind has as much to do with that noble art as the hand--Such a <title corresp="#ChrstEJrslm_Haydon">picture</title> is only another &amp; a finer form of poetry.<metamark rend="cross" place="above"/><add place="bottom of page"><title corresp="#ChrstEJrslm_Haydon">Christ Entry to Jerusalem</title></add>--But you are a great Poet too even out of the canvas my dear <persName ref="#Haydon">Mr. Haydon</persName> with your <q>"whirlwind as quick as your own thoughts"</q>--those beautiful words of yours would be fit companions for <persName ref="#Wordsworth_Wm">Mr. Wordsworth</persName>'s <quote>"crescent boat"</quote><note resp="#lmw">A reference to the Prologue of Wordsworth's Peter Bell:  There's something in a flying horse,/And something in a huge balloon;/But through the clouds I'll never float/Until I have a little Boat,/Whose shape is like the crescent-moon" (page 1, stanza 1).</note>--I do not know which I should like best to travel in--the whirlwind I think.--You must be content with the <placeName ref="#Reading_city">Reading</placeName> Coach which in point of speed you will find a very decent substitute, &amp; a good deal safer. They are the very best coaches on the road. Mind you try them.</p><closer><lb/>Kindest regards from <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#Russell_M">Mama</persName>--Ever my dear Sir
             <lb/><salute>Most sincerely <choice><sic>your's</sic><reg>yours</reg></choice></salute><lb/><signed><persName ref="#MRM">M. R. Mitford</persName>.</signed></closer><pb n="3"/><postscript><p>I rejoice to hear of the success of your pupil <persName ref="#Bewick_Wm">Mr. Bewick</persName> whose <placeName ref="#Northumberland">Northumberland</placeName> name is very agreeable to my ears. Is he a son or grandson of the celebrated wood engraver<note resp="#lmw"><persName ref="#MRM">Mitford</persName> refers here to <persName ref="#Bewick_Thos">Thomas Bewick</persName> (1753-1828), best known for his sharply detailed wood engravings for works such as A History of British Birds (1797, 1804, and 1821) and illustrated editions of Aesop's Fables. He was not related to <persName ref="#Haydon">Haydon</persName>'s pupil <persName ref="#Bewick_Wm">William Bewick</persName>.</note>? I am afraid that is not the right phrase--but you know what I mean.--
        </p></postscript></div></body><back>
            <!-- back list complete and removed to si-add-LMW 2015 10 04 --></back></text></TEI>