<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><!--<?xml-model href="http://ebeshero.github.io/MRMValidate.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>--><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title xml:id="MRM1740">Letter to <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir William Elford</persName>, <date when="1819-06-08">June 8, 1819</date></title><author ref="#MRM">Mary Russell Mitford</author><editor ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</editor><sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford Project</orgName></sponsor><sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor><sponsor>Pittsburgh Supercomputing Center</sponsor><principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal><respStmt><resp>Transcription and coding by</resp><persName ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</persName><persName>Wilmina Sainbert</persName><!-- Change to your name and use assigned xml:id for ref="#" --></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Date last checked: <date when="2015-10-15">2015-10-15</date>
                  Proofing and corrections by</resp><persName ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</persName></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>First digital edition in TEI, date: <date when="2015-04-26">26 April 2015</date>. P5.</edition><respStmt><resp>Edition made with help from photos taken by</resp><orgName>Digital Mitford editors</orgName></respStmt><respStmt><orgName>Digital Mitford</orgName><resp> photo files: <idno>DSCF9476.jpg, DSCF9477.jpg, DSCF9478.jpg, DSCF9479.jpg, DSCF9480.jpg, DSCF9481.jpg, DSCF9482.jpg. DSCF9483.jpg. DSCF9484.jpg. DSCF9485.jpg</idno></resp></respStmt></editionStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority><pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace><date>2013</date><availability><p>Reproduced by courtesy of the <orgName ref="#ReadingCL">Reading Central Library</orgName>.</p><licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                  License</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Mitford Letters: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><repository ref="#ReadingCL">Reading Central Library</repository><collection>The letters of Mary Russell Mitford, vol. 4, 1819-1823</collection><idno>qB/TU/MIT Vol. 4 Horizon No.: 1361550 ff.373</idno></msIdentifier><head>Letter from Mary Russell Mitford to Sir William Elford, <date when="1819-06-08">1819 June 8</date>.</head><physDesc><objectDesc><supportDesc><support><p>Single sheet of <material>paper</material>, four surfaces photographed, folded in half, folded again in thirds.</p><p>Address leaf bearing round black postmark, partially illegible, reading <stamp><lb/><placeName>READING</placeName><lb/></stamp>.</p><p> A large 3 denoting the posting fee has been written in black ink by the postal service across the address leaf.</p></support><condition><p>Sheet (pages three and four) torn on edge of page where wax seal was removed.</p></condition></supportDesc></objectDesc><sealDesc><p>Red wax seal, complete, adhered to page four.--&gt;</p></sealDesc></physDesc></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><handNotes><handNote corresp="#rc" medium="red_crayon"> Red crayon or thick red pencil. Probably a different hand from Mitford's that marks many of her letters, sometimes drawing diagonal lines across pages, and sometimes writing words overtop and perpendicularly across Mitford's writing. On this letter, a red line is drawn from top left to bottom right of leaves one, two and three. A red line is also drawn diagonally from the top center right to center left across the two text blocks of page four. There is no red pencil on the address block.</handNote><handNote corresp="#pencil" medium="pencil"> Someone, apparently other than Mitford, perhaps cataloging letters and describing them, who left grey pencil marks and numbered her letters now in the Reading Central Library's collection. This letter is numbered "11" in the top left of the first leaf.
           </handNote></handNotes></profileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><p>Mitford’s spelling and punctuation are retained, except where a word is split at the end of a line and the beginning of the next in the manuscript. Where Mitford’s spelling and hyphenation of words deviates from the standard, in order to facilitate searching we are using the TEI elements “choice," “sic," and “reg" to encode both Mitford’s spelling and the regular international standard of Oxford English spelling, following the first listed spelling in the Oxford English Dictionary. The long s and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="letter"><opener><add hand="#pencil">11</add><dateline><name type="place" ref="#Bertram_house">Bertram House</name><date when="1819-06-08">June 8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1819</date>. 
               </dateline></opener><p><persName ref="#Russell_M">Mama</persName> desires me to thank you very sincerely, my dear <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir William</persName>, for your kindness in so soon &amp; so carefully returning her letter. There is no end to <persName ref="#Dundas_C">Mr. Dundas</persName>'s talent for blundering, but this mistake could not have happened to any one in whose honour (honour is rather too grand a word for the occasion) in whose gentlemanliness my Mother would place more implicit confidence. The letter will now pursue its destination Northward instead of Westward under the auspices of <persName ref="#Palmer_CF">Mr. Fyshe Palmer</persName>--I shall not send my epistle to him--for fear of another blunder--the good Town of <placeName ref="#Reading_city">Reading</placeName> would be very sorry if its Members yielded to the County <orgName ref="#MPs">M.P's</orgName> in any quality <metamark rend="caret" place="below"/><add place="above">whatsoever</add>--&amp; in that of puzzlepatedness (<q>"though <persName ref="#Palmer_CF">Mr. P</persName> is my friend"</q>) I don't think they do.--What were we talking about in my last letter? Of my journey to <placeName ref="#Oxfordshire">Oxfordshire</placeName>?--But I did not go--Luckily I had in my engagement put in a saving clause about the weather--You who know the qualities of our horse --his admirable slowness--his delightful knack of standing <metamark rend="caret" place="below"/><add place="above">still</add>and ride may imagine what his performance would be in the wet up a hill which we flat-country folks call a mountain--So it was good enough to rain &amp; I escaped. People may say what they will about the uncertainty of our English climate, but I think for my part one may always be tolerably certain of a little rain. My escape was greater even than I thought--there were 35, Godfathers Godmothers &amp; others--a bed broke down, &amp; a table--the very house cracked under the weight of its burthen--&amp; if I had been there they would have laid it all to me--<persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</persName> would have declared it was all my fatness--indeed it is almost as bad as it is--for the friend who wrote me this account finished the paragraph by saying <q>"You being away, my dear, we cannot understand how these things can have happened."</q>--Only see my dear Friend how they <pb n="1"/>use me! <metamark rend="#jerk"/>So you are really <unclear/><title ref="#Camilla_FB">Camilla</title>! I mean to do the same myself that I may have the satisfaction &amp; honour of fighting under your banners &amp; helping to knock down that buckram hero <persName ref="#MandlebertE_char">Mr. Edgar Mandlebert</persName>. I suspect that poor dear <persName ref="#Dickinson_Mrs">Mrs. Dickinson</persName> is not very much obliged either to your complaisance or mine on this score--for I certainly &amp; you probably read not to be convinced which you know never happens (<foreign xml:id="lat">vide</foreign><title ref="#Hudibras_SB">Hudibras</title>) but to find fault--&amp; next to reading with an undivided &amp; enthusiastic admiration such as I feel for the <title ref="#FaerieQu_ES">Faerie Queen</title> you for <title ref="#TomJones_HF">Tom Jones</title> &amp; both of us for <title ref="#Pride_and_Prejudice">Pride and Prejudice</title>--next to that absorbing delight the greatest pleasure in reading is to be critical &amp; fastidious, &amp; laugh at, &amp; pull to pieces. Whether this be wise or <del rend="squiggle" unit="word" n="1"/> not, I cannot tell--both the child &amp; the botanist are amused in <del rend="squiggle" unit="word" n="1">pull</del>picking off the leaves of the flowers to come at the internal structure--&amp; perhaps the younger philosopher who performs this operation from the mere instinct of mischief is as happy--that is as wise--as the graver and elder demolisher. I am no scientific puller to pieces at all events--though lately I have almost wished myself a reviewer to vent my grievances at a quantity of maudlin Travels I have been reading--Walks in <placeName ref="#Switzerland">Switzerland</placeName>--Autumns near the <placeName ref="#Rhine">Rhine</placeName>--Picturesque Tours--Visits to <placeName ref="#LaTrappe">La Trappe</placeName> countless others names forgotten--Don't you think there ought to be a high duty on this importation of nonsense in these times of financial difficulty? Though very likely a tax of that sort would not catch them--these travels are perhaps all written at home--but to me there is a real grievance in having the bloom brushed from the grape--in disenchanting the <persName ref="#Dulcinea_DQ">Dulcinea</persName>s of one's imagination--in cutting asunder the fine links by which great names are united to local objects--in turning that which should be a vision &amp; a dram, into dull &amp; flat reality--making <placeName ref="#Meillerie">Meillerie</placeName> as common as old <placeName ref="#Brentford">Brentford</placeName> &amp; laying <placeName ref="#Vaucluse">Vaucluse</placeName> as open <pb n="2"/> as <placeName ref="#HounslowHeath">Hounslow Heath</placeName>. I have a good mind not to read another book of Travels till <persName ref="#Clarke_ED">Dr. Clarke</persName>'s next Volume. Apropos to <persName ref="#Clarke_ED">Dr. Clarke</persName>--his name is Edward Daniell--so he was not your preacher.--The pleasantest very pleasant account of foreign countries I meant to mention to you--did I? <title ref="#TenYearsatTripoli">A Ten years residence in <choice><sic><placeName ref="#Tripoli">Tripoly</placeName></sic><reg>Tripoli</reg></choice></title>--written by <rs type="person" ref="#Tully_Miss">a lady</rs>--She lets one quite into the interior of those inaccessible places Seraglios Harems &amp; so forth--<persName ref="#Montague_MW">Lady M. W. Montague</persName> herself was less learned in <metamark rend="caret" place="below"/><add place="above">fair</add> fatimas &amp; slippers &amp; sashes &amp; handkerchiefs &amp; caftans &amp; all the mysteries of a Turkish toilette--besides this womanish knowledge there is a vast deal of knowledge not womanish--&amp; an account of the Bashaw's family which but for the misfortune of its being true would pass for one of the finest tragic narratives in the world. In short if you are not alarmed at the size of the book you will find it to say the least a great deal more entertaining than <title ref="#Camilla_FB">Camilla</title>.--Before I have done with <gap reason="torn" quantity="1" unit="word"/><unclear/><supplied resp="lmw">literature</supplied> I must ask if you have seen an imitation of your part<gap reason="torn" quantity="6" unit="chars"/><unclear/><supplied resp="lmw">icular</supplied> favorite <persName ref="#Wordsworth_Wm">Mr. Wordsworth</persName> called <title ref="#PeterBell_JHR">Peter Bell</title>?--He--the real  <persName ref="#Wordsworth_Wm">Mr. Wordsworth</persName> had announced a ditty so called--&amp; some wicked wit much of your mind with regard to that great Poet--came out a week before him with this parody by anticipation--I only saw it the other day for five minutes but I thought it extremely clever particularly an Epitaph on <persName ref="#Wordsworth_Wm">Mr. Wordsworth</persName>--which I don't quite recollect but which was to this effect</p><l>Here lyeth W.W.</l><l>Who never more will trouble you trouble you</l><note resp="#lmw">From stanza 43 of <title ref="#PeterBell_JHR">Peter Bell: A Lyrical Tale</title>: "The letters printed are by fate,/The death they say was suicide;/He reads—"Here lieth W. W./Who never more will trouble you, trouble you:"/The old man smokes who 'tis that died".</note><p>--I am not sure of any part of these lines being quite right except the rhymes--but you will agree with me that they are not to be forgotten.--I saw too a very clever <orgName ref="#Tory">tory</orgName> squib from a little book called the <title ref="#NewWhigGuide">New Whig Guide</title>--there are several very good things in it--but that which struck me particularly was the Trial of <persName ref="#Brougham_H">Henry Brougham</persName> for Mutiny--Nothing can be more laughable. <pb n="3"/> Now you must write to me very soon--&amp; find fault with <title ref="#Camilla_FB">Camilla</title> &amp; tell me that you found your family all well--&amp; if you should be at a loss for a subject send me a description of <placeName ref="#Bickham_village">Bickham</placeName>. I want very much to know all about it.--Adieu my dear Friend--<persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</persName> is in <placeName ref="#London_city">London</placeName>--<persName ref="#Russell_M">Mama</persName> sends her kindest remembrances--</p><closer>&amp; I am ever most sincerely &amp; affectionately <choice><sic>your's</sic><reg>yours</reg></choice><lb/><persName ref="#MRM">M.R. Mitford</persName></closer><postscript><p>P.S. I had a complete elucidation one very dark night soon after your visit of your theory of the <metamark rend="caret" place="below"/><add place="above">remaining</add> senses being quickened by one's lying dormant--We quite traced our way home from <placeName ref="#Wokingham_city">Wokingham</placeName> (9 miles off) by the succession of sweet scents which in the day we had hardly noticed, the bean fields--the stocks &amp; honeysuckles of the Cottage gardens were as completely our landmarks as the fields &amp; cottages themselves could have been in the broad day light. <metamark rend="jerk"/>Adieu once more my dear Friend. Pray excuse my bad writing--worse than common owing to a wretched pen.</p></postscript><closer><address><addrLine><lb/>To <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir William Elford Bar<hi rend="superscript">t</hi></persName></addrLine><addrLine><lb/><placeName ref="#Bickham_village">Bickham</placeName></addrLine><addrLine><lb/><placeName ref="#Plymouth_city">Plymouth</placeName></addrLine><addrLine><lb/><date when="1819-06-08">June 8 1819</date></addrLine></address></closer></div></body><back>
       <!-- backlist pulled to si-add-lmw 2015-10 --><div>
      
           </div></back></text></TEI>