<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><!--<?xml-model href="http://ebeshero.github.io/MRMValidate.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>--><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title xml:id="MRM1738">Letter to <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir William Elford</persName>, <date when="1819-01-09">January 9, 1819</date></title><author ref="#MRM">Mary Russell Mitford</author><editor ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</editor><sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford Project</orgName></sponsor><sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor><sponsor>Pittsburgh Supercomputing Center</sponsor><principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal><respStmt><resp>Transcription and coding by</resp><persName ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</persName><persName ref="#msp">Margo Paine</persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Date last checked: <date when="2015-10-15">2015-10-15</date>
                  Proofing and corrections by</resp><persName ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</persName> <!-- LMW:  corrected letter id and shelfmark. Revised header. 2015-10-15--><persName ref="#mco">Molly C. O'Donnel</persName><persName/></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>First digital edition in TEI, date: <date when="2014-10-10">10 October 2014</date>. P5.</edition><respStmt><resp>Edition made with help from photos taken by</resp><orgName>Digital Mitford editors</orgName></respStmt><respStmt><orgName>Digital Mitford</orgName><resp> photo files: <idno>IMG_0271.jpg, IMG_0272.jpg,IMG_0273.jpg,IMG_0274.jpg</idno></resp></respStmt></editionStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority><pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace><date>2013</date><availability><p>Reproduced by courtesy of the <orgName ref="#ReadingCL">Reading Central Library</orgName>.</p><licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                  License</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Mitford Letters: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><repository ref="#ReadingCL">Reading Central Library</repository><collection>The letters of Mary Russell Mitford, vol. 4, 1819-1823</collection><idno>qB/TU/MIT Vol. 4 Horizon No.: 1361550 ff. 370</idno></msIdentifier><head>Letter from Mary Russell Mitford to Sir William Elford, <date when="1819-05-14">May 14, 1819</date>.</head><physDesc><objectDesc><supportDesc><support><p>One sheet of folio <material>paper</material>, four surfaces photographed.</p><p>Address leaf bearing black postmark, partially illegible, reading <stamp><lb/><placeName>READING</placeName><lb/><lb/>NO 14<lb/><lb/>1819<lb/></stamp>. Also bearing red double circle postmark, partially illegible, reading <lb/>B<lb/><lb/>15<unclear/>15<lb/><lb/>1819<lb/>. Someone has written a large 7 across the address in black ink.</p></support><condition><p>Sheet torn on right edge where wax seal was removed.</p></condition></supportDesc></objectDesc><sealDesc><p>Red wax seal.</p></sealDesc></physDesc></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><handNotes><handNote corresp="#rc" medium="red_crayon"> Red crayon or thick red pencil. Probably a different hand from Mitford's that marks many of her letters, sometimes drawing diagonal lines across pages, and sometimes writing words overtop and perpendicularly across Mitford's writing. On this letter, a red line is drawn from top left to bottom right of each of the 3 leaves containing letter text. The fourth leaf is unmarked.</handNote></handNotes></profileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><p>Mitford’s spelling and punctuation are retained, except where a word is split at the end of a line and the beginning of the next in the manuscript. Where Mitford’s spelling and hyphenation of words deviates from the standard, in order to facilitate searching we are using the TEI elements “choice," “sic," and “reg" to encode both Mitford’s spelling and the regular international standard of Oxford English spelling, following the first listed spelling in the Oxford English Dictionary. The long s and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="letter"><opener><dateline><name type="place" ref="#Bertram_house">Bertram House</name><date when="1819-05-14">May 14<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1819</date>.
               </dateline><salute><persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir W. Elford</persName></salute><add hand="#pencil">9</add></opener><p>It appears to be very unnecessary, <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">my dear friend</persName> to trouble you with a letter just to tell you I am not coming to <placeName ref="#London_city">Town</placeName>--but <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</persName> tells me that he engaged that I should write--so being a dutiful daughter I obey. I am not detained by indisposition or any thing half so pretty-sounding being perfectly recovered from my cough &amp; sound &amp; flourishing as a <name type="plant" ref="#Cabbage_red">red Cabbage</name>in a housewife's garden--indeed it's quite provoking to have had so genteel a complaint (as a young lady of my acquaintance calls it) without the consolation of losing a whit of my ruddiness or rotundity--The reason that I cannot keep the engagement <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</persName> made for me in <placeName ref="#London_city">London</placeName>, is that I had before made one for myself in the Country--a young friend of mine, who is leaving the neighborhood &amp; therefore not put-off-able is coming here for a couple of days on <date when="1819-05-16">Sunday</date>. I regret this very much since it prevents my seeing <persName ref="#James_Miss">Miss James</persName>--I should regret it much more if I thought it would likewise prevent my seeing you but I do not--I have no such fear--You are pledged to the nightingales &amp; <persName ref="#whitekitten_WEpet">white kitten</persName> &amp; under their <del rend="squiggles" unit="word" n="1">influence</del>auspices I shall be fortunate enough to see you myself. My <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Father</persName> will be in <placeName ref="#London_city">Town</placeName> soon--<date when="1819-05-16">Sunday</date>perhaps, or <date when="1819-05-17">Monday</date> or <date when="1819-05-18">Tuesday</date> &amp; you can settle with him or with me by letter when we shall have the pleasure of your company. He will certainly be home by <date when="1819-05-21">Friday</date>, before which day you I understand do not intend to leave <placeName ref="#London_city">London</placeName>.</p><p>So you cannot <del rend="squiggles" unit="word" n="1">read</del>make out my writing! And so my honoured <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Father</persName> cannot help you! Really this is too affronting! The <pb n="2"/> two persons in all the world who have had the most of my letters cannot read them! Well there is the secret of your liking them so much--obscurity is sometimes a great charm--you just make out my meaning &amp; fill it up by the force of your own imagination--the outline is mine--the colouring your own. So much the better for me. I assure you however whatever you may think of the matter that there are persons who write a worse hand than I. Here is my friend <persName ref="#Dickinson_Charles">Mr. Dickinson</persName>--if you saw his writing! He can't read it himself--And if you heard him admire mine! <foreign xml:lang="fr">Parmi les aveugles les borgnes sont Rois</foreign><note resp="#lmw">Proverbial for "Among the blind, the one-eyed is King."</note> for this. He thinks me the greatest (what is the <del rend="squiggles" unit="word" n="1"/>fine grand word for a person who writes a good hand?--Dear me I wish I had a Dictionary!) the greatest Calligrapher (is that <choice><sic>spelt</sic><reg>spelled</reg></choice> right <persName ref="#Russell_M">Mama</persName>?) that ever trod the earth--&amp; I keep up my dignity &amp; never tell him what you say or what <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</persName> says I assure you. By the way <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</persName> says he can read my writing in general--only he was puzzled in that particular case because it was a hard word &amp; he had not got his spectacles. The word is Undine, Sir, U.N.D.I.N.E. Can you read it now?</p><p>I have not seen your friend <title ref="#InvariablePrin_WLB"><persName ref="#Bowles_Wm">Mr. Bowles</persName>'s pamphlet</title>but I have no doubt of his being quite right--I was always of his opinion about <persName ref="#Pope_Alex">Pope</persName>--a great wit--a great Satyrist--a great writer certainly--but not a great Poet in the highest sense of the word, the sense in which <persName ref="#Spenser_Edmund">Spenser</persName>&amp; <persName ref="#Milton">Milton</persName> are Poets. Even if <persName ref="#Campbell_Thos">Mr. Campbell</persName> had been right in the matter of his criticism his manner was the very worst that could have been devised<note resp="#lmw">In 1806, Bowles had edited a ten-volume edition of the complete works of Pope, entitled The Works of Alexander Pope, Esq., in Verse and Prose: Containing the Principal Notes of Drs. Warburton and Warton. When Campbell published his Specimens of British Poets in 1819, Bowles replied with a pamphlet entitled The invariable principles of poetry, in a letter addressed to Thomas Campbell, Esq.; occasioned by some critical observations in his Specimens of British poets, particularly relating to the poetical character of Pope. Bowles continued the controversy into 1821 with a pamphlet to Byron entitled Two letters to the Right Honorable Lord Byron, in answer to his Lordship's letter to **** ******  on the Rev. Wm. L. Bowles's strictures on the life and writings of Pope: more particularly on the question, whether poetry be more immediately indebted to what is sublime or beautiful in the works of nature, or the works of art?</note>--an attempt at a sneer--not a sneer proper--for a good sneer is a great thing--a man had need have the upper lip of a Greek statue to to execute it--your good sneerers &amp; have been of different persons from <persName ref="#Campbell_Thos">Mr. Thomas Campbell</persName>--<persName ref="#Voltaire">Voltaire</persName>--<persName ref="#HorneTooke">Horne <pb n="3"/> Tooke</persName>, <persName ref="#Byron">Lord Byron</persName>, <persName ref="#Napoleon">Buonaparte</persName>--these are your sneerers--Now <persName ref="#Campbell_Thos">Mr. Campbell</persName> is a pretty poet &amp; a <quote>"smooth &amp; sober gentleman"</quote><note resp="#lmw">A quotation from <title ref="#EdinburghRev_per">The Edinburgh Review</title> on <title ref="#BrPoets_Campbell">Campbell's work</title> from <date when="1819-03">March 1819</date>.</note> as he says of <persName ref="#Drummond_Wm">Drummond of Hawthornden</persName>--but no sneerer. He can't sneer, he does not know how--but he tries with all his might &amp; main, &amp; the objects whom he selects for this very unlucky attempt are <persName ref="#Bowles_Wm">Mr. Bowles</persName>, <persName ref="#Lamb_Chas">Mr. Lamb</persName> (a much better critic than himself by the bye) <persName ref="#Webster_John">Webster</persName>, one of the greatest dramatists of the great Dramatic age &amp; <persName ref="#Fletcher_John">Fletcher</persName>'s <title ref="#FaithfulShepherdess_JF">Faithful Shepherdess</title>, the finest pastoral in any language. Truly I think he has put <persName ref="#Bowles_Wm">Mr. Bowles</persName> into very good company.</p><p>I have heard in two letters from <placeName ref="#London_city">Town</placeName> from people who love Painting of the fine landscape which <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</persName> tells me is to be a landscape royal--<unclear><supplied resp="#lmw">O rare!</supplied></unclear> He tells me of two of the flowers which are not in <rs type="place" ref="#RoyalAcademy">the Exhibition</rs> but which will be I hope next year. I always thought the <gap reason="torn" quantity="1" unit="word"/><unclear><supplied resp="#lmw">anemone</supplied></unclear> one of the loveliest of all flowers--the one which is fitter for painting because it has no scent to lose &amp; all its char<gap reason="torn" quantity="1" unit="chars"/><unclear><supplied resp="#lmw">m</supplied></unclear> can be given by that lovely Art. Some of the purple &amp; red <name ref="#anemone">Anenomes</name>preserve the rich lost tints of the old stained glass--You are lucky that a friend is just come to interrupt me &amp; save you a platitude about Nature's never losing a beauty or a sunset, &amp;c, &amp;,--.</p><p>Goodbye my dear <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir William</persName>--Good bless you--Kindest regards from <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#Russell_M">Mama</persName>.</p><closer><lb/>Ever most affectionately<choice><sic>your's</sic><reg resp="#lmw">yours</reg></choice><lb/><persName ref="#MRM">M.R. Mitford</persName>.<lb/></closer><postscript><p>Have we any chance of seeing <persName ref="#Elford_J">Mr. Elford</persName> with you? People do not speak of him as they do of the rest of the world--I hope his distressing complaint is relieved--Adieu--</p></postscript><closer><address><pb n="4"/><addrLine><lb/><date when="1819-05-14"/>May 14<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></addrLine><addrLine>1819</addrLine><addrLine><lb/>To <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir William Elford</persName> Bart</addrLine><addrLine><lb/>176<placeName ref="#Piccadilly"> Piccadilly</placeName></addrLine><addrLine><lb/><placeName ref="#London_city">London</placeName></addrLine></address></closer></div></body></text></TEI>