<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><!--<?xml-model href="http://ebeshero.github.io/MRMValidate.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>--><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title xml:id="MRM1737">Letter to <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir William Elford</persName>, <date when="1819-04-08">1819 April 8</date></title><author ref="#MRM">Mary Russell Mitford</author><editor ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</editor><sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford Project</orgName></sponsor><sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor><sponsor>Pittsburgh Supercomputing Center</sponsor><principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal><respStmt><resp>Transcription and coding by</resp><persName ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</persName><persName ref="#tlh">Tracy Harnish</persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Proofing and corrections by</resp><persName ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</persName><!-- LMW; proofing and updated header 2015 10 11. --></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>First digital edition in TEI, date: <date when="2014-11-08">8 November 2014</date>. P5.</edition><respStmt><resp>Edition made with help from photos taken by</resp><orgName>Digital Mitford editors</orgName></respStmt><respStmt><orgName>Digital Mitford</orgName><resp> photo files: <idno>IMG_0262.jpg, IMG_0263.jpg, IMG_0264.jpg, IMG_0265.jpg, IMG_0266.jpg, IMG_0267.jpg, IMG_0268.jpg, IMG_0269.jpg</idno></resp></respStmt></editionStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority><pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace><date>2013</date><availability><p>Reproduced by courtesy of the <orgName ref="#ReadingCL">Reading Central Library</orgName>.</p><licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                  License</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Mitford Letters: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><repository ref="#ReadingCL">Reading Central Library</repository><collection>The letters of Mary Russell Mitford, vol. 4, 1819-1823</collection><idno>qB/TU/MIT Vol. 4 Horizon No.: 1361550 ff. 368</idno></msIdentifier><head>Letter from Mary Russell Mitford to Sir William Elford, <date when="1819-04-08">April 8, 1819</date>.</head><physDesc><objectDesc><supportDesc><support><p>One and one-half sheets of folio <material>paper</material>, six surfaces photographed.</p><p>Address leaf bearing black mileage stamp, partially illegible, reading <stamp><lb/><placeName>WOKINGHAM</placeName><lb/><lb/>35<lb/></stamp>.</p></support><condition><p>Half sheet (pages five and six) torn on right edge where wax seal was removed.</p></condition></supportDesc></objectDesc><sealDesc><p>Red wax seal.</p></sealDesc></physDesc></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><handNotes><handNote corresp="#rc" medium="red_crayon"> Red crayon or thick red pencil. Probably a different hand from Mitford's that marks many of her letters, sometimes drawing diagonal lines across pages, and sometimes writing words overtop and perpendicularly across Mitford's writing. On this letter, a red line is drawn from top left to bottom right of each of the leaves. On leaf six (the address leaf), red lines are drawn from top left to bottom right over each of two text blocks.</handNote><handNote corresp="#pencil" medium="pencil"> Someone, apparently other than Mitford, perhaps cataloging letters and describing them, who left grey pencil marks and numbered her letters now in the Reading Central Library's collection. This letter is numbered "8" in the top left of the first leaf.
            </handNote></handNotes></profileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><p>Mitford’s spelling and punctuation are retained, except where a word is split at the end of a line and the beginning of the next in the manuscript. Where Mitford’s spelling and hyphenation of words deviates from the standard, in order to facilitate searching we are using the TEI elements “choice," “sic," and “reg" to encode both Mitford’s spelling and the regular international standard of Oxford English spelling, following the first listed spelling in the Oxford English Dictionary. The long s and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="letter"><opener><salute>To <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir W. Elford</persName></salute><add hand="#pencil">8</add><dateline><name type="place" ref="#Bertram_house">Bertram House</name><date when="1819-04-08">April 8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1819</date>.
               </dateline><salute/></opener><p>No--I have not fixed any time for going to Town--I don't think I shall be there before the middle of <date when="1819-05">May</date>--It depends on half a hundred trifling contingencies--or rather I believe the country is so lovely in this <name type="plant" ref="#cowslip">Cowslip</name>-tide--one has such pleasure in <emph rend="underline">doddering</emph> along the hedgerows, gathering <name type="plant" ref="#violet">violets</name> &amp; <name type="plant" ref="#woodsorrel">wood sorrel</name>--listening to the woodlark--watching for the nightingale--Such enjoyment in the mere consciousness of existence in this sunny springy atmosphere with all its sweet scents &amp; sounds, that there is no making up one's mind to leave it for smoky dusty <placeName ref="#London_city">London</placeName>--So I make excuses to myself &amp; my friends, &amp; invent apologies <metamark rend="caret" place="below" function="insertion"/><add place="above">for staying at home</add> which everybody believes--even myself--from all this you will find, my dear <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir William</persName>, that must <emph rend="underline">come</emph> &amp; fetch the <persName ref="#whitekitten_WEpet">white kitten</persName> Will you? You must come--the nightingales will never fail us in such beautiful weather--&amp; in that you must come either going or coming. Let me know two days before that I may be sure to be at home--two days are necessary because our Post boy is sometimes not here till long after we have ridden out--&amp; if you do not come in your journey to <placeName ref="#London_city">Town</placeName> tell me where you shall be when there--that if I should (as may possibly happen) be in <placeName ref="#London_city">London</placeName> I may let you know. Of course we should be very happy to see your friend with the magnificant name--Mr. Champer--Champern. <unclear reason="illegible"><supplied resp="#lmw"><persName ref="#Champernowne_A">Champernowne</persName></supplied></unclear>(you have written this name as badly as ever I wrote) Mr.<unclear><supplied resp="#lmw">Champernowne</supplied></unclear> with you. You will prepare him for our homely ways. But you must come either upwards or downwards.</p><metamark rend="jerk"/><p>You are more candid to your enemies than I am to my <pb n="2"/>Friends--(political friends &amp; Enemies I mean) but that's not saying much--candour's not my forte. Your account of <persName ref="#Northmore_Thos">Mr. Northmore</persName> is charity itself. I think much the better of him for what you say--&amp; probably Absence, like distance in a landscape has tended to soften down the rugged points &amp; glaring hues of his character. <persName ref="#Northmore_Thos">Mr. Northmore</persName> is much better calculated for recollected than a present friend. This is my last word of him--perhaps the last word would have been saucier still had <title ref="#WashingtonEpic_TN">Washington</title> made its appearance--but as that <said>"heroic in Tens"</said><note resp="#lmw">A reference to Northmore's epic poem on George Washington, the phrase refers to the convention of epics being written in ten cantos. Mr. Bellamy advises her to create an epic out of the Book of Ruth.</note> (as <persName ref="#Bellamy_John">Mr. Bellamy the Bible-man</persName> once advised me to construct out of the <title ref="#Ruth_OT">book of Ruth</title>) has not yet arrived here for me to yawn &amp; stretch &amp; pity myself over &amp; try to praise--why I can afford to be charitable enough.</p><metamark rend="jerk"/><p>Upon my honour you had never before told me the story of <persName ref="#Marriott_Mr">Mr. Marriott</persName>--I would not have lost for <quote>"all the worlds one ever has to give"</quote><note resp="#lmw">A quotation from chapter 28 of <persName ref="#Austen_Jane">Austen</persName>'s <title ref="#Emma_JA">Emma</title></note>--It is admirable. Is not somebody with such supernatural pretentions mentioned in one of the periodical papers? I think <title ref="#Spectator">the Spectator</title>. In <persName ref="#Marriott_Mr">Mr. Marriott</persName>'s case I apprehend the addresses first sent deterred him from exerting his powers--he might very willingly have accomodated some ready believer--some cullible <note resp="#lmw">A now-obsolete words that describes someone who is easily deceived, similar to "gullible" Source:  OED.</note>Squire or Squiress--but when he found he had to do with an acute &amp; sceptical man of wit (I hope you let me tell this truth) then he drew in his horns--There is in the new &amp; delightful volume of <title ref="#ClarkesTravelsScand">Clarke's Travels in Sweden, Norway &amp; so forth</title> an anecdote of a Baron who professed Animal Magnetism which quite confirms my idea--he was pressed to show off by <persName ref="#Clarke_ED">Dr. Clarke</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#Acerbi_J">Signor Acerbi</persName> (the other great Northern Traveller) &amp; performed very sucessfully upon the led Italian &amp; the led Englishman Messieurs <persName ref="#Lucetti">Lucetti</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#Cripps_JM">Cripps</persName>, but utterly failed when he attempted their shrewd &amp; wary leaders. Depend upon it if you had sent letters addressed to some Mr. Smith or Miss Brown, or <pb n="3"/>even to <emph rend="underline"><name ref="#Webb_James">J. Webb</name></emph> Esq<hi rend="superscript">re</hi> he would have given you the amusement you required. Do tell me if you ever hear<del rend="squiggles" unit="word" n="1">of</del> any more of this curious affair. Is he the <persName ref="#Marriott_Mr">Mr. Marriott</persName>, <persName ref="#Scott_Wal">Walter Scott</persName>'s friend to whom one of the letters between the Cantos of <title ref="#Marmion_WS">Marmion</title> are addressed? He was a clergyman and went to live in <placeName ref="#Devonshire_county">Devonshire</placeName>--You will see that I have recovered my appetite for reading--I have been quite delighted with <persName ref="#Clarke_ED">Dr. Clarke</persName> as I told you--very much amused with <title ref="#TomCrib">"Tom Crib's Memorial"</title> the Battle is capital--better than <title ref="#TwopennyPost">the Twopenny post bag</title>--better than <title ref="#FudgeFamilyParis">the Fudge's</title>--in short <persName ref="#Moore_Thos">Moore</persName>'s best--all the best is "Caviare"--Then I have admired <persName ref="#Rogers_Sam">Mr. Rogers</persName>'s <title ref="#HumanLife_SR">Human Life</title>--with a certain quiet &amp; calm sort of admiration such as one bestows on those which are works very short &amp; seem very long--I have been very much pleased <title ref="#KingAnecd"><persName ref="#King_Wm">Dr. King</persName>'s Anecdotes</title>--a curious little book in which amongst many other choice stories he insinuates that a certain Poet called <persName ref="#Pope_Alex">Mr. Pope</persName> died of Dram drinking--&amp; gives an account of <persName ref="#James_oldPretender">the Pretender</persName> which if there were such things as Jacobites now a days would cure them though it did not cure the author--moreover I have been perfectly disgusted with <persName ref="#Maturin_Charles">Mr. Maturin</persName>'s <title ref="#Women_CM">Women</title> --a vile hotch potch of <title ref="#Glenarvon_fict">Glenarvon</title> &amp; <title ref="#Corinne_deS">Corinne</title>--such a book as any clergyman, not Irish, would have blushed to write--very much amused with <persName ref="#Holcroft_Thos">Holcroft</persName>'s <title ref="#Holcroft_Mems">Memoirs</title>, begun by himself &amp; finished by <persName ref="#Hazlitt_Wm">Hazlitt</persName>--quite delighted with <title ref="#Undine">Undine</title> the prettiest German story of a watersprite that ever was written--all poetry from end to end--&amp; charmed--enchanted with another new Volume of <persName ref="#Walpole_Hor">Horace Walpole</persName>'s letters<note resp="#lmw">It is unclear to which volume of Walpole's many volumes of letters Mitford refers here, since several volumes to different recipients appeared in the 1810's. The most likely candidate is <title ref="#WalpoletoMontagu">Letters from the Hon. Horace Walpole to George Montagu, Esq. from the year 1736, to the year 1770: Now first published from the originals in the possession of the editor</title>, published by Rodwell and Martin in 1818 and published in a second edition in 1819.</note>--That <persName ref="#Walpole_Hor">Horace Walpole</persName> was beyond a doubt the best letter writer of his day better than <persName ref="#hume">Hume</persName>--better than <persName ref="#Gray_Thos">Gray</persName>--better than <persName ref="#Cowper">Cowper</persName>--you and I thought so always--the world seems now to be pretty much of the same opinion--&amp; I mean to reward the world by cheating <pb n="4"/> it into pleasure in the same way that a very whimsical friend of mine <choice><sic>chuses</sic><reg>chooses</reg></choice>\to preserve the common practice by giving <choice><sic>Champaign</sic><reg>Champagne</reg></choice> under the name of Gooseberry wine. I intend to treat the public with a 3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> Volume of Walpolian letters--a little later in point of time--&amp; dated not from <placeName ref="#Strawberry_Hill">Strawberry Hill</placeName> but from <placeName ref="#Devonshire_county">Devonshire</placeName>--I shall leave out names &amp; <del rend="squiggles" unit="word" n="1">changes</del> places &amp; I have no doubt of taking in the whole "Reading Public"--<title ref="#EdinburghRev_per">Edinburgh</title> &amp; <title ref="#QuarterlyRev_per">Quarterly</title> Reviewers not excepted. How do you like my plan? Shall you apply for an Injunction to the <persName ref="#Scott_John_LdEldon">Chancellor</persName> to stop the publication? Seriously, my dear <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir William</persName>, the resemblance in style, in playfulness, in humour, in Tact, is so perfect that if ever your letters should be printed anonymously I am sure they would be attributed to <persName ref="#Walpole_Hor">Horace Walpole</persName>. People would miss a little of our honourable Friends small talk to be sure, &amp; a great deal his selfishness &amp; coldness, but in every other respect they <metamark rend="caret" place="below" function="insertion"/><add place="above">are</add> as much alike as <persName ref="#Sebastian_TN">Sebastian</persName> was to <persName ref="#Viola_TN">Viola</persName>.</p><metamark rend="jerk"/><p>I am very much obliged to you for your kindness respecting the poor <persName ref="#Hofland_B #Hofland_TC">Hoflands</persName>--things are very bad at <placeName ref="#Whiteknights">Whiteknights</placeName>--I don't think they will ever get anything but the sale of those 50 copies--for the <persName ref="#Scott_John_LdEldon">Chancellor</persName> has no respect for the Arts--&amp; <persName ref="#Geo_SpencerChurchill">the Duke</persName>'s vanity will now be as much mortified by <del rend="squiggle" unit="word" n="1">at</del><add place="above">by</add> this Catalogue &amp; description of pictures &amp; books which are there no longer as it would once have been gratified. Nothing can be more pitiable than this loss to <persName ref="#Hofland_TC">Mr. Hofland</persName>. They are excellent people--with regard to <persName ref="#James_Miss">Miss James</persName> all my eloquence was quite unnecessary for they have relinquished the plan--At least as I understand from a letter I have just received from her--the only silly letter I suppose she ever wrote in her life, in which meaning to tell things delicately to avoid all vulgar mention of Governess-ships <pb n="5"/>Schools, money &amp; such vulgar things she is as obscure as one of <persName ref="#Castlereagh_RS">Lord Castlereagh</persName>'s explanations.  I am quite glad to have detected this sweet but too perfect creature in such a silly fault. It seems like animating <persName ref="#Pygmalion">Pygmalion</persName>'s Statue</p><metamark rend="jerk"/><p>Our <persName ref="#Palmer_CF">M.P.</persName> is to make his triumphal entry into <placeName ref="#Reading_city">Reading</placeName> next <date when="1819-04-13">Tuesday</date>--in a grand procession--masculine &amp; feminine. Pray is it common for ladies to make part of the Cortege on such an occasion? I thought the Etiquette was to stand at windows &amp; in balconies waving handkerchiefs &amp; looking as pretty as possible--However the present plan is that ladies (<persName ref="#Palmer_Mad">Lady Madalina</persName> included) are to fill all manner of Barouches Curricles Postchaises Gigs &amp; Carts--(to say nothing of the Pedestrian Elegantes) &amp; to make in this way the Tour of our independent Borough. Don't tell--but I am afraid our Pat<gap reason="torn" unit="chars" quantity="5"/><unclear><supplied resp="#lmw">riota</supplied></unclear> are a little cowardly &amp; put <metamark rend="caret" place="below" function="insertion"/><add place="above">on</add> all these petticoats for <add place="above">fear</add> prote<gap reason="torn" unit="chars" n="5"/><unclear><supplied resp="#lmw">ction</supplied></unclear> The <persName ref="#Weyland_John">Weylandites</persName> being prodigiously enraged at the failure of their petition &amp; ready enough to vent their wrath in besetting their adversary--What a strange thing party spirit is! These <persName ref="#Palmer_CF">Palmer</persName>ites are almost to a man reformers &amp; <persName ref="#Burdett_F">Burdett</persName>ites &amp; <persName ref="#Cartwright_Maj">Cartwright</persName>ites as violent as <persName ref="#Northmore_Thos">Mr. Northmore</persName> himself--haters of pensions--at least of all pensions but this--&amp; now for the success of this Pension they prepare not only an Ovation but a Triumph. Well it is one step toward consistency to see the inconsistency of others--&amp; another not to ride behind the pension--which I don't intend to do--having the offer of a most convenient window &amp; being something of the dear <persName ref="#GeoIV">King</persName>'s mind who told <persName ref="#Beechey_W">Sir W. Beechey</persName> vide <title ref="#Holcroft_Mems"><persName ref="#Holcroft_Thos">Holcroft</persName>'s Memoirs</title>) <q>"That he envied him the right of a Procession to <placeName ref="#StPauls">St. Paul's</placeName>, he being able to see nothing but the back of his <pb n="6"/> Coachman."</q>--<persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</persName> who was very unpolitely looking over my shoulder <metamark rend="caret" place="below" function="insertion"/><add place="above">has just</add> told me as I turned the page that the plan was altered &amp; after being advertised in handbills &amp; <placeName ref="#Reading_city">Reading</placeName> papers, ladies were not to go--because they could only muster <emph rend="underline">4</emph> or <emph rend="underline">5</emph> handsome carriages--so that the procession is now to be almost all mounted &amp; all male, &amp; the ladies are to look on--Really we patriots are so poor its quite shocking.--You will not suspect me of having fabricated this story of the ladies' procession in order to fill up a page--My credit for <unclear reason="illegible"/> in nonsense stands so high with you that I have no fear of that accusation.--</p><metamark rend="jerk"/><p>Adieu my dear Friend--Kindest regards from <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</persName> &amp; <persName>Mama</persName>--Write soon--&amp; above all Come--</p><closer><lb/>Ever most affectionately <choice><sic>your's</sic><reg>yours</reg></choice><lb/><signed><persName ref="#MRM">M.R. Mitford</persName></signed><lb/></closer><postscript><p>The <persName ref="#whitekitten_WEpet">white kitten</persName> sends a very fine message half love half duty</p></postscript><closer><address><pb n="6"/><addrLine><placeName ref="#Wokingham_city">Wokingham</placeName><date when="1819-04-13"/>April Thirteen</addrLine><addrLine>1819</addrLine><addrLine><persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir W<hi rend="superscript">m</hi>Elford</persName> Bart</addrLine><addrLine><placeName ref="#Bickham_village">Bickham</placeName></addrLine><addrLine><placeName ref="#Plymouth_city">Plymouth</placeName></addrLine><addrLine><persName ref="#Palmer_CF">CFPalmer</persName></addrLine></address></closer></div></body><back>
            
           
         </back></text></TEI>