<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><?xml-model href="http://ebeshero.github.io/MRMValidate.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title xml:id="MRM1739">Letter to <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir William Elford</persName>, May 30, 1819</title><author ref="#MRM">Mary Russell Mitford</author><editor ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</editor><sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford Project</orgName></sponsor><sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor><sponsor>Pittsburgh Supercomputing Center</sponsor><principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal><respStmt><resp>Transcription and coding by</resp><persName ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</persName><persName ref="#oa">Olivia Allard</persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Date last checked: <date when="2015-10-18">2015-10-18</date>
               Proofing and corrections by</resp>
               <!-- List all proofreaders here, <persName> by <persName>.--><persName ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</persName></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>First digital edition in TEI, date:  <date when="2015-10-06">6 October 2015</date>. P5.</edition><respStmt><resp>Edition made with help from photos taken by</resp><orgName>Digital Mitford editors</orgName></respStmt><respStmt><orgName>Digital Mitford</orgName><resp> photo files: <idno>DSCF9464.jpg, DSCF9465.jpg, DSCF 9466.jpg, DSCF9467.jpg, DSCF9468.jpg, DSCF9469.jpg, DSCF9470.jpg, DSCF9471.jpg, DSCF9472.jpg, DSCF9473.jpg, DSCF9474.j pg, DSCF9475.jpg</idno></resp></respStmt></editionStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority><pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace><date>2013</date><availability><p>Reproduced by courtesy of the <orgName ref="#ReadingCL">Reading Central Library</orgName>.</p><licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                  License</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Mitford Letters: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><repository ref="#ReadingCL">Reading Central Library</repository><collection>The letters of Mary Russell Mitford, vol. 4, 1819-1823</collection><idno>qB/TU/MIT Vol. 4 Horizon No.: 1361550 ff. 371</idno></msIdentifier><head>Letter from Mary Russell Mitford to Sir William Elford, <date when="1819-05-30">1819 May 30</date>. 
                  
               </head><physDesc><objectDesc><supportDesc><support><p>One and a half leaves of <material>paper</material>, six surfaces photographed. Folded in half, folded again in thirds for sealing. </p><p>Address leaf bearing black postmark, partially illegible, reading <stamp><lb/><placeName>NEWBURY</placeName><lb/></stamp>.</p></support><condition><p>Sheet (pages five and six) torn on edge of page three where wax seal was removed.</p></condition></supportDesc></objectDesc><sealDesc><p>Red wax seal, complete, wrong side facing, adhered to page six.</p></sealDesc></physDesc></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><handNotes><handNote corresp="#rc" medium="red_crayon"> Red crayon or thick red pencil. Probably a different hand from Mitford's that marks many of her letters, sometimes drawing diagonal lines across pages, and sometimes writing words overtop and perpendicularly across Mitford's writing. A red line is drawn from top left to bottom right of each of the first five leaves. On leaf six, a red line is drawn from top left to bottom right across each of the two text blocks. There is no red crayon across the address text block.</handNote><handNote corresp="#pencil" medium="pencil"> Someone, apparently other than Mitford, perhaps cataloging letters and describing them, who left grey pencil marks and numbered her letters now in the Reading Central Library's collection. This letter is numbered "10" in the top left of the first leaf.
           </handNote></handNotes></profileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><p>Mitford’s spelling and punctuation are retained, except where a word is split at the end of a line and the beginning of the next in the manuscript. Where Mitford’s spelling and hyphenation of words deviates from the standard, in order to facilitate searching we are using the TEI elements “choice," “sic," and “reg" to encode both Mitford’s spelling and the regular international standard of Oxford English spelling, following the first listed spelling in the Oxford English Dictionary. The long s and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="letter"><opener><add hand="#pencil">10</add><dateline><name type="place" ref="#Bertram_house">Bertram House</name><date when="1819-05-30">May 30<hi rend="superscript">th </hi>1819</date>. 
               </dateline><salute>To <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir William Elford</persName>--&gt;</salute></opener><p><persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</persName> having made <persName ref="#Dundas_C">Mr. Dundas</persName> promise and repromise not to transmogrify you into a lady (or as once before happened you know my dear friend) &amp; I avail myself of his obliging offer to transmit to you "these presents"--indeed I am impatient to thank you again &amp; again for the delightful kindness of your visit, to tell you how deeply we all regarded its shortness, &amp; with how much pleasure we anticipate a visit into <placeName ref="#Devonshire">Devonshire</placeName>--this year. I do hope we shall not be disappointed--only I must try not to set my heart too much on it, for I am unlucky &amp; if I do our plans will be sure to be overturned--I got your kindest of all kind letters <date>Tuesday</date> morning--<persName ref="#Dickinson_Mrs">Mrs. Dickinson</persName> was still with us having kept prisoner by the loss of her carriage horses which <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</persName> &amp; I by the way, who were obliged to go in our elegant machine ten miles through the rain to a birthday dinner <!--2 words here I don't know--> in the good town of <placeName ref="#Wokingham_city">Wokingham</placeName><metamark rend="caret" place="below"/><add place="above"> as we were coming home</add> Monday night--so I showed her what you said of her, &amp; she laughed &amp; exclaimed &amp; was very much pleased. She is a most excellent person. I assure you I never yet know any human being so perfectly fine &amp; single minded--of so pure &amp; generous &amp; lofty a spirit. She is compared to the common run of accomplished women what sculpture is to paintings--something real &amp; solid &amp; unadorned. I don't say this because I love her very dearly &amp; because she is unutterably good to me but that is my genuine &amp; impartial opinion as to her literary taste I think as badly as you do--this to say my<pb n="2"/> opinion like your Worship's happens to be quite different. I wish you had heard her sing! That is her forte. Such a voice! Such compass! Such power! And as never can happen without power such expression! She will sing the finest highest music of <persName ref="#Handel">Handel</persName>, <persName ref="#Haydn">Haydn</persName> or <persName ref="#Mozart">Mozart</persName> with an enunciation of the words as just &amp; as perfect, as true to the letter &amp; of meaning as you or I would give in reading them. Nothing but the perfect ease which results from the certainty of power could enable her to do this--Her voice dances on a rope just as securely as one walks on the ground.--though by the way had she sung in your sublime presence this said voice might have got a tumble--but she is more nervous at times than can be conceived &amp; I have seen her obliged to sit down when singing only two or three intimate friends first &amp; not able even to talk all the rest of the evening. Perhaps my dear <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir William</persName>, I have said all this before. You talk sometimes of your repetitions whilst the only one you ever make is that fear of repeating yourself--Now to me nothing is more probable than that I should write over &amp; over again the same thing--living constantly at home--seeing so few people--with so little variety of pursuit of &amp; a happy <del rend="squiggles" quantity="1" unit="chars"/>facility of forgetting any nonsense I may write the moment I have sent it off--with all these elements of "tautology of sense" as I once absurdly called it--the probability is that I am as great a repeater as <persName ref="#Richardson_Sam">Richardson</persName> &amp; nothing but my having the most indulgent Correspondent in the world &amp; administering my tediousness in distant doses prevents my being turned off like <persName ref="#Clarissa_fict">Clarissa</persName> or <persName ref="#Chas_Grandison_fict"/>Sir Charles Grandison. Having thus apologized for talking of my <persName ref="#Dickinson_Mrs">Mrs. Dickinson</persName> &amp; telling you what I had probably <pb n="3"/>told you before I must now talk a little of that very clever very odd man her husband--You would gather from one conversation <add place="above">that <persName ref="#Dickinson_Charles">Mr. Dickinson</persName> not only translate but is <unclear/></add>the story of the Translations (in which affair you deserted me very treacherously for you must know that I was right, &amp; must I think have admired a little at the modesty which was proved by a desire to publish these poems with a puffing preface a la <unclear/><persName ref="#Dickinson_Charles">Mr. Dickinson</persName> is besides <add place="above">an original Poet (in</add><del rend="squiggles" unit="chars" quantity="3"/> that capacity rather baddish) having written an unreadable quarto styled <title ref="#Cyllenius_epic">the Travels of Cyllenius</title>--a sort of didactic Epic--a great patriot--quite an Ultra--one of <persName ref="#Cartwright_Maj">Major Cartwright</persName>'s disciples (N.B I don't go so far by ten degrees--I am a very moderate person--very moderate indeed--neither <orgName ref="#Whigs">Whig</orgName> nor <orgName ref="#Tory">Tory</orgName> nor <orgName>Reformer</orgName>--Nothing but a Buonapartiste--a simple Buonapartiste!)--a very accomplished &amp; eloquent man (though sometimes when one wants him  to talk especially in a party he won't say a word--I have seen him sit at the bottom of his own table looking just like a whipt schoolboy) &amp; without any "but" or "though" or any parenthesis or compunction whatever the finest reader of Poetry English French or Italian that I ever heard in my life. To hear him read or recite the finest parts of <title ref="#Hamlet_play">Hamlet</title><title ref="#King_Lear_play">Lear</title> or <title ref="#Othello_play">Othello</title> is a thousand times better than to see <persName ref="#Kean_Edmund">Kean</persName> in them--It realizes the idea one has of <persName ref="#Garrick_David">Garrick</persName>--the passion is quite aweful. For the rest he is in manner a perfect Gentleman &amp; in mind singularly benevolent &amp; provokingly just, for he will dispute an odd <del rend="squiggles" unit="word" quantity="1"/> shilling for twelve good years &amp; make twenty quarrels for twenty pence whilst he would think nothing of giving away a hundred pounds of supporting a dozen poor families--From this <emph rend="underline">clear</emph> character you may <pb n="4"/> gather that he is respected &amp; beloved by the poor &amp; a little shunned by the Gentry--indeed if it were not for his splendid hospitability &amp; his Wife I don't think one of them would go near him. I like him very much &amp; think him the best reader &amp; the best Translator in the world--only I wish he would publish his Translations quietly without wanting me to intermeddle.--Mem:  I shan't.--<persName ref="#Dickinson_Mrs">Mrs. Dickinson</persName> was delighted with your promise to read <title ref="#Camilla_FB">Camilla</title>--I don't much think you will find <persName ref="#MandlebertE_char">Mr. Edgar Mandlebert</persName> (the very name is as stiff as poker) improve on acquaintance--the only persons in that book who much delighted me, were <persName ref="#Camilla_char">Camilla</persName> herself <persName ref="#DubsterMr_Camilla">Mr. Dubster</persName>, &amp; <persName ref="#HughSir_Camilla">Sir Hugh</persName>--that delightful <persName ref="#HughSir_Camilla">Sir Hugh</persName>! And they are precisely I believe the three whom <persName ref="#Dickinson_Mrs">Mrs. Dickinson</persName> would if she could leave out--at least she skips them--just as she does <persName ref="#Mr_Dexter_fict">Mr. Dexter</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#LadySingleton_fict">Lady Singleton</persName> in <title ref="#ODonnel_SO">ODonnel</title>. But I always thought poor <persName ref="#Camilla_char">Camilla</persName>'s fate so terrible in being joined to that man, that I had hardly patience to read the rest of the book--And to confess to you a truth (which may I believe be more safely said now than it might have been twenty years ago) I do not think very highly of any of <persName ref="#Burney_F">Madame D'Arblay</persName>'s books. The style is so strutting--she does so stalk about on <persName ref="#Johnson">Dr. Johnson</persName>'s old stilts.  What she says wants so much translating into common English &amp; when translated would seem so commonplace, that I have always felt strongly tempted to read all the serious parts with my finger's ends. Comedy is her strong side or rather farce--her <persName ref="#SmithMr_Evelina">Mr. Smith</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#BranghtonMiss_Evelina">Miss Branghton</persName>, <persName ref="#DubsterMr_Camilla">Mr. Dubster</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#BriggsMr_Cecilia">Mr. Briggs</persName> are as good as any characters can be which appear <del rend="squiggles" unit="chars" quantity="1"/> always to exemplify one unmixed quality--they are personifications  of coxcombry vulgarity &amp; avarice <metamark rend="caret" place="below"/><add place="above">&amp; are compared to the mixed characters the human beings of <persName ref="#Austen_Jane">Miss Austen</persName></add>--something like the comedy of humours introduced by <persName ref="#Jonson_B">Ben Jonson</persName> in opposition to the Comedy of nature which <persName ref="#Shakespeare">Shakespeare</persName> wrote probably unconsciously--or as a picture would be composed of unmixed colours, by the side <pb n="5"/>of one where the tints were properly blended.--Pray forgive this critique--written with even more than usual puzzleheadedness--thought upon paper isntead of being considered in the addled brains of <del rend="squiggles" unit="word" quantity="1">the</del>your poor little correspondent--&amp; sent to you with the confident carelessness which your too great goodness has encouraged.</p><metamark rend="jerk"/><p><persName>Lady Pitt</persName>'s death has added a thousand a year to the <persName ref="#Wellington_Duke">Duke of Wellington</persName>'s new estate<note resp="#lmw">George Pitt, 2nd Baron Rivers sold this portion of his estates (Stratfield Saye) in 1818 to the crown, in order that the crown could award them to the Duke of Wellington.</note>. This great Captain of ours is a prodigiously lucky man. Besides the property he gets a very pretty place, finely situated--If he should build he will probably live in that house till his palace is completed. You did not leave me the four landmarks you promised--You must send them to me in your next.</p><metamark rend="jerk"/><p>I am going this week (unless it should be good enough to rain which seems likely) To a great Christening twenty mi<gap reason="torn" unit="chars" quantity="3"/><unclear><supplied resp="#lmw">les</supplied></unclear> off in <placeName ref="#Oxfordshire">Oxfordshire</placeName>--a very shocking prospect--Christen<gap reason="torn" unit="chars" quantity="4"/><unclear><supplied>ings</supplied></unclear> &amp; weddings &amp; such like things are always bad enough e<gap reason="torn" unit="chars" quantity="3"/><unclear><supplied>spe</supplied></unclear>cially where there are dozens of Uncles &amp; Aunts, &amp; Grandfathers &amp;Grandmothers &amp; Brothers &amp; Sisters <metamark rend="caret" place="below"/><add place="above">&amp; Nephews &amp; Nieces</add> to all eternity--but in addition to this tremendous family congregation there is a quarrel to be made up metamark rend="caret" place="below"/&gt;<add place="above">a quarrel about nothing between two old Dons</add> &amp; there will be crying &amp; all the <unclear/> of a Scene--always a shocking thing to me who can't cry &amp; am sometimes apt to laugh. <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</persName> is Godfather &amp; will take me because they are civil enough to make a fuss--but I intend to get out of it if I can--I should take up more room than they can spare, unless the young ladies lay in Strata as Tom Crib says--&amp; moreover I am quite sure that with one horse &amp; the tackle &amp; <placeName ref="#Oxfordshire">Oxfordshire</placeName> hills &amp;<pb n="6"/><placeName ref="#Oxfordshire">Oxfordshire</placeName> roads we never should arrive there altogether--Of a certainty some at least of the heavy baggage--I perhaps &amp; my old Chum <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</persName>'s box Coat should be left midway. But I think it will rain--&amp; so make sure we have begun mowing--Adieu, my dear Friend--<persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#Russell_M">Mama</persName> send their kindest regards &amp; <persName ref="#Mossy_pet">Mossy</persName> his duty--poor <persName ref="#Mossy_pet">Mossy</persName> he missed you very much at breakfast next morning--your mode of education was quite to his taste--&amp; to mine--I love to see <persName ref="#Mossy_pet">Mossy</persName> fed--Adieu--God bless you--   </p><closer>Ever most affectionately <choice><sic>your's</sic><reg>yours</reg></choice><lb/><persName ref="#MRM">M.R. Mitford</persName>.
             
               <address><addrLine><lb/><placeName ref="#Newbury">Newbury</placeName><date when="1819-06-01">First June 1819</date></addrLine><addrLine><lb/><persName ref="#Dundas_C">C Dundas</persName></addrLine><addrLine><lb/><persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir W<hi rend="superscript">m</hi> Elford Bar<hi rend="superscript">t</hi></persName></addrLine><addrLine><lb/><placeName ref="#Bickham_village">Bickham</placeName></addrLine><addrLine><lb/><placeName ref="#Plymouth_city">Plymouth</placeName></addrLine></address></closer></div></body><back><div> 
          
           <!-- <persName>Lady Pitt</persName> Unidentified.  Possibly referring to some kind of jointure legal hold on the estate? George Pitt, 2nd Baron Rivers sold the Stratefield Saye estate in 1818 to the state in order for it to be given to the Duke of Wellington. Appears to have never married. Title went to his nephew, Horace Beckford (later Pitt-Rivers). His father, George Pitt, 1st Baron Rivers, died in 1803. His wife Penelope (2nd baron's mother) died in 1795. None of the second Baron's sisters seem eligible either. Definitely nothing to do with William Pitt the younger, who never married.--></div></back></text></TEI>