<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><!--<?xml-model href="http://ebeshero.github.io/MRMValidate.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>--><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title xml:id="MRM2021">Letter to <persName ref="#Webb_Mary_younger">Mary Webb</persName>, <date when="1819-07-05">July 5, 1819</date></title><author ref="#MRM">Mary Russell Mitford</author><editor ref="#csc">Catherine Cox</editor><sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford Project</orgName></sponsor><sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor><sponsor>Pittsburgh Supercomputing Center</sponsor><principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal><respStmt><resp>Transcription and coding by</resp><persName ref="#csc">Catherine Cox</persName><persName ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Date last checked: <date when="2015-10-19">2015-10-19</date>
                  Proofing and corrections by</resp><persName ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</persName><!--LMW:  Proofed body text against ms., added tags.  Needs header proofing and corrections. 2015 10 15--></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>First digital edition in TEI, date: <date when="2015-05-29">29 May 2015</date>. P5.</edition><respStmt><resp>Edition made with help from photos taken by</resp><orgName>Digital Mitford editors</orgName></respStmt><respStmt><orgName>Digital Mitford</orgName><resp> photo files: <idno>DSCF8963.jpg, DSCF8964.jpg, DSCF8965.jpg, DSCF8966.jpg, DSCF8967.jpg, DSCF8968.jpg</idno></resp></respStmt></editionStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority><pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace><date>2013</date><availability><p>Reproduced by courtesy of the <orgName ref="#ReadingCL">Reading Central Library</orgName>.</p><licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                  License</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Mitford Letters: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><repository ref="#ReadingCL">Reading Central Library</repository><collection>The letters of Mary Russell Mitford, vol. 4, 1819-1823</collection><idno><!--LMW: No shelfmark. In set of loose folders at RCL.--></idno></msIdentifier><head>Letter from Mary Russell Mitford to Eliza Webb, <date when="1819-07-05">1819 July 5</date>.</head><physDesc><objectDesc><supportDesc><support><p>Single sheet of <material>paper</material>, four surfaces photographed.</p><p>Address leaf bears no postmarks.</p></support><condition><p>Paper badly foxed.</p><p>Sheet (pages three and four) torn on right edge of page three where wax seal was removed.</p></condition></supportDesc></objectDesc><sealDesc><p>Red wax seal, complete, adhered to upper edge of page four.</p></sealDesc></physDesc></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><handNotes><handNote corresp="#pencil" medium="pencil"> Someone, apparently other than Mitford, perhaps cataloging letters and describing them, who left grey pencil marks and numbered her letters now in the Reading Central Library's collection. This letter has [<del rend="strikethrough"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/>early</del><add place="above">5</add> July, 1819] written in the top center of the first leaf.
           </handNote></handNotes></profileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><p>Mitford’s spelling and punctuation are retained, except where a word is split at the end of a line and the beginning of the next in the manuscript. Where Mitford’s spelling and hyphenation of words deviates from the standard, in order to facilitate searching we are using the TEI elements “choice," “sic," and “reg" to encode both Mitford’s spelling and the regular international standard of Oxford English spelling, following the first listed spelling in the Oxford English Dictionary. The long s and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="letter"><opener><add hand="#pencil">[<del rend="strikethrough"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/>early</del><add place="above">5</add> July, 1819]</add><dateline><date when="1819-07-05">Monday</date> Even<hi rend="superscript">g</hi><!--LMW:  Needham dates from Mitford's journal. Perpetual calendar indicates that July 5 was a Monday.--></dateline></opener><p>My <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Father</persName> is going to <placeName ref="#Reading_city">Reading</placeName> tomorrow to take <persName ref="#Russell_M">Mama</persName> to hear the <persName ref="#Fisher_John">Bishop of Salisbury</persName> preach &amp; hopes to get the <title ref="#TomCrib">Tom Crib</title>for our own dear <persName ref="#Webb_Mary_younger">Miss Webb</persName> In this hope I sit down to thank you all my dear &amp; kind friends for notes past &amp; present--I being just now in debt all round--to thank you all &amp; to beg you to look on this as an answer general. The first thing is pleasing to hear that one dear <persName>Friend</persName><!-- #ebb : Do you know who this refers to? LMW:  not so far.--> is not worse--I hope this journey to <placeName ref="#London_city">London</placeName> will make him much better--relieve his mind &amp; and heal his body--The next thing in this <quote>"mingled yarn"</quote><note resp="#lmw">A quotation from <title ref="#AllsWellTEW">All's Well that Ends Well</title>: "The web of our life is of a mingled yarn, good and ill together" (Act 4, scene 3).</note>is regret for the lost broach--I still think you will find it. Did I never tell you how <persName ref="#Hill_Lucy">Lucy</persName> &amp; I found a broach of my <persName>Grandmother</persName>'s with <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</persName>'s hair which I had lost for eight months? We found it--guess where--in my empty purse--where for that eight months aforesaid it had been sole inhabitant.--The next thing is to ask if you have <pb n="2"/>heard of <persName ref="#Dickinson_Charles">Mr. Dickinson</persName>'s bad accident? He was thrown from his horse on <date when="1819-07-02">Friday</date> &amp; his left shoulder dislocated. <persName ref="#Jackson_Mr">Mr. Jackson</persName> as the nearest surgeon was sent for to reduce the dislocation--He &amp; 6 men tugged at him for three hours without success--they then sent for <persName>Mr. Markley</persName> <!-- #ebb #lmw : Is this right? lmw:  Bulley?--> who very speedily &amp; skilfully accomplished it. Thank God <persName ref="#Dickinson_Mrs">Mrs. Dickinson</persName> was away! <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</persName> saw him on <date when="1819-07-04">Sunday</date> &amp; is in perfect admiration of his patience &amp; philosophy<note resp="#csc">As in Stoicism.</note>--There is nothing I admire so much as that sort of passive courage--the courage of endurance--the only courage that belongs exclusively to the human animal. That of fighting they share with braver brutes.--</p><p>I had a charming letter from <persName ref="#James_Miss">Miss James</persName> yesterday--She is just now consoling her <persName ref="#James_Mrs">Mother</persName> for the loss of <emph rend="underline"><persName ref="#James_Susan">Susy</persName></emph> who is gone to reside with a family at <placeName ref="#LakeDistrict">the Lakes</placeName>--gone I mean as a Governess--They send a thousand loves to you all--She wants to see me she says very much--but only think of her impudence!--She does not want me to meet <persName ref="#Maurice_Mr">Mr. Maurice</persName> because she says <said>"there is <pb n="3"/>is <note resp="#lmw">Mitford repeats a word here over the page break.</note>a freebooting spirit about him which I should draw out &amp; cherish to the extinction of graver things."</said> Theres a pretty opinion for you! A fine specimen of partiality truly! I do really believe that she thinks of me as <persName ref="#Edie_Ochiltree">Edie Ochiltree</persName> said of himself--that <quote>"I should be a very bad example in any well regulated family"</quote>--but so it is--I am misused past endurance. <persName ref="#Rowden_Fr">Mrs. Rowden</persName> forsooth saith that <said>"my wickedness is of a peculiarly dangerous character--it is so catching"</said>--And this <persName ref="#Webb_Mary_younger">Mary Webb</persName> is the worst sauce box of all. Oh dear me! What will become of me--with all these wicked wits upon me--and I such a poor harm<gap reason="torn" quantity="4" unit="word"/><supplied>less</supplied> civil-spoken person with no soul to take my part!--I assure you <persName ref="#Webb_Mary_younger">Mary</persName> dear that I was not home a moment too soon--<persName ref="#Russell_M">Mama</persName>'s first salutation was that she had always given me up--the ride was very pleasant but so cold that we were forced to have a fire to thaw ourselves--quite unheard of on the <date when="1819-07-05">5</date><hi rend="superscript">th</hi> of July.--<persName ref="#Russell_M">Mama</persName> is better--so much better that she talks of going into the <placeName>Vale</placeName> next week when <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</persName> goes to the Sessions. <pb n="4"/> I hope you mean to come &amp; see me--Let me know on <date when="1819-07-10">Saturday</date> when I may look out for my dearest visitors, as well as as how your dear <persName ref="#Webb_James">Father</persName> continues.--Poor <persName ref="#Valpy_Penelope">Penelope Valpy</persName> is very ill still--the medical men are very much alarmed--Adieu my very dear friends--kindest love to all from all--</p><closer><lb/>Ever most faithfully <choice><sic>your's</sic><reg>yours</reg></choice><lb/><persName ref="#MRM">M.R. Mitford.</persName><address><addrLine><lb/>To </addrLine><addrLine><lb/><persName>Miss <emph rend="underline">Webb</emph></persName></addrLine></address></closer></div></body><back>
        
        
        <!--LMW <persName>Grandmother</persName> MRM's grandmother (which one? Maternal or paternal?) unidentified.  -->
        <!--LMW: Physician or surgeon who fixed Mr. D's dislocated shoulder. Unknown (ms. illegible) <persName>Mr. Markley</persName> #ebb #lmw : Is this right? lmw:  Bulley?--></back></text></TEI>