<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><!--<?xml-model href="http://ebeshero.github.io/MRMValidate.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>--><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title xml:id="MRM1736">Letter to <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir William Elford</persName>, <date when="1819-03-13">March 13, 1819</date></title><author ref="#MRM">Mary Russell Mitford</author><editor ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</editor><sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford Project</orgName></sponsor><sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor><sponsor>Pittsburgh Supercomputing Center</sponsor><principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal><respStmt><resp>Transcription and coding by</resp><persName ref="#hl">Heather Long</persName><persName ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Date last checked: <date when="2015-10-12">2015-10-12</date><!--LMW: header updated. -->
               Proofing and corrections by</resp><persName ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</persName><persName ref="#nlh">Nathaniel Hebert</persName></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>First digital edition in TEI, date: <date when="2015-10-01">1 October 2015</date>. P5.</edition><respStmt><resp>Edition made with help from photos taken by</resp><orgName>Digital Mitford editors</orgName></respStmt><respStmt><orgName>Digital Mitford</orgName><resp> photo files: <idno>IMG0254.jpg, IMG0255.jpg, IMG0256.jpg, IMG0257.jpg, IMG0258.jpg, IMG0259.jpg,IMG0260.jpg, IMG0261.jpg</idno></resp></respStmt></editionStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority><pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace><date>2013</date><availability><p>Reproduced by courtesy of the <orgName ref="#ReadingCL">Reading Central Library</orgName>.</p><licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                  License</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Mitford Letters: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><repository ref="#ReadingCL">Reading Central Library</repository><collection>The letters of Mary Russell Mitford, vol. 4, 1819-1823 </collection><idno>qB/TU/MIT Vol. 4 Horizon No.: 1361550 ff. 366</idno></msIdentifier><head>Letter from Mary Russell Mitford to Sir William Elford, <date when="1819-03-13">1819 March 13</date>.</head><physDesc><objectDesc><supportDesc><support><p>One sheet of <material>paper</material>, four surfaces photographed.</p><p>Address leaf bearing red postmark surmounted by a crown (franking stamp), reading <stamp><lb/>FREE<date when="1819-03-29"><lb/>29 MR 29<lb/>1819</date></stamp>.</p></support><condition><p>Sheet (pages three and four) torn on right edge of page three where wax seal was removed.</p></condition></supportDesc></objectDesc><sealDesc><p>Red wax seal, complete, adhered to page four.</p></sealDesc></physDesc></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><handNotes><handNote corresp="#rc" medium="red_crayon"> Red crayon or thick red pencil. Probably a different hand from Mitford's that marks many of her letters, sometimes drawing diagonal lines across pages, and sometimes writing words overtop and perpendicularly across Mitford's writing.  A red line is drawn from top left to bottom right of each of the first three leaves. On leaf four, there is no red crayon.</handNote></handNotes></profileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><p>Mitford’s spelling and punctuation are retained, except where a word is split at the end of a line and the beginning of the next in the manuscript. Where Mitford’s spelling and hyphenation of words deviates from the standard, in order to facilitate searching we are using the TEI elements “choice," “sic," and “reg" to encode both Mitford’s spelling and the regular international standard of Oxford English spelling, following the first listed spelling in the Oxford English Dictionary. The long s and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="letter"><opener><salute>To <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir W. Elford--</persName></salute><dateline><name type="place" ref="#Bertram_house">Bertram House</name><date when="1819-03-13">March 13<hi rend="superscript">th</hi><lb/>1819</date>. 
               </dateline></opener><salute>My dear <rs type="person" ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir</rs></salute><p>I rather think my <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Father</persName> is going to <placeName ref="#London_city">London</placeName> tomorrow--so as he will be able to get a frank--a thing which if our poor unlucky <rs type="person" ref="#Weyland_John">pensioned M. P.</rs> gets turned out<note resp="#lmw">Parliamentary elections took place on <date when="1819-03-16">16 March 1819</date> in which <persName ref="#Palmer_CF">Charles Fysshe Palmer </persName>defeated incumbent <persName ref="#Weyland_John">John Weyland</persName>, as Mitford hints may happen here.</note> may be rather a rare article in this unparliamentary neighborhood--&amp; as you may take it into your head not to write till you hear, &amp; for many other good reasons I shall trouble you with a letter at once. Besides I have been meeting a <rs type="person" ref="#Northmore_Thos"><placeName ref="#Devonshire">Devonshire</placeName> Squire</rs> of <choice><sic>your's</sic><reg>yours</reg></choice> &amp; I want to talk about him, &amp; to ask questions &amp; so forth. I write tell you the whole story. The husband of my most intimate friend in this neighborhood (<persName ref="#Dickinson_Charles">Mr. Dickinson</persName> of <placeName ref="#Farley_Hill">Farley Hill</placeName>--first Cousin to the <persName>Member for <placeName ref="#Somersetshire">Somersetshire</placeName></persName>) happens you must know to be a very clever man--and a patriot--(such unions--lamentable as they are do <del rend="squiggles" unit="word" n="1">happen</del> occur occasionally)--worse than a Patriot--he is an Ultra--an actual disciple of the old <unclear/><persName ref="#Cartwright_Maj">Major Cartwright</persName>. Well he had had some correspondence with your <placeName ref="#Devonshire">Devonshire</placeName> Dema- (bless me I was going to write Demagogue!) with your <placeName ref="#Devonshire">Devonshire</placeName> Patriot <persName ref="#Northmore_Thos">Mr. Northmore</persName>--&amp; they both belong to the <orgName ref="#Hampden_Club">Hampden Club</orgName>--&amp; <persName ref="#Northmore_Thos">Mr. Northmore</persName> being I suppose sent to Coventry<note resp="#lmw">In British idiom, to be "sent to Coventry" was "to be ignored or ostracized. This behaviour often takes the form of pretending that the shunned person, although conspicuously present, can't be seen or heard."  Thought to originate in the English Civil Wars, but the first recorded citation is from 1765. See "The Phrase Finder": <ref target="http://www.phrases.org.uk/meanings/sent-to-coventry.html"/>. Here, Mitford uses the phrase to indicate someone who, although known, is not received in polite society, someone who might be "cut" in public.</note> in his own Country has &amp; mind <q>"to make his bear garden flourish here</q>--for he is going about <placeName ref="#Berkshire">Berkshire</placeName> estate hunting--so he invited himself to <placeName ref="#Farley_Hill">Farley Hill</placeName> at a time when I happened to be staying there &amp; he came &amp; astonished us all prodigiously. My dear <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">sir William</persName>, what a man! How loud &amp; shrewd &amp; full of himself &amp; sharp all over from his eagle nose to his pointed hook toe! What a perpetual sky rocket bouncing starting &amp; flaming! What a talker against time! Well might <persName ref="#Hobhouse_JC">Mr. Hobhouse</persName> call him <said>"the gentleman who came all the way from <placeName ref="#Devonshire">Devonshire</placeName> to tell <pb n="2"/>us that he was a great man at home."</said> And he is a Poet too. Has written an <rs type="title" ref="#WashingtonEpic_TN">Epic</rs>, which must have appeared incognito--for I never remember to have heard it mentioned in my life. An <rs type="title" ref="#WashingtonEpic_TN">Epic Poem</rs> about <persName ref="#Washington_Geo">Washington</persName>. A friend of his who came with him a very different sort of person--<persName ref="#Johnson_Mr">Mr. Johnson</persName>--the <persName ref="#Junius">Junius</persName> of <placeName ref="#Marlow">Marlow</placeName>--who under the quaint name of <persName ref="#Trueman_T">Timothy Trueman</persName> contrives to <choice><sic>exersize</sic><reg>exercise</reg></choice> so singular an influence in the <del rend="squiggles" unit="word" n="1">party</del> county politics of this part of the world--<persName ref="#Johnson_Mr">Mr. Johnson</persName> told me in answer to my questions about this poem, <said>"That it displayed a very great spirit of liberty--&amp; that independently of that there were some passages which were sufficiently felicitous."</said> Is not this character the very model of the praise that damns? I dare say your abuse of it (if you should ever have seen it) will be much more merciful--at all events you must know the man--such a Volcano can hardly exist in a county without having been felt in its noise &amp; smoke &amp; stones &amp; cinders--you must know about him &amp; and do tell us--I never saw anyone who excited my curiosity more. Is he a gentleman born? And bred? What sort of woman is his wife? Is she sent to Coventry? And how do you class the animal?--I asked him if he knew you &amp; he said you were a very able leader in the opposite forces--Perhaps you may know <persName ref="#Johnson_Mr">Mr. Johnson</persName> too--only that he has been always so much of a literary recluse--for though originally of <placeName ref="#Northumberland">Northumberland</placeName> &amp; now fixed in <placeName ref="#Buckinghamshire">Buckinghamshire</placeName> he has lived much in <placeName ref="#Devonshire">Devonshire</placeName>--if you did know him I am sure you would like him--he is one of those delightful old men that render age so charming--mild playful kind &amp; wise--talking just as <persName ref="#Walton_I">Isaac Walton</persName> would have talked if we were to <metamark rend="caret" place="below" function="insertion"/><add place="above">have</add> gone out fishing with him. It is one of <persName ref="#Northmore_Thos">Mr. Northmore</persName>'s sins in my eyes that he did not pay the proper attention to his venerable friend--If you suspect that he has affronted me you are mistaken--for except a little im<pb n="3"/>pertinent sort of praise which he thought very flattering, he was exceedingly civil--but that manner of his affronts every body without meaning it--that astonishing quantity of modest assurance--&amp; moreover when my beautiful <persName ref="#Dickinson_Mrs">Mrs. Dickinson</persName>, <unclear/>'s <!--hl/lmw: Loti?'s-->best pupil, was singing what I think <persName ref="#Handel">Handel</persName>'s best song (<title corresp="#Whereer_Handel">"Where'er you walk"</title>) he kept on one constant <said>"very pretty, very pretty, very pretty"</said> as a sort of running accompaniment--this was really too provoking--<persName ref="#Dickinson_Mrs">Mrs. Dickinson</persName>'s singing is not only my delight but my pride--Good bye <persName ref="#Northmore_Thos">Mr. Northmore</persName>--<foreign xml:lang="fr">Beau ideal</foreign> of a democrat farewell! I have done with you--no--not quite either, for <rs type="title" ref="#WashingtonEpic_TN">Washington</rs> is coming--at least <persName ref="#Johnson_Mr">Mr. Johnson</persName> threatened to send the book--but I never promised to read it. Good bye for the present <persName ref="#Northmore_Thos">Mr. Northmore</persName> I am going to talk of better things--I have just been reading the book I mentioned to you in my last--<title ref="#Marriage_SF">"Marriage"</title>--very amusing indeed, though not quite so excellent as to be suspected to be a posthumous work of <persName ref="#Austen_Jane">Miss Austen</persName>'s--still I recommend it to you very strongly--It has the one great charm of a novel--it makes one laugh. There are four most delightful personages all new <del rend="squiggles" unit="word" n="2">and yet</del> in books, &amp; old in nature--three Scotch old maids--<persName ref="#Jacky_Marriage">Miss Jacky</persName>--<persName ref="#Nicky_Marriage">Miss Nicky</persName>--<persName ref="#Grizzy_Marriage">Miss Grizzy</persName> &amp; a married friend <persName ref="#Maclaughlan_Marriage">Lady<choice><sic> Maclaughlin</sic><reg>MacLaughlan</reg></choice></persName>--all are good--but <persName ref="#Jacky_Marriage">Miss Jacky</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#Grizzy_Marriage">Miss Grizzy</persName> are the inimitable pair--their letters, are equal to <persName ref="#Collins_Mr_fict">Mr. Collins</persName>'s--How you would enjoy two such Correspondents!--What hearty laughs they would give you! Besides these exquisite portraits there is a great deal of comic talent throughout the work. And there had need. Nothing but the bouyant air-bladder of Comedy could have floated such heavy materials as the prosing &amp; preaching of the second Volume--the total want of everything resembling interest from first to last--the interminable speeches--&amp; that deadest of dead weights the all perfect Heroine. A book so heavy<pb n="4"/> had need be covered all over with Cork-jackets not to sink--of these grievances the heroine is much the worst. Somebody has said that we never forgive perfection unless it be made properly wretched--Now this heroine is not wretched at all. She is a female <persName ref="#Chas_Grandison_fict">Sir Charles Grandison</persName> with no cares but the sentimental conflicts of duty &amp; love. How I do hate those over good book people. They are just like triple refined sugar sweet &amp; bright &amp; hard &amp; spotless, &amp; good for nothing till mixed with some powerful acid--good for nothing at all. Luckily we know how to skip (invaluable discovery, I wonder no one has ever written an essay in its praise) &amp; <persName ref="#Grizzy_Marriage">Grizzy</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#Jacky_Marriage">Jacky</persName> make ample amends for the fair <persName ref="#Mary_Marriage">Mary</persName>'s sins of wisdom &amp; virtue.--<persName ref="#Grizzy_Marriage">Grizzy</persName> is my favorite--I think I shall christen the <persName ref="#whitekitten_WEpet">white kitten</persName><persName ref="#whitekitten_WEpet"><emph rend="underline">your</emph> kitten</persName>--by that melodious name--Do you like it? Here am I talking of kittens &amp; novels &amp; <persName ref="#Northmore_Thos">Mr. Northmore</persName>'s &amp; such like baubles &amp; quite forgetting the opportunity I have to shew off &amp; look grand &amp; learned, &amp; classical &amp; critical, &amp; bluer than a blue bag. Do you know that I am holding the responsible office of critic to a <title>Volume of translations</title> which a friend of mine--<persName ref="#Dickinson_Charles">Mr. Dickinson</persName> by the bye--is about to print at his private press as soon as ever they have undergone <emph rend="underline">my</emph> last revisal? There's for you. Translations from <persName ref="#Dante">Dante</persName>--<persName ref="#Tasso">Tasso</persName>--<persName ref="#Ariosto">Ariosto</persName>--<persName ref="#Petrarch">Petrarch</persName>--<persName ref="#Ovid">Ovid</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#Virgil">Virgil</persName>. Very fine translations too--combining in a most extraordinary degree fidelity to the words &amp; the spirit of the Author with the most flowing versification &amp; the purest syle. The <persName ref="#Ugolino">Ugolino</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#Isabella_Dante">Isabella</persName> stories are superb. These Italian people are my old acquaintance--I was not quite so intimate with <rs type="person" ref="#Virgil">the Latin Gentleman</rs>--I had read <title><persName ref="#Dryden">Dryden</persName>'s <persName ref="#Virgil">Virgil</persName></title> to be sure--but then it was a long time ago--&amp; of <persName ref="#Ovid">Mr Ovid</persName> I knew nothing at all. I have now had the honour of an introduction--to his <persName ref="#Phaeton_Ovid">tale of Phaeton</persName> &amp; I think him a very fine fellow indeed. I don't know anybody who talks so much magnificent nonsense--he goes far beyond <persName ref="#Southey_R">Mr. Southey</persName>--<title ref="#Kehama">Kehama</title><pb n="5"/> is <q>"pale pink compared to the flaming scarlet"</q> of the <title ref="#Metamorphoses">Metamorphoses</title>. The 4th <title ref="#Aeneid_Virgil">Aeneid</title> too surprised me with its matchless beauties &amp; its in my mind intolerable faults. How <persName ref="#Virgil">Virgil</persName> could make his pious hero such a cold heartless abominable rascal--&amp; his tender heroine such an incomparable fool passes my comprehension. In the critical readings which passed between <rs type="person" ana="#Dickinson_Charles #Dickinson_Mrs">Mr &amp; Mrs Dickinson</rs> &amp; myself we of course did not fail to compare <persName ref="#Dickinson_Charles">Mr D</persName>'s translations with those of others--<persName ref="#Pitt_Chris">Pitt</persName>'s--<persName ref="#Dryden">Dryden</persName>'s--&amp; <persName ref="#Beresford_James">Beresford</persName>'s--which <metamark rend="caret" place="below" function="insertion"/><add place="above">last</add> has without intending it all the merit of a travestie. In the finest part of <persName ref="#Dido_Aeneid">Dido</persName>'s passion where she talks of sacrificing her faithless lover--immolating his son &amp; so forth--<persName ref="#Beresford_James">Mr. Beresford</persName> very quietly makes her say--<quote>"Why should not I smile as kill <persName ref="#Ascanius">Ascanius</persName> &amp; <emph rend="underline">Dish him</emph> to his father?"</quote> This <persName ref="#Beresford_James">Mr. Beresford</persName> was no other than the Author of the <title ref="#Miseries_JB">"Miseries"</title> &amp;c--&amp; this doughty Translation is subscribed for by a<gap reason="torn" n="2" unit="chars"/><unclear/><supplied resp="lmw">ll</supplied><placeName ref="#Oxford_city">Oxford</placeName> &amp; half <placeName ref="#Cambridge_city">Cambridge</placeName>--I think they ought <del rend="squiggles" unit="word" n="2">and yet</del> to have known be<gap reason="torn" n="4" unit="chars"/><unclear/><supplied resp="lmw">tter</supplied>. Don't you?--</p><p><date when="1819-03-17">Wednesda<gap reason="torn" n="1" unit="chars"/><unclear/><supplied resp="lmw">y</supplied></date> My <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Father</persName> did not go to <placeName ref="#London_city">London</placeName> &amp; <gap reason="torn" n="1" unit="word"/><unclear/><supplied resp="lmw">Mr.</supplied><persName ref="#Palmer_CF">Palmer</persName> is returned--<metamark rend="caret" place="below" function="insertion"/><add place="above">&amp; we shan't</add> to use the words of a Blacksmith Friend who wrote to the Votary of Vulcan on the occasion--<said>"Our <emph rend="underline">Frend Charls Fish</emph> Palmer is <emph rend="underline">got a good seet</emph>--&amp; <emph rend="underline">hopes</emph> he'll keep it."</said>--He is to make his grand Entree into <placeName ref="#Reading_city">Reading</placeName> Tomorrow--bells are to be rung--bonfires made--houses illuminated--&amp; that his Victory may be graced in all possible ways he shall have the honour of franking this letter--I am very glad he has beaten <persName ref="#Weyland_John">Mr. Weyland</persName>--but I hope he'll give up the Pension.<note resp="#lmw">Palmer's wife <persName ref="#Palmer_Mad">Madalina</persName> received a state pension and it was a point of contention during the election and after, as to whether or not an M.P.'s wife should accept one.</note></p><metamark rend="jerk"/><p>Now you must write very soon &amp; tell me that the jujubie (is that right?) has cured your cough--that you are coming <metamark rend="caret" place="below" function="insertion"/><add place="above">to</add><placeName ref="#London_city">London</placeName> this Spring--&amp; about the time you are likely to see us--for I will take care to be at home &amp; bespeak the nightingales--Adieu my dear Friend--<persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#Russell_M">Mama</persName> join in kindest remembrances &amp; I am always </p><closer>most affectionately <choice><sic>your's</sic><reg resp="#lmw">yours</reg></choice><signed><persName ref="#MRM">M. R. Mitford</persName></signed><address><addrLine><placeName ref="#London_city">London</placeName><date when="1819-03-29"/>March Twenty nine</addrLine><addrLine>1819</addrLine><addrLine><persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sr Wm Elford Bart</persName></addrLine><addrLine><placeName ref="#Bickham_village">Bickham</placeName></addrLine><addrLine><persName ref="#Palmer_CF"/>CFPalmer<placeName ref="#Plymouth_city">Plymouth</placeName></addrLine></address></closer></div></body><back><div>
           
        <!-- backlist pulled to si-add-LMW 2015-10-12 --></div></back></text></TEI>