<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><?xml-model href="http://ebeshero.github.io/MRMValidate.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title xml:id="MRM2018">Letter to <persName ref="#Webb_Mary_younger">Mary Webb</persName>, <date when="1819-04">19 April 1819</date></title> <!--alg: date discrepancy:  Needham note  indicates 19 April, 1819 "[For exact date, see Diary]"; first page indicates "Monday [April, 1819]." Confirm date. --> <!--lmw: April 19 was a Monday. --><author ref="#MRM">Mary Russell Mitford</author><editor ref="#alg">Amy L. Gates</editor><sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford Project</orgName></sponsor><sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor><sponsor>Pittsburgh Supercomputing Center</sponsor><principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal><respStmt><resp>Transcription and coding by</resp><persName ref="#alg">Amy L. Gates</persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Date last checked: <date when="2015-10-14">2015-10-14</date>
                  Proofing and corrections by</resp><persName ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</persName><!--lmw:  Proofing text and header from ms.  2015-09-29. Updated header and tags, 2015-10-14--></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>First digital edition in TEI, date: <date when="2015-05-29">29 May 2015</date>. P5.</edition><respStmt><resp>Edition made with help from photos taken by</resp><orgName>Digital Mitford editors</orgName></respStmt><respStmt><orgName>Digital Mitford</orgName><resp> photo files: <idno>DSCF8929.jpg, DSCF8930.jpg, DSCF8931.jpg, DSCF8932.jpg, DSCF8933.jpg, DSCF8934.jpg, DSCF8935.jpg. </idno></resp></respStmt></editionStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority><pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace><date>2015</date><availability><p>Reproduced by courtesy of the <orgName ref="#ReadingCL">Reading Central Library</orgName>.</p><licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                  License</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Mitford Letters: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><repository ref="#ReadingCL">Reading Central Library</repository><collection>The letters of Mary Russell Mitford</collection><idno/><!--LMW/EBB: MRM 2014 has no shelfmark. From a collection of loose folders at Reading Central Library.--></msIdentifier><head>Letter from Mary Russell Mitford to Mary Webb, <date when="1819-04-19">1819 April 19</date>.</head> <!-- alg: This letter includes a note from Francis Needham which specifies 1819-04-09 and refers to Diary for specific date; the pencil note added on the first page of the letter specifies 1819-04; Mitford dates the letter "Monday."--> <!--lmw:  Needham note not transcribed. on photo # DSCF8928.JPG --><physDesc><objectDesc><supportDesc><support><p><material>Paper</material> and ink.</p><p>Two sheets of paper. Two sheets of quarto-post (23.3 x 18.3 cm) folded in thirds twice. Pages are unnumbered, but by context, one sheet includes pages 1, 2, 3, 4; the second sheet includes pages 5 and 6. Page 6 also includes addressee and seal.</p></support><condition><p>Rusty paperclip mark on first page. Tear about halfway down pages 5-6 where the seal had been attached. Some spotting along folds on page 6. Round red wax seal intact.</p></condition></supportDesc></objectDesc></physDesc></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><handNotes><handNote corresp="#pencil" medium="pencil"> Someone, apparently other than Mitford, perhaps cataloging letters and describing them, who left grey pencil marks and numbered her letters now in the Reading Central Library's collection. This letter has inserted the date "April, 1819" in square brackets at the top left of the first leaf, underneath the place and date line, "Bertram House Monday."
           </handNote><handNote>There is no red crayon on this letter.</handNote></handNotes></profileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><p>Mitford’s spelling and punctuation are retained, except where a word is split at the end of a line and the beginning of the next in the manuscript. Where Mitford’s spelling and hyphenation of words deviates from the standard, in order to facilitate searching we are using the TEI elements “choice," “sic," and “reg" to encode both Mitford’s spelling and the regular international standard of Oxford English spelling, following the first listed spelling in the Oxford English Dictionary. The long s and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="letter"><opener><dateline><name type="place"><placeName ref="#Bertram_house">Bertram House</placeName></name><date when="1819-04-19">Monday.</date>. 
                  <add><handShift resp="pencil"/><date when="1819-04">[April, 1819]</date></add></dateline></opener><p>Many thanks my own dear <persName ref="#Webb_Mary_younger">Mary</persName> for your kind letter &amp; the good account of the dear <persName ref="#Webb_James">Papa</persName>--that he has not suffered much by his exertions of last week is a most excellent account--you must give my best love to dear <persName ref="#Webb_Mary_elder">Aunt Mary</persName> &amp; beg her to continue to give me a bulletin of his health when you &amp; our <persName ref="#Webb_Eliza">Eliza</persName>are gone to the gay <rs type="place" ref="#London_city">City</rs>--I enclose a note for <persName ref="#James_Miss">Miss James</persName> which you will be so good my dear to let <persName ref="#Dobbs_Mrs">Mrs. Dobbs</persName>'s servant put into the twopenny post--perhaps you will enclose it in one from yourself for I find from a letter received from her yesterday that she has written to you to <placeName ref="#Hatton_Garden">Hatton Garden</placeName> begging you to come &amp; see her at <placeName ref="#Richmond">Richmond</placeName>--I told her you were going to <placeName ref="#London_city">Town</placeName> &amp; she thought you were there already. Pray go &amp; see her--She seems to have set her heart on it &amp; I am sure would make you both very comfortable--you should see <placeName ref="#Richmond">Richmond</placeName> &amp; <placeName ref="#Twickenham">Twickenham</placeName>--they are such show places &amp; nobody can be fitter to show <pb n="2"/> them to you than our dear Friend--<persName ref="#Dobbs_Mrs">Mrs. Dobbs</persName> who you say likes jaunting about in a morning would I dare say take you there &amp; fetch you again either the next day or the next but one as you might settle--Do go--<persName ref="#James_Miss">Miss James</persName> would be so happy &amp; I should so like to think of you all three together. You will certainly find a note from her at <persName ref="#Dobbs_Mrs">Mrs. Dobbs</persName>'s.--I shall try to contrive about <persName ref="#Haydon">Haydon</persName><!--alg: Consider correspondence module to reference previous letter about Haydon?-->--I expect to hear from him every day &amp; in my answer I dare say I shall manage it--&amp; will let you know the where &amp; the when &amp; all about it--In the mean time say nothing to anyone--&amp; above all do not name him to <persName ref="#James_Miss">Miss James</persName>.<metamark rend="jerks"/></p><p>I am sitting up here in apple pie order<note resp="#alg">"Apple pie order" is a colloquial reference which means, according to the <title>OED</title>, "perfect order or neatness."</note> as white as a snowball &amp; as round waiting for the <persName ref="#Palmer_Mad">"Right Honourable Lady"</persName> as the <title ref="#ReadingMer_per"><placeName ref="#Reading_city">Reading</placeName> paper</title> calls her who has signified her intention to call--No--a snowball is not a fit simile--a snowball is a thing at liberty--a thing that can roll about--I am more like a maggot in a nut--a fine fat white maggot with a pink head--a comfortable-looking sort <pb n="3"/> of prisoner.--I must tell you the whole story. <date>Tuesday</date>,<!-- lmw:  she means the last election day, presumably. Was that 1819-04-13, the previous Tuesday? If we could find out, that would narrow down the exact letter date. --> that day of triumph &amp; <unclear><supplied resp="#alg">topping</supplied></unclear><!-- lmw:  I'm not sure either but I don't think the first letter is a t. Possibly an s or r. Sopping? Sapping? --><persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</persName> as you know did go to <placeName ref="#Reading_city">Reading</placeName> &amp; I did not--Well--to my sorrow nothing must serve him but that he made an appointment with <persName ref="#Palmer_CF">Mr. Palmer</persName> or <persName ref="#Palmer_Mad">Lady Madelina</persName> (<foreign xml:lang="la">vel haec vel hoc</foreign><note resp="#alg"> Latin phrase meaning "either her or him."</note> no matter) that I should wait on her <persName ref="#Palmer_Mad">Ladyship</persName> the next morning--In the mean time said <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</persName> got tipsy--was put to bed &amp; never made his appearance at home till the next day at breakfast, when out he came with his orders. I who have a natural hatred to great people, especially to fine grand ladies, was nevertheless so taken by surprise that I actually went up to prepare for the visit &amp; had accomplished the changing one cotton <emph rend="underline">hose</emph> for a silk one when they came to announce that my honoured <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</persName> was forced to go to bed &amp; that he had sent <persName ref="#George">George</persName> into <placeName ref="#Reading_city">Reading</placeName> to make apologies--So forth I went to <placeName ref="#Penge_Wood">Penge Wood</placeName>--ruminating how to get out of a business so little to my taste--I don't know why I dislike Grandees except that<pb n="4"/> their sort of pride interferes with my sort of pride &amp; that I like to sit on the ground like <persName ref="#Constance_KJ">Constance</persName> &amp; cry <quote corresp="#King_John_play">"Here is my throne--Let Kings come bow to it"</quote><note resp="#alg"><persName ref="#MRM">Mitford</persName> slightly misquotes from <persName ref="#Shakespeare">Shakespeare</persName>'s <title ref="#King_John_play">The Life and Death of King John</title>: "Here is my throne; bid kings come bow to it" (3.1.74).</note><!-- alg: Confirm this is a misquote. I read "Let" in MRM's letter, not "bid." Is there a standard format for citing act and scene? Is there a specific edition we reference, and should I cite by line number? (This is line 74 in the edition I consulted.) --><!-- lmw:  I think it's let also in MRM. We decided we could just cite act/scene/line and let people figure it out. At least, my Renaissance colleague said not to worry about editions in our notes. -->--However it was the more I thought of this broken appointment the more I disliked it--I hate to go to any strange people who have before seen <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</persName> because he is so like a flourish of trumpets <quote corresp="#Hamlet_play">"still harping on my daughter"</quote><note resp="#alg">Spoken by Polonius to Hamlet in <title ref="#Hamlet_play">Hamlet</title> (2.2.87-88)<!-- alg: Format for citation? Line number? (Lines 87-88 in the edition I consulted.) --></note>--so I bethought me--&amp; on my return said as innocently as possible <said>Dear me I hope <persName ref="#Frankland_Mrs">Mrs. Frankland</persName>'s<!-- alg: Is this the same as Eleanor Franklin in the si file? I created a new si tag for Frankland_Mrs, but if this is Eleanor Franklin, then new tag needs to be eliminated and this instance needs to be retagged as "Franklin_Eleanor." --><!-- lmw:  I read Frankland also, so not the same. --> children have not got the measles"</said><persName ref="#Russell_M">Mama</persName> heard it as I intended &amp; immediately said she would go herself--&amp; went accordingly--&amp; found <persName ref="#Palmer_Mad">Lady Mad.</persName> very pleasant--but unluckily our message of the day before had never reached her so she had <choice><sic>sate</sic><reg>sat</reg></choice> <!-- alg: Is "sate" the right word here? LMW:  Yes. You can use choice tags to indicate alternative.-->within doors all day waiting for me--&amp; more unluckily still she was so polite as to express a hope of seeing me when she called &amp; <persName ref="#Russell_M">Mama</persName> has actually not let me stir out from home ever since--I have been dying to go to <placeName ref="#Penge_Wood">Penge Wood</placeName>--wild to go to <placeName ref="#Farley_Hill">Farley Hill</placeName>--&amp; not a step would they let me stir--&amp; here as far as I see I am likely to remain--It is enough to make one take the measles<pb n="5"/> in good earnest, &amp; that would be a pity too, for it would deprive me of a capital excuse for not going where I do not like for at least three months of every year.--</p><p>I have been reading two books which I think you might see in <placeName ref="#London_city">London</placeName> &amp; which you would probably like to see--<bibl><author ref="#Frere_JH">Whistlecraft</author>'s <title ref="#Specimen_Nat_poem">Specimen of a National Poem</title></bibl>--a very clever imitation of the burlesque poetry of the Italians--&amp; almost as good--by <persName ref="#Frere_JH">Mr. Frere</persName><!-- alg: Does Mitford give both the J.H. as I have indicated, or is it just a J.? LMW:  I think it's a Mr.-->--too elegant to be called <emph rend="underline">fun</emph> &amp; too entertaining to be called by any other name. They are only two little pamphlets--not an hour's reading in both. The other is <bibl><author ref="#Hazlitt_Wm">Hazlitt</author>'s <title ref="#LecComic_WHaz">lectures on the Comic Writers</title></bibl>. You like <persName ref="#Hazlitt_Wm">Hazlitt</persName>--&amp; I like you to read him because <del> rend="squiggles"<gap quantity="2" unit="letter"/></del> I want your curiosity whetted to read other things--&amp; <persName ref="#Hazlitt_Wm">Hazlitt</persName> is an excellent razor strop.--These <title ref="#LecComic_WHaz">Lectures </title> are particularly agreeable--the account of the <title ref="#Tatler">Tatler</title> &amp; <persName ref="#Johnson">Dr. Johnson</persName> is admirable for its truth &amp; candour--We must expect a little paradox to be sure--It would not be Mr. <gap reason="torn" quantity="1" unit="word"/><unclear><supplied resp="#alg">Hazlitt</supplied></unclear> without something of that sort--&amp; one or two of his sayings <gap reason="torn" quantity="1" unit="word"/><unclear><supplied resp="#lmw">are</supplied></unclear>startling enough--for instance he prefers <title ref="#City_Wives_play">The City Wives' Confederacy</title>--one of that disagreeable <persName ref="#Vanbrugh">Vanbrugh</persName>'s most disagreeable plays, to <title ref="#Merry_Wives_play">The Merry Wives of Windsor</title>--the finest <unclear><supplied resp="#alg">prose</supplied></unclear><!-- alg: Confirm this word is "prose." LMW: I'm not sure either. --> Comedy perhaps in the world.</p><p>Adieu my dear love! Write to me soon &amp; often take great care of yourself--by taking care of yourself I don't mean staying at home--on the contrary go out wherever you are likely to be amused--I mean wrap up well in leaving Theatres--&amp; take advice if you want it--&amp; tell truth mine own dearest &amp; say when you are unwell--In a word Be Good--As to my sweet <persName ref="#Webb_Eliza">Eliza</persName> I shall not send her any admonitions--Thank God she does not want them--but she must write to me &amp; love me &amp; tell me how many lovers you both pick up--&amp; take as many exhibitions Plays Dances Concerts &amp;<pb n="6"/> parties as may happen to come in her way--God bless you both my own dear Girls--I could not anticipate my own amusements with greater pleasure than I do <choice><sic>your's</sic><reg>yours</reg></choice>.</p><p>Love to the <persName ref="#Webb_James">"Mayor of <placeName>Wokingham</placeName>"</persName><!-- alg: Confirm MRM is referring to James Webb here. If so, should this epithet be added as a persName for James Webb in the si file? -->--<persName ref="#Webb_Mary_elder">Aunt Mary</persName>--<persName ref="#Wheeler_Kate">Kate Wheeler</persName> &amp; all that you love--</p><closer><lb/>Ever dearest <persName ref="#Webb_Mary_younger">Mary</persName> most affectionately your's<lb/><signed><persName ref="#MRM">M. R. Mitford</persName>.</signed><address><addrLine>To <persName ref="#Webb_Mary_younger">Miss Webb</persName></addrLine></address></closer><postscript><p><persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</persName> is going to the Sessions, &amp; talks of going to <placeName ref="#Reading_city">Town</placeName><!-- alg: Confirm this is London. LMW:  If it's the quarter session, I expect it's Reading.--><date when="1819-04-25">Sunday</date> morning--not I believe for long. His &amp; <persName ref="#Russell_M">Mama</persName>'s best love.</p></postscript></div></body><back>
        <!-- back list complete and removed to si-add-LMW 2015 10 04 --></back></text></TEI>