<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><!--<?xml-model href="http://ebeshero.github.io/MRMValidate.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>--><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title xml:id="MRM1733">Letter to <persName ref="#Haydon">Benjamin Robert Haydon</persName>, <date when="1819-02-13">February 13, 1819</date></title><author ref="#MRM">Mary Russell Mitford</author><editor ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</editor><sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford Project</orgName></sponsor><sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor><sponsor>Pittsburgh Supercomputing Center</sponsor><principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal><respStmt><resp>Transcription and coding by</resp><persName ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</persName><persName ref="#wnb">William Barr</persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Date last checked: <date when="2015-10-14">2015-10-14</date>
                  Proofing and corrections by</resp><persName ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</persName><persName ref="#mco">Molly C. O'Donnell</persName>
               <!--mco: 2015-09-27: Proofed the body and the TEI header. Added tags and SI entries provided by lmw at bottom to si-add-MCO. Unchecked against ms.-->
               <!--LMW: updating header and tags. 2015 -10-14--></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>First digital edition in TEI, date: <date when="2014-10-05">5 October 2014</date>. P5.</edition><respStmt><resp>Edition made with help from photos taken by</resp><orgName>Digital Mitford editors</orgName></respStmt><respStmt><orgName>Digital Mitford</orgName><resp> photo files: <idno>IMG_0237.jpg, IMG_0238.jpg, IMG_0239.jpg, IMG_0240.jpg, IMG_0241.jpg, IMG_0242.jpg, IMG_0243.jpg</idno></resp></respStmt></editionStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority><pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace><date>2013</date><availability><p>Reproduced by courtesy of the <orgName ref="#ReadingCL">Reading Central Library</orgName>.</p><licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                  License</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Mitford Letters: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><repository ref="#ReadingCL">Reading Central Library</repository><collection>The letters of Mary Russell Mitford, vol. 4, 1819-1823</collection><idno>qB/TU/MIT Vol. 4 Horizon No.: 1361550 ff.362 </idno></msIdentifier><head>Letter from Mary Russell Mitford to Benjamin Robert Haydon, <date when="1819-02-13">1819 February 13</date>.</head><physDesc><objectDesc><supportDesc><support><p>One sheet of folio <material>paper</material>, four surfaces photographed.</p><p>Address leaf bearing no postmarks.</p></support><condition><p>Sheet (pages three and four) torn on right edge where wax seal was removed. Upper corner also torn.</p></condition></supportDesc></objectDesc><sealDesc><p>Black wax seal, remnants of black wax adhered elsewhere on page three.</p></sealDesc></physDesc></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><handNotes><handNote corresp="#rc" medium="red_crayon"> Red crayon or thick red pencil. Probably a different hand from Mitford's that marks many of her letters, sometimes drawing diagonal lines across pages, and sometimes writing words overtop and perpendicularly across Mitford's writing. On this letter, a red line is drawn top left to bottom right of each of the leaves. Page three has three additional diagonal lines drawn through the text blocks on the bottom half of the page. There is no red crayon on page four, the address leaf.</handNote><handNote corresp="#pencil" medium="pencil"> Someone, apparently other than Mitford, perhaps cataloging letters and describing them, who left grey pencil marks and numbered her letters now in the Reading Central Library's collection. This letter is numbered "4" in the top left of the first leaf, underneath the opening line, "To Sir W. Elford." The year 1819 is also written twice at the top of the letter.
           </handNote></handNotes></profileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><p>Mitford’s spelling and punctuation are retained, except where a word is split at the end of a line and the beginning of the next in the manuscript. Where Mitford’s spelling and hyphenation of words deviates from the standard, in order to facilitate searching we are using the TEI elements “choice," “sic," and “reg" to encode both Mitford’s spelling and the regular international standard of Oxford English spelling, following the first listed spelling in the Oxford English Dictionary. The long s and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="letter"><opener><salute>To <persName ref="#Haydon">B. R. Haydon Esq.</persName></salute><add hand="#pencil">4</add><add hand="#pencil">1819</add><dateline><placeName ref="#Bertram_house">Bertram House</placeName><date when="1821-02-13">Feb<hi rend="superscript">y</hi> 13<hi rend="superscript">th</hi><add hand="#pencil">1819</add></date>.
               </dateline></opener><salute>My dear Sir</salute><p>My <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Father</persName> is going tomorrow into <placeName ref="#Hampshire_county">Hampshire</placeName> to course for a few days &amp; tells me that he hopes to be able to send you a hare--I take the opportunity to thank you a thousand times for your kind letter &amp; kinder promise--You must not forget it--we shall not I assure you--&amp; I trust when my <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Father</persName> goes to <placeName ref="#London_city">London</placeName> you will be able to fix a time for favouring us with your company.--Not content with plaguing you with a note I have been so encroaching as to trouble you with <title ref="#Poems_1st_ed_MRM">a book</title> very little worth the honour of your acceptance--It was written when extreme youth &amp; haste might apologize for the incorrectness the silliness &amp; the common place with which it abounds--but I am afraid it has deficiences which are worse than <pb n="1"/>any faults. Do not think of reading it through--If your kind indulgence should lead you to look at any part, let it be <title corresp="#Beauty_MRM">Beauty</title>, <title corresp="#Sun_Set_MRM">Sun-set</title> &amp; the <title corresp="#VoiceofPraise_MRM">Voice of Praise</title>--they are, not better, that is too vain a word, but less bad than the rest.<note resp="#lmw">It appears that <persName ref="#MRM">Mitford</persName> sends <persName ref="#Haydon">B. R. Haydon Esq.</persName> a copy of the one-volume first edition of <title ref="#Poems_1st_ed_MRM">her 1810 Poems</title> with this letter, although she may possibly have sent him a copy of the two-volume <title ref="#Poems_2nd_ed_MRM">second edition</title>.</note></p><p>I am enchanted to hear you have a favourite Greyhound--<persName ref="#MRM_maledog_pet">My pet</persName> is neither very good nor very handsome--I did not choose him--he chose me--he sought me, followed me, loved me, would be loved &amp; was loved. There is no resisting preference &amp; affection come from where they may, so he is my pet. He has a rival just now in <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</persName>'s heart in the shape of a beautiful <rs type="person" ref="#Miranda_pet">puppy</rs> sent to me as a present--who has associations in her favour which are almost irresistable, having been pupped in an outhouse belonging to the identical butcher's shop at <placeName ref="#Stratford_upon_Avon_city">Stratford upon Avon</placeName> where <persName ref="#Shakespeare">Shakespeare</persName> was born. She is moreover exceedingly beautiful--blue all sprinkled with little white spots <pb n="2"/>just like a starry night. We call <gap reason="torn" quantity="1" unit="word"/><unclear/><supplied resp="lmw">her </supplied><persName ref="#Miranda_pet">Miranda</persName>--you know it is the coursi<gap reason="torn" quantity="2" unit="chars"/><unclear/><supplied resp="lmw">ng</supplied>etiquette that the initial of the <choice><sic>dogs</sic><reg resp="#lmw">dog's</reg></choice> nam<gap reason="torn" quantity="1" unit="chars"/><unclear/><supplied resp="lmw">e</supplied> should correspond with the <choice><sic>masters</sic><reg resp="#lmw">master's</reg></choice>.<!--LMW:  Is there a better way to code the missing apostrophe's in ms.? It is similar to how we are handling yours/your's,--></p><p>Your pupils have done that which I thought impossible--they have added to your fame. Every new arrival from <placeName ref="#London_city">Town</placeName> talks of their drawings--How very fine drawings must be to make people talk of them! <!--lmw  can we find specific reference? exhibition by Haydon pupils?-->Yes--You will certainly found a school in this land of joys &amp; liberty &amp; we shall live to see it. <!--lmw: cross marked in pencil.--></p><p>Adieu, my dear Sir. <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#Russell_M">Mama</persName> beg their kindest remembrances &amp; good wishes, &amp; I am ever</p><closer><lb/>most sincerely <choice><sic>your's</sic><reg resp="#lmw">yours</reg></choice><lb/><lb/><persName ref="#MRM">M. R. Mitford</persName>.<lb/></closer><postscript><p>&amp; Ah my dear friend, not with these pupils--<!--lmw: Who adds this?--></p></postscript><postscript><p>There is no other <persName ref="#MRM">Miss Mitford</persName>--I am the only daughter--the only child--Pray don't think it necessary to say any thing civil of my rhymes--I hope your eyes are much better. Once more farewell.</p></postscript><closer><address><addrLine>To <persName ref="#Haydon">B.R. Haydon Esq<hi rend="superscript">re</hi></persName></addrLine></address></closer></div></body><back><div> <!-- back list complete and removed to si-add-LMW 2015 10 04 --></div></back></text></TEI>