<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><?xml-model href="http://ebeshero.github.io/MRMValidate.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title xml:id="MRM1732">Letter to <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir William Elford</persName>, <date when="1819-02-10"> February 10, 1819</date></title><author ref="#MRM">Mary Russell Mitford</author><editor ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</editor><sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford Project</orgName></sponsor><sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor><sponsor>Pittsburgh Supercomputing Center</sponsor><principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal><respStmt><resp>Transcription and coding by</resp><persName ref="#hsar">Heather Sarsfield</persName><persName ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Date last checked: <date when="2015-10-13">2015-10-13</date>
                        Proofing and corrections by</resp><persName ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</persName></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>First digital edition in TEI, date: <date when="2014-10-13">13 October 2014</date>. P5.</edition><respStmt><resp>Edition made with help from photos taken by</resp><orgName>Digital Mitford editors</orgName></respStmt><respStmt><orgName>Digital Mitford</orgName><resp> photo files: <idno>IMG_0219.jpg, IMG_0220.jpg, IMG_0221.jpg, IMG_0222.jpg, IMG_0223.jpg, IMG_0224.jpg, IMG_0225.jpg, IMG_0226.jpg, IMG_0227.jpg, IMG_0228.jpg, IMG_0229.jpg, IMG_0230.jpg, IMG_0231.jpg, IMG_0232.jpg, IMG_0233.jpg, IMG_0234.jpg, IMG_0235.jpg, IMG_0236.jpg</idno></resp></respStmt></editionStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority><pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace><date>2013</date><availability><p>Reproduced by courtesy of the <orgName ref="#ReadingCL">Reading Central Library</orgName>.</p><licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                        License</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Mitford Letters: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><repository ref="#ReadingCL">Reading Central Library</repository><collection>The letters of Mary Russell Mitford, vol. 4, 1819-1823</collection><idno>qB/TU/MIT Vol. 4 Horizon No.: 1361550 ff. 360</idno></msIdentifier><head>Letter from Mary Russell Mitford to Sir William Elford, <date when="1819-02-10">1819 February 10</date>.</head><physDesc><objectDesc><supportDesc><support><p>Two sheets of <material>paper</material>, eight surfaces photographed.</p><p>Address leaf bearing sepia double circle postmark, partially illegible, reading <stamp><lb/>FREE<lb/><lb/>17FE17<lb/><lb/>1819<lb/></stamp>.</p></support><condition><p>Leaves seven and eight torn on edge where wax seal was removed.</p></condition></supportDesc></objectDesc><sealDesc><p>Red wax seal</p></sealDesc></physDesc></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><handNotes><handNote corresp="#rc" medium="red_crayon"> Red crayon or thick red pencil. Probably a different hand from Mitford's that marks many of her letters, sometimes drawing diagonal lines across pages, and sometimes writing words overtop and perpendicularly across Mitford's writing. On this letter, a red line is drawn from top left to bottom right of each of the leaves. On the address leaf, two red lines are drawn from top left to bottom right over each text block.</handNote><handNote corresp="#pencil" medium="pencil"> Someone, apparently other than Mitford, perhaps cataloging letters and describing them, who left grey pencil marks and numbered her letters now in the Reading Central Library's collection. This letter is numbered "13" in the top left of the first leaf.</handNote></handNotes></profileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><p>Mitford’s spelling and punctuation are retained, except where a word is split at the end of a line and the beginning of the next in the manuscript. Where Mitford’s spelling and hyphenation of words deviates from the standard, in order to facilitate searching we are using the TEI elements “choice," “sic," and “reg" to encode both Mitford’s spelling and the regular international standard of Oxford English spelling, following the first listed spelling in the Oxford English Dictionary. The long s and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="letter"><opener><salute>To <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir W. Elford</persName></salute><add hand="#pencil">3</add><dateline><name type="place" ref="#Bertram_house">Bertram House</name><date when="1819-02-10">Feb<hi rend="superscript">y</hi> 10<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1819.</date>.
                    </dateline></opener><p>I sit down with malice prepense to scold you my own dear naughty <choice><sic>goodfornothing</sic><reg>good-for-nothing</reg></choice>Friend–-to think of your passing so close &amp; never calling--never writing a line to say you meant to pass--quite forgetting your poor little Correspondent--quite neglecting the <persName ref="#whitekitten_WEpet">white kitten</persName>! Oh dear dear, to apply the philosophy of a fair Cousin of mine, aged five upon a similar desertion--<said>"Oh dear, dear, Mans is all alike!"</said>--Well--I can't scold any longer--writing to you always puts me in a good humour, so I must tell you seriously how very sorry we are not to have seen you here, &amp; how particularly my <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Father</persName> regrets being at the very time in <placeName ref="#Reading_city">Reading</placeName>, being there all the time you were, &amp; yet missing you. We were forced to leave <placeName ref="#Bear_Inn">"the Bear"</placeName> last summer on account of an election trick played by them which put life &amp; limb <del rend="squiggles" unit="chars" n="1"/>in danger--nothing less than <del rend="squiggles" unit="word" n="1">pull</del> taking out the linch pins from the Gig--&amp; now our anchorage in <placeName ref="#Reading_city">Reading</placeName> is at a 6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> or 7<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> rate Inn kept by <add rend="caret" place="above">the father of</add>an old servant--<placeName ref="#Red_Cow_Inn">"The Red Cow,"</placeName> an it please your worship--thither was your note sent--but most unluckily the host (one <persName ref="#Brulgruddery_D">Mr. Dennis Brulgruddery</persName> you know) was not informed of the place where <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</persName> dined--&amp; after sending &amp; going about to ask all his usual haunts &amp; hearing no tidings of him gave up the search--so that poor <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</persName> never heard a word of any enquiry till he got your note when he went for his horse &amp; found on going to <placeName ref="#Bear_Inn">the Bear</placeName> that you must be by that time nearly at <placeName ref="#Newbury">Newbury</placeName> (N.B. Poor <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</persName> in addition to his own disappointment--got very undutifully scolded when he came home for not <pb n="2"/>having seen you--upon the same feminine principle which leads every woman to scold people for cutting their own fingers.)--Much as I always wish to see you I particularly desired the pleasure of your company now because we are expecting <persName ref="#Hofland_B">Mrs. Hofland</persName> today &amp; I think you would have been equally pleased &amp; amused by this very acute clever &amp; imaginative woman. I don't know any thing more entertaining than the contrast &amp; between her strong <placeName ref="#Yorkshire_county">Yorkshire</placeName> dialect, which has a twang like <placeName ref="#Cheshire_county">Cheshire</placeName> cheese, &amp; the elegant &amp; ornamented diction in which she clothes her original &amp; fanciful conceptions--one can scarcely think that the voice &amp; the words belong to each other--I am sure you would have liked her--she has so much enthusiasm--&amp; fancies she has none--lets her heart out so completely thinking all the time that she keeps it in--claims for herself <del rend="squiggles" unit="word" n="1">all</del> the honours of utility &amp; common sense &amp; coldness &amp; hardness, &amp; is all the while as romantic as eloquent &amp; as nonsensical as <persName ref="#Rousseau">Rousseau</persName>. She is the very person for me--I like contrasts as you may have discovered--&amp; <persName ref="#Hofland_B">Mrs. Hofland</persName> is the complete personification of Contrast--a living breathing moving antithesis. I do wish you had seen her--&amp; above all I do wish she had seen you--to hear a person one likes &amp; admires described by her eloquent tongue is like looking at a favourite landscape through a <persName ref="#Lorrain_Cl">Claude <choice><sic>Lorraine</sic><reg>Lorrain</reg></choice></persName> glass--all rich &amp; glowing &amp; sun se<emph rend="underline">tty.</emph><note resp="#lmw">A "Claude glass" is a convex-shaped dark-colored glass used by landscape artists, travellers, and other admirers of pictureque landscape to allow them to more easily distill the image of a large landscape into gradations of color. Named for the 17th-century landscape painter Claude Lorraine, whose work was much admired in Mitford's time as quintessentially "picturesque." Claude glasses were usually carried about in a case for easy portability. As Mitford notes, one effect of the glass was to make a landscape appear to be more "rich and glowing and sunsetty" than it did to the naked eye.</note> I do wish she had seen you.</p><metamark rend="jerk"/><p>Winter--just as I had got so far the heroine of this last page <persName ref="#Hofland_B">Mrs. Hofland</persName> in her own proper person put up her appearance &amp; forced me to break off abruptly--then came your kind letter--then all manner of jaunting about to <placeName ref="#Reading_city">Reading</placeName> &amp; to <placeName ref="#Farley_Hill">Farley Hill</placeName> so that I had not a moment for writing till now <date when="1819-02-15">(Monday the 15th)</date> when our visitor having departed &amp; all being quiet again I am at leisure <pb n="3"/>to finish my epistle as fast as thick ink and an unmendable pen &amp; a most stupefying cold will permit. Your dear letter I had almost answered before its arrival--I had told you of the lamentations of both <rs type="person" ana="#whitekitten_WEpet #Selima_cat_pet">your white kittens</rs>--the large &amp; the little--These lamentations have by no means ceased--<persName ref="#whitekitten_WEpet">Selima</persName> the big ones Oh Dear--<persName ref="#whitekitten_WEpet">Selima the small</persName> says  <choice><sic>Miau</sic><reg resp="#lmw">Meow</reg></choice>as often as they think of their misfortune in not seeing you. By the way what shall we do with <persName ref="#whitekitten_WEpet">the fair Persian</persName>? Is there any chance that you may come <placeName ref="#London_city">London</placeName>-ward again this Spring? If you do you <emph rend="underline">must</emph> come &amp; see us positively. (Really I have made a very good pen of this at last--I improve.) If you stay in the West would you like that she should be sent by Coach or by  <choice><sic>waggon</sic><reg resp="#lmw">wagon</reg></choice>? or How? Or shall we at all events keep her till we meet?--<persName ref="#Miranda_pet">Miranda</persName> is very good to her--there is no fear from that charming puppy--but her Papa, old <persName ref="#Selim_pet">Selim</persName>, is a perfect--perfect--perfect--(what is the word in <unclear><emph rend="underline">Ide</emph></unclear> to express a He Cat who kills his own sons &amp; daughters?)--he drove the poor pretty <persName ref="#whitekitten_WEpet">kitten</persName> fairly up the Chimney the other day over the burning fire--frightened us all out of our wits &amp; soiled your little beauty's spotless coat so that she has not been white since. <persName ref="#Selim_pet">Selim</persName> is banished for this offense--he is never to approach the parlour again. <q>"Love me love my <emph rend="underline">Cat</emph>"</q>--I assure you I take great care of your <persName ref="#whitekitten_WEpet">kitten</persName>.</p><metamark rend="jerk"/><p>I congratulate you most sincerely on escaping the Sheriffalty--you have surely done your duty in all constitutional services--as militia Colonel &amp; Member of Parliament &amp; ought to be left to your own avocations &amp; amusements. In such a County as <placeName ref="#Devonshire_county">Devonshire</placeName> they cannot be at a loss for respectable Gentlemen who so far from being <q>"Candidates for non-employment"</q> would consider the Sheriffalty an object of Ambition. Ministers have acted very wisely. I shall certainly grow ministerial in time--especially if they turn out <rs type="person" ref="#Palmer_CF">our poor aquatic Member</rs><note resp="#lmw">"Our poor acquatic member" is a joking reference on Charles Fyshe Palmer's name. His nickname was "Long Fyshe."</note>, &amp; give us the fun of another election--for <persName ref="#Weyland_John">Mr. Weyland</persName> having bribed away at a most glorious rate<pb n="4"/> will certainly be met by a counterpetition should his petition succeed. I must confess (though it is not quite handsome to say so in a letter which I mean <persName ref="#Palmer_CF">Mr. Palmer</persName> to address) that <persName ref="#Palmer_Mad">Lady Madalina</persName>'s pension does--rather turn in my stomach--There is no moral sin certainly in receiving a pension--but then he who receives it has no right to set up for such a violent <unclear><supplied resp="#lmw">reformer</supplied></unclear>--Well--he is a charming man <persName ref="#Palmer_CF">Mr. Fyshe Palmer</persName>! And I hope he means to let <persName ref="#Weyland_John">Mr. Weyland</persName>'s petition be thrown out &amp; then give up the 200 a year.<note resp="#lmw">Refers to Weyland's petition that Palmer be declared ineligible to serve as M.P. because his wife receives a state pension. The Commons ultimately rejected Weyland's petition.</note> This is what you would do is it not?</p><metamark rend="jerk"/><p> To return to where we were at <persName ref="#Hofland_B">Mrs. Hofland</persName>'s Entrance. "Winter &amp; foul weather" have kept me so <del rend="squiggles" unit="word" n="1"/><add place="above">entirely</add>within that I have read so much &amp; with so little <unclear/> between as to produce a sort of mental indigestion a loathing of books--very convenient just now when the change from black to colours gives me plenty of employment of another sort. One of these books was 12 Volumes of <persName ref="#Burke_E">Burke</persName>'s works--No need to say how exceedingly I admired this great man, but may I without presumption, without affecting to talk of that which is sometime thought above a woman's comprehension, say that the admiration I felt was excited by very different qualities from those which I expected to find in this celebrated Orator. In a word I admired his wisdom more than his eloquence. His writings (those especially of his earlier days) seemed to me to breathe the very soul of Statesmanship--wide open--honest &amp; <del rend="squiggles" unit="word" n="1">good</del><add place="above">true</add>--but those splendid passages which are so cried up--that on <persName ref="#Howard_John">Howard</persName>--that on the <persName ref="#Marie_Antoinette">Queen of France</persName> &amp; so forth--did not please me. They are neither prose--nor verse--They are like <persName ref="#Ossian">Ossian</persName>--like <persName ref="#Hervey_Wm">Hervey</persName>--like <persName ref="#Phillips_Chas"><choice><sic>Philips</sic><reg>Phillips</reg></choice></persName>--<persName ref="#Porter_AM">Miss Anna Maria Porter</persName>Like <persName ref="#Owenson_S">Lady Morgan</persName>. Luckily they are <del rend="squiggles" unit="word" n="1">very</del> few &amp; rare, &amp; the effect of his admirable good sense cannot be diminished by these occasional sacrifices to the genius of his Country--(for if <del rend="squiggles" unit="word" n="1"/><add place="above">we</add> wanted to express Irish Eloquence by one word must not that word be Bombast?)--I should not perhaps have been so much struck with this false taste had I not been first reading <del rend="squiggles" unit="word" n="1"/><add place="above"><persName ref="#Junius">Junius</persName></add> whose severe purity of <pb n="5"/>style forms such a complete contrast with this kind of grandiloquence.--But if I was disappointed one way in <persName ref="#Burke_E">Mr. Burke</persName>, I was more surprised in another at missing the inconsistency of which one has heard so much. I do not think him inconsistent--he was a party man it is true, &amp; of a party which being mostly in opposition seemed to take the <del rend="squiggles" unit="word" n="1">part</del><add place="above">side</add> of Freedom, as the opposition always must--But from the first to that last <persName ref="#Burke_E">Mr. Burke</persName> was an Aristocrat--a violent aristocrat--I have not an idea that the pension had the least to do with his aversion to French Politics--I believe him to have been sincere--&amp; though somewhat awed by the opposition to his old friends, somewhat fiercer than ordinary, like a man who takes up a position where he expects to be attacked, yet as little <del rend="squiggles" unit="chars" n="2">un</del>changed as any man in the <orgName ref="#House_Commons">House</orgName>--as <persName ref="#Fox_ChasJ">Mr. Fox</persName> himself. All this seems so different from the view that I commonly find taken of <persName ref="#Burke_E">Mr. Burke</persName>'s conduct both by friends &amp; foes, that I must most probably be wrong--tell me if you think so--I can only say that it is my sincere opinion--Then I have been reading some very amusing old writing edited a few years back--<title ref="#Letters_Hearne_Aubrey">Letters selected from the Bodleian Library--<persName ref="#Hearne_Thos">Hearne</persName>'s visits to <placeName ref="#Reading_city">Reading</placeName> &amp;c--&amp; last not least <persName ref="#Aubrey_John">Aubrey</persName>'s Lives</title><add place="above">(a little softened &amp; purified I believe)</add><!-- caret --> Oh what a delicious painter of mind &amp; body is that worshipful Master <persName ref="#Aubrey_John">Aubrey</persName>--What portraits in Enamel he produced, how fresh, how rich, how fine!--<title ref="#Johnson_Lives"><persName ref="#Johnson">Johnson</persName>'s Lives</title> are but <persName ref="#Aubrey_John">Aubrey</persName> diluted--very often <persName ref="#Aubrey_John">Aubrey</persName> spoilt. Do read them particularly the Life of <persName ref="#Kettle_Dr">Dr. Kettle</persName>--the <persName ref="#PembrokeI">first Lord Pembroke</persName><persName ref="#Jonson_B">Ben Jonson</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#Hobbes">Hobbes</persName>--but read them all--Why is it that English people in this age can no more write portraits like <persName ref="#Aubrey_John">Aubrey</persName> than the present race of <orgName ref="#Italians">Italians</orgName> can paint portraits like <persName ref="#Titian">Titian</persName>? And yet we are good Colourists--we can give fancy pictures well enough. <del rend="squiggles" unit="word" n="1">but</del> as witness <persName ref="#Scott_Wal">Scott</persName>--<persName ref="#Austen_Jane">Miss Austen</persName>--&amp; Novellists by the dozen--but we cannot take a likeness--there is no Biographer of the present day who has given any thing like the graphic identity of <del rend="squiggles" unit="word" n="1"/><persName>Aubrey</persName> or <persName ref="#Walton_I">Isaac Walton</persName> to his hero<pb n="6"/>--<persName ref="#Boswell">Boswell</persName> indeed has enabled us to paint for ourselves the picture of <persName ref="#Johnson">Dr. Johnson</persName>--but <persName ref="#Aubrey_John">Aubrey</persName> would have given him in half a page, at one stroke of the pen we should have seen the <persName ref="#Johnson">Lexicographer</persName>--I think one reason why we have no <persName ref="#Aubrey_John">Aubrey</persName>s now is that we do not sufficiently cultivate the habits of truth severe scrupulous truth--we paint in praise or in caricature--in oil--or in pasto--led away by love or by fancy--or by naughty wicked wit.--I myself without the excuse of wit, am sometimes conscious that though I say that which I think &amp; believe--yet that memory &amp; imagination &amp; fondness may sometimes give too sunshiny a character to my portraits--&amp; that the ridiculous (<persName ref="#Crowther_Mr">my pet dandy</persName> always excepted) is not quite so ridiculous abroad &amp; walking as set down on paper. Having thus fairly given you warning not to believe a word that I say--though I intend in future to be as accuarate as <persName>Aubrey</persName> himself--I cannot help recommending to you another book which I have read before &amp; you perhaps likewise--<title>Forsyth's Italy</title>--the most amusing--the best written--&amp; shortest of all the books on that well beaten subject--Pray have you read my <persName ref="#Owenson_S">Lady Morgan</persName>'s <title ref="#Florence_Macarthy_SO">Florence Macarthy</title>? And what do you think of it?  And how do you like the Dramatis Personae <persName ref="#Napoleon">Buonaparte</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#Byron">Lord Byron</persName>, <persName ref="#Croker_JW">Mr. Croker</persName>, <persName ref="#Owenson_S">Lady Morgan</persName>, &amp; the mad schoolmaster?<!-- reference? --> Altogether the medley is such as Master Peter's puppets<!-- reference? --> exhibited after <persName ref="#Don_Quixote_char">Don Quixote</persName> had <del rend="squiggles" unit="word" n="1">knocked</del><add place="above">hacked</add> them to pieces--about as valuable &amp; nearly as well arranged. There are glimmerings of talent too about <persName ref="#Owenson_S">Lady Morgan</persName>, &amp; if she would but abstain from <placeName ref="#Ireland">Ireland</placeName> (I would not trust her so near as <placeName ref="#Holyhead">Holyhead</placeName>) keep clear from <placeName ref="#Ireland">Ireland</placeName> &amp; Irish politics old &amp; new--be content with English &amp; abstain from French latin &amp; Italian good or bad--but especially from bad (Mem. (as <persName ref="#Aubrey_John">Aubrey</persName> says) I don't mean to tie her to <emph rend="underline">good</emph> English--that would too barbarous)--&amp; above <pb n="7"/> all if she would engage never to have any thing to say of <persName ref="#Napoleon">Napoleon</persName> (I can't bear her dragging him <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="3" unit="words"/><unclear/></del>in between <persName ref="#Punch">Punch</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#Judy">his Wife</persName>)--if she would do all this &amp; write only a Volume a year--why then one might really read her books from end to end--&amp; say if people asked "How do you like it?" Why the book is decent."--I wonder whether she would box my ears if you were to tell her what I say! </p><metamark rend="jerk"/><p>You do not in your kind short letter mention what I told you of my dear <persName ref="#James_Miss">Miss James</persName> (I never overpraised her)--but I am so sure of your goodness that I have ventured to trouble you with a copy of the terms &amp;c which <persName ref="#James_Susan">Miss Susan James</persName> has just sent me, &amp; which you may perhaps have the goodness to give to any one who is likely to recommend her. Observe my dear Friend that I do not wish to encroach on your goodness by making you an Advertiser of <persName ref="#James_Miss">Miss James</persName>'s school, but merely to request that if any one likely to place a young lady <del rend="squiggles" unit="chars" n="2">there</del><add place="above">"near Town"</add> should <gap reason="torn" quantity="1" unit="word"/><unclear/><supplied resp="lmw">apply</supplied> to you, that you will give her the countenance of your <gap reason="torn" quantity="1" unit="word"/><unclear/><supplied resp="lmw">mention.</supplied> I am sure she would never disappoint the hopes of any Parent. </p><metamark rend="jerk"/><p>We trust that you found <persName ref="#Elford_J">Mr. Elford</persName>much better than you feared--Write soon &amp; give me an excellent account of yourself.--You must write soon &amp; long--Think how much we have been disappointed by not seeing you.--<persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#Russell_M">Mama</persName> beg their kindest remembrances &amp; I am ever my dear <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir William</persName></p><closer><lb/>most faithfully &amp; affectionately <choice><sic>your's</sic><reg resp="#lmw">yours</reg></choice><lb/><persName ref="#MRM">M.R. Mitford</persName>.
                    
                    <address><pb n="8"/><addrLine><placeName ref="#London_city">London</placeName><date when="1819-02-17">February Seventeen <lb/>1819</date></addrLine><addrLine><persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir William Elford</persName> Bart</addrLine><addrLine><placeName ref="#Bickham_village">Bickham</placeName></addrLine><addrLine><persName ref="#Palmer_CF">CFPalmer</persName><lb/><placeName ref="#Plymouth_city">Plymouth</placeName></addrLine></address></closer><postscript><p>P.S. Are you interested in the reprinting of old Poetry? We are likely to have some selections printed in great style at <placeName ref="#Reading_city">Reading</placeName>--<persName ref="#Milman_HH">Mr. Milman</persName>, whose taste &amp; genius fit him so exactly for an Editor of such gems &amp; who has the wide range of <persName ref="#Heber_Rich">Mr. Heber</persName>'s library, has been lucky enough to find a Curate ready placed who is equally qualified for the mechanical part of printing--so they are going to procure a private press &amp; fall to printing ding dong. I am glad of this.--I have abused our stupid &amp; independent <placeName ref="#Reading_city">Town</placeName> so long that I have worn out all condemning phrases, &amp; shall be delighted with the novelty of saying civil things on the subject. Besides I like a printing press--my Friend <persName ref="#Dickinson_Charles">Mr. Dickinson</persName> has one at <placeName ref="#Farley_Hill">Farley Hill</placeName> where I am a <unclear/> of the Printer's Devil. Only think of my not knowing <persName ref="#Milman_HH">Mr. Milman</persName> yet. <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</persName> won't call on him, say all I can. Pray excuse this very stupid letter--It is all my cold's fault, which makes me feel as if the place where the brains ought to be were filled up with lead.--The <persName ref="#whitekitten_WEpet">little white kitten</persName> sends love &amp; duty.--Adieu my dear friend --Pray write soon--I am going to bed--Good night--God bless You </p></postscript></div></body><back>
            <!--LMW;  backlist pulled to si-add-LMW 2015 10 13 --></back></text></TEI>