<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><?xml-model href="http://ebeshero.github.io/MRMValidate.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Title</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Publication Information</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Information about the source</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p><lb/><placeName ref="#Bertram_house">Bertram House</placeName><lb/><date when="1819-12-23">Dec. 23<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi></date><rs type="person" ref="#Webb_Mary_younger">My dear Friend</rs><persName ref="#Kuyvett_Chas">Mr. Charles Kuyvett</persName> &amp; you do me no more than justice in believing me, though come of Moss trooping Ancestry, very little inclined to perpetuate a <!--fraud?--> from generation to generation--So much indeed am I of <persName ref="#Franklin_Ben">Dr. Franklin</persName>'s mind that there never was a good war or a bad peace that I should be exceedingly happy to bring about a cessation of hostilities between the present Belligerents--that however might be a little difficult--certainly with my Gentleman--probably with his--so we have nothing for it but to be as pacific as possible in our own persons &amp; to make up by tenfold amity &amp; goodwill for the quarrelling sins of our angry progenitors. In token of this friendly disposition I send six of my <persName ref="#Russell_Richard">Grandfather</persName>'s sermons. <persName ref="#Kuyvett_Chas">Mr. Charles Kuyvett</persName> will not like them the less for being written by a <orgName ref="#Westminster_Sch">Westminster</orgName> &amp; <orgName ref="#Christchurch_Oxf">Christchurch</orgName> man.--one old enough to remember <persName ref="#Pope_Alex">Pope</persName> and <persName ref="#Gay_John">Gay</persName> &amp; the intimate friend of <persName ref="#Melmoth_Wm">Melmoth</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#Fielding_Henry">Fielding</persName>. Perhaps I may be partial but <persName ref="#Russell_Richard">Dr. Russell</persName>'s style seems to me singularly soft flowing &amp; graceful--with an occasional touch of <persName ref="#Walton_I">Isaac Walton</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#Addison_Joseph">Addison</persName> about it--something quite different from the edgy angular abruptness of these sharp pointed days--Any thing at all obsolete (for my <persName ref="#Russell_Richard">Grandfather</persName> died at 88 leaving <rs type="person" ref="#Russell_M">my mother</rs> a very young woman &amp; these sermons were mostly written in his own youth) can easily be altered in transcribing them. I would have sent more but <persName ref="#Russell_M">Mama</persName> had unluckily taken nearly all our stock to <placeName ref="#Winchester_city">Winchester</placeName> for <persName ref="#Woodburn_Mr">Mr. Woodburn</persName>'s benefit &amp; <persName ref="#Woodburn_Mr">Mr. Woodburn</persName> being of all mortals the most indolent &amp; dilatory nothing can be so uncertain as the time which he may take in getting them copied.--Of course there can be no doubt of the case of <persName ref="#Kuyvett_Chas">Mr. C. Kuyvett</persName> in returning them, or of yours, my dear <persName ref="#Webb_Mary_younger">Mary</persName> in putting them by for me--They are very valuable to <persName ref="#Russell_M">Mama</persName> as reliques of a very dear &amp; respectable <persName ref="#Russell_Richard">Father</persName>.--After all my dear <rs type="person" ref="#Webb_Mary_younger">Friend</rs> these are not the "long old sermons" of which you have heard me speak--They are undoubtedly as well known to <persName ref="#Kuyvett_Chas">Mr. K.</persName> as to me <pb n="3"/> the sermons of <persName>Barron <!--??--></persName> &amp; above all of <persName>Jeremy Taylor</persName>--It would not be very wise to compile from these fine sources since they are unluckily of a nature not to be forgotten or mistaken--&amp; even if it were I have not one of these divines comeatable most of them are packed up at <placeName ref="#Coley_Berks">Coley</placeName>, &amp; the others were only borrowed &amp; are just returned.--To be sure my dear <persName ref="#Dickinson_Mrs">Mrs. Dickinson</persName> must be as mad as a mad-Cow--to think of seeing the bull baiting in her situation--What makes it the more wonderful is that the very last time we were in <placeName ref="#Reading_city">Reading</placeName> she frightened me to death by the fright she took at a harmless quiet tame Cow who was walking as peaceably as possible along the middle of the Street.--I am very glad you did not deliver my message about <persName ref="#Haydon">Mr. Haydon</persName>, he has now a violent fancy for a thorough bred handsome blue gentleman to his thorough bred handsome blue <persName>lady</persName>. "Only think," he says "how graceful it would be for me to sally forth every day with my brace of greyhounds!" Don't you delight in this frank &amp; open profession of foppery?<pb n="4"/> Is there any chance of its being gratified? Let me know--&amp; write to tell me that the Sermons came safe &amp; were liked--<del rend="squiggles"/> there is no hurry about returning them.--I have a letter from <persName ref="#Nooth_C">Miss Nooth</persName> today who says the "Monsters" in <placeName ref="#Paris">Paris</placeName> are supposed to be employed by a great foreign power to inoculate for the plague. What a comfortable idea for those whom they Stab!!!--I have a letter from <persName ref="#James_Miss">Miss James</persName> too who sends a thousand loves to you all--She talks of going to <placeName ref="#Birmingham_city">Birmingham</placeName> in <date when="1820-02">Februar</date>y.--Adieu my dear <rs type="person" ref="#Webb_Mary_younger">Friend</rs>--Best love to All--I hope your dear <persName ref="#Webb_James">Father</persName> did not suffer from the fatigue of yesterday--Ever most affectionately <choice><sic>your's</sic><reg>yours</reg></choice><persName ref="#MRM">M.R. Mitford</persName>.</p></body><back><div type="historical_people"><listPerson sortKey="histPersons"><person xml:id="Kuyvett_Chas" sex="1"><persName><surname>Kuyvett</surname><forename>Charles</forename></persName><occupation>clergy</occupation></person><person xml:id="Woodburn_Mr" sex="1"><persName><surname>Woodburn</surname><forename/><roleName>Mr.</roleName></persName><occupation>clergy</occupation></person><person xml:id="Gay_John" sex="1"><persName><surname>Gay</surname><forename>John</forename><roleName/></persName><occupation/></person><person xml:id="Melmoth_Wm" sex="1"><persName><surname>Melmoth</surname><forename>William</forename><roleName/></persName><occupation/>
                 <!-- Is this the elder or the younger?  Richard Russell was born in 1695. --></person></listPerson><listOrg sortKey="histOrgs"><org xml:id="Westminster_Sch"><orgName>Westminster School</orgName></org><org xml:id="Christchurch_Oxf"><orgName>ChristChurch, Oxford University</orgName></org></listOrg></div></back></text></TEI>