<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><?xml-model href="http://ebeshero.github.io/MRMValidate.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title xml:id="MRM1730">Letter to <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir William Elford</persName>, <date when="1819-01-09">January 9, 1819</date></title><author ref="#MRM">Mary Russell Mitford</author><editor ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</editor><sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford Project</orgName></sponsor><sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor><principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal><respStmt><resp>Transcription and coding by</resp><persName ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Date last checked: <date when="2015-10-12">2015-10-12</date><!-- Updating header, checking James tags.  LMW -->
               Proofing and corrections by</resp><persName ref="#mco">Molly C. O'Donnell</persName> <!--mco: 2015-09-29:Checked against whole manuscript, added tags, and proofed body and TEI header.-->
               <!-- Updating header, checking James tags.  LMW --></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>First digital edition in TEI, date: <date when="2014-10-05">5 October 2014</date>. P5.</edition><respStmt><resp>Edition made with help from photos taken by</resp><orgName>Digital Mitford editors</orgName></respStmt><respStmt><orgName>Digital Mitford</orgName><resp> photo files: <idno>IMG_0200.jpg, IMG_0201.jpg, IMG_0202.jpg, IMG_0203.jpg, IMG_0204.jpg, IMG_0205.jpg, IMG_0206.jpg, IMG_0207.jpg, IMG_0208.jpg, IMG_0209.jpg, IMG_0210.jpg, IMG_0211.jpg</idno></resp></respStmt></editionStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority><pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace><date>2013</date><availability><p>Reproduced by courtesy of the <orgName ref="#ReadingCL">Reading Central Library</orgName>.</p><licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                  License</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Mitford Letters: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><repository ref="#ReadingCL">Reading Central Library</repository><collection>The letters of Mary Russell Mitford, vol. 4, 1819-1823</collection><idno>qB/TU/MIT Vol. 4 Horizon No.: 1361550 ff. 357</idno></msIdentifier><head>Letter from Mary Russell Mitford to Sir William Elford, <date when="1819-01-09">1819 January 9</date>.</head><physDesc><objectDesc><supportDesc><support><p>One and one-half sheets of folio <material>paper</material>, six surfaces photographed.</p><p>Address leaf bearing black circular mileage stamp, partially illegible, reading <stamp><lb/><placeName>READING</placeName><lb/></stamp>.</p></support><condition><p>Half sheet (pages five and six) torn on right edge where wax seal was removed.</p></condition></supportDesc></objectDesc><sealDesc><p>Black wax seal, remnants of black wax adhered elsewhere on page six.</p></sealDesc></physDesc></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><handNotes><handNote corresp="#rc" medium="red_crayon"> Red crayon or thick red pencil. Probably a different hand from Mitford's that marks many of her letters, sometimes drawing diagonal lines across pages, and sometimes writing words overtop and perpendicularly across Mitford's writing. On this letter, a red line is drawn from top left to bottom right of each of the leaves. On leaf six (the address leaf), two red lines are drawn from top left to bottom right over each of two text blocks.</handNote><handNote corresp="#pencil" medium="pencil"> Someone, apparently other than Mitford, perhaps cataloging letters and describing them, who left grey pencil marks and numbered her letters now in the Reading Central Library's collection. This letter is numbered "1" in the top left of the first leaf.
           </handNote></handNotes></profileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><p>Mitford’s spelling and punctuation are retained, except where a word is split at the end of a line and the beginning of the next in the manuscript. Where Mitford’s spelling and hyphenation of words deviates from the standard, in order to facilitate searching we are using the TEI elements “choice," “sic," and “reg" to encode both Mitford’s spelling and the regular international standard of Oxford English spelling, following the first listed spelling in the Oxford English Dictionary. The long s and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="letter"><opener><dateline><name type="place" ref="#Bertram_house">Bertram House</name><date when="1819-01-09">Jan<hi rend="superscript">y</hi> 9<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1819</date>.
               </dateline></opener><p>I don't remember that I promised in my last not to write till I heard from you, my dear Friend. So for once I may indulge my scribbling inclination without incurring the risk of being laughed at--no not laughed--<emph rend="underline">smiled</emph> at by you as <quote>"infirm of purpose"</quote>.<note resp="#lmw">Shakespeare's <title ref="#Macbeth_play">Macbeth</title>, II.ii</note>--<quote>"A very woman"</quote><note resp="#lmw">The title of a <title ref="#VeryWoman_play">1655 play by Massinger and Fletcher</title>. Also a line from Beaumont and Fletcher's <title ref="#WomanHater_play">A Woman Hater</title>:  "Thou art a filthy impudent whore; a woman, a very woman" (2.1.46).</note> &amp; so forth. Besides next week is <rs type="event">Sessions</rs> week &amp; Members will be "as plentiful as blackberries" <note resp="#lmw">Falstaff from <title ref="#HenryIVpt1_play">Henry IV, part one</title>: "If reasons were as plentiful as blackberries, I would give no man a reason upon compulsion, I." (II.iv).</note>--And then considering my doleful prognostications you will like to know that I have outlived the Ball--So I must write.  <choice><sic>Its</sic><reg resp="#lmw">It's</reg></choice>a thing of necessity. Yes I am living &amp; <quote>lifelich</quote>--as <persName ref="#Chaucer">Chaucer</persName> says<note resp="#lmw">"The letter sleeth, the spirit yeveth lifelich understandyng." From <persName ref="#Chaucer">Chaucer</persName>'s <title ref="#TestofLove">The Testament of Love</title>. Mitford may have read this text in <title ref="#WorksEngPoets_1810">The Works of the English Poets, with prefaces, biographical and critical, from Chaucer to Cowpwer (1810)</title>. Volume 1 of 21 features Chaucer.</note>--And that I did survive that dreaded night I owe principally to that charming thing a Dandy. Don't you like Dandies--the beautiful race? I am sure you must--But such a Dandy as our Dandy<note resp="#lmw">In Mitford's 1819 January 10 letter to Mary Webb, she identies her "Dandy" as Mr. Crowther.</note> few have been fortunate enough to see. In general they are on a small scale--slim whipper snapper youths fresh from College--or new mounted on a Dragoon's saddle--Dainty Lighthorsemen--or trim schoolboys--Ours is of a Patagonian breed--6 feet &amp; upwards without his shoes, &amp; broad in proportion--Unless you have seen a wasp in a Solar Microscope you have never seen any thing like him--Perhaps a <placeName ref="#Brobdingnag">Brobdingnagian</placeName> Hourglass <note resp="#ncl">Reference to <placeName ref="#Brobdingnag">Brobdingnag</placeName>, fictional land of giants in <title ref="#GulliversTr_JS">Swift's Gulliver's Travels</title>.</note> might be more like him still--only I don't think the hourglass would be small enough in the waist. Great as my admiration has always been for the mechanical <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/>forces</del><add place="above">inventions</add> of this age, I know no thing that has ever given me so high an idea of the power of machinery--not the <placeName ref="#Portsmouth_Blockhouses">Portsmouth Blockhouses</placeName>, or the <placeName ref="#Mint_new">new Mint</placeName>--as that perfection of mechanism--by which those ribs are endued in those stays. I think one or two must have been <pb n="2"/> broken to render such <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="2" unit="chars"/><unclear/></del>compression possible. But it is improper to dwell so exclusively on the <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/>breast</del><add place="above">stays</add> when every part <metamark rend="caret" place="below" function="insertion"/><add place="above">of the thing</add> was equally perfect.  <choice><sic>Trowsers</sic><reg resp="#lmw">Trousers</reg></choice>, Coat, neckcloth--Shirt Collar--head inside &amp; out--All were <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/>alike</del> in <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="chars"/>&amp;</del> exact keeping. Every look every word, every attitude belonged to those inimitable stays. Sweet Dandy! I have seen nothing like him since <persName ref="#Liston_John">Liston</persName> in <persName ref="#Grizzle_Lord">Lord Grizzel</persName><note resp="#lmw"><persName ref="#Liston_John">John Liston</persName> played <persName ref="#Grizzle_Lord">Lord Grizzle</persName> in the pantomime <title ref="#TomThumb_OHaraAdpt">Tom Thumb</title> at the <placeName ref="#Haymarket_Theatre">Haymarket</placeName> in <date when="1810">1810</date>. <persName ref="#Lamb_Chas">Lamb</persName> and <persName ref="#Hazlitt_Wm">Hazlitt</persName> mention <persName ref="#Liston_John">Liston</persName> in this role. More usually spelled Grizzle. In <persName ref="#Lamb_Chas">Charles Lamb</persName>'s essay, "The New Style of Acting," he writes:  "For a piece of pure drollery, Liston's Lord Grizzle has not competitor." <persName ref="#Hazlitt_Wm">Hazlitt</persName> also mentions <persName ref="#Liston_John">Liston</persName> in this role in <title ref="#LecComic_WHaz">Lectures on the English Comic Writers</title>.</note>--He kept me awake &amp; alive the whole evening. I don't think I ever laughed so much in my life--and all this laughter I owe to that exquisite person. Dancing or sitting still he was my "Cynosure"--I followed him with my eyes <note resp="#lmw">A cliche by Mitford's time, the phrase refers to <persName ref="#Milton">Milton</persName>'s <title ref="#Lallegro">L'Allegro</title> (1632): "the cynosure of neighb'ring eyes."</note>as a schoolboy follows the vagaries of <del rend="line"><gap quantity="2" unit="word"/>a new</del><add place="above">his</add> top--or the rolling of <del rend="line"><gap quantity="1" unit="chars"/>a</del><add place="above">his</add> hoop--Much &amp; generally as he was admired I don't think he made so strong an impression on anyone as on me--He is even indebted to me for the distinguished attention of a great wit, who was attacking a friend of mine, &amp; whose shafts I was lucky enough to direct to that impenetrable Target of Dandyism--He owed me for at least twenty good things said by the aforementioned wit--&amp; for twenty other good things more valuable still as being spoken by those who never uttered a good thing before in their lives--All this he owes me--&amp; is like to owe me still--for I am sorry to say my Dandy is an ungrateful Dandy--Our admiration was by no means mutual--"He had an idea" he said (a very bold assertion by the bye)--<said>"He had an idea that I was Blueish"</said>--So he scorned away <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="3" unit="word"/></del><add place="above">upon being threatened</add><del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/></del><add place="above">with</add> an introduction, just as my dog <persName ref="#Mossy_pet">Mossy</persName> (begging <persName ref="#Mossy_pet">Mossy</persName>'s pardon for the comparison) whisks off at the first whiff of our dog-hating Cook. Well peace be to him--poor swain--&amp; better fortune--for the poor Dandy is rather unlucky. He fell into the <placeName ref="#Thames">Thames</placeName> last summer on a water party &amp; got wet through his stays--&amp; this Autumn having affronted a young <pb n="3"/> lady &amp; being knocked down by her brother a lad not 19 he had the misfortune to fall flat on his back &amp; was forced to lie till some one came to pick him up being too strait laced to help himself. How I should have enjoyed the sight! Should not you? Oh if he had lain till I had helped him! </p><metamark rend="jerk"/><p>Now for an enormous jerk.</p><metamark rend="jerk"/><p>two jerks one is not enough to express the immense distance between a Dandy &amp; a clever woman!</p><metamark rend="jerk"/><p>I see that poor <persName ref="#Brunton_Mary">Mrs. Brunton</persName> is dead--The Authoress you know of <title ref="#Self_Control">Self Control</title> &amp; <title ref="#Discipline">Discipline</title> &amp; I believe some other book. Did I ever talk to you about her? If I did it was probably under the name of <rs type="person" ref="#Brunton_Mary">Mrs. Discipline</rs>--the name by which <persName ref="#Rowden_Fr">Mrs. Rowden</persName><note resp="#lmw">In The Queens of Society by Grace and Philip Wharton, the authors note that, while unmarried, <persName ref="#Rowden_Fr">Frances Rowden</persName> "styled herself Mrs. Rowden" (1860:  148).</note>used to call her. You are not likely to have admired her books which always seemed to me to have almost all the faults which very clever books could have--preachy <metamark rend="caret" place="below" function="insertion"/><add place="above">&amp;</add> prosy--false to character, to nature &amp; to passion--and yet with occasional powerful flashes of sense &amp; talent. I liked the lady much better than her works. She was exceedingly robust in mind &amp; person--perhaps even coarse in both respects--large boned, dark complexioned,<del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="chars"/></del> red complexioned rather,<del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="chars"/>&amp;</del> of loud speech &amp; abrupt manner. But there was in all she said some point &amp; much strength--much <emph rend="underline">body</emph>she seemed too perfectly frank, kindly, &amp; unaffected,--&amp; her very awkwardness had sometimes a grace from its genuineness (Have I  <choice><sic>spelt</sic><reg resp="#lmw">spelled</reg></choice>that hard word right?) its genuineness its ease &amp; its power. Now that she is dead, poor thing, I wish I had cultivated her acquaintance more earnestly--I met her once or twice at the house of some very clever people in <placeName ref="#Sloane_St">Sloane Street</placeName> where <persName ref="#Rowden_Fr">Mrs. Rowden</persName> was intimate--but I did not like <persName>her husband</persName> who was exceedingly priggish &amp; parsonic--that was one reason <pb n="4"/> &amp; vanity (perhaps at the time I might call it modesty) was another--She was always  civil but it was perfectly clear that she did not care a farthing for me--Besides I never could get over those sermonizing books.</p><metamark rend="jerk"/><p>Have you read <persName ref="#Fearon_HB">Mr. Fearon</persName>'s <title ref="#Sketches_of_America">book</title> on <placeName ref="#USA">America</placeName>? I have just finished it with the greatest amusement. I don't know any thing more agreeable than to have one's preconceived notions of a place or people confirmed by a good clever authority--a matter of fact authority--who brings you in a tangible shape good reasons for old prejudices. This is the pleasure <persName ref="#Fearon_HB">Mr. Fearon</persName> has given me. I always detested <placeName ref="#USA">America</placeName> &amp; the <orgName ref="#Americans">Americans</orgName> (all except <persName ref="#Washington_Geo">Washington</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#Franklin_Ben">Franklin</persName>) without very well knowing why--except that in that fair &amp; fresh &amp; beautiful world--<del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="chars"/></del>with every thing to inspire &amp; incite them to excellence in Art &amp; in Nature--they had done nothing, &amp; they were Nothing. <persName ref="#Fearon_HB">Mr. Fearon</persName> has now added positive to these negative proofs, &amp; has fairly set them forth as the most boasting vainglorious, ignorant trumpery cold hearted people that ever crept on the face of the earth. His book is invaluable as an antidote to the delicious poison of <persName ref="#Birkbeck_M">Mr. Birkbeck</persName>'s beautifully written works--an antidote the more powerful as coming from a friend to Liberty &amp; an admirer of the Republican form of government.</p><metamark rend="jerk"/><p>I have just had a very pretty little present <title ref="#Lit_Pocket_Bk">The Literary Pocket Book.</title> Have you seen one of them <del rend="crossout">my dear <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir William</persName></del>? They are edited I believe by <persName ref="#Hunt">Leigh Hunt</persName> certainly the greater part is written by him &amp; exceedingly well written. I have seen nothing of the sort so well executed. First of all there is a Naturalist's Calendar very beautifully written--indeed those not quite extensive enough for the title <pb n="5"/> It should rather have been called the Florist's Calendar--&amp; even then it would seem a little suburbian--rather <placeName ref="#Hampstead">Hampstead Heath</placeName>ish--but very pretty nevertheless--Then in the common pocket book part--the months &amp; weeks &amp; days there are occasional notices of birth days of great men--<persName ref="#Bacon">Bacon</persName><persName ref="#Shakespeare">Shakespeare</persName> &amp; so forth, which come upon one very pleasantly--Then lists of Artists Musicians Actors &amp; Authors (only think of their having left me out! That Authorial list is very incomplete indeed! Not one word about me! And my own friends too! Ah they have no "idea that I am blueish" to borrow my friend the Dandy's phrase--He would have stuck me at the head of the list) well these catalogues notwithstanding this great omission are very gratifying--&amp; then there is Poetry--not quite so good as I expected from <persName ref="#Hunt">Mr. Hunt</persName>, <persName ref="#Keats">Mr. Keats</persName>, &amp;c but still much better than ever adorned a pocket book before--<gap reason="torn" quantity="1" unit="word"/><unclear/><supplied resp="lmw">good</supplied> enough to stare &amp; wonder how it came there. If you wa<gap reason="torn" quantity="2" unit="chars"/><unclear/><supplied resp="lmw">nt</supplied> such a book I would recommend it to you.--And now my <gap reason="torn" quantity="1" unit="word"/><unclear/><supplied resp="lmw">very</supplied>dear Friend good bye! I shall finish before <date when="1819-01-12">Tuesday</date>.</p><p><date when="1819-01-11">Monday</date> Morning. I have just finished <title ref="#NightmareAbbey">Nightmare Abbey</title>--Have you met with it? By far the best of <persName ref="#Peacock_TL">Mr. Peacock</persName>'s works--worth all his prose &amp; all his poetry <title ref="#Rhododaphne">Rhododaphne</title> &amp; <title ref="#Melincourt">Melincourt</title> inclusive. There never was a more cheerful &amp; amiable piece of persiflage--full of laughing raillerie &amp; smiling philosophy--This <title ref="#NightmareAbbey">Nightmare Abbey</title> is really the most sunshiny book I have met with for many a day in spite of its gloomy title--It is a very clever attack <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="2" unit="chars"/></del> on mystical metaphysics &amp; misanthropical poetry (Deuce take the book for putting me to hard words.) And knocks them completely down in the person of my poor dear friend <persName ref="#Coleridge_ST">Mr. Coleridge</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#Byron">Lord Byron</persName>--knocks them down (as his unruly subjects did poor <persName ref="#Sancho_Panza">Sancho</persName> in the <placeName ref="#Island_Barataria">Island of Barataria</placeName>&amp; then dances upon them--Nothing was ever better managed than the way in which <persName ref="#Peacock_TL">Mr. <pb n="6"/>Peacock</persName> continues to put divers stanzas of <title ref="#ChildeHaroldsPil">Childe Harolde</title> done into prose into the mouth of <persName ref="#Cypress_Mr">Mr. Cypress</persName>--the <persName ref="#Byron">Lord Byron</persName> of the story. The book has another great merit too. It is short.</p><metamark rend="jerk"/><p>After great search we have been lucky enough to obtain an actual &amp; undoubted <rs type="person" ref="#whitekitten_WEpet">son</rs> of my White cat <persName ref="#Selim_pet">Selim</persName>, nearly half grown <metamark rend="caret" place="below" function="insertion"/><add place="above">&amp; quite White</add>--but I am sorry to say rather defective in two material points--being unluckily neither deaf nor two eyed--misfortunes which he owes to his vulgar English Mama. I shall keep him for you very carefully &amp; take all the care that I can that my beautiful puppy <persName ref="#Miranda_pet">Miranda</persName> does not kill him, till you tell me what to do with him. Do come &amp; fetch him, my dear Friend, there is no way so safe.--</p><closer>Adieu--<persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#Russell_M">Mama</persName> join in kindest regards &amp; good wishes, &amp; I am always most affectionately <choice><sic>your's</sic><reg resp="#lmw">yours</reg></choice><lb/><persName ref="#MRM">M.R. Mitford.</persName><lb/></closer><closer><address><addrLine><placeName ref="#Reading_city">Reading</placeName><date when="1819-01-09"/>January ninth</addrLine><addrLine>1819</addrLine><addrLine><persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir W<hi rend="superscript">m</hi>Elford</persName> Bar<hi rend="superscript"/>t.</addrLine><addrLine><placeName ref="#Bickham_village">Bickham</placeName></addrLine><addrLine><placeName ref="#Plymouth_city">Plymouth</placeName></addrLine><addrLine><persName ref="#Palmer_CF">CFPalmer</persName></addrLine></address></closer></div></body></text></TEI>