<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><!--<?xml-model href="http://ebeshero.github.io/MRMValidate.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>--><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title xml:id="MRM1751">Letter to <persName ref="#Russell_M">Mrs. Mitford</persName>, <date when="1819-12-10">1819 December 10</date></title><author ref="#MRM">Mary Russell Mitford</author><editor ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</editor><sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford Project</orgName></sponsor><sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor><principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal><respStmt><resp>Transcription and coding by</resp><persName ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Proofing and corrections by</resp><persName ref="#mco">Molly C. O'Donnell</persName></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>First digital edition in TEI, date: <date when="2015-04-26">26 April 2015</date>. P5.</edition><respStmt><resp>Edition made with help from photos taken by</resp><orgName>Digital Mitford editors</orgName></respStmt><respStmt><orgName>Digital Mitford</orgName><resp> photo files: <idno>P1020340.jpg, P1020341.jpg, P1020342.jpg</idno></resp></respStmt></editionStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority><pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace><date>2013</date><availability><p>Reproduced by courtesy of the <orgName ref="#ReadingCL">Reading Central Library</orgName>.</p><licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                  License</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Mitford Letters: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><repository ref="#ReadingCL">Reading Central Library</repository><collection>The letters of Mary Russell Mitford, vol. 4, 1819-1823</collection><idno>qB/TU/MIT Vol. 4 Horizon No.: 1361550 ff.392</idno></msIdentifier><head>Letter from Mary Russell Mitford to <persName ref="#Russell_M">Mrs. Mitford</persName>, <date when="1819-12-10">1819 December 10</date>.</head><physDesc><objectDesc><supportDesc> <!-- Physical description of the letter goes here: paper size and condition, seal, postmarks, etc. --><support/><condition/></supportDesc></objectDesc></physDesc></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><handNotes><handNote corresp="#rc" medium="red_crayon"> Red crayon or thick red pencil. Probably a different hand from Mitford's that marks many of her letters, sometimes drawing diagonal lines across pages, and sometimes writing words overtop and perpendicularly across Mitford's writing. <!-- Describe red crayoning on this letter here. --></handNote><handNote corresp="#pencil" medium="pencil"> Someone, apparently other than Mitford, perhaps cataloging letters and describing them, who left grey pencil marks and numbered her letters now in the Reading Central Library's collection. This letter is numbered "22" in the top left of the first leaf, underneath the opening line, "To Mrs. Mitford. Rt Rev. J. Woodburn Close Winchester."
           </handNote></handNotes></profileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><p>Mitford’s spelling and punctuation are retained, except where a word is split at the end of a line and the beginning of the next in the manuscript. Where Mitford’s spelling and hyphenation of words deviates from the standard, in order to facilitate searching we are using the TEI elements “choice," “sic," and “reg" to encode both Mitford’s spelling and the regular international standard of Oxford English spelling, following the first listed spelling in the Oxford English Dictionary. The long s and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p> <!-- Do not change any of this text. --></editorialDecl></encodingDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="letter"><opener><add hand="#pencil">11</add><dateline><name type="place" ref="#Bertram_house">Bertram House</name><date when="1819-12-10">December 10<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></date>. 
               </dateline><salute>To <persName ref="#Russell_M">Mrs. Mitford</persName></salute></opener><p>I wonder whether <persName ref="#Woodburn_Mr">Mr. Woodburn</persName> has taken his departure this snowy morning, my own dear <persName ref="#Russell_M">Granny</persName>! If so, he will have a sad journey--Of that however I am not so much afraid as that he will seize the weather as a good excuse.--I hope &amp; trust that you will not think of coming home in the snow out of complaisance to <date>my birthday</date>--Much as we long to have you back again you must not risk catching cold in the transportation.--I hope you find your cloth gown comfortable &amp; that you have worn my shawl constantly--Have you done a frill? Does it look pretty? You must want something of the sort to wear by this time I think--though I suppose they wash in <placeName ref="#Winchester_city">Winchester</placeName> though they do not keep netting needles--The only thing about which <persName ref="#Hill_Lucy">Lucy</persName> is troubled is your nightcap which she says can't be washed because you have no change--I dare say however you borrowed one of <persName ref="#Woodburn_Mrs">Mrs. Woodburn</persName>.--I have a letter from <persName>Fyshe</persName> to day to whom, in enclosing a letter to forward to <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir William</persName><date>last Sunday</date>, I had mentioned your not having received that I sent to you--<persName>Fyshe</persName>'s letter is not particularly civil I think--though perhaps the man only means to be funny &amp; does not know how--It is not every body that can combine playfulness with goodbreeding.--At all events the delay was his as he confesses.--So I shall never trust any Despatch that requires dispatch to his punctuality--He seems to have taken a lesson in writing from his friend <persName ref="#Parr_Dr">Dr. Parr</persName>--half his words one is forced to guess at--he literally "writes as ill as a Member of Parliament."--I have had a superb present from <persName ref="#Valpy_John">Mr. John Valpy</persName>--a fine thick grand quarto volume--printed upon wire wove paper &amp; hotpressed <pb n="1"/>the book has but one fault--the small fault of being totally unreadable. It is an English Poem by a <persName>German Gentleman</persName> called <title>Time or Light &amp; Shade</title>--And seems in all points a very fit companion to a certain work called <title>Cyllenius</title>--I intend to make <persName ref="#Dickinson_Charles">Mr. Dickinson</persName> read it &amp; expect to be exceedingly amused by his strictures--He'll pull it to pieces just as muh as if <title>Cyllenius</title> was not made of such stuff--"A fellow feeling makes us wondrous kind"--may be a true axiom in some cases but not in poetry.--You will be glad to hear that <persName>Kate Valpy</persName> is better--the Doctor was going to dine at the <unclear/> which was held at Jacobs--&amp; Jacob pressed Drum very much to dine with them--but Drum is inexpressibly good he had never dined in Reading except the once we dined togehter at Dr. Valpy's &amp; indeed I think goes in a morning only to get me books.  You have no notion how well we get on. --I have got two new numbers of <title ref="#Blackwoods">Blackwood</title>.--The rest of the <unclear>Tent</unclear> is capital.--<persName ref="#Parr_Dr">Dr. Parr</persName> courses there.--&amp; Prince Leopold--they make famous use of the Doctor.--That is famous Inn--There certainly is an originality &amp; audacity of impudence about Messrs Lockhart and Wilson. more musing than anything that can be imagined. I shall keep there two numbers for you to read.--Jacob was so much better that he did not go to Mr. Arnott.--Have a great number of Bobbies coming every day to be fed, which is a great delight poor little lamsb I don't know what they would do without by bounty--unless something in your Sunday's letter--(for you must write Sunday my dear Granny) should require it I shall not write again--Good bye my own dear darling--Kind regards to dear Mrs. Woodburn.  </p><closer>Ever most fondly your own
               <lb/>M. R&gt; Mitford</closer><postscript><p>Lucy and Molly desire their duty.</p></postscript></div></body><back><div><!--
          <persName ref="#Woodburn_Mr">Mr. Woodburn</persName>  "Rt. Rev. J. Woodburn Close Winchester"
          <persName ref="#Woodburn_Mrs">Mrs. Woodburn</persName>
          <persName ref="#Parr_Dr">Dr. Parr</persName>--></div></back></text></TEI>