<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><!--<?xml-model href="http://ebeshero.github.io/MRMValidate.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>--><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title xml:id="MRM1762">Letter to Sir William Elford, 24 August 1820</title><author>Mary Russell Mitford</author><editor>Rebecca Nesvet</editor><sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford
               Project</orgName></sponsor><sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor><principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal><respStmt><resp>Transcription and coding by</resp><persName ref="#rnes">Rebecca Nesvet</persName><persName ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</persName>
               <!-- LMW:  proofed against ms. and completed transcription 2015 10-04. Needs revised header. --></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Proofing and corrections by</resp><persName ref="#ebb">Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName><persName ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</persName>
               <!--ebb8: 29 May 2014: Transcription and header needs to be checked. Prosop is good. --></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>This is optional, used to describe this edition, and "should contain phrases
               describing the edition or version: First digital edition in TEI, date: 2 June 2013.
               P5.</edition><respStmt><resp>We can include a respStmt here.</resp><persName>Who?</persName></respStmt></editionStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority><pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace><date>2013</date><availability><licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                  License</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Mitford Letters: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title></seriesStmt><notesStmt><note>Any special notes on this text? (optional)</note><note>You can have multiple notes here.</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><repository ref="#ReadingCL">Reading Central Library</repository><collection>The letters of Mary Russell Mitford, vol. 4, 1819-1823</collection>
                  <!-- Change to reflect correct ms. collection. --><idno>qB/TU/MIT Vol. 4 Horizon No.: 1361550 ff. 411</idno></msIdentifier><head>Letter from Mary Russell Mitford to Sir William Elford <date when="1820-08-24">24 August 1820</date>.</head></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><p>Describes our editorial practice.</p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="letter"><opener><dateline><name type="place" ref="#ThreeMileCross">Three Mile Cross</name><date when="1820-08-24">August 24<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>, 1820.</date></dateline><salute>To <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir William Elford</persName></salute></opener><p>As <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</persName> is going to this Club dinner which
               you my dear Friend wish so devoutly at the ---<note resp="#rnes #lmw">Mitford
                  anonymizes the place. She likely means "the devil."</note> I take the opportunity
               of getting a frank to reply to your kind &amp; delightful &amp; most welcome
               letter.--What you say of <persName ref="#Palmer_Mad">Lady Madelina</persName> is
               charming--she must be a most fascinating woman--&amp; something better than a
               fascinating woman to have excited such admiration in you. I hope I shall see her. I
               went into <placeName ref="#Reading_city">Reading</placeName> yesterday to call on her
               if she were arrived--but she was not. I saw <persName ref="#Palmer_CF">Mr.
                  Palmer</persName> &amp; pleased him very much (for he is exceedingly fond &amp;
               proud of her) by telling him something of what you said. She came however at night, I
               understand from some friends who have been here today--but today I myself was out
               coursing according to an engagement of a fortnight's standing. Very likely she will
               call tomorrow, if not I will wait on her <date>Saturday</date>. You will comprehend,
               my dear Friend, that your opinion has excited this desire of an honour which to
               confess the truth I have hitherto rather shunned--I don't know why--but in spite of
               my age &amp; my rotundity &amp; rubincundity which seem to <del rend="squiggles" unit="word" n="3"/><add place="above">take away my</add>right to such feelings, I
               am by fits &amp; starts desperately shy--I have a particular aversion to seeing
               people who desire to see one as they would desire to see <persName ref="#Punch">Punch</persName>, which I rather understood to be the case with the party in
               question. Another thing was, that her particular friend &amp; favourite in this
               neighborhood is a person whom I do not like. A single woman of eight &amp; thirty
               with manners too light, too bold too young for eighteen--rouge on her cheeks and a
               leer in her eyes--a rattle without an idea--full of the outward and visible signs of
               cheerfulness, but with none of the inward and spiritual grace<pb n="2"/>--a person
               whose hoity-toityness is depressing beyond beyond conception--this was the favorite
               of the chosen, of one whose station &amp; talents gave her the power to <choice><sic>chuse</sic><reg>choose</reg></choice>--And this it was that gave me the impression which you must have seen &amp;
               which you have so completely counteracted. But I have not you yourself something
               judged of people by their associates? Don't you like to meet with good company in the
               hearts of your friends, as well as at their tables? Now that we shall have you to
               talk about we shall get on excellently--&amp; except that she will be furiously
               disappointed, &amp; that I shall be shy &amp; ashamed when ever I think of my
               letters--those letters which are first like so many bottles of ginger beer, bouncing
               &amp; frothy &amp; flying in every body's face--with these trifling drawbacks we
               shall admire one another as much as is proper &amp; possible. N. B. I hope &amp;
               trust my dear friend that friend that you will have the discretion to keep this
               paragraph to yourself--at least not to let any one see it <del rend="squiggles" unit="word" n="1">by</del>through whom it can by any chance work round to her
               Ladyship's ears.<metamark rend="#jerk"/></p><p><placeName ref="#Reading_city">Reading</placeName>--&amp; which is worse <placeName ref="#ThreeMileCross">Three Mile Cross</placeName> is <persName ref="#Queen_Caroline">Queen</persName>-mad.--Our opinions I believe are exactly
               alike--The letter was a firebrand tossed by a hand as reckless as it is mischievous.
               I have no patience with the meetings, &amp; Addresses &amp; the intolerable quantity
               of nonsense that is talked on the occasion. She may or she may not be guilty to the
               extent imputed--she may or she may not be able to prove the crime--but no one can
               think her innocent--It is impossible. No modest woman could endure to hear that which
               she hears day by day--The courage she displays is the hard impudence of guilt--not
               the firmness of virtue.--Besides, my dear <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir
                  William</persName>, women do not give up reputation except for the gratification
               of passion.--She cannot be innocent. I say this without having read a syllable of the
               trial--for having perfectly <del rend="squiggles" unit="word" n="3"/><add place="above">made up my mind</add><pb n="3"/>I do not wish to litter my brains
               with a quantity of trash just to settle whether an immodest woman be a little more or
               less bad than I had imagined. You will laugh at my earnestness, but really I am
               provoked at the quantity of <emph rend="underline"><persName ref="#Queen_Caroline">Queen</persName>ery</emph><note resp="lmw">Here, in a construction akin to
                  "Whiggery," "Queenery" is used to denote followers of the Queen's party.</note>
               that is going on here <add place="above">not in this house for <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</persName> and <persName ref="#Russell_M">Mama</persName> are very moderate but everywhere else</add>is going on
               here--There has been a meeting at <placeName ref="#Reading_city">Reading</placeName>,
               &amp; the address was signed by a thousand of the Inhabitants men and boys--&amp; I
               am sorry to say by some soldiers quartered there. Is this wise?--The hold she has on
               the soldier's affections is really alarming--we hear of it on all sides. God grant
               the trial were safely over! If it do pass by tranquilly, it will do some good by
               showing ministers that a standing army is a two edged sword.--You see I have not lost
               all my <orgName ref="#Whigs">Whig</orgName>Whiggery--though I am no <persName ref="#Queen_Caroline">Queen</persName>'s woman, I am indeed not a little disgusted
               at the part the opposition have taken in the question. Tell me what you think on the
               subject. For though I have said that our opinions were alike, I spoke only from my
                  <del rend="squiggles" unit="word" n="1"/><add place="above">my</add>preconceived
               ideas of your mode of thinking.--I can generally guess what you will say on most
               points. On <rs type="title" corresp="#ChrstEJrslm_Haydon"><persName ref="#Haydon">Haydon</persName>'s Picture</rs> for instance I foresaw that you did not like
               the disjointed Head. After all, I myself only like it conditionally--think it answers
               to the Artist's own design of perfect abstraction--thoughts turned inward &amp;
               upward--a mind absorbed in the contemplation of its own divine task of immeasurable
               love--loving the present in the glorious future--This was his intention &amp; this he
               has accomplished. But I do not think that this was the best expression he would have
               given--&amp; the disproportion was visible even to my unlearned eyes, though I could
               not have imagined it to be so monstrous. Moreover no authority can reconcile me to
               the glory--I do not believe that our Saviour was surrounded by any other light than
               the <del rend="squiggles" unit="chars" n="2"/>moral effulgence<pb n="4"/> of his
               divine virtues, &amp; why should that which did not exist in nature be represented in
               an imitation of nature? Your praise of the rest of the <title corresp="#ChrstEJrslm_Haydon">Picture</title> is a most valuable sanction to my ardent
               admiration. I am afraid he will not dispose of it as he had hoped--the subscription
               with the limitation to 10 guineas has entirely failed &amp; he now means to throw it
               open without limitation--but as those who would have given their 50d. have already
               given their 10£. I do not foresee much of an advantage from this change. His best
               chance is in its being purchased by some rich patron of Art--though the largeness of
               the price &amp; of the picture are both against him. Nevertheless he is going on ding
               dong with a picture quite as large--&amp; this intensity of purpose &amp; and of
               will--this absolute devotion to one great end is what I admire in him.--I like his
               simplicity too, his kindheartedness, his perfect singleness of mind. He is something
               of a <q>"Gunpowder Percy"</q><note resp="#lmw">A reference to Shakespeare's <title ref="#HenryIVpt1_play">Henry IV part I, act five, scene four</title>. <persName ref="#Falstaff_WS">Falstaff</persName>: "Zounds, I am afraid of this gunpowder
                  Percy, though he be dead."</note>to be sure, &amp; there is a stern brightness in
               his insufferable eyes which is exceedingly startling &amp; disagreeable--nevertheless
               little as I have seen of him--I do like him very much. Next to <persName ref="#Napoleon">Napoleon</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#Chantrey_F">Chantrey</persName>&amp; <persName ref="#Wordsworth_Wm">Wordsworth</persName>. I
               think him the greatest man of the Age--but <persName ref="#Napoleon">Napoleon</persName> is <emph rend="underline">the</emph> man--there is no putting
               any body within a million of miles of the Exile of St. Helena. <persName ref="#James_Miss">Miss James</persName> brought me a little Cast of him from
                  <placeName ref="#Birmingham_city">Birmingham</placeName> which cost sixpence &amp;
               which is really the most beautiful thing ever seen. He is looking down upon me at
               this moment with the most gracious benignity. My <persName>little dog</persName> is,
               as dogs &amp; children always are, a great physiognomist--moreover she is a very
               fastidious lady--won't go bear one person in a hundred--&amp; has generally speaking
               a singular aversion to busts &amp; pictures. <persName ref="#Russell_M">Mama</persName> put <persName ref="#Napoleon">Napoleon</persName> down to her
               expecting that she would as usual growl &amp; bark--when to our great astonishment
               she ran up to the last<pb n="5"/> put her paws on the shoulders &amp; kissed the
               beautiful <del rend="squiggles" unit="word" n="1">lips</del><add place="above">mouth</add> three times--She who never in her life kissed any but smiling lips
               &amp; lips that she loved--<persName ref="#Hill_Lucy">Lucy</persName>'s or mine.--We
               have lost poor dear <persName ref="#Hill_Lucy">Lucy</persName>--our faithful &amp;
               excellent servant. It is like losing a limb--I never saw or knew such perfect
               devotedness as she displayed--she was really absorbed in me--loved all whom I
               loved--was glad when I was glad &amp; sorry when I was sorry. Poor dear <persName ref="#Hill_Lucy">Lucy</persName>! She is married &amp; I have not even the
               consolation of liking the <rs type="person" ref="#Hill_Charles">bridegroom</rs>--He
               is a demure boy--too young--too grave--too fine--too <unclear/>. I know no harm of
               him &amp; the society of such an excellent &amp; affectionate creature must improve
               him--but still I cannot like him--&amp; I cannot like a woman of 30 marrying a lad of
               20. The poor dear face cried for a fortnight before the wedding, night &amp; day.
               &amp; I really believe if her successor had not arrived that she would even at the
               last have left her lover in the lurch. I have been to see her according to promise,
               &amp; she went out coursing with me. She lives in a very beautiful country Mortimer
               West End--&amp; <placeName ref="#Silchester">Silchester</placeName>--fine
               localities!--the next time you come &amp; see as you must go to see the old walls at
                  <placeName ref="#Silchester">Silchester</placeName> &amp; we will call upon
                  <persName ref="#Hill_Lucy">Lucy</persName>--&amp; is coursing be not quite out of
               season have a course. I should like you to see what a fine animation a brace of
               greyhouds after a hare gives to a Landscape.--Did you ever see one?--So you have
               actually altered that pretty landscape? Really I had not a notion of making a
               criticism when I remarked to you the effect of those sunny fields. I meant merely to
               admire the manner in which you had succeeded in the difficult attempt of painting a
               view from a hill--I have no doubt however but that a Common is equally beautiful--I
               have a passion for Commons--those pretty <del rend="squiggles" unit="word" n="1"/>
               irregular green patches with cottages round them &amp; dipping fronds glancing so
               brightly &amp; crossing foot <pb n="6"/> paths among the scattered trees seem to me
               the characteristics of English scenery--Ah! they are passing away! We shall soon see
               nothing but straight hedgerows &amp; gravelled lanes. I sigh over every inclosure
               bill--&amp; am always delighted when some glorious obstinate bumpkin of the true John
               Bull breed takes it into his head to quarrel with the Lord of the Manor &amp; oppose
               one--as is luckily the case in this Parish of <placeName ref="#Shinfield">Shinfield</placeName>.<metamark rend="jerk"/></p><p>I suppose we must talk about books a little must not we! Pray my dear friend have you
               heard of a novel called <title ref="#Warbeck_Wolfstein_MH">Warbeck of
                  Wolfstein</title>? It is written by <persName ref="#Holford_Marg_younger">Miss
                  Holford</persName> who seems to me a bolder woman than the <persName ref="#Queen_Caroline">Queen</persName>. The <persName ref="#Holford_Marg_younger">Miss Holford</persName> who wrote a very fine Poem called <title ref="#Wallace_MHpoem">Wallace</title>. Well this novel is a portrait or rather a
               hideous caricature of <persName ref="#Byron">Lord Byron</persName>, nobody can
               mistake it--&amp; yet God forbid it should be at all true. It is dedicated in terms
               of great affection &amp; familiarity to <persName ref="#Baillie_Joanna">Miss Joanna
                  Baillie</persName>--for which I am very sorry, since such a <del rend="squiggles" unit="word" n="1"/> sanction <del rend="squiggles" unit="word" n="1"/> will make
               every body suppose it a retaliation on <persName ref="#Byron_Annab">Lady
                  Byron</persName>'s part which should of all things have been avoided. But what can
                  <persName ref="#Holford_Marg_younger">Miss Holford</persName> expect but to be
                  <del rend="squiggles" unit="word" n="1"/> empaled in <persName ref="#Byron">Lord
                  B</persName>'s next Poem? By the bye I heard a curious anecdote of him yesterday
               from a very truth-telling person. A gentleman was with him on a visit to an old house
               in the country which had the reputation of being haunted--They had been telling ghost
               stories all the evening &amp; in the middle of the night he was awakened by <persName ref="#Byron">Lord B.</persName> with his hair on end &amp; his teeth
               chattering--who declared that his room was full of strange shapes &amp; sounds that
               he could not return to it, &amp; begged his man to allow him to sit by the side of
               his bed till day light. <add place="above">which he did</add> I have always thought
               he would end by being a Methodist.--Did I mention to you the second Volume of the
               American book which <pb n="7"/>is so incredibly good--the <title ref="#SketchBook_WI">Sketch Book</title>? It is a little sentimental--too sentimental certainly-=but
               the comic part is excellent--particularly the account of Little Britain. I should
               think the Americans must crow over <persName ref="#Irving_Wash">Mr. Washington <choice><sic>Irvine</sic><reg>Irving</reg></choice></persName> like a hen with one chick. (Do Hens crow? I suspect here is a
               little confusion of metaphor.)--<title ref="#WinterNts_ND">Winter
               nights</title>Winter nights by <persName ref="#Drake_Nathan">Dr.
                  Drake</persName> ought to be such a book as the <title ref="#SketchBook_WI">Sketch
                  Book</title>--is that when I read it--but it is altogether another thing being
               indeed the most daring and barefaced specimen of book making which I have met with
               even in this book making age. Only think of the mean impudence in transcribing pretty
               nearly all <persName ref="#Goldsmith">Goldsmith</persName>--half <persName ref="#Young_Ed">Young</persName>--three parts of <persName ref="#Collins_Wm">Collins</persName> &amp; a good <unclear>lump</unclear> of the <del rend="squiggles" unit="word" n="1"/><title ref="#Odyssey">Odyssey</title> under the pretence of pointing out three or
               four unknown, unheard of, authors who have no beauties to detect--&amp; so he
               compounds his book. Fine thievery--is it not? One forgave him &amp; indeed thanked
               him for making a book of scraps of <title ref="#Shakespeare_Times_nonfict">Shakespeare
                  &amp; his Times</title> because the books he stole from were both good &amp;
               scarce--but to filch from <persName ref="#Cowper">Cowper</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#Goldsmith">Goldsmith</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#Pope_Alex">Pope</persName> is past bearing.--I am now stuck fast in the heaviest book I ever
               plunged into. <persName ref="#Coxe_Wm">Coxe</persName>'s <title ref="#Life_DukeofMarl_WC">Life of the Duke of Marlborough</title>. Don't read it. It is molten lead. Six
               dreary endless volumes of military detail &amp; political intrigue--most prosingly
               written--I shall certainly give it up. <metamark rend="jerk"/></p><p>What an extraordinary thing it is that so many grown persons have had the whooping
               Cough this summer! <persName ref="#Russell_M">Mama </persName>feels much sympathy for
                  <persName ref="#Elford_J">Mr. Elford</persName> having been a sufferer <add place="above">years ago</add>in a similar way herself. <del rend="crossout" unit="word" n="10">who with the additional circumstance of being big with
                  child</del><del rend="squiggles" unit="word" n="2"/> --I should think it very easy to make a
               good <pb n="8"/>likeness of you--I hope it will be in the <placeName ref="#London_city">London </placeName>Exhibition next year. I shall like to see
               it.--Adieu my very dear Friend. Excuse this stupid letter--I have been walking all
               day &amp; my brains seem blown away by the fine keen <placeName ref="#Silchester">Silchester</placeName> air--notwithstanding which I <del rend="squiggles" unit="word" n="1"/><add place="above">may</add> say with <persName ref="#Anacreon">Anacreon</persName>'s Dove <q>"I have chattered like a Pie."</q> You will take
               this for two letters at least. Pray write soon.</p><closer>Kindest comp<choice><sic><hi rend="superscript">ts</hi></sic><reg>compliments</reg></choice> from all here--Ever my dear <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir
                  William</persName> most affectionately <choice><sic>your's</sic><reg resp="#lmw">yours</reg></choice><lb/><persName ref="#MRM">M.R.M.</persName></closer><postscript><p>I hope the parrot was found--or rather that he was enticed back--what a
                  tantalizing thing to have a <del rend="squiggles" unit="word" n="1"/><add place="above">pet</add>that hears &amp; answers &amp; will not come to the
                  voice of the charmer.--My dear Friend Adieu. Pray write soon.--<persName ref="#Palmer_Mad">Lady M.P.</persName> has not made her appearance.</p></postscript><closer><address><addrLine><lb/><placeName ref="#Reading_city">Reading</placeName><date when="1820-08-25">August twenty five 1820</date></addrLine><addrLine><lb/><persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">S<hi rend="supserscript">r</hi> W<hi rend="supserscript">m</hi> Elford Bar<hi rend="supserscript">t</hi></persName></addrLine><addrLine><lb/><placeName ref="#Bickham_village">Bickham</placeName></addrLine><addrLine><lb/><persName ref="#Monck_JB">J.B. Monck </persName><placeName ref="#Plymouth_city">Plymouth</placeName></addrLine></address></closer></div></body><back>
         <!-- added all new backlist to my compilation LMW 2015 10 04 -->
         <!--ebb8: Prosopography all up to date with site index. --></back></text></TEI>