<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><?xml-model href="http://ebeshero.github.io/MRMValidate.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title xml:id="MRM1768">Letter to <persName ref="#Haydon">B.R. Haydon</persName>, October 2,
               1820.</title><author ref="#MRM">Mary Russell Mitford</author><editor ref="#ebb">Eric S. Hood</editor><sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford Project </orgName></sponsor><sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg </sponsor><principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal><respStmt><resp>Transcription and coding by</resp><persName ref="#esh">Eric S. Hood</persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Proofing and corrections by</resp><persName ref="#rnes">Rebecca Nesvet</persName>  <!--2014-06-02--><persName ref="#ebb">Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName><!--ebb: 29 May 2014: Added Prosop to Site Index, but transcription and teiHeader needs to be checked.--><persName ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</persName><!-- 2015 10 04 --></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>First digital edition in TEI, date: June 2, 2014. P5.</edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority><pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace><availability><p>Reproduced by courtesy of the <placeName>Reading Central Library</placeName>.</p><licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                  License</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Mitford Letters: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><repository ref="#ReadingCL">Reading Central Library</repository><collection>The letters of Mary Russell Mitford, vol. 4, 1819-1823</collection><idno>qB/TU/MIT Vol. 4 Horizon No.: 1361550 ff. 420</idno></msIdentifier><head>Letter from Mary Russell Mitford to B. R. Haydon, <date when="1820-10-02">02 October 1820</date>. </head><physDesc><objectDesc><supportDesc><support><p>Folio sheet of <material>paper</material> folded in half to form four
                              quarto pages, with correspondence on 1-4 with address leaf also on page 4,
                              then folded in thirds twice more and sealed for posting.</p><p>Address leaf bearing the following postmarks: 1) black circular
                              mileage stamp <!-- Applied upon deposit of letter at local PO -->
                              reading <stamp>READING<lb/><unclear><gap quantity="1" unit="chars" reason="illegible"/></unclear></stamp>. 2)Red double circle Evening Duty stamp
                              <!-- Applied upon arrival in London --> reading <date when="1821-11-01"><stamp>B<lb/>1 OC 7<lb/>1820</stamp></date>. 3) Sepia-inked oval Delivery stamp
                              <!-- Applied upon transfer from Inland Mail to
                                 London's local Penny Post for delivery. -->
                              reading <stamp><time>10 o'Clock</time><lb/><date>* OC * 7 *</date><lb/><date>1820</date> F.N<hi rend="superscript">n </hi></stamp></p></support><condition><p/></condition></supportDesc></objectDesc><sealDesc><p>Red wax seal, only partially visible</p></sealDesc></physDesc></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><handNotes><handNote xml:id="rc" medium="red_crayon"> Red crayon or thick red pencil. Probably a
               different hand from Mitford's, drawing a diagonal line across pages 1-4.</handNote><handNote corresp="#pencil" medium="pencil">Someone cataloguing the letters has placed an X on page 1.</handNote></handNotes></profileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><p>Mitford’s spelling and punctuation are retained, except where a word is split at the
               end of a line and the beginning of the next in the manuscript. To facilitate
               searching, where Mitford’s spelling and hyphenation of words deviates from the standard, 
               we use the TEI elements “choice," “sic," and “reg" to encode both
               Mitford’s spelling and the regular international standard of Oxford English spelling,
               following the first listed spelling in the Oxford English Dictionary. The long s and
               ligatured forms are not encoded.</p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="letter"><opener><dateline><date when="1820-10-02">October 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> 1820.</date><name type="place">Three Mile Cross</name></dateline><salute>My dear Sir</salute></opener><p>
               Your most welcome parcel containing <persName ref="#Keats">Mr. Keats’s</persName> charming poems &amp; your own charming letter arrived here only yesterday. I hope before that time that you received a <supplied>post</supplied> from me <supplied>informing</supplied> you of the safe arrival of your dogs &amp; begging you to come and see them <supplied>soon</supplied>. I shall not send off this letter till you have answered our petition with a yes—for I will not anticipate the possibility of a refusal, but I must thank you immediately for the great pleasure I have derived from your packet. <persName ref="#Keats">Mr. Keats’s</persName> poetry is exquisite—so fresh &amp; <supplied resp="#rnes">racy</supplied> &amp; full of fine juices. If anything can make the <title ref="#QuarterlyRev_per">Quarterly Reviewer</title>s &amp; <title ref="#Blackwoods">Blackwood’s</title> people blush this volume will, but they have probably lost that sign of grace. The notice of the fate of <title ref="#Endymion">Endymion</title> in <supplied>the</supplied> advertisement was a fine rebuke. I hope <persName ref="#Keats">Mr. Keats</persName> is better. Is he in good hands? Has he any near female relation, sister, wife <supplied resp="#rnes">or</supplied> mother to take care of him? Don’t fancy that I under value the kindness of manly friendship but where there is kindness there should be a woman. Nursing &amp; taking care are the most precious of our privileges. —Now for your very able article on the Scottish novels. It was really a pity to waste such excellent writing on a letter. I wish you would take the affair in hand. <persName ref="#Hazlitt_Wm">Mr. Haslitt</persName>, delightful writer as he is, does not produce so much effect as you do, partly because he is by profession a “setter up &amp; puller down of kings”. We are accustomed to see him tossing great names into a topsy turvy confusion, &amp; partly that he has a trick of escaping occasionally from some serious and earnest 
               <pb n="2"/> criticism by a piece of sudden pleasantry which gives an air of Persiflage to all that he has said. He is the most delightful critic in the wor<supplied resp="#rnes">l</supplied>d-- puts all his <supplied>taste</supplied>, his wit, his deep thinking, his matchless acuteness into his subject, but he does not put his whole heart &amp; soul into it &amp; <supplied>you</supplied> do &amp; there is the difference. What charms me most in <persName ref="#Hazlitt_Wm">Mr. Haslitt</persName> is the beautiful candour which he bursts forth <supplied>sometimes</supplied> from his own prejudices—much as the <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/></del><supplied>charms</supplied> of <persName ref="#Johnson">Dr. Johnson</persName> in the <title>Comic Writers</title> &amp; the account of the <supplied>Reformation</supplied> in the <title>Age of Elizabeth</title>. I admire him so ardently that when I begin to talk of him I never know how to stop. I could talk on for an hour in a see saw of praise and blame as he himself does of <persName ref="#Beaumont_Fr">Beaumont</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#Fletcher_John">Fletcher</persName> &amp; some of his old favo<supplied resp="#rnes">u</supplied>rites. I remember his article in <title ref="#LondonMag">Baldwin’s Magazine</title>. It was excellent—only not quite so good as your letter. Certainly those novels are over-rated. One cannot help suspecting that the Scotchmen who compare them so gravely to our great Authors are better acquainted with the works of <persName ref="#Scott_Wal">Walter Scott</persName> than with those of <persName ref="#Milton">Milton</persName> or <persName ref="#Shakespeare">Shakespeare</persName>. You have exposed the absurdity of such comparisons admirably. One consequence of the exaggerated praise will be a violent reaction in public opinion. They will sink as much below their merit in the next generation as they have risen above it in this—like the <supplied>Dramatists</supplied> I have mentioned, <persName ref="#Beaumont_Fr">Beaumont</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#Fletcher_John">Fletcher</persName> who were at one time preferred to <persName ref="#Shakespeare">Shakespeare</persName> &amp; at another scarcely heard of, &amp; whom by the way much more than <persName ref="#Shakespeare">Shakespeare</persName><persName ref="#Scott_Wal">Walter Scott</persName> resembles. <persName ref="#Rebecca_Ivanhoe">Rebecca</persName> in <title ref="#Ivanhoe">Ivanhoe</title> is exactly one of <persName ref="#Fletcher_John">Fletcher's</persName> women—another <persName ref="#Aspatia">Aspatia</persName> or <persName ref="#Bellario"><supplied>Bellario</supplied></persName>. Besides the faults you have pointed out a very great one in my mind is the tendency of these books to foster a melodramatic has he a want of strong excitement which is the besetting sin 
               <pb n="3"/> of the age—a sin much cherished by our great theatres by <persName ref="#Byron">Lord Byron’s</persName> poetry &amp; by these novels.—After all I have a feeling of remorse about me for saying a word against them. It seems ungrateful even to nourish a detracting thought of such <supplied>sources</supplied> of innocent <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/></del> &amp; attainable amusement. I am so grateful too for one <supplied>circumstance</supplied> that you mention. <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/></del> Every body can talk of them. What a comfort that is—what a <supplied>resource</supplied> to a person who has no great variety of conversation to have something to say to a stranger when we have settled the weather. How thankful we ought to be for an Author who has provided us all with a spell to set talk a flowing, to unclose the shyest lips by such a simple “open <supplied resp="#rnes">Sesame</supplied>” as Have you read <title ref="#Abbot_WS">The Abbot</title> or Do you like <title ref="#Monastery">The Monastery</title>.—The part of these works that please me the most are those that approach nearest to common life <persName ref="#Oldbuck_Jonathan"><supplied>Oldbuck</supplied></persName> &amp; <persName ref="#Edie_Ochiltree">Edie Olchiltree </persName>—<persName ref="#Pleydell">Pleydell</persName> and <persName ref="#Dandie_Dinmont">Dandie Dinmont</persName>—Give me such as these—&amp; take who will <persName ref="#Elspeth">Elspeth </persName><persName ref="#Balfour_John">Balfour </persName><persName ref="#Dirk_Hatteraick">Dirk Hatteraick </persName><persName ref="#Meg_Merrilies">Meg Merrilies</persName> &amp; all such <supplied>questionable</supplied> compounds of <supplied>witch and gipsey</supplied>. This is a sad ignominious confession and goes near to prove that “the gods have <supplied>not made me</supplied> poetical”<!-- an allusion to As You Like it -->—but such is the melancholy <supplied>sort</supplied>.  My dear <persName ref="#Haydon">Mr. Haydon</persName> how ashamed I ought to be to send such impertinence to you—but you are so indulgent that one is not half so afraid of you as is proper—&amp; my pleasure at hearing from you an opinion I had long entertained setting pen a going irresistibly. Ah you little guessed what a shower bath would fall about your ears when you pulled the string.  Well I will not say another word about <persName ref="#Scott_Wal">Walter Scott</persName> I am determined. —How are you off for Summer in <placeName ref="#London_city">London</placeName>? <!-- begin the only portion of this letter recorded by L'estrange -->These few days have brought it <!-- L'estrange supplies 'summer' --> back to us in all its splendor. I am writing out of doors in our little arbour--with my attention a good deal distracted by a superb butterfly which 
                     <pb n="4"/> is hovering about a large tuft of <rs type="plant" nymRef="#China_Aster">China Asters</rs> close by—now fluttering round &amp; round in the sun &amp; now swinging in the rich blossoms. The butterflies love <rs type="plant" nymRef="#China_Aster">China Asters</rs>—so do I. They come when flowers begin to be so rare &amp; precious—their colours are so rich—&amp; they are so hardy. They lift up their gay heads and will live let the weather be what it may. Now goodbye for today I shall not finish till I hear from you. Oh I hope you will come. We shall be more disappointed than words can tell is you do not.<!-- end the only portion of this letter recorded by L'estrange --></p><closer><lb/>Good bye dear Sir.<lb/></closer><postscript><p>Friday 6th—Having the opportunity of <!--turn of the paper-->
                 a <supplied>frank</supplied> I <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/></del> shall send this off to beg to know if you can come to us next Sunday fortnight the 22nd--or the Monday—<rs type="person" ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="#Russell_M">Mama</rs> go into <placeName> Hampshire </placeName><del rend="squiggles"><supplied resp="#rnes">will</supplied></del>
               but shall be returned by that time and most happy &amp; <supplied>proud</supplied> to see you &amp; to shew you better the week after in <placeName>Oxfordshire</placeName>.—My <rs type="person" ref="#Mitford_Geo">Father</rs> desires me to say that if you should prefer to see a coursing meeting for a Cup there will be one at <unclear><gap quantity="3" unit="words" reason="illegible"/></unclear> engaged on the 22nd, do come then—the weather will be better &amp; the days longer &amp; the <supplied>earliest</supplied> time is always the best. Adieu my dear Sir &amp; ever yours
               </p><signed>M. R. Mitford. </signed></postscript><closer><address><addrLine>B. R. Haydon Esqre </addrLine><addrLine><placeName><district ref="#StJohns_Place">St. John's
                        Place </district></placeName></addrLine><addrLine><placeName><district ref="#Lisson_Grove">Lisson Grove 
                        North</district></placeName></addrLine><addrLine><placeName><district ref="#Regents_Park">Regent's Park</district></placeName></addrLine><addrLine><placeName ref="#London_city">London</placeName></addrLine></address></closer></div></body><back>
         <!--ebb: 29 May 2014: Added Prosopography information to Site Index. --></back></text></TEI>