<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><?xml-model href="http://ebeshero.github.io/MRMValidate.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title xml:id="MRM1769">Letter to <persName ref="#Haydon">[B. R. Haydon]</persName>, November 4, 1820.</title>
            <!--This letter is marked unknown but context makes it almost certain that it is written to B.R. Haydon-->
            <!--LMW:  Greg says that Needham mentions this letter in his research.--><author ref="#MRM">Mary Russell Mitford</author><editor ref="#esh">Eric Hood</editor><sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford Project</orgName></sponsor><sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor><principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal><respStmt><resp>Transcription and coding by</resp><persName ref="#esh">Eric Hood</persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Date last checked: <date when="2014-06-02">2014-06-02</date>. Proofing and corrections by</resp><persName ref="#kdc">Kellie Donovan-Condron</persName><persName ref="#ebb">Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName><persName ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</persName>
               <!--ebb: Entered prosopography to site index. Still need to check letter transcription and code. 02-05-2014. -->
               <!-- LMW:  updating tagging 2015 10 05 --></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>First digital edition in TEI, date: 1 July 2013. P5.</edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority><pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace><date>2013</date><availability><p>Reproduced by courtesy of the <placeName>Reading Central Library</placeName>.</p><licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                  License</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Mitford Letters: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><repository ref="#ReadingCL">Reading Central Library</repository><collection>The letters of Mary Russell Mitford, vol. 4, 1819-1823</collection><idno>qB/TU/MIT Vol. 4 Horizon No.: 1361550 ff. 421</idno></msIdentifier><head>Letter from Mary Russell Mitford to [B. R. Haydon], <date when="1820-11-04">November 4th 1820</date>.</head><physDesc><objectDesc><supportDesc><support><p><material>Paper</material>. Letter is written on a single octavo sheet folded in half.</p></support><condition>Letter incomplete. No address leaf, envelope, or postmark.</condition></supportDesc></objectDesc><sealDesc><p>Missing seal.</p></sealDesc></physDesc></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><handNotes><handNote xml:id="pencil" medium="pencil">Someone, apparently other than Mitford, perhaps cataloging letters and describing them.</handNote><handNote xml:id="pen_unknown">An unknown person, presumably not Mitford, who wrote what appears to be an illegible name at the top of this letter, followed by Mitford's initials.</handNote></handNotes></profileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><p>Mitford’s spelling and punctuation are retained. Where Mitford’s spelling and hyphenation of words deviates from the standard, in order to facilitate searching we are using the TEI elements “choice,” “sic,” and “reg” to encode both Mitford’s spelling and the regular international standard of Oxford English spelling, following the first listed spelling in the Oxford English Dictionary. The long s and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="letter"><opener><add><handShift resp="#pencil"/>20</add><add><handShift resp="#rc"/><!--Red diagonal line across page--></add><dateline><date when="1820-11-04">Nov. 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1820.</date><placeName ref="#ThreeMileCross">Three Mile Cross</placeName></dateline><salute>My dear Sir</salute></opener><p>The puppy is arrived &amp; will be taken great care of--What a beauty it is! <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</persName> says he never saw one more promising.--<persName ref="#Daphne_pet">Daphne</persName> has not yet been tried--partly because my <rs type="person" ref="#Mitford_Geo">Father</rs> has been much engaged lately &amp; has had little coursing--but chiefly I really believe because he thinks her delicate &amp; is so afraid of injuring her. She shall be tried soon though--for I will take her coursing myself. In the meantime we walk out together every day, &amp; I tell her your messages, &amp; exhort her to earn her collar. I do think <persName ref="#Daphne_pet">Daphne</persName> has sense enough to understand that it is a high honour to belong to <persName ref="#Haydon">Mr. Haydon</persName>. By the by you have fallen into a very natural mistake for a young sportsman in fancying that <q>"killing <pb n="2"/>the hare first"</q> is the criterion of excellence in a greyhound. It has very little to do with the matter--When a hare is put up before two dogs the one nearest to her generally turns her towards the other, who comes up &amp; turns her back again--&amp; so they go on if evenly matched for many minutes until at last the hare is exhausted &amp; caught by either as it happens. Now the great proof of superior speed, is, to pass the nearest dog (which in technical terms is called a <emph rend="underline"><choice><sic>go by</sic><reg resp="#esh">go-bye</reg></choice></emph>) &amp; take two turns together--&amp; this is what I am sure <persName ref="#Daphne_pet">Daphne</persName> will do by any greyhound of my <choice><sic>acquaintaince</sic><reg resp="#ebb">acquaintance</reg></choice>. I am afraid my explanation is not very clear--It seems to me that nobody could understand it that did not know the whole mystery beforehand--but if you wish to get a thorough insight into coursing look at the rules drawn up by the <persName ref="#Howard_Tho">Duke of Norfolk</persName> in <persName ref="#ElizI">Queen Elizabeth</persName>'s day which you will find in <title ref="#Daniells">Daniell's Rural Sports</title>. They are the authority to all Coursers to this hour.</p><pb n="3"/><p>And <rs type="title" corresp="#ChrstEJrslm_Haydon">your picture</rs> is really going to <placeName ref="#Edinburgh">Edinburgh</placeName>! What an answer to <title ref="#Blackwoods">Blackwood's Magazine</title>!<note resp="#ebb"><persName ref="#MRM">Mitford</persName> refers to Haydon's painting, <title corresp="#ChrstEJrslm_Haydon">"Christ's Entry Into Jerusalem"</title> which he exhibited in <placeName ref="#Edinburgh">Edinburgh</placeName> in <date when="1820-12">December 1820</date>. See Haydon's letter to <persName ref="#Beaumont_Sir_Geo">George Beaumont</persName> of <date when="1820-12-26">26 December 1820</date> in <bibl corresp="#Haydon_Corresp"><title>Benjamin Robert Haydon: Correspondence and Table-Talk</title><biblScope unit="vol">1 of 2</biblScope><biblScope unit="page">350</biblScope></bibl><bibl>The mention of <title ref="#Blackwoods">Blackwood's</title> likely recalls the <date when="1818-08">August 1818</date> issue in which <persName ref="#Haydon">Haydon</persName> was attacked by <author>the anonymous "Z."</author> who had been lambasting the <persName>Hunt</persName> and <persName>Keats</persName> circle as the "Cockney School."</bibl> The <date when="1818-08">August 1818</date> article had described <persName ref="#Haydon">Haydon</persName> as <quote>"that clever, but most affected artist, who as little resembles <persName ref="#Raphael">Raphael</persName> in genius as he does in person, not-withstanding the foppery of having his hair curled over his shoulders in the old Italian fashion."</quote></note> Will <orgName ref="#Scots">the Scotch</orgName> have taste enough to find out its exquisite beauty? I hope they will--for I have a sneaking kindness for the Countrymen of <persName ref="#hume">Hume</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#Smollett_Tob">Smollett</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#Burns_Rob">Burns</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#Scott_Wal">Scott</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#Wilkie_Wil">Wilkie</persName>--in spite of their sins--&amp; in spite of our being Borderers on the English side. My <rs type="person" ref="#Mitford_Geo">Father</rs> had an Aunt<note resp="#ebb">This aunt of <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">George Mitford</persName>'s has not yet been identified.</note> who bred him up &amp; with whom I liked to spend a good deal of my time whose national prejudice against her Scottish neighbors realised all that has been told of the old border hatreds. She could not bear a <orgName ref="#Scots">Scotchman</orgName> in her sight--nor one who had a drop of Scotch blood in his veins. Oh how she would have gloried in such a Champion as you! <persName ref="#James_Miss">Miss James</persName> is just such another--albeit <supplied reason="illegible">unused</supplied> to the hating mood--she quite detests them. I had a letter from her the other day, &amp; she expressed very strongly her regret at missing you--I can well believe that poor <placeName ref="#Richmond">Richmond</placeName> looked like a faded beauty. There is no<pb n="4"/> place that requires so much fine weather, bright sunshine, blue sky, &amp; white robed ladies, as <placeName ref="#Richmond">Richmond</placeName>. For <placeName ref="#Richmond">Richmond</placeName>, charming place as it is, with its rosy gardens &amp; its brimmming river is not that fresh homely delightful thing the Country. It is rather a holiday spot for ladies &amp; gentleman where they lead a happy out-of-door life like the gay folks in <persName ref="#Watteau_Wil">Watteau</persName>'s pictures &amp; have nothing to do with the work a day world. But I should have thought the view from the hill would have been improved by the rich tints of Autumn which would break the uniformity of those heavy masses of foliage--since to confess the truth I have often been tempted to agree with the American criticism &amp; to think the view wanted "clearing." Nevertheless it is a charming place--full of quiet elegance--&amp; <del rend="squiggles" quantity="1" unit="word"/><note resp="#esh">begin cancelling in red pencil</note><del rend="strikethrough" hand="#rc" unit="word" quantity="9">of <persName type="hist" ref="#James_Miss">Miss James</persName>--its greatest attraction in my eyes.</del><note resp="#esh">end strikethrough cancelling in red pencil</note> I am hoping &amp; expecting to see her here--She threatens not to come--but she cannot have the heart to disappoint<pb n="1"/> me.</p><closer>Ever yours, <signed><persName ref="#MRM">MRM</persName></signed>.<note resp="#ebb">The last word of the letter, together with the closer and signature are written across the top of the letter's first page.</note></closer>
               
               <!-- ADDRESS LEAF AND POSTMARKS ARE MISSING-->
               <!--No postmark or address available--></div></body><back>
         <!--ebb: 02-05-2014: Entered all new listings to site index, and removed from this file.--></back></text></TEI>