<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><?xml-model href="http://ebeshero.github.io/MRMValidate.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title xml:id="MRM1767">Letter to <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir William Elford</persName>, <date when="1820-09-30">30 September 1820</date></title><author ref="#MRM">Mary Russell Mitford</author><editor ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</editor><sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford Project</orgName></sponsor><sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor><principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal><respStmt><resp>Transcription and coding by</resp><persName ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Proofing and corrections by</resp><persName ref="#ebb">Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName> 
               <!--2016-06-07 ebb: Adding an editorial note on the likely identification of "Mr. Marsham" so that the SI can properly reference a more general entry on Robert Marsham.-->
               <!--ebb early July 2014, checked code only --></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>First digital edition in TEI, date: <date when="2014-06-06">6 June 2014</date>. P5.</edition><respStmt><resp>Edition made with help from photos taken by</resp><orgName>Digital Mitford editors</orgName></respStmt><respStmt><orgName>Digital Mitford</orgName><resp> photo files: <idno>30sept1820SirWilliamElford1a#.jpg, 30sept1820SirWilliamElford1b#.jpg, 30sept1820SirWilliamElford2a#.jpg, 30sept1820SirWilliamElford2b#.jpg, 30sept1820SirWilliamElford3a#.jpg, 30sept1820SirWilliamElford3b#.jpg, 30sept1820SirWilliamElford4a#.jpg, 30sept1820SirWilliamElford4b#.jpg, 30sept1820SirWilliamElford5a#.jpg, 30sept1820SirWilliamElford5b#.jpg, 30sept1820SirWilliamElford6a#.jpg, 30sept1820SirWilliamElford6b#.jpg</idno></resp></respStmt> <!-- need to update with new photos.  LMW --></editionStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority><pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace><date>2013</date><availability><p>Reproduced by courtesy of the <orgName ref="#ReadingCL">Reading Central Library</orgName>.</p><licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                  License</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Mitford Letters: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><repository ref="#ReadingCL">Reading Central Library</repository><collection>The letters of Mary Russell Mitford, vol. 4, 1819-1823</collection><idno>qB/TU/MIT Vol. 4 Horizon No.: 1361550 ff.418</idno></msIdentifier><head>Letter from <persName ref="#MRM">Mary Russell Mitford</persName> to <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir William Elford,</persName><date when="1820-09-30">30 September 1820</date>.</head><physDesc><objectDesc><supportDesc><support>One and one-half sheets of folio <material>paper</material>, six surfaces photographed.</support><condition>Half sheet (pages five and six) torn on right edge where wax seal was removed; also torn in center of page.</condition></supportDesc></objectDesc></physDesc></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><handNotes><handNote corresp="#rc" medium="red_crayon"> Red crayon or thick red pencil. Probably a different hand from Mitford's that marks many of her letters, sometimes drawing diagonal lines across pages, and sometimes writing words overtop and perpendicularly across Mitford's writing. On this letter, a red line is drawn from top left to bottom right of each of the leaves. On leaf six (the address leaf), two red lines are drawn from top left to bottom right over each text block.
           </handNote></handNotes></profileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><p>Mitford’s spelling and punctuation are retained, except where a word is split at the end of a line and the beginning of the next in the manuscript. Where Mitford’s spelling and hyphenation of words deviates from the standard, in order to facilitate searching we are using the TEI elements “choice," “sic," and “reg" to encode both Mitford’s spelling and the regular international standard of Oxford English spelling, following the first listed spelling in the Oxford English Dictionary. The long s and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="letter"><opener><dateline><name type="place">Three Mile Cross</name><date when="1820-09">Sept. -- I don't know What--
                  In the <emph rend="underline">last</emph>--How many days has September?</date></dateline></opener><p>You delight me, my dear <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Friend</persName> by what you say about the <persName ref="#Queen_Caroline">Queen</persName>--It is just what I knew you would say--just what I think--only your Toryism takes some <del rend="squiggles" unit="charas" n="5">thing</del><add place="above">what</add> of a party view of the question which my Whiggism does not. She is &amp; must be guilty of a fatal want of all modesty all decency all the outworks to Virtue--And what is a woman without them! And what a terrible thing is party Spirit when such a woman is set up as an idol! If she were acquitted a thousand times it would never alter my opinion--&amp; acquitted I hope she will be for the quiet of the nation--A mob in a good humour is a much more peaceable thing than a mob in an ill one--And as you say every body <del rend="squiggles" unit="chars" n="1"/> knows what she is--they they talk so grandly about innocence and purity &amp; whatnot!--<quote>"Springes to catch woodcocks"</quote>--I liked your note to <persName ref="#Palmer_Mad">Lady Madelina</persName> exceedingly--Ah if she begins to write to you she will quite put my nose <metamark rend="caret" place="below" function="insertion"/><add place="above">out</add> of Joint--My only chance for favour was her going away--but if she begins to write--that charming person--&amp; if she writes only half as delightfully as she talks--it is all over with <persName ref="#MRM">your poor little Correspondent</persName>--She will be thrown aside like an old glove--poor luckless Cast away--not worth stooping for--poor unhappy thing! Won't she?--The only comfort is that my charming rival cannot put her Scotch voice upon paper--that sweet Scotch voice--she cannot write that <pb n="2"/> Can she?--There is my only chance. Ah I see that I am sinking in your good graces already--you accuse me of talking politics--&amp; I avow to you my dear friend that I talk politics less than any body of my acquaintance--never when any one will talk to me of flowers or greyhounds or pictures or books--Never, unless I meet with a person who is utterly ignorant of all better subjects &amp; then when we have done with the weather &amp; the Scotch novels--why there is nothing else to turn to--And then the Scotch novels--you accuse me of over-rating them--when I will be <del rend="squiggles" unit="chars" n="2"/>bound to say that there is amongst all the nonsense that I have written to you full twenty sheets of sheer fault-finding &amp; impertinence &amp; sauciness about these same works. And then you accuse me of under-rating Misses <persName ref="#Edgeworth_Maria">Edgeworth</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#Austen_Jane">Austen</persName>--when amongst the aforementioned bundle of trash might be found at least the same quantity of admiring praises of these worthies. The fact is my dear <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir Wiliam</persName> that our taste in novels, particularly these novels, is remarkably similar--I am more headlong &amp; ardent than you, &amp; I have not half of your clearness &amp; soundness of judgment &amp; therefore may be sometimes carried away by my admiration of the beauties to overlook the faults that accompany them--but the parts that I particularly admire are precisely those which you yourself would select as nearest to Common nature--to real existing life--<persName ref="#Oldbuck_Jonathan">Oldbuck</persName> and <persName ref="#Edie_Ochiltree">Edie Ochiltree</persName>--<persName ref="#Pleydell">Pleydell</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#Dandie_Dinmont">Dandie Dinmont</persName>--<persName ref="#Denison_Jenny_WS">Jenny Dennison</persName><note resp="#lmw">Character in <bibl corresp="#Old_Mortality"><author ref="#Scott_Wal">Walter Scott</author>'s <title level="m">Old Mortality</title></bibl>, spelled <quote>Denison</quote> in the novel.</note>--<persName ref="#Deans_Jeanie_WS">Jeanie Deans</persName>--the <persName ref="#Bradwardine_Baron_WS">Baron of Bradwardine</persName>--these are my heroes--these I hold by--&amp; utterly reject &amp; abominate the <persName ref="#Meg_Merrilies">Meg Merrilies</persName>--&amp; <persName ref="#Balfours_WS">Balfours of Burleys</persName>--&amp;<persName ref="#Elspeth">old Elspeths</persName>--&amp; <persName ref="#White_Spirit_WS">white Spirits</persName> of all sorts<pb n="3"/> Now is this not your Creed? Moreover I hold the wit &amp; the admirable delineation of character &amp; of manners in the Mesdemoiselles <persName ref="#Edgeworth_Maria">Edgeworth</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#Austen_Jane">Austen</persName> to be fifty times more valuable and less imitable than the romantic &amp; historical &amp; poetical parts of the Scotch novels--preferring <persName ref="#Austen_Jane">Miss Austen</persName> to <persName ref="#Edgeworth_Maria">Miss Edgeworth</persName> inasmuch as she has more heart &amp; never deviates into the slang and vulgarity of high life as <persName ref="#Edgeworth_Maria">Miss Edgeworth</persName> sometimes condescends to do--Is not this your Creed also? And will you rank me any longer with your <persName ref="#Marsham_Robt">Mr. Marsham</persName>s?<note resp="#lmw #ebb">Possibly a reference to <persName ref="#Marsham_Robt">Robert Marsham</persName> (1708-1797), English naturalist. <persName ref="#WhiteGilbert">Gilbert White</persName> described Marsham as a <quote>painful and accurate naturalist</quote>, so it is possible that Mitford here pokes fun at the notion of his painstaking detail. More research is needed to definitely identify the Marsham mentioned here. Source of Gilbert White's comment on Robert Marsham: <bibl>excerpt from an unpublished letter in <title level="s">The Zoologist</title> (<date when="1876-07">July 1876</date>) <biblScope unit="page">4979</biblScope></bibl>.</note> or such unwise scorners &amp; scoffers your dear faithless Correspondent? Eh?--After all I believe you knew my opinion as well as I did myself &amp; only threw out the reproach which has occasioned this tirade <del rend="squiggles" unit="chars" n="1"/> just as one struts up to a Bantam Hen sometimes to have the pleasure of <del rend="squiggles" unit="word" n="1">vexing</del>putting the little fool in a pet &amp; making her ruffle up her feathers--If so you deserve to be published by this tedious explanation--Ah you little knew what a shower bath was coming when you pulled the string--or you would have <del rend="squiggles" unit="word" n="1"/>jumped out first--as the gentleman did in a story you once told me--Would not you?--Perhaps I may like <persName ref="#Scott_Wal">Walter Scott</persName> better than you did first from having more enthusiasm of that particular sort--&amp; feeling therefore somewhat more strongly the gratitude due to the Author of fine books--Secondly from not having <del rend="squiggles" unit="word" n="1"><supplied resp="#lmw">the</supplied></del><add place="above">your</add> variety of resources in conversation &amp; being most thankful to any one who spares <del rend="scribble" unit="word"><supplied resp="#lmw">one</supplied></del><add place="above">me</add> the trouble of hunting for a subject to talk of to strangers or the stupid. Ah what an inexpressible comfort it is when perched on a sofa next to some pretty bland Miss whom one is expected to entertain to have the power of <pb n="4"/> of breaking the Ice &amp; making her  <del rend="scribble" unit="word"><supplied resp="#lmw">tongue</supplied></del><add place="above">speech</add> flow by the simple question. <q>"Have you read <title ref="#Abbot_WS">the Abbott</title>?"</q> or <q>"Do you like <title ref="#Monastery">the Monastery</title>?"</q> All the world can talk of the Scotch novels &amp; half the world can talk of nothing else.--Before we entirely leave the subject of Novels, Have you read or heard of ? A new novel by <persName ref="#Dallas_RC">Mr. Dallas</persName>. <persName ref="#Dallas_RC">Dallas</persName> is a bad writer &amp; this can hardly be called a good work, bad the plan, &amp; the character of the heroine very fine indeed. Nothing of this appears in the first Volume which is so dull as almost to have tempted me to throw down the book--but as the character opens one becomes interested--It is founded on the grand sublime, elevating virtue of Repentance &amp; the hero is more exalted by his humility &amp; self-abasement than can be imagined--All the best of the book is very bad--quite below <unclear>inferior</unclear>--but this fine conception makes it worth reading. <persName ref="#Dallas_RC">Mr. Dallas</persName> is the person to whom <persName ref="#Byron">Lord Byron</persName> gave the profits of the first Canto of <title ref="#ChildeHaroldsPil">Childe Harold</title>--he being ruined I believe by an expensive wife--(indeed I have heard that she will not dine without being serenaded by Musicians, &amp; I cannot help thinking--though there is no visible allusion that in the character though not in the story there is an occasional hint at <persName ref="#Byron">Lord Byron</persName>--At least that the <persName ref="#Dallas_RC">Author</persName> means to suggest him &amp; of him--that lost fame and lost virtue &amp; lost happiness may be recovered &amp; redressed. <metamark rend="jerk"/> How are you off for Summer in <placeName ref="#Devonshire_county">Devonshire</placeName>? The two last days have brought ours back again--I am writing out of doors in our little Arbour <!-- handshift here, parens in red crayon LMW-->with my attention somewhat distracted by a superb butterfly close by who is fluttering around &amp; around in the sun <del rend="squiggles" unit="word" n="1"/> swinging in the rich blossom of a <rs type="plant" ref="#China_Aster">China Aster</rs>--how fond they are of <rs type="plant" ref="#China_Aster">China Asters</rs>! So am I--They come when flowers<pb n="5"/> begin to be most precious &amp; rare--I have never had so many before--or so fine--&amp; they are always beautiful with their rich colours like so many patterns for winter gowns--or with the pure delicate white stripes mingled with purple like violets of both hues--And they are so hardy too--they hold up their gay heads &amp; <emph rend="underline">will</emph> live and let the weather be what it may--I dearly love <rs type="plant" ref="#China_Aster">China Asters</rs> &amp; so do the butterflies. But indeed <!-- handshift here, parens in red crayon LMW-->in this little garden I have had a great crop of flowers of all sorts--Its quite astonishing how little room they will do with, &amp; I like that crowd of bright blossoms mingling <del rend="squiggles" unit="word" n="1"><supplied resp="#lmw">the</supplied></del> one with the other like flowers in a basket or the mimic qaiety of a <gap reason="torn"/><add place="above">carpet</add><!--It looks to me like the paper was torn, MRM crossed out the -pet of carpet and wrote in carpet above; Unless it is added in another hand?  LMW  --> I have been <gap reason="torn" unit="chars" n="2"/><supplied resp="#lmw">ge</supplied>tting in my harvest of sweet peas to day.--What <gap reason="torn" unit="chars" n="1"/><supplied resp="#lmw">s</supplied>tuff I write to you my dear Friend--full of confidence in your kindness--&amp; presuming upon it almost past bearing--But these trifles are my pleasures--a part even of my happiness &amp; why should I not talk about them! <metamark rend="jerk"/><persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</persName> has seen <persName ref="#Palmer_CF">Mr. Palmer</persName> today, who gives an excellent account of <persName ref="#Palmer_Mad">Lady Madelina</persName><!-- I can't tell if MRM writes this name Madalina or Madelina.  In the reference sources we found it was spelled with two A's.  But the more I look at examples the more I think MRM spells it with an e.  LMW -->--perhaps I may see him tomorrow--If I do I will let you know any news I may hear of her--Am I not a generous rival?-- Adieu my dear Friend--Pray write soon. Kindest regards from all here--Ever most affectionately,</p><closer><persName ref="#MRM">M.R. Mitford</persName><lb/></closer><postscript><p>Have you seen a <title ref="#Letter_to_HM_1820">letter to <persName ref="#More_Hannah">Hannah More</persName> from an English woman on the present Crisis</title>? It is by my friend <persName ref="#Hofland_B">Mrs. Hofland</persName>--Exceedingly well &amp; even elegantly written.</p><pb n="1"/> <!-- MRM returns to write on first leaf here.  How did we decide to code?  LMW --><p>I had half a mind not to let this scrawl go--it is so stupid--but I will send it--you will be entertained with my jealousy--&amp; I love to make you laugh whether with me or at me. Good bye my dear Friend--</p><p>Don't you think the Whigs are much to blame to encourage the <persName ref="#Queen_Caroline">Queen</persName>? Why do they I wonder. Once more Goodbye--</p></postscript><closer><address><pb n="6"/><addrLine><placeName ref="#Reading_city">Reading</placeName><date when="1820-10-03"/>October three--<emph rend="underline">1821</emph></addrLine><addrLine><persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir W<hi rend="superscript">m</hi>Elford</persName> Bart</addrLine><addrLine><placeName ref="#Bickham_village">Bickham</placeName></addrLine><addrLine><placeName ref="#Plymouth_city">Plymouth</placeName></addrLine><addrLine><persName ref="#Palmer_CF"><emph rend="underline">CFPalmer</emph></persName></addrLine></address></closer></div></body><back>
       <!--ebb 2016-06-07: Backlist was evidently updated and incorporated into si-Add-LMW_2016-04-24.xml. Removed from here, as I'm adding updates and adding a note to this letter.--></back></text></TEI>