<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><?xml-model href="http://ebeshero.github.io/MRMValidate.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title xml:id="MRM1754">Letter to <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir William Elford</persName>, January
               30, 1820</title><author>Mary Russell Mitford</author><editor ref="#ad">Alexandra Drayton</editor><sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford Project</orgName></sponsor><sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor><principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal><respStmt><resp>Transcription and coding by</resp><persName ref="#ad">Alexandra Drayton</persName><persName ref="#scw">Samantha Webb</persName><persName ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Proofing and corrections by </resp><persName ref="#scw">Samantha Webb</persName><!-- 2014-06-02 --><persName ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</persName><!-- LMW:  2015 10 08 updating header info. and tags, completing additional transcription; needs final proofing and revised header.--></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>First digital edition in TEI, date: <date when="2014-06-02">2 June 2014</date>. P5.</edition> <!-- Change this date to the date you BEGIN the xml file. --><respStmt><resp>Edition made with help from photos taken by</resp><orgName>Digital Mitford editors</orgName></respStmt><respStmt><orgName>Digital Mitford</orgName><resp> photo files: <idno>30Jan1820SirWilliamElford1#.jpg, 30Jan1820SirWilliamElford2#.jpg, 30Jan1820SirWilliamElford3#.jpg,30Jan1820SirWilliamElford4#.jpg, DSCF9186.jpg, DSCF9187.jpg, DSCF9187.jpg, DSCF9187.jpg, DSCF9190.jpg, DSCF9191.jpg, DSCF9192.jpg, DSCF9193.jpg, DSCF9194.jpg, DSCF9195.jpg, DSCF9196.jpg, DSCF9197.jpg, DSCF9198.jpg, DSCF9199.jpg, DSCF9200.jpg, DSCF9201.jpg, DSCF9202.jpg, DSCF9203.jpg, DSCF9204.jpg, DSCF9205.jpg, DSCF9206.jpg, DSCF9207.jpg, DSCF9208.jpg</idno></resp></respStmt></editionStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority><pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace><date>2013</date><availability><p>Reproduced by courtesy of the <orgName ref="#ReadingCL">Reading Central Library</orgName>.</p><licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                  License</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Mitford Letters: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><repository ref="#ReadingCL">Reading Central Library</repository><collection>The letters of Mary Russell Mitford, vol. 4, 1819-1823</collection><idno>qB/TU/MIT Vol. 4 Horizon No.: 1361550 ff. 396</idno></msIdentifier><head>Letter from Mary Russell Mitford to Sir William Elford, <date when="1820-01-30">1820 January 30
                     </date>.</head><physDesc><objectDesc><supportDesc> <!-- Physical description of the letter goes here: paper size and condition, seal, postmarks, etc. --><support><p>Two an a half sheets of <material>paper</material>, ten surfaces photographed, folded in half once and folded again in thirds for posting.</p><p>Address leaf bearing red franking stamp, reading <stamp><lb/>FREE<lb/>FE<lb/>1820</stamp>.</p><p>A black mileage stamp reading <stamp><lb/>BEDFORD<lb/>51</stamp></p></support><condition><p>Sheet (leaves nine and ten) torn on right edge of page three where wax seal was removed.</p></condition></supportDesc></objectDesc><sealDesc><p>Black wax seal, complete, adhered to page four.</p>  <!-- change. --></sealDesc></physDesc></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><handNotes><handNote corresp="#rc" medium="red_crayon"> Red crayon or thick red pencil. Probably a different hand from Mitford's that marks many of her letters, sometimes drawing diagonal lines across pages, and sometimes writing words overtop and perpendicularly across Mitford's writing. A red line is drawn from top left to bottom right of each of the first five leaves as well as leaves seven through nine. On leave six and ten, a red line is drawn from top left to bottom right across each of the text blocks. There is no red crayon across the address text block.</handNote><handNote corresp="#pencil" medium="pencil"> Someone, apparently other than Mitford, perhaps cataloging letters and describing them, who left grey pencil marks and numbered her letters now in the Reading Central Library's collection. This letter is numbered "2" in the top left of the first leaf. Also numbered 1820 on the top of the fifth leaf.
            </handNote></handNotes></profileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><p>Mitford’s spelling and punctuation are retained, except where a word is split at the end of a line and the beginning of the next in the manuscript. Where Mitford’s spelling and hyphenation of words deviates from the standard, in order to facilitate searching we are using the TEI elements “choice," “sic," and “reg" to encode both Mitford’s spelling and the regular international standard of Oxford English spelling, following the first listed spelling in the Oxford English Dictionary. The long s and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="letter"><opener><add hand="#pencil">2</add><dateline><name type="place">Bertram House</name><date when="1820-01-30"><choice><abbr>Jany</abbr><expan>Jan<ex>uar</ex>y</expan></choice>
                     30<emph rend="superscript">st</emph>1820.</date></dateline><salute>To <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir W. Elford</persName></salute></opener><p> I have just this moment received your most kind &amp; entertaining letter, <rs type="person" ref="#Elford_SirWm">my dear friend</rs>, &amp; I hasten to answer it on
               the full gallop that I may catch our flying M.P. <persName ref="#Palmer_CF">Mr
                     Fyshe Palmer</persName>
               - who was in <placeName ref="#Reading_city">Reading</placeName> yesterday &amp; <del rend="squiggles" unit="word" quantity="1"/><damage rend="smudge"/><unclear><supplied>our</supplied></unclear>
               (Deuce take that
               blot--more haste worse speed!) our moveable <rs type="person" ref="#Palmer_CF">
                 Member</rs> who was in <placeName ref="#Reading_city">Reading</placeName> yesterday &amp; <emph rend="underline">therefore</emph> will not be there tomorrow. First let me express how unfeignedly
               sorry I am--we are--for the sickness you have had to encounter at
               <placeName ref="#Bickham_village">Bickham</placeName>--I hope this will find your <persName>daughter</persName> recovering
               both her strength &amp; her looks--&amp; that your cough will disappear in this mild
               weather--melt &amp; go off like the snow. <rs type="person" ref="#Russell_M">
                  Mama</rs> &amp; I have kept quite
               well this unhealthy winter--<rs type="person" ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</rs> has not--
               he has had a great deal of <choice><sic>head ach</sic><reg>headache</reg></choice><!--scw:the correction of "headache"continues to appear in the html transformation--> &amp; heavy cold
               --&amp; as he takes no manner of care of himself--comes down from
                  <placeName ref="#London_city">London</placeName> at <time>four
                  <sic>oclock</sic><corr>o'clock</corr></time><!--scw: the corrected version of "o'clock" continues to appear in the html version--> in the morning on the outside of a
               coach--&amp; other tendencies of the same nature (I hope he is looking over my
               shoulder) can scarcely expect to be free from complaint. <persName ref="#Dickinson_Mrs">M<emph rend="superscript">rs</emph> Dickinson</persName> is not yet confined &amp; keeps pretty well as to health
               though a good deal troubled with superstitious forebodings which I do all in my power
               to drive out of her head by <unclear><supplied>gayer</supplied></unclear> nonsense. Now you have our
                  bulletin<unclear>s</unclear> all round.<gap rend="jerk"/>What you say of
                  <title ref="#Ivanhoe">Ivanhoe</title> is admirably just and true - <persName ref="#Rowena_WS"> Rowena</persName> is a mere woman of straw - a peg to hang <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/></del>love upon--as almost all <rs type="person" ref="#Scott_Wal">his</rs> heroines are--of that horrible old
               woman I had before made dishonourable mention--&amp; those two scenes of burning
               &amp; of torture are quite unworthy of so great a Poet--He picked up that love of
               representing bodily suffering though, where<pb n="2"/><unclear><supplied resp="#scw">by word</supplied></unclear> syllable by syllable--It is their <emph rend="underline">fault</emph>, that they are of <gap reason="ms photo"/>
               <!-- AD: page obscured in photograph - check in library letter --> Poems the most
               recherchés--Moreover <persName ref="#deGenlis_Mme">Madame de Genlis</persName> makes
                  <title>Petrarque</title> out an angel &amp; then says she is just like him! Really
               these French women are vain of their own vanity! - Do you ever read <persName ref="#Burney_SH">Miss
                  Burney</persName>'s novels? I mean the lesser <persName ref="#Burney_SH">Burney</persName>--not
                  <persName ref="#Burney_F">Madame D'Arblay</persName>but her sister whom I like better. We are
               reading one now--<title ref="#Country_Neighbours">Country Neighbours</title>--pretty enough I think. <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" quantity="1"/>
                by millions--a heroine who is
               so young so wise so good so beautiful
                &amp; so accomplished
               that she makes one sick even before she saves her lover's life, an iniquity so
                  <persName ref="#Porter_AM">Miss-Porterish</persName>
              that I quite wonder at <persName ref="#Burney_SH">Miss Burney</persName>'s
               lighting upon it--the plot too is exceedingly disagreeable &amp; entangled--all in a
                  <emph rend="underline">snarl</emph> as the cotton-spinners say, &amp; mighty
               difficult to undo. But nevertheless the book is
               pretty--there is some good observation in it--&amp; a <rs type="person">sarcastic old lady</rs> whom I
               like exceedingly--to say nothing of a most <rs type="person">amiable old maid</rs> - Well I think I have
               talked enough of novels--Did you ever read a little book which has been lately
               reprinted <title ref="#CaptivityCaptKnox">The Captivity of Captain John Knox
                        <sic>in</sic><reg>on</reg>the Island of
               Ceylon</title>? It
               is charming--If one did not know it to be nothing but a real true history told by
               the very man to whom it happened one should take it for one of the enchanting
               fictions of <persName ref="#Defoe_D">Defoe</persName>--Nothing but <title ref="#RobinsonCrusoe_DD">Robinson Crusoe</title> was ever so vividly
               real<del rend="squiggle" unit="word" n="1"/> I thought I had done with books--but I find I have not
               --<persName ref="#Jonson_B">Ben Jonson</persName>'s <title ref="#Sad_Shepherd_BJ">Sad Shepherd</title>is a fragment of a
               Pastoral Drama said to have been left unfinished in consequence of the ill success of
               his friend <persName ref="#Fletcher_John">Fletcher</persName>'s exquisite <title ref="#FaithfulShepherdess_JF">Faithful
                  Shepherdess</title>--only two acts &amp; a scene remain, but they are enchanting--
               not in <rs type="person" ref="#Jonson_B">old Ben</rs>'s common Dramatic style, so stiff &amp; artificial--but in the sweet
               &amp; tender manner of some of his beautiful lyrics--If finished it would have been one of the
               finest things in the language--the story relates to--
               <title ref="#GammerGurton">Gammer Gurton's <pb n="3"/>Needle</title> is quite another matter--you know that it
               is the oldest English play--&amp; really it is one of the most diverting--coarse
               enough to be true but exceedingly fresh &amp; frolicsome &amp; funny &amp; not at all
               unintelligible--<persName ref="#James_Miss">Miss James</persName> who is <del rend="crossout" unit="word" n="2">by
                  far</del><hi rend="superscript">one of</hi> the most elegant person of my
               acquaintance says she likes it better than any comedy in the language--one of the
               characters in it always put me in mind of <persName ref="#Edie_Ochiltree">
                  Edie Ochiltree</persName>--not in <add place="above"><metamark function="insertion" rend="caret">his</metamark></add> supernatural
               capacity--<del rend="squiggle" unit="word" n="1"/> which you dislike so
               much--but in his better vocation of a merry old beggar--that
                  <title ref="#Antiquary">"Antiquary"</title> after all is my favourite of the whole set of Scotch
               novels--it is written with more verve--is more a pure exertion of Intellect--seems to be the favorite of the Author.--&amp; above all is the least popular among the novel reading young Misses whose praise is not fame. There are more faults than in any including <persName ref="#Elspeth">Old Elspeth</persName> &amp; all the <unclear>ford</unclear> story--as well as that incredible <persName ref="#Dousterwivel_WS">Dousterwivel</persName>--&amp; still it is my favorite--Tell me is it your's? </p><metamark rend="#jerk"/><p> you are very good to the <rs type="person" ref="#Fisher_John">Bishop of Salisbury</rs> to assign his "distractions" as a reason for this thefts--or an excuse--but did you never observe that your absent people sometimes make very good use of their absences? I had a friend--an old <persName>Portuguese Countess</persName> who came here when the rest of <del rend="squiggles" unit="word" n="1"><supplied resp="#lmw">the</supplied></del><add place="above">her</add> tribe went to <placeName ref="#Brazil">the Brazils</placeName>--she could not bear to be beaten at Chess--&amp; being like the Bishop very absent, always when she saw the game going against her used to stare about a little--sweep the men off the board and get up with a <foreign>"Finisons!--J'ai de distractions!"</foreign> I never knew her to have "distraction" when she was winning in my life--And some such useful fit of absence seized the <rs type="person" ref="#Fisher_John">Right Revd.</rs> when he forgot to return <del rend="squiggles" unit="word" n="1"/>poor <persName ref="#Dickinson_Charles">Mr. Dickinson</persName>'s <unclear/> and <persName ref="#Rembrandt">Rembrandt</persName>s--How you love to laugh at my pedantry!--Well I do think the elements are in me &amp; that if I knew any thing at all I really should be a Pedant <pb n="4"/> But I was full of those fine etchings when I <del rend="squiggles" unit="word" n="1">talked</del><add place="above">wrote</add> to you &amp; could not help talking of them--<unclear>Weinotter's</unclear> are chiefly little tiny <del rend="squiggles" unit="word" n="1"/><add place="above">landscapes</add> on slips of paper--abundantly sweet &amp; delicate &amp; graceful--&amp; <persName ref="#Dickinson_Charles">Mr. Dickinson</persName> says rare.</p><metamark rend="#jerk"/><p>I have just heard that the <persName ref="#GeoIII">King</persName> is dead--Poor venerable old Man!--It is fortunate for you that my paper is nearly filled &amp; the servant waiting to take my letter into <placeName ref="#Reading_city">Reading</placeName> or I should have vented to you, my ever kindest &amp; most indulgent friend, some of that fullness of thought &amp; feeling which such an event forces into every mind!</p><metamark rend="#jerk"/><p>Adieu! Pray write soon--&amp; give us a good account of you all--My <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Father</persName> and <persName ref="#Russell_M">Mother</persName> join in kindest compliments, &amp; I am always, my dear <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir William</persName></p><closer><lb/>Most sincerely &amp; affectionately <choice><sic>your's</sic><reg>yours</reg></choice><lb/><persName ref="#MRM">M.R. Mitford</persName>.</closer><postscript><p>Pray forgive my blobs and blunders</p><p><date when="1820-02-02">Feb<hi rend="superscript">y</hi> 2<hi rend="supserscript">nd</hi></date>--Have you read <title ref="#SpencesAnec">Spence's Anecotes</title>? I have just finished them--a delightful chitchat book after the manner of <persName ref="#Boswell">Boswell</persName><persName ref="#Pope_Alex">Pope</persName> being the hero. I never saw <persName ref="#Pope_Alex">Pope</persName> to such advantage--nor <persName ref="#Bolinbroke">Bolingbroke</persName>--<persName ref="#Addison_Joseph">Addison</persName> cuts a very shabby figure indeed--How very out-of-fashion the critical remarks seem now! a list of English Prose writers &amp; neither <persName ref="#Taylor_Jer">Jeremy Taylor</persName> nor <persName ref="#Walton_I">Isaac Walton</persName>, nor <persName ref="#Brown_Thos">Sir Thomas Brown</persName> so much as hinted at!--Observations on English Poets &amp; <persName ref="#Sackville_Chas">Lord Dorset</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#Wilmot_John">Rochester</persName> &amp; the two Dukes of Buckingham examined &amp; sifted &amp; talked about as if they were worth finding fault with!--What a famous text book this of <persName ref="#Spence_Jos">Spence</persName>'s will be for one of <persName ref="#Dickinson_Charles">Mr. Dickinson</persName>'s long lectures! How he will glory in these opinions positive &amp; negative these omissions &amp; <choice><sic>commisions</sic><reg>commissions</reg></choice>! How he will buffet me with <persName ref="#Spence_Jos">Mr. Spence</persName> &amp; knock me down with <persName ref="#Pope_Alex">Mr. Pope</persName>!  Excellent sport for him!--&amp; no very bad fun for me.--no baby there yet.--I wonder very much when I shall get a frank--If I don't get one soon my letter will be too heavy--Do you know this calamity did actually befell me once with <persName ref="#James_Miss">Miss James</persName>--I waited for a cover, &amp; wrote on &amp; on,--till I filled four sheets and was forced to send them by the Coach. Good bye my dear Friend. I have at last pulled the wax off to lighten my packet--for the half dozenth time Adieu dear Friend.</p></postscript>
               <!-- LMW:  need to add the additional four leaves of the letter, including the address. 2015 10 10 --></div></body><back>
   <!-- backlist thus far pulled 2015 10 09 LMW--></back></text></TEI>