<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><?xml-model href="http://ebeshero.github.io/MRMValidate.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title xml:id="MRM1774">Letter to <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir William Elford</persName>, <date when="1821-02-08"> February 8,
                    1821</date>.</title><author ref="#MRM">Mary Russell Mitford</author><editor ref="#mco">Molly C. O'Donnell</editor><sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford
                    Project</orgName></sponsor><sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor><principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal><respStmt><resp>Transcription and coding by</resp><persName ref="#mco">Molly C. O'Donnell</persName> <!--2015-10-06 mco: header updated.--></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Proofing and corrections by</resp><persName ref="#lmw">Lisa Wilson</persName><!--2015-09-27 lmw: Proofed against ms. --><persName ref="#ebb">Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName><!--2015-09-29 ebb: only spot checked the code and repaired some coding errors.--></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>First digital edition in TEI, date: <date when="2014-07-29">July 29, 2014</date>. P5.</edition><respStmt><resp>Edition made with help from photos taken by</resp><orgName>Digital Mitford editors</orgName></respStmt><respStmt><orgName>Digital Mitford</orgName><resp> photo files: <idno>8Feb1821SirWilliamElford6b.jpg, 8Feb1821SirWilliamElford6a.jpg, 8Feb1821SirWilliamElford5c.jpg, 8Feb1821SirWilliamElford5a.jpg, 8Feb1821SirWilliamElford5b.jpg, 8Feb1821SirWilliamElford4a.jpg, 8Feb1821SirWilliamElford4b.jpg, 8Feb1821SirWilliamElford3b.jpg, 8Feb1821SirWilliamElford3a.jpg, 8Feb1821SirWilliamElford2b.jpg, 8Feb1821SirWilliamElford2a.jpg, 8Feb1821SirWilliamElford1b.jpg, 8Feb1821SirWilliamElford1a.jpg</idno></resp></respStmt></editionStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority><pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace><date>2014</date><availability><p>Reproduced by courtesy of the <orgName ref="#ReadingCL">Reading Central Library</orgName>.</p><licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                        License</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Mitford Letters: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><repository ref="#ReadingCL">Reading Central Library</repository><collection>The letters of Mary Russell Mitford, vol. 4, 1819-1823</collection><idno>qB/TU/MIT Vol. 4 ff.430 Horizon No.: 1361550</idno></msIdentifier><head>Letter from <persName ref="#MRM">Mary Russell Mitford</persName> to <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm"/>Sir William Elford, <date when="1821-02-08">8 February 1821</date>. </head><physDesc><objectDesc><supportDesc><support><p>Folio sheet of <material>paper</material> folded in half to form six
                                        quarto pages, with correspondence on 1-6 and address leaf on page 6,
                                        then folded in thirds twice more and sealed for posting.</p><p>Address leaf bearing one postmark: partial black stamp that is illegible<stamp/></p></support></supportDesc></objectDesc><sealDesc><p>Red wax seal</p></sealDesc></physDesc></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><handNotes><handNote xml:id="rc" medium="red_crayon">Red crayon or thick red pencil. Probably a
                    different hand from Mitford's drawing a diagonal line across pages 1-6, though only visible across pages 2, 4, 5 and 6.</handNote><handNote corresp="#pencil" medium="pencil">Someone cataloging the letters, apparently other than Mitford, numbered each on page 1. This page one numbered 26.</handNote><handNote corresp="#pencil" medium="pencil">Someone cataloging the letters wrote "To Sir W. Elford" at the top left of page 1, numbered 26, possibly the same hand.</handNote><handNote corresp="#pencil" medium="pencil">Someone cataloging the letters wrote at the top right of page 1, numbered 26, "date on see frank" in the upper right-hand corner of the same page, possibly the same hand.</handNote><handNote corresp="#pencil" medium="pencil">Someone cataloging the letters wrote the corrected date as Feb. 8th 1821 in pencil below Mitford's, possibly altered in black ink, date February 18th, 1821, at the top left of page 1, numbered 26. <!--@mco ebb: I think the black_ink editor (probably Harness) writes "date on see frank" and this just sends the reader to the address leaf. I don't see a franking mark, but I do see a date there: February 10 1821, and I think this is what our editor is referring to.--></handNote><handNote corresp="#pencil" medium="pencil">Someone cataloging the letters wrote "1821" to the left side on page 6 possibly the same hand.</handNote><handNote medium="black_ink" xml:id="black_ink">There are some notes in the text that in black ink including checkmarks in various places and the possibly altered date on page 1 to Feb 18th.</handNote></handNotes></profileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><p>Mitford’s spelling and punctuation are retained, except where a word is split at the
                    end of a line and the beginning of the next in the manuscript. Where Mitford’s
                    spelling and hyphenation of words deviates from the standard, in order to facilitate
                    searching we are using the TEI elements “choice," “sic," and “reg" to encode both
                    Mitford’s spelling and the regular international standard of Oxford English spelling,
                    following the first listed spelling in the Oxford English Dictionary. The long s and
                    ligatured forms are not encoded.</p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc></teiHeader><text><front><div type="witness"><listWit><witness xml:id="mco">Molly O'Donnell</witness><witness xml:id="LEst1870"><bibl><title>The Life of Mary Russell Mitford Related in a Selection from Her
                            Letters to Her Friends, Second and Revised edition</title>, 3 vols., Ed.
                            <author>Alfred Guy Kingan L’Estrange</author>. <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>:
                            <publisher>Richard Bentley</publisher>, <date>1870</date>. </bibl></witness></listWit></div></front><body><div type="letter"><opener><dateline><placeName ref="#ThreeMileCross">Three Mile Cross</placeName><date when="1821-02-08">February 8<handShift resp="#black_ink"/><add hand="#black_ink">18</add><hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1821.</date><!-- lmw:  I believe there is a lighter penciled date underneath reading Feb 8th 1821. Does anyone else see? Same pencil as #20? --></dateline></opener><p>Your last kind letter, my dear <rs type="person" ref="#Elford_SirWm">Friend</rs>, gave me more than usual pleasure--so you scold me, do you? Well that is greater proof of kindness than I ever expected to receive. Pray scold me again, for I like it. It makes me laugh &amp; glow <handShift resp="#black_ink"/><add hand="#black_ink">checkmark</add> &amp; blush, Like a tickled child--who says "<unclear><supplied resp="#mco">sir</supplied></unclear><!-- lmw: I think the word is Ah or Oh--> don't" &amp; yet puts herself in the way to be teased &amp; pleased again. I would be exceedingly disappointed to be let alone. Scold on, my dear Friend. No fear but I shall give you causes. That expression was very affected--I wonder how I came by it--for I have often remarked the idiom in others as "the very quintessence of affectation." But I am delighted to find that you don't think me affected in general, for I can tell you that amongst two or three of my friends (not the most intimate however) I have that bad name--<handShift resp="#black_ink"/><add hand="#black_ink">checkmark</add>very unjustly in my opinion. I have gained it by over frankness <handShift resp="#black_ink"/><add hand="#black_ink">checkmark</add>--by letting out real opinions &amp; little ends of character which because unlike their own seem impossible; <del rend="squiggles"/><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/><add place="above"><metamark place="below" function="insertion" rend="caret"/>in short by</add> letting truths which nobody believes. It's astonishing what creatures of habit &amp; imitation young girls generally are--they are as alike as so many shillings &amp; sixpences &amp; have not the capacity to believe that any coin can be genuine which bears a different impress. So <persName ref="#Webb_Mary_younger">Miss Webb</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#Webb_Eliza">Miss Eliza</persName> talk scandal of their poor dear Friend &amp; say she is affected. But however as you do not, nor <persName ref="#James_Miss">Miss James</persName>, nor <persName ref="#Dickinson_Mrs">M<hi rend="superscript">rs.</hi> Dickinson</persName>, I shall console myself under my calamity. <persName ref="#Dickinson_Mrs">M<hi rend="superscript">rs.</hi> Dickinson</persName> was here yesterday. I gave her your message with which she was very much entertained--she begs her compliments in return &amp; <pb n="2"/> says she wishes both the mothers as much pleasure with their darlings as she has with hers. Her little <persName ref="#Dickinson_Daughter">Frances</persName> is a beautiful child. The most beautiful I think that I ever saw. <persName ref="#Dickinson_Mrs">M<hi rend="superscript">rs.</hi> Dickinson</persName><!--mco @ebb Mitford uses two dots under rs of every Mrs. I have recorded the superscript nature of the letters but am unsure how to record the two dots and seems like every Digital Mitford editor is doing it differently--> has had great success matchmaking lately--an amusement of which--deny it as she may--she is remarkably fond. We have a celebrated beauty hereabouts, a <persName ref="#Broughton_Betsy">Miss Broughton</persName>(<persName ref="#James_Miss">Miss James</persName>, no respecter of beauties compares her to <persName ref="#Maritornes_DQ">Maritornes the Asturian wench of the Inn</persName> in <title ref="#Don_Quixote_novel">Don Quixote</title> a fine gentlemanly dashing spirited girl--who with the usual fate of beauties attracted a good deal of admiration &amp; very little love. On the other hand there was a soft ladylike fair delicate youth with <unclear><supplied resp="#mco">sidewhiskers</supplied></unclear> <!--lmw: redwhiskers? there are only three letters before whiskers.  -->&amp; a great talent for silence the son grandson &amp; great grandson of three generations of Generals <persName>Hawley</persName>--who well born well bred &amp; well estated seemed just made to lean upon such a fine manly supporter as <persName ref="#Broughton_Betsy">Betsy Broughton</persName>. So thought <persName ref="#Dickinson_Mrs">M<hi rend="superscript">rs.</hi> Dickinson</persName>--&amp; the match is made--they are already deep in <del rend="squiggles"/><unclear><gap quantity="1" unit="char"/></unclear> settlements &amp; wedding <choice><sic>cloaths</sic><reg>clothes</reg></choice>, &amp; the <del rend="squiggles"/><unclear><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/></unclear><add place="above"><metamark place="below" function="insertion" rend="caret"/><supplied resp="#mco">marriage</supplied></add> will take place forthwith--how she brought him to the offer I cannot imagine--she says he did it all himself--but I don't believe her. I must tell you of a misfortune that befell me in this case. I was dining at <placeName ref="#Farley_Hill">Farley Hill</placeName> on the very day that it happened to strike <persName ref="#Dickinson_Mrs">M<hi rend="superscript">rs.</hi> Dickinson</persName> that they would make a <del rend="squiggles"/><unclear><gap quantity="1" unit="char"/><supplied resp="#mco">good</supplied></unclear> nice couple &amp; had the ill luck to sit next to <persName ref="#Hawley_Mr">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Hawley</persName> at table, who held his tongue in the most provoking manner possible, &amp; when I made him talk, talked, not nonesense but the dullest gravest prosiest sense, vapid, stale, commonplace, a hundred years behind the spirit of the age, such tame moralities as the first <persName ref="#Hawley_GeneralSr">General Hawley</persName> might have discussed with one of the <persName ref="#Queen_Anne">Queen Anne</persName>'s maids of honor. Well after dinner, as I was standing wearily before the drawing room fire indulging in the ennui engendered of <persName ref="#Hawley_Mr">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Hawley</persName>'s <pb n="3"/> silence &amp; conversation, <persName ref="#Dickinson_Mrs">M<hi rend="superscript">rs.</hi> Dickinson</persName> full <handShift resp="#black_ink"/><add hand="#black_ink">checkmark</add> of her new project &amp; wanting my assistance to accomplish it brought <persName ref="#Broughton_Betsy">Miss Broughton</persName> up to me &amp; asked in her quick manner <q>"How do you like <persName ref="#Hawley_Mr">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Hawley</persName>'s face? What does it express?"</q>--<q>"Nothing"</q> said I in a lazy truthtelling tone--little dreaming that I was giving this flattering opinion before his future lady &amp; love--&amp; now must I apologise, like <persName ref="#Bennet_Mrs_fict">M<hi rend="superscript">rs.</hi> Bennett</persName> to <persName ref="#Lizzy_fict">Lizzy</persName> for having so much disliked <persName ref="#Darcy_fict">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Darcy</persName>--do you remember? In our old friend <title ref="#Pride_and_Prejudice">Pride &amp; Prejudice</title>. This <del rend="squiggles"/><gap quantity="1" unit="char"/>awkward blunder notwithstanding--&amp; notwithstanding my inevitable habit of laughing at serious things I am really glad of the match--they are both very worthy &amp; well-meaning young people though its a pity they cannot change sexes, &amp; there is great chance of their improving one another &amp; greater still of their being happy together--which is a much better thing.</p><metamark rend="jerk"/><p>Have you read <title ref="#Melmoth_CM">Melmoth</title>? I don't advise you so to do--any more than I should advise you to have the nightmare. And yet it's a very grand thing. I never read much of <persName ref="#Maturin_Charles">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Maturin</persName>'s writing before--<title ref="#Bertram_CM">Bertram</title> I did not like &amp; just skimmed <title ref="#Women_CM">Women</title> I did not like &amp; left off in the middle, &amp; <title ref="#Montorio_CM">Montorio</title> &amp; the rest I never met with. But <title ref="#Melmoth_CM">Melmoth</title> I have read fairly through almost without taking breath--nobody can lay that down--&amp; yet nobody I should think would ever <del rend="squiggles"/><gap quantity="1" unit="char"/> wish to read it a second time--it is so inconceivably painful. But there's power, terrible power--some matchless painting of external scenery-&amp; some touches of pathos &amp; horror equal to any written except the elder Dramatists. With all these merits there are a thousand faults--particularly a font of grandiloquence which is you know the patrimony of <placeName ref="#Ireland"><country>Ireland</country></placeName> from <persName ref="#Owenson_S">Lady Morgan</persName> to <persName ref="#Phillips_Chas">Charles <choice><sic>Philipps</sic><reg>Phillips</reg></choice></persName>.--Now I am going to talk about <title ref="#Kenilworth_WS">Kenilworth</title> but you may read on <pb n="4"/> for a little till you meet with a hook--&amp; truly if I were to have a wager I would bet that you went on after you met with the hook. What! Shall there be a <persName ref="#Bluebeard_fict">Blue Beard</persName>'s chamber in a letter &amp; you have the key &amp; not open it! Is not a man as curious as a woman? I am quite certain that you will read on--but I shall put the hooks notwithstanding Now for it [<title ref="#Kenilworth_WS">Kenilworth</title> seems to be the most painful of any book that <persName ref="#Scott_Wal">Walter Scott</persName> has ever written--the <title ref="#Bride_of_Lammermoor_WS">Bride of Lammermoor</title> not excepted. The catastrophe hangs over one like a sense of real calamity--it is like some over time misfortune--long expected--&amp; yet when it comes even more crushing than fear had anticipated--There is a sense of helpless grief--of powerful pity--I would rather read <title ref="#Melmoth_CM">Melmoth</title> again than <title ref="#Kenilworth_WS">Kenilworth</title>. Besides there is too much villainy--the author has not protected us as he generally does by interposing some sweet &amp; frank &amp; delightful character between his knaves &amp; villains &amp; the reader's feelings. And we the less forgive this from the age in which he has placed the story--an age of fine spirits of <unclear><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/><supplied resp="#lmw">fierce</supplied></unclear> intellect--of noble during. Why such men as <persName ref="#Shakespeare">Shakespeare</persName><persName ref="#Raleigh_Wal">Raleigh</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#Spenser_Edmund">Spenser</persName> must have purified the very air--the atmosphere that they breathed could not have nourished a <persName ref="#Varney_Kenil">Varney</persName> or a <persName ref="#Lambourne_Kenil">Lambourne</persName>. <title ref="#Kenilworth_WS">Kenilworth</title> is very powerful too--full of fine delineation of manners--&amp; <persName ref="#ElizI">Queen Elizabeth</persName> is a matchless portrait--It is much stronger &amp; more finished than the <title ref="#Abbot_WS">Abbot</title> or the <title ref="#Monastery">Monastery</title>, though I prefer either of them--&amp; will probably be cried up as a second <title ref="#Ivanhoe">Ivanhoe</title>. But I regret to find his spirit saddened &amp; darkened--I fear we shall have no more <persName ref="#Oldbuck_Jonathan">Oldbucks</persName> or <persName ref="#Dandie_Dinmont">Dandie Dinmonts</persName> or <persName ref="#Baron_Bradwardine">Barons of Bradwardine</persName>. Tell me what you think of <title ref="#Kenilworth_WS">Kenilworth</title>] And now goodbye for a day or two my dear <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir William</persName>--Here is quite enough for one dose--Is there not?--</p><pb n="5"/><p><date when="1821-02-09">Feb. 9<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></date>--I have a frank in view &amp; shall therefore finish hastily--Pray do you see those <bibl>magazines</bibl> respecting one of which I made my false step? If you do you will have seen that there has been something like a battle between the Editors, <persName ref="#Lockhart_JG">Mr. Lockhart</persName> [<persName ref="#Scott_Wal">Sir W. Scott</persName>'s son in law] <persName ref="#Lockhart_JG">John Gibson Lockhart</persName> alias <persName ref="#Morris_DrP">D<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Morris</persName>, alias <persName ref="#North_Christopher">Christopher North</persName> &amp;c &amp;c &amp;c editor of <title ref="#Blackwoods">Blackwood</title>'s<note resp="#lmw">Here, <persName ref="#MRM">Mitford</persName> seems to believe that <persName ref="#Lockhart_JG">Lockhart</persName>, editor of <title ref="#Blackwoods">Blackwood</title>'s Magazine, wrote under pseudonyms <persName ref="#North_Christopher">Christopher North</persName> and <persName ref="#Morris_DrP">Dr. Morris</persName><persName ref="#North_Christopher">Christopher North</persName> was actually the pen name of Blackwood's writer <persName ref="#Wilson_John">John Wilson</persName>. <persName ref="#Morris_DrP">"Peter Morris"</persName> was the pseudonym Lockhart used in  <title ref="#Peters_Letters_novel">Peter's Letters to his Kinfolk</title>.</note> challenged <persName ref="#Scott_John">John Scott</persName> Editor of <title ref="#LondonMag">Baldwin</title>'s--who upon some etiquette of Editorship or the Duell (which I as a woman <gap reason="torn" quantity="1" unit="word"/><supplied resp="#mco">cannot</supplied> of course understand) refused to fight &amp; has pub<gap reason="torn" quantity="6" unit="chars"/><supplied resp="#lmw">lished</supplied> the documents. These documents are very diverting chiefly from their profound &amp; statesman like gravity--You will find them at the begining of the last n<hi rend="superscript">o.</hi> of the <placeName ref="#London_city">London</placeName>. <title ref="#LondonMag">Baldwin's London</title>. For the other is a trumpery catchpenny thing--<title ref="#LondonMag">Baldwin</title>'s is the "real Simon Pure." <!-- LMW:  NEEDs footnote. Find my other note on "the real simon pure." -->--</p><metamark rend="jerk"/><p>Pray what do you mean to do with yourself this Spring? Are you bound for <placeName ref="#Bath_city">Bath</placeName> or for <placeName ref="#London_city">London</placeName>? In a word have we any chance of seeing you? You must not pass us again--Will you--I am fairly sick of the <persName ref="#Queen_Caroline">Queen</persName>. So really will not say another word of her except that your mark of <unclear><supplied resp="#mco">Shippification</supplied></unclear> is the very best thing I have seen on the subject.--Very glad you like <persName ref="#Palmer_CF">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Palmer</persName>'s politics--though as to moderation--he is about as moderate as <persName ref="#Burdett_F">Sir Francis Burdett</persName> or <persName ref="#Hobhouse_JC">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Hobhouse</persName>. I have not seen him these six months or more--his <placeName ref="#Reading_city">Reading</placeName> constituents complain of his absence &amp; I am very much afraid that a candidate with money &amp; residence would oust our poor friend in spite of all the patriotism of <placeName ref="#Reading_city">Reading</placeName> &amp; <del rend="squiggles"/><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/><supplied resp="#mco">the</supplied> its Members. Don't tell <persName ref="#Palmer_Mad">Lady Madelina</persName> that I say so!--Pray is it true that your friend &amp; neighbour <persName ref="#Morpeth_GH">Sir Morpeth</persName>threatened to bring in <persName ref="#Cobbett_Wm">Cobbett</persName> if he were not released? This is the Whig story--&amp; truly if he did I think he was right--He &amp; <pb n="6"/><persName ref="#Swan_Mr">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Swan</persName> seem to have been very unjustly imprisoned--Whilst the present system lasts nothing can be so inconsistent as to make sacrifices to the purity of Cornish Boroughs.--Well I won't begin talking politics.--Adieu my dear friend. Write to me very soon--&amp; believe me ever                           
                </p><lb/><closer><salute> most gratefully yours</salute><signed><app><lem wit="#mco">MR Mitford.</lem><rdg wit="#LEst1870">M. R. Mitford.</rdg><!-- lmw:  I agree with L'estrange here.  I see M.R. Mitford. --></app></signed></closer><lb/><postscript><p> Kindest regards from <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#Russell_M">Mama</persName>--I hope you have been all quite well this unhealthy winter.--Once more goodbye my dear Friend--Pray write soon.</p></postscript><closer><address><addrLine><placeName ref="#Reading_city">Reading</placeName><date when="1821-02-10">February <unclear><supplied resp="#lmw">Ten</supplied>&gt;</unclear> 1821</date><lb/></addrLine><addrLine>S<hi rend="superscript">ir</hi> W<hi rend="superscript">m</hi> Elford Bart<lb/></addrLine><addrLine><placeName><district ref="#Bickham_village">Bickham</district></placeName><lb/></addrLine><addrLine><persName ref="#Monck_JB">J. B. Monck</persName><placeName ref="#Plymouth_city">Plymouth</placeName></addrLine></address></closer></div></body><back><div>
                
                <!-- Compiled 2015-10-03 LMW --></div></back></text></TEI>