<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><?xml-model href="http://ebeshero.github.io/MRMValidate.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Letter to <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir William Elford</persName>, 1 July
               1821.</title><author ref="#MRM">Mary Russell Mitford</author><editor>Molly C. O'Donnell</editor><sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford
               Project</orgName></sponsor><sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor><principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal><respStmt><resp>Transcription and coding by</resp><persName ref="#mco">Molly C. O'Donnell</persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Proofing and corrections by</resp><persName ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</persName><!--LMW: Proofed against ms. 2016-09-02. Needs updated header.--></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>First digital edition in TEI, date: 4 June 2014. P5.</edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority><pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace><date>2014</date><availability><p>Reproduced by courtesy of the <placeName>Reading Central Library</placeName>.</p><licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                  License</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Mitford Letters: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><repository ref="#ReadingCL">Reading Central Library</repository><collection>The letters of Mary Russell Mitford, vol. 4, 1819-1823</collection><idno>qB/TU/MIT Vol. 4 ff.441 Horizon No.: 1361550</idno><!--Update metadata numbers?--></msIdentifier><head>Letter from Mary Russell Mitford to Sir William Elford, <date>1 July 1821</date>. </head><physDesc><objectDesc><supportDesc><support><p>Folio sheet of <material>paper</material> folded in half to form four
                              quarto pages, with correspondence on 1-3 and address leaf on page 4,
                              then folded in thirds twice more and sealed for posting.</p><p>Address leaf bearing the following postmarks: double circle Duty stamp
                              illegible date other than year 1821</p>.                            
                        </support></supportDesc></objectDesc><sealDesc><p>Red wax seal</p></sealDesc></physDesc></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><handNotes><handNote xml:id="rc" medium="red_crayon">Red crayon or thick red pencil. Probably a
               different hand from Mitford's drawing a diagonal line across pages 1-3 and an end parenthesis mark on Page 2 and an opening parenthesis on Page 3 of this letter.</handNote><handNote corresp="#pencil" medium="pencil">Someone cataloging the letters, apparently
               other than Mitford, numbered each on page 1. This page one numbered 33.</handNote><handNote corresp="#pencil" medium="pencil">Someone cataloging the letters, apparently
               other than Mitford, wrote "To Sir W. Elford." at the top left of page 1, numbered 33, possibly by same hand.</handNote><handNote xml:id="black_ink" medium="black_ink">There are some notes in the text that are not made by Mitford in black ink including an X that corresponds to a note at the bottom of the first page that reads "Sir W Elfords intended marriage with Mrs. Waldron"</handNote></handNotes></profileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><p>Mitford’s spelling and punctuation are retained, except where a word is split at the
               end of a line and the beginning of the next in the manuscript. Where Mitford’s
               spelling and hyphenation of words deviates from the standard, in order to facilitate
               searching we are using the TEI elements “choice," “sic," and “reg" to encode both
               Mitford’s spelling and the regular international standard of Oxford English spelling,
               following the first listed spelling in the Oxford English Dictionary. The long s and
               ligatured forms are not encoded.</p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc></teiHeader><text><front><div type="witness"><listWit><witness xml:id="ebb">Elisa Beshero-Bondar</witness><witness xml:id="LEst1870"><bibl><title>The Life of Mary Russell Mitford Related in a Selection from Her
                        Letters to Her Friends, Second and Revised edition</title>, 3 vols., Ed.
                        <author>Alfred Guy Kingan L’Estrange</author>. <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>:
                        <publisher>Richard Bentley</publisher>, <date>1870</date>. </bibl></witness></listWit></div></front><body><div type="letter"><opener><dateline><date when="1821-07-01">July 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> 1821.</date><name type="place">Three Mile Cross</name></dateline></opener><p>Yes, <persName ref="#Dickinson_Mrs">M<hi rend="superscript">rs.<!--@ebb Mitford uses two dots under rs of every Mrs. I have recorded the superscript nature of the letters but am unsure how to record the two dots and seems like every Digital Mitford editor is doing it differently--></hi> Dickinson</persName> had told the news, my dear friend--did you suppose it possible she would not? She was too much interested in it herself &amp; knew so well how I should be interested, that she did not wait till we met but wrote a note the moment she reached home to convey the information <handShift resp="#black_ink"/><add hand="#black_ink">X</add><note resp="#MRM">Sir W Elfords intended marriage with Mrs. Waldron</note><!-- LMW:  is this a handshift?  I think we decided these were probably MRM's in a different ink. How did we code? -->--&amp; I have been watching the papers ever since that I might at the very first moment send warm congratulations, the unfeigned <choice><sic>goodwishes</sic><reg>good wishes</reg></choice> <!--LMW:  Probably this is kind of thing we should be silently corrected, as we do with I am written I am?-->with which my whole heart is filled--My <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Father</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#Russell_M">Mother</persName> join in them most sincerely--God bless you my dear Friend--and all whom you love!--<persName ref="#Dickinson_Mrs">M<hi rend="superscript">rs.</hi> Dickinson</persName> has the pleasure of being slightly acquainted with <persName ref="#Elford_MrsE">M<hi rend="superscript">rs.</hi><unclear>Waldron</unclear></persName>persName&gt; &amp; speaks of her with the highest respect &amp; consideration--she was so desirous to see you that she had half a mind to give up her journey for a day to meet you at <persName ref="#Elford_MrsE">M<hi rend="superscript">rs.</hi> Wall</persName>'s at breakfast &amp; she certainly would have had a whole mind had she not left that little angel of a brat of hers in the country &amp; made her husband stay to take care of it. Once more my dear friend accept our sincerest congratulations both on this event &amp; on the intended marriage of your daughter--May they prove equally happy!</p><p>Besides the very great pleasure which your letters always give me &amp; especially this one, I had great delight in seeing the handwriting of <persName ref="#Palmer_CF">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Palmer</persName>. I don't think that I have seen any part of him since last <date when="1820-09">September</date>--I shall do him the honour of taking to him as franker again--for my dear &amp; kind friend <persName ref="#Monck_JB">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Monck</persName> whose frankful bounty knows no limits <unclear><supplied resp="#mco">talks</supplied></unclear> of going to <placeName ref="#Spain">Spain</placeName><pb n="2"/><del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="chars"/></del> during the recess &amp; it would be rather too much to send one's letters round by <placeName>Madrid</placeName> even if the privilege extended beyond <placeName ref="#England">England</placeName>--I cannot think what he expects to see in <placeName ref="#Spain">Spain</placeName>--but the travelling mania has seized him &amp; having seen every other country in <placeName ref="#Europe">Europe</placeName> he is going to pay a visit to the beloved <persName ref="#Ferdinand_I">Ferdinand</persName>--He had much better stay in <placeName ref="#England">England</placeName> &amp; direct my letters <handShift resp="#rc"/><add hand="#red_crayon">)</add>.</p><p>It is so long since I have written to you anything more than a note, that I forget whether I told you, I had been to <placeName ref="#SeymourCt">Seymour</placeName>'s near <placeName ref="#Marlow">Marlow</placeName> on the awkward business of dividing the late <persName ref="#Johnson_Mr">M <hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Johnson</persName>'s books between <persName ref="#Northmore_Thos">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Northmore</persName> &amp; <rs type="person" ref="#Johnson_Miss">his sister</rs>--The political books were left to <persName ref="#Northmore_Thos">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> N.</persName> &amp; the others to her <add place="above"><metamark place="below" function="insertion" rend="caret"/>(<persName ref="#Johnson_Miss">Miss Johnson</persName>)</add>, &amp; as <persName ref="#Northmore_Thos">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Northmore</persName> would not come to select them himself she sent for me to assist in the division &amp; to catalogue &amp; arrange the library. Never to be sure had mortal such a job since the <persName>Princess <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="chars"/></del></persName> in the fairy tale who was set to select the plumage of every bird from a great hall full of feathers. Fancy to yourself a large room &amp; a long dark closet literally filled with books all in a mass--no two <add place="above"><metamark place="below" function="insertion" rend="caret"/>volumes</add> together--&amp; very often single volumes come apart with damp &amp; age &amp; lying four or five yards asunder--&amp; no one to help but a <persName ref="#Johnson_Miss">mistress</persName> half blind &amp; a <persName>maid</persName> wholly stupid--The Library was a singularly rich historical collection in almost all languages--&amp; I cannot help thinking that the greater part of that <del rend="squiggles"/><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/> relating to English History was intended to be included in <persName ref="#Northmore_Thos">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Northmore</persName>'s Legacy--but <persName ref="#Johnson_Miss">Miss Johnson</persName> thought otherwise--she stuck to the letter--so she cheated the poor dear man--or rather made him cheat himself--by leaving him a catalogue of the doubtful books &amp; begging him to mark those he would like to have--I wish they had all gone to him--It was a pity to part such a collection, &amp; they will not sell for much in the present state of the book market. It was <pb n="3"/> a curious trait of political bigotry that amongst thirty or forty Histories of England (more than I thought had been written) there was no <title ref="#HistEngland_Hume">copy of Hume</title>. To make amends there were two editions of <rs type="person" ref="#hume">his</rs><title>Essays</title> I grieved to leave this beautiful place, &amp; the more as it went from his family--being held on a lease of lives which he had neglected to renew till his health was in such a state that the terms asked were too exorbitant to be thought of--more especially as <add place="above"><metamark place="below" function="insertion" rend="caret"/><persName ref="#Johnson_Miss">Miss Johnson</persName></add> his only near relation is comfortably though not affluently provided for--which I did not know till the books were divided--or I should certainly have made a stronger effort for <persName ref="#Northmore_Thos">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> N.</persName></p><p><handShift resp="#rc"/><add hand="#red_crayon">(</add> I had the honour a week or two ago to be introduced to your friend <persName ref="#Bowles_Wm">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Bowles</persName> the Poet. I must tell you the story. Going in <persName ref="#Valpy_Richard">D<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Valpy</persName>'s the back way, I met the old <persName ref="#Newman_but">Butler</persName>--<q>"Are the ladies in the parlour <persName ref="#Newman_but">Newman</persName>?"</q><q>"Yes, ma'am--And ma'am there is <persName ref="#Bowles_Wm">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Bowles</persName>, the Poet"</q> quoth <persName ref="#Newman_but">Newman</persName> Well I thought I shall be very glad to see him &amp; in I walked--<persName ref="#Valpy_Richard">The Doctor</persName> met me at the do<gap reason="torn" quantity="2" unit="chars"/><supplied resp="#mco">or</supplied> snatched my hand led me triumphantly up to the window where <persName ref="#Bowles_Wm">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Bowles</persName> was standing &amp; then snatched his hand &amp; endeavoured to join the two after the fashion of the marriage ceremony (you know how that is dear <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir William</persName>) introducing him to me as "<persName ref="#Bowles_Wm">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Bowles</persName> the Poet" but calling me as I have since remembered nothing but "Mary"--<persName ref="#Bowles_Wm">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Bowles </persName>rather astounded drew back--I astounded in my turn at such a way of receiving the daughter of an old acquaintance (for my <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Father</persName> has known him these thirty years) drew back too--&amp; between us we left the dear <persName ref="#Valpy_Richard">Doctor</persName> in worse consternation than either standing alone in the window--A minute after <persName ref="#Valpy_Penelope">Miss Valpy</persName><note resp="#lmw">Valpy daughter's identification uncertain. Mary Valpy was married at the time of writing, so presumably Penelope, the eldest daughter living at home, is referred to here.</note> asked after <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">D<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Mitford</persName> &amp; all was immediately right--<persName ref="#Bowles_Wm">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Bowles</persName> was very pleasant &amp; sociable talked a great deal of <persName ref="#Byron">Lord Byron</persName> &amp; the <persName ref="#Pope_Alex">Pope</persName> question in which we exactly agree--&amp; in which from not having read <title>the prosy pamphlet</title> in which he has so marred his own good cause I <pb n="4"/> was able to agree with him most conscientiously without any of the drawback on my civility which the perusal of the aforementioned wretched pamphlet would have occasioned--"Pray <add place="above"><metamark place="below" function="insertion" rend="caret"/><supplied resp="#mco">sir</supplied></add> do you like his wife? Is she not the coarse cold hard woman? And rather vulgarish? All this she seemed to me. He is very unaffected &amp; agreeable.--Well I write not perhaps much longer--for with so much to do &amp; to think of a trespass it must be--You will write to me when you have time--&amp; you will persuade <persName ref="#Elford_MrsE">Mrs. Waldron</persName>--<persName ref="#Elford_MrsE">Lady Elford</persName>--into partaking of the family indulgence towards your poor little Correspondent--my <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Father</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#Russell_M">Mother</persName> join me in rejoicing at <persName ref="#Elford_J">Mr. Elford</persName>'s recovery as well as in best remembrances &amp; goodwishes--&amp; I am ever my dear <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir William</persName></p><lb/><closer><salute> most sincerely &amp; affectionately your's</salute><signed><persName ref="#MRM">MR Mitford.</persName></signed></closer><lb/><postscript><p><title ref="#Fiesco_MRMplay">Fiesco</title> has been returned on my hands as I <choice><sic>fore saw</sic><reg>foresaw</reg></choice> &amp; I am now knee deep in another <title ref="#Foscari_MRMplay">Tragedy</title> on the subject of the Venetian <persName ref="#Doge_F_hist">Doge Foscari</persName> who was obliged to condemn his own son--I had been waiting for <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</persName>'s going to <placeName ref="#London_city">Town</placeName> to get my letters--but he puts it off so--that I have sent an authority to another friend this very night--Once more my dear Friend God bless you.  
                  </p></postscript><closer><address><addrLine><placeName ref="#London_city">London</placeName><date when="1821-07-01">July <unclear><supplied resp="#lmw">five</supplied></unclear> 1821</date></addrLine><addrLine><persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">S<hi rend="superscript">ir</hi> W<hi rend="superscript">m</hi> Elford Bart</persName></addrLine><addrLine><placeName ref="#Bickham_village">Bickham</placeName></addrLine><addrLine><placeName ref="#Plymouth_city">Plymouth</placeName></addrLine><addrLine><persName ref="#Monck_JB">J. B. Monck</persName></addrLine></address></closer></div></body><back>
         <!--Prosopography information to be added to Site Index below.-->
         <!-- LMW:  I added all new SI's directly to my add list.  2015 09-30. --></back></text></TEI>