<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><?xml-model href="http://ebeshero.github.io/MRMValidate.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Letter to <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir William Elford</persName>, 20 April
               1821.</title><author ref="#MRM">Mary Russell Mitford</author><editor>Molly C. O'Donnell</editor><sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford
               Project</orgName></sponsor><sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor><principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal><respStmt><resp>Transcription and coding by</resp><persName ref="#mco">Molly C. O'Donnell</persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Proofing and corrections by</resp><persName ref="#lmw">Lisa Wilson</persName><!--Update proofing and correction eds names.--></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>First digital edition in TEI, date: 1 June 2014. P5.</edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority><pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace><date>2014</date><availability><p>Reproduced by courtesy of the <placeName>Reading Central Library</placeName>.</p><licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                  License</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Mitford Letters: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><repository ref="#ReadingCL">Reading Central Library</repository><collection>The letters of Mary Russell Mitford, vol. 4, 1819-1823</collection><idno>qB/TU/MIT Vol. 4 ff.441 Horizon No.: 1361550</idno></msIdentifier><head>Letter from Mary Russell Mitford to Sir William Elford, <date>20 April 1821</date>. </head><physDesc><objectDesc><supportDesc><support><p>Folio sheet of <material>paper</material> folded in half to form four
                              quarto pages, with correspondence on 1-3 and address leaf on page 4,
                              then folded in thirds twice more and sealed for posting.</p><p>Address leaf bearing the following postmarks: 1) black circular
                              mileage stamp illegible, 2) red double circle Duty stamp
                              reading <date when="1821-04-23"><stamp>B<lb/>23 AP 23<lb/>1821<lb/></stamp></date></p>. 
                           <p>A large 7 denoting the fee for a single-sheet letter has been written
                              in black ink by the postal service across the address leaf.</p>
                           <!--Page 4 letter mailing info contains stray marks; 2 or 3, possibly postal charge; and someone in another hand wrote 20 April 1820.--></support></supportDesc></objectDesc><sealDesc><p>Red wax seal</p></sealDesc></physDesc></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><handNotes><handNote xml:id="rc" medium="red_crayon"> Red crayon or thick red pencil. Probably a
               different hand from Mitford's drawing a diagonal line across pages 1-3.</handNote><handNote corresp="#pencil" medium="pencil">Someone cataloging the letters, apparently
               other than Mitford, numbered each on page 1. This page one numbered 31.</handNote></handNotes></profileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><p>Mitford’s spelling and punctuation are retained, except where a word is split at the
               end of a line and the beginning of the next in the manuscript. Where Mitford’s
               spelling and hyphenation of words deviates from the standard, in order to facilitate
               searching we are using the TEI elements “choice," “sic," and “reg" to encode both
               Mitford’s spelling and the regular international standard of Oxford English spelling,
               following the first listed spelling in the Oxford English Dictionary. The long s and
               ligatured forms are not encoded.</p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc></teiHeader><text><front><div type="witness"><listWit><witness xml:id="ebb">Elisa Beshero-Bondar</witness><witness xml:id="LEst1870"><bibl><title>The Life of Mary Russell Mitford Related in a Selection from Her
                        Letters to Her Friends, Second and Revised edition</title>, 3 vols., Ed.
                        <author>Alfred Guy Kingan L’Estrange</author>. <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>:
                        <publisher>Richard Bentley</publisher>, <date>1870</date>. </bibl></witness></listWit></div></front><body><div type="letter"><opener><dateline><name type="place">Three Mile Cross</name><date when="1821-04-20">April 20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1821.</date></dateline></opener><p>I thank you very much, my ever dear &amp; kind friend, for your good humoured indulgence of my importunate request--I have given you good reason to think me a spoilt child, &amp; perhaps I shall give you still more by a trait peculiar to spoilt children &amp; which though generally regarded as an additional proof of their obstinacy &amp; self will is in reality the tribute they pay to reason in correcting their own unreasonableness. (Do you understand puzzled sentence?) In short after having coaxed and persuaded you to <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="letter"/></del><emph rend="underline">lend</emph> me the plaything I wanted, &amp; which you are afraid I shall spoil, nothing is more probable, than that I may either make no use of it at all--or that I may make the precise use which you point out. <choice><sic>Any way</sic><reg>Anyway</reg></choice>, I am glad to see these poor <rs type="letter">letters</rs> again (for I do not think that I have ever written any with so little reserve so much <foreign>con amore</foreign>) &amp; I promise you to keep them safely <emph rend="underline">for you</emph>--not to spoil them--if I can possibly help it in my way--&amp; to look them over with the view to make a Volume <add place="above"><metamark place="below" function="insertion" rend="caret"/>or Two!</add> of them if I can,--before I proceed to the <emph rend="underline">gutting</emph> process I threatened. Is this making as much amends as I can for my unreasonableness?--As to their mode of conveyance, that which I should much prefer would be your bringing them here (Do come &amp; see us my dear <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir William</persName>--but if you won't do that--there is a very safe &amp; certain mode of conveyance--<persName ref="#Monck_JB">Mr. Monck</persName> is in <placeName ref="#London_city">Town</placeName> for the <rs type="person" ref="#Magnay_C">Lord Mayor</rs>'s dinner &amp; returns <date when="1821-04-25">Wednesday</date>, &amp; if you will have the goodness to send the packet directed to me to his care No. 10 <placeName ref="#Barton_street">Barton Street</placeName><placeName ref="#Westmnstr">Westminster</placeName>--it will reach me very safely. Nevertheless as I said before I should greatly rather receive the <rs type="letter">letters</rs> from your own kind hand. It is too long since we have seen you--&amp; as to my going to <placeName ref="#London_city">Town</placeName> I have no prospect of that this spring.--You are very saucy with your Hieroglyphics &amp; as much mistaken <pb n="2"/> as a man can be. You were discreet I hope in the management of your <emph rend="underline">eyes</emph> &amp; tongue when you saw <persName ref="#Haydon">Mr. H.</persName> (I know that you have seen him.) He says the <title corresp="#Lazarus_Haydon">Lazarus</title> shall be the best picture he has painted yet, but that that shall be a nonentity if he lives to those that he will paint in the future. This is the true spirit--Is it not? Tell me what you think of <title corresp="#Gala_Richmond_TCH">a <unclear><supplied resp="#lmw">Gala</supplied></unclear> at <placeName ref="#Richmond">Richmond</placeName></title><note resp="lmw"><persName ref="#MRM">Mitford</persName> gives the title of <persName ref="#Hofland_TC">Hofland</persName>'s painting here as <title corresp="#Gala_Richmond_TCH">"A Gala at Richmond"</title>. Research has not revealed a painting with that precise title; however, the description and date fit <title corresp="#Richmond_TwickPk_TCH">Richmond from Twickenham Park</title>), a landscape painting of <placeName ref="#Richmond">Richmond</placeName> with figures in the foreground, completed before 1822 and engraved by Heath. <placeName ref="#Richmond">Richmond</placeName> and its environs was a frequent subject for Hofland.</note> --&gt;which <persName ref="#Hofland_TC">Mr. Hofland</persName> has just sent to <placeName ref="#Somerset_House">Somerset House</placeName>. <persName ref="#Hofland_B">His wife</persName> (one good judge) says that it is excellent--equal to <title corresp="#ChrstEJrslm_Haydon">Jerusalem</title>--&amp; <persName ref="#James_Miss">Miss James</persName> (<add place="above"><metamark place="below" function="insertion" rend="caret"/>also a good</add><del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/></del> judge) says that it is detestable--I incline to the latter because I know that <persName ref="#Hofland_TC">Mr. Hofland</persName> like many other fine landscape painters fails in figures. But I want your opinion. By the way I must tell you a remarkable circumstance which has just happened to <persName ref="#Hofland_B">Mrs. Hofland</persName>--They have been for many years engaged in a <orgName ref="#Chancery">Chancery</orgName> suit on the expected success of which they have placed great reliance--It has been given in their favor but as the costs are to be paid out of the property not a farthing will come to them. At first however they knew nothing <del rend="strikethrough">for</del> of this for their solicitor having neglected to write they heard only from a neighbour that the <persName>Chancellor's</persName> decree was in their favor &amp; <persName ref="#Hofland_B">Mrs. Hofland</persName> immediately set off for <placeName ref="#London_city">London</placeName> to learn the particulars--She was quite overcome by what she heard, &amp; was about to mount the outside of the <placeName ref="#Twickenham">Twickenham </placeName>Coach to return <foreign>"all amort"</foreign> as you must suppose, when recollecting she should save sixpence in going by the <placeName ref="#Richmond">Richmond</placeName>Stage--&amp; such a one being at hand, she withdrew her foot although a most respectable woman with her husband at her side offered to make room for her. Home she came by the <placeName ref="#Richmond">Richmond</placeName> Coach &amp; saved her sixpence--&amp; her life. The <placeName ref="#Twickenham">Twickenham </placeName>Coach was overturned an hour after, &amp; that decent woman in whose place she would have sat killed on the spot. The husband had his <choice><sic>collar bone</sic><reg>collarbone</reg></choice> &amp; a rib broken. This most striking event gave a new &amp; just turn to her thoughts--<persName ref="#James_Miss">Miss James</persName><add place="above"><metamark place="below" function="insertion" rend="caret"/>says</add> nothing was ever half so pathetic as her manner of detailing it. <pb n="3"/> Two things in this neighbourhood annoy me very much--First &amp; most <persName ref="#Dickinson_Charles">Mr. Dickinson</persName>--he is really killing himself. Never man had such symptoms of approaching apoplexy, &amp; because he has all his life combated the received theories of medicine especially what he calls the Sangrado System <note resp="#lmw">"Sangrado" was a fictional physician in Gil Blas who bled his patients to death. Throughout the nineteenth century, the term "Sangrado System" becomes proverbial for such methods.</note>--&gt; (which was of no consequence whilst confined to mere speculative harangues) he is now determined to stand by his opinions to the last, &amp; really will rather die by the blood rushes to <gap reason="torn" quantity="2" unit="chars"/><unclear><supplied resp="#mco">his</supplied></unclear> head than live by the lancet. Is not this vicious? Has a man any right to take himself out of the world before his time from sheer obstinacy, when <add place="above">all his friends</add><del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="2" unit="word"/></del> want <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="chars"/></del>him to live life merry? <choice><sic>Every body</sic><reg>Everybody</reg></choice> has warned him--two physicians to my knowledge &amp; three apothecaries-- &amp; not counting <emph rend="underline">me</emph> a quack--but he is absolutely unpersuadable &amp; has made <persName ref="#Dickinson_Charles">Mr. Dickinson</persName> believes he knows more of physic than <choice><sic>every one</sic><reg>everyone</reg></choice> else.--The other calamity need not annoy me in the least--but it does <unclear><gap reason="torn" quantity="2" unit="chars"/><supplied resp="#mco">nonetheless</supplied></unclear>. You shall hear it. The <persName ref="#Wellington_Duke">Duke of Wellington</persName>'s sons are home for the Eton holidays, &amp; they come every day to a little <gap reason="torn" quantity="2" unit="words"/><unclear><supplied resp="#mco">ale house</supplied></unclear> next door to take lessons in French of a Jew who is lodging there purposely to teach them. "The poor little lads Ma'am" said my neighbour the landlord "are kept very strict--they never look up but their tutor corrects them, &amp; there they sit in my parlour from eleven <choice><sic>oClock</sic><reg>o'clock</reg></choice> till half past four &amp; never have a glass of anything." Without sympathasizing very deeply in the last grievance enumerated by my friend taproom, I am quite indignant at the poor little boys being cheated out of their <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/></del> holidays. Learning French poor souls when they ought to be playing cricket or stealing bird's nests or doing mischief or doing nothing--Beating Napoleon was a joke to this wickedness. The only thing which even looks like the holidays is their mode of conveyance which is generally five in a gig rain or shine--once they came on horseback &amp; then they had a humpbacked boy on a donkey galloping <unclear><gap quantity="2" unit="chars" reason="folded"/><supplied resp="#mco">off</supplied></unclear> <!--I have invented the gap tag folded but it only exists in this letter thus far--><pb n="4"/> them by way of footman to carry their books. <metamark rend="jerks"/></p><p>I must finish soon--for I have no frank--<persName ref="#Monck_JB">Mr. Monck</persName> is I suppose Lord-Mayoring &amp; <persName ref="#Palmer_CF">Mr. Palmer </persName>has made himself wings &amp; flown away--I have not seen him these six months. Have you heard <choice><sic>any thing</sic><reg>anything</reg></choice> of <persName ref="#Palmer_Mad">Lady Madelina</persName>?--I have no news of <title ref="#Fiesco_MRMplay">my play</title> yet. <persName ref="#Macready_Wm">Mr. Macready</persName> has taken himself out of <placeName ref="#London_city">Town</placeName> before my <persName ref="#Talfourd_Thos">friend</persName> returned from the <placeName ref="#Oxford_Circuit">circuit</placeName>--which will likewise delay till <date when="1821-06">June</date> the appearance of my <bibl>Dramatic Sketches</bibl><note resp="#lmw">Here, it appears that <persName ref="#MRM">Mitford </persName>refers to the individual sketches, such as <title ref="#Emily_DS">"Emily,"</title> which were appearing in periodicals such as the <title ref="#LondonMag">London Magazine</title>.  She could not be referring to the later book-length work of the same name, since it did not appear until 1827 (as <title ref="#DramaticScenes">Dramatic Scenes, Sonnets, and Other Poems</title>).</note>in <title ref="#LondonMag">Baldwin's Magazine</title>.--<foreign>Adieu</foreign> my dear friend--If we may hope for the pleasure of seeing you let us know a day or two before. <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">My Father</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#Russell_M">Mother</persName> join in kindest regards &amp; I am always</p><lb/><closer><salute> most gratefully &amp; affectionately your's</salute><signed><persName ref="#MRM">MR. Mitford.</persName></signed></closer><lb/><postscript><p>Pray do come--We shall all be so glad to see you.
                  </p></postscript><closer><address><addrLine>To Sir William Elford Bar<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>.</addrLine><addrLine>54 <placeName ref="#Piccadilly">Picadilly</placeName></addrLine><addrLine><placeName ref="#London_city">London</placeName></addrLine></address></closer></div></body><back><div>
            
            <!-- LMW:  I completed the backlist and added it to my si-dd-lmw compliation. 2015 09-30 --></div></back></text></TEI>