<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><?xml-model href="http://ebeshero.github.io/MRMValidate.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Letter to <persName ref="#Talfourd_Thos">T.N. Talfourd</persName>1821 November 12-13</title><author ref="#MRM">Mary Russell Mitford</author><editor ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</editor><sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford Project</orgName></sponsor><sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor><principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal><respStmt><resp>Transcription and coding by</resp><persName ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Proofing and corrections by</resp><persName ref="#ebb">Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName><!-- correct when proofed LMW --></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>First digital edition in TEI, date: 17 June 2014. P5.</edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority><pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace><date>2013</date><availability><p>Reproduced by courtesy of the <placeName>The John Rylands University Library</placeName>.</p><licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
               License</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Mitford Letters: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><repository>The John Rylands University Library</repository><idno>MS 665 no. 7</idno></msIdentifier><head>Letter from <persName ref="#MRM">Mary Russell Mitford</persName> to <persName ref="#Talfourd_Thos">Thomas Noon Talfourd</persName>, <date when="1821-11-12">12 November 1821</date>.</head><physDesc><objectDesc><supportDesc><support><p>One large large sheet folded in half vertically to make four pages. Folded in half again horizontally.</p></support><condition><p/></condition></supportDesc></objectDesc></physDesc></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><p>Mitford’s spelling and punctuation are retained, except where a word is split at the end of a line and the beginning of the next in the manuscript. Where Mitford’s spelling and hyphenation of words deviates from the standard, in order to facilitate searching we are using the TEI elements “choice," “sic," and “reg" to encode both Mitford’s spelling and the regular international standard of Oxford English spelling, following the first listed spelling in the Oxford English Dictionary. The long s and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="letter"><opener><dateline><date when="1821-11-12">Monday night</date></dateline></opener><p>
               I beg a thousand pardons <persName ref="#Talfourd_Thos">my dear Sir</persName> for trespassing again on your valuable time--but I am so anxious to do the best that my feeble power can do for this poor <title ref="#Foscari_MRMplay">play</title> &amp; so certain of improvement from your suggestions that I cannot resist the temptation of sending you the rough draft of the poisoning Catastrophe. Is it at all do you think what <persName ref="#Macready_Wm">Mr. Macready</persName> intended? I am afraid not.  And what shall I do to make it better?  Is it too long?  Too short? Should <persName type="fict" ref="#Erizzo">Erizzo</persName> be brought in?  Should there be <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/></del> more rejoicing at first amongst the other characters &amp; should <persName type="fict" ref="#Foscari_Fr">Foscari</persName> himself forget in the first moments of joy that he carried death in his bosom?  Should his end be quieter--with less of delirium &amp; more of penitence?  And is there the smallest chance that I may make it such as <persName ref="#Macready_Wm">Mr. Macready</persName> would approve?  Pray tell me frankly--You have no notion how much I desire to write such a death as may please him--the more so a thousand times for the fine gentlemanly spirit with which <metamark rend="caret" place="below"/><add place="above" rend="metamark">he left</add> the alteration so completely at my option.  The more I think of his kindness &amp; of your's the more I feel that I never can deserve it.  Do you think he would like the death by joy for <persName type="fict" ref="#Foscari_Fr">Foscari</persName>?  It would not be so good as the <persName ref="#Doge_F">Doge's</persName>--but newer than this certainly--&amp; perhaps in better keeping with the character--Shall I try it?  At all events I shall make <emph>this</emph> Catastrophe as good as I possibly can [with your powerful aid] &amp; write over the whole act with the necessary alterations so as to be sent to you early in next week for<persName ref="#Macready_Wm">Mr. Macreadys</persName> &amp; your decision.  I do not think the early part of the act <pb n="1"/> will require so much altering--I think it may still open in the same way, only making <persName ref="#Cosmo">Cosmo</persName> enquire of the <persName ref="#Jailer_F">Jailer</persName> reply that a servant had been <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/></del>with him twice, that he had just been with him twice, that he had just drank some wine &amp; fallen asleep after a sleepless &amp; delirious night &amp;c--Will this do, do you think?  The other alterations are obvious enough even for me. Or should the audience know of the poison?--Be so good as to send back my rough draft with your remarks enclosed to <placeName ref="#Coley_Berks">Coley</placeName>--I will send there for it.--There is no end to the trouble I give you or to your goodness--&amp; really <persName ref="#Macready_Wm">Mr. Macready</persName> seems cast in the same mold--to be only two days in <placeName ref="#London_city">Town</placeName> and to take the trouble of reading the Play!--but your kindness is catching my dear <persName ref="#Talfourd_Thos">Mr. Talfourd</persName>--&amp;people who keep you company become kind they don't <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/></del>know how. God bless you. I shall finish in the morning.</p><p>Pray shall you think me a thief if I keep <persName ref="#Macready_Wm">Mr. Macready's</persName> letter? I hope not for I certainly shall keep it nevertheless--it is so exceedingly comforting--which is worth all the flattery in the world.  I am afraid to look at my Catastrophe by daylight farther than to see that the writing as if in emulation is really far worse than his--for which I very humbly beg pardon.  Is it not terribly disjointed that dying scene--far too full of transition? Be a severe critic for once in your life.</p><p>You would see by the <placeName ref="#Reading_city">Reading</placeName> paper that the Purity of Election dinner <!-- needs context note on political dinner LMW -->is fixed for the Thursday after the January Sessions--they had an extra meeting to fix the day <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/></del>&amp; chose the Tenth that they might be sure of you.  Of course you have had an official notice of this <pb n="2"/> They talk of very great company -- "an audience worth speaking to" as the dear <persName ref="#Valpy_Richard">Doctor</persName> once said -- <persName>Sir F. Burdett</persName>, <persName>Sir R. Wilson,</persName><persName ref="#Bennet_G">Mr. Grey Bennett</persName>, <persName ref="#Hume_Jos">Mr. Hume</persName> &amp; others whose names I have forgotten.  Oh I hope they will come!  It will be quite delightful that they should hear you in your own <placeName ref="#Reading_city">Reading</placeName> on subjects worthy of your powers &amp; with an audience so zealous to admire--I hope they will come. </p><p>I have now gotten "the real Simon Pure" <note resp="#lmw">Not a quote but a colloquial reference to anything that is genuine, authentic.  From <bibl><author>Centlivre's</author><title>A Bold Stroke for a Wife</title> (<date>1717</date>)</bibl>, in which the character Simon Pure appears, impersonated during part of the play by another character.</note> the true <title ref="#Th_d_Gr">Theatre des Grecs</title> recommended by <persName ref="#Burgess">Mr. Burgess</persName>, for before by some odd confusion I had only a volume of extracts &amp; remarks -- &amp; really it is a better way of getting at <persName ref="#Sophocles">Sophocles</persName> than in an English version which affects to be poetical--one is sure of the sense here--which is the great thing &amp; not confused &amp; teased by a clatter of<gap reason="torn"><!-- ms. torn.  Size of tear? LMW --></gap> .  Your comparison of the statues is perfect.  I have <gap reason="torn"><!-- ms. torn LMW; Coles inserts "so far"--></gap> only read the <title ref="#Oedipus_play">Oedipus Tyrranus</title> &amp; <title ref="#Philoctetes_play">Philoctetes</title> -- Is not the last much the finest? You don't quite say so in your remarks, but I think you <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/></del>think so.  I never read any thing so fine as the Philoctetes--&amp; surely the other is overpraised--that plot, or that riddle seems to me to engross far too much of the play--the passions are lost in the story--&amp; that story how intolerably &amp; visibly artificial it is -- there is none of the looseness &amp; freedom of nature.  Things do not happen in such a circle. I remember many years ago feeling exactly this objection to that other cried up story <title>Tom Jones</title>.  But I suppose I am wrong.  I must thank you once again for the loan of the <title ref="#Enc_Metr">Encyclopedia</title><note resp="#lmw"><persName ref="#Talfourd_Thos">Talfourd</persName> contributed to the <title ref="#Enc_Metr">Encyclopedia Metropolitana</title>, started by <persName ref="#Coleridge_ST">Coleridge</persName>, a volume on the Greek poets.</note> -- I have three times the delight in <persName ref="#Sophocles">Sophocles</persName> &amp; in reading him with your admirable remarks -- Those on <persName ref="#Euripides">Euripides</persName> are exquisite.
               
            <pb n="3"/>But it is great presumption in me even to say so. </p><closer>Adieu my dear <persName ref="#Talfourd_Thos">Sir</persName> -- Kindest regards from my <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Father</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#Russell_M">Mother</persName>--Ever most sincerely &amp; gratefully your's       
            <lb/><signed><persName ref="#MRM">M.R. Mitford</persName></signed><lb/></closer></div></body><back>
        <!--ebb: 29 May 2013: New prosopography data entered in site index. --></back></text></TEI>