<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><?xml-model href="http://ebeshero.github.io/MRMValidate.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title xml:id="MRM0532">Letter to <persName ref="#Talfourd_Thos">Thomas Noon Talfourd</persName>, <date when="1821-10-22">October 22, 1821</date></title><author ref="#MRM">Mary Russell Mitford</author><editor ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</editor><sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford Project</orgName></sponsor><sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor><principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal><respStmt><resp>Transcription and coding by</resp><persName ref="#hsar">Heather Sarsfield</persName><persName ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Proofing and corrections by</resp><persName ref="#ebb">Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>First digital edition in TEI, date: <date when="2014-05-26">26 May 2014</date>. P5.</edition><respStmt><resp>Edition made with help from photos taken by</resp><orgName>Digital Mitford editors</orgName></respStmt><respStmt><orgName>Digital Mitford</orgName><resp> photo files: <idno>DSCF6104.jpg, DSCF6105.jpg, DSCF6106.jpg, DSCF6107.jpg</idno></resp></respStmt><respStmt><orgName>The Digital Mitford</orgName><resp> The editors' photos from this archive are not permitted for public distribution.</resp></respStmt></editionStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority><pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace><date>2013</date><availability><p>Courtesy of <orgName ref="#Rylands">The University of Manchester</orgName>.</p><licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                  License</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Mitford Letters: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><repository ref="#Rylands">The John Rylands University Library</repository><collection>Mitford-Talfourd Correspondence: Letters from Mary Russell Mitford to Thomas Noon Talfourd: vol. 665</collection><idno>JRL English MS 665 no. 5, Coles no. 15</idno></msIdentifier><head>Letter from Mary Russell Mitford to T.N. Talfourd, <date when="1821-10-22">1821 October 22</date>.
                  <note resp="#lmw">MRM dates this letter "Monday" and it is postmarked 1821-10-25; 1821-10-22 was a Monday, checked in perpetual calendar. Coles dates it the 22nd.</note></head><physDesc><objectDesc><supportDesc><support><p>One sheet of folio <material>paper</material>, four surfaces photographed.</p><p>Address leaf bearing the following postmarks: 1) black postmark, illegible, and 2) a sepia indented single rim oval stamp reading <stamp><lb/><time>10 o'Clock</time><lb/><date when="1821-10-25"/><lb/>25 OC<lb/><lb/>1821<lb/></stamp></p><p>A large 2 denoting the fee for a single-sheet letter has been written
                              in black ink by the postal service across the address leaf.</p></support><condition><p>The right edge of page three is torn where wax seal was removed. <!--lmw: "The right side of the sheet has a diagonal tear about four inches long, diminishing from one inch in width at the top to about a quarter-inch at the bottom" (Coles, #15, p. 87, note 6).--></p></condition></supportDesc></objectDesc><sealDesc><p>Red wax seal, wrong side showing.</p></sealDesc></physDesc></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><handNotes><handNote corresp="#rc" medium="red_crayon"> Red crayon or thick red pencil. Probably a different hand from Mitford's that marks many of her letters, sometimes drawing diagonal lines across pages, and sometimes writing words overtop and perpendicularly across Mitford's writing. On this letter, a red line is drawn from top left to bottom right of each of the leaves. On leaf six (the address leaf), two red lines are drawn from top left to bottom right over each text block.</handNote><handNote corresp="#pencilRy" medium="pencil"> Someone, apparently other than Mitford, perhaps cataloging letters and describing them, who left grey pencil marks and numbered her letters now in the John Rylands Library's collection. This letter is numbered "15" on the first leaf.
            </handNote></handNotes></profileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><p>Mitford’s spelling and punctuation are retained, except where a word is split at the end of a line and the beginning of the next in the manuscript. Where Mitford’s spelling and hyphenation of words deviates from the standard, in order to facilitate searching we are using the TEI elements “choice," “sic," and “reg" to encode both Mitford’s spelling and the regular international standard of Oxford English spelling, following the first listed spelling in the Oxford English Dictionary. The long s and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="letter"><opener><dateline><name type="place" ref="#ThreeMileCross">Three Mile Cross</name><date when="1821-10-22">Monday morning</date></dateline><salute><persName ref="#Talfourd_Thos">My dear Sir,</persName></salute></opener><p>I am always sinning--not quite tragical sins; &amp; repenting--not quite perhaps with a tragical repentenace, but very sincerely &amp; uncomfortably of the thousand faults which inconsideration &amp; want of tact make me commit every day &amp; almost every hour--to say nothing of my terrible tendency to say from pure flutter what I should not &amp; what I do not mean, &amp; not to say from sheer awkwardness what I should say &amp; do mean. <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="3" unit="word"/>Ever since I</del> So that whoever comes into my company had need provide themselves with a large stock of charity &amp; forgiveness.  But this is worse than my usual misdoings. Ever since I gave you my wretched article on <date when="1821-11-19">Friday</date> morning, I have had the consciousness that nobody but you ought to have attempted it--especially that I should not--that being, upon occasion, as obstinate as my neighbors, I should have given the dear <persName ref="#Valpy_Richard">Doctor</persName> a touch of my quality, instead of taking the post assigned me so quietly &amp; really checking my <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">father</persName> when with a much better taste &amp; feeling he tried to get me off. I only thought at the moment how shabby it would be to turn over a disagreeable occupation to you, quite forgetting that the subject &amp; the <placeName ref="#Reading_School">school</placeName> &amp; the charm of writing of <placeName ref="#Reading_city">Reading</placeName> &amp; for <placeName ref="#Reading_city">Reading</placeName> would have made it almost as pleasant <add place="above"><metamark place="below" function="insertion" rend="caret"/>as it would have been</add> to you <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/><unclear/></del> delightful to every body, <choice><reg resp="#lmw">everybody</reg></choice> else--How could I be so foolish &amp; presumptuous!<pb n="2"/><del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/><unclear/></del> When I found by your condescending note how much trouble you had taken--&amp; that you still had another account to write &amp; not for <placeName ref="#Reading_city">Reading</placeName>--I was more ashamed &amp; more angry with myself (&amp; this is saying much) than ever I was in my life.  Well the dear <persName ref="#Valpy_Richard">Doctor</persName> is fitly punished in the abominable badness of my report, &amp; so am I. I have a good mind to apologize to the poor boys in the next paper for cheating them of your valuable praise. You must write a Magazine Article to console them. In the mean time <choice><reg resp="#lmw">meantime</reg></choice> I could not resist the opportunity of asking your pardon afforded by our sending <persName ref="#James_Miss">Miss James</persName> a basket of roots &amp; flower seeds &amp; such underground treasures the announcement of which you had the goodness to convey. She will of course think my note contains more last words of <title ref="#Foscari_MRMplay">Foscari</title>. Do not notice it even to say you forgive me--I am so ashamed.</p><p>Did I beg you to tell <persName ref="#Macready_Wm">Mr. Macready</persName> that I should willingly &amp; thankfully make any &amp; every alteration that he might suggest in <title ref="#Foscari_MRMplay">Foscari</title>, in case, which I do not expect, he should deem it worth altering. I have just finished my new copy &amp; am more &amp; more conscious that the part is utterly unworthy of his great powers. He might to be sure be everything to the play as he was to <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/><title ref="#Foscari_MRMplay">Foscari</title></del><title ref="#Wallace_play">Wallace</title>--my usual consolation when I think of the badness of <title ref="#Foscari_MRMplay">Foscari</title>--but that is too much to ask. Perhaps there is more opportunity for an Actor in the <persName ref="#Doge_F">Doge</persName>--at least he might <emph rend="underline">make</emph> that part which could hardly be done in <title ref="#Foscari_MRMplay">Foscari</title>.  But this <pb n="3"/>must of course be left to him &amp; you. I <gap reason="torn" quantity="2" unit="word"/><unclear/><supplied resp="lmw">thank you</supplied> very much for the report of <persName ref="#Quayle_Mr">Mr. Quale</persName>--&amp; re<gap reason="torn" quantity="9" unit="chars"/><unclear/><supplied resp="lmw">ly wholly </supplied> on his zeal &amp; kindness. But I have very lit<gap reason="torn" quantity="9" unit="chars"/><unclear/><supplied resp="lmw">tle hope.</supplied> Since this last weary copying, I am come <gap reason="torn" quantity="1" unit="word"/><supplied resp="lmw">back</supplied> to my original opinion of the general feeb<gap reason="torn" quantity="6" unit="chars"/><unclear/><supplied resp="lmw">leness</supplied> of the <title ref="#Foscari_MRMplay">Play</title>--Just as I had done <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</persName> told m<gap reason="torn" quantity="4" unit="chars"/><unclear/><supplied resp="lmw">e of</supplied>the "sweets &amp; dears"--Shall I write it over <gap reason="torn" quantity="1" unit="word"/><unclear/><supplied resp="lmw">again</supplied> to get quit of them? Or shall we wait to <gap reason="torn" quantity="1" unit="word"/><unclear/><supplied resp="lmw">hear</supplied> what<persName ref="#Macready_Wm">Mr. Macready</persName> says? As soon as I was to s<gap reason="torn" quantity="10" unit="chars"/><supplied resp="lmw">end this I</supplied> found it out--just as in the case of the "own <gap reason="torn" quantity="1" unit="word"/> Really my stupidity is hopeless. How you can you h<gap reason="torn" quantity="3" unit="chars"/><unclear/><supplied resp="lmw">ave</supplied> such patience with me--Such indulgence such <gap reason="torn" quantity="1" unit="word"/><unclear/><supplied resp="lmw">great</supplied> kindness I cannot imagine. I don't think I sha<gap reason="torn" quantity="2" unit="chars"/><supplied resp="lmw">ll</supplied> attempt the "Euripedean Enterprise"--Oh it is <gap reason="torn" quantity="1" unit="word"/><unclear/><supplied resp="lmw">quite</supplied> quite above me--I shall leave that to <emph rend="underline">your </emph>Tragedy--&amp; beguile my hopes &amp; fears for <title ref="#Foscari_MRMplay">Foscari</title>.  (Did not I say just now that I had no hope?) by the soothing &amp; sedative properties of needlework the most composing &amp; quieting occupation in the world. Luckily I have a dozen jobs that cry out to be done. It is almost--not quite--worthwhile to be a woman to have such a resource.</p><p>Did I--was I bold enough to ask you when we were talking of your article on <persName ref="#Homer">Homer</persName> &amp; I was wishing so much to see it--did I ask you to lend it to me? And will you? And that on the Greek Tragedians if it comes your way? Will you? I want to read a translation of <persName ref="#Sophocles"/><persName ref="#Burgess">Mr. Burgess</persName><!-- Coles says this is the same person mentioned in the Intro. Check to be sure it is the same and whether name has one s or two. (Burges.) See Coles #15, p. 89, note 12. LMW--> recommended one in French prose--but French prose--will not English be better? And pray when you saw that astonishing thing about my writing a Comedy--(in which we seemed mutually to amuse each other) did you mean it quite, really?  Or was it only <pb n="4"/> a very pretty way of saying "I don't think, Madam, that "you will ever make much of Tragedy"--?</p><p>My <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">father</persName> is going to the <persName ref="#Valpy_Richard">Doctor</persName>'s dance tonight--he sent me a very kind invitation on <date when="1821-10-20">Saturday</date>--but I stay away from pure cowardice--I really cannot encounter <persName ref="#Culpepper_Mrs">Mrs. Culpepper</persName>. I wonder if they won't prevail on you to stay.--My fingers are so cramped with writing that they slide every way but the right--Good bye. God bless you--pray forgive me.</p><closer><lb/> Ever <choice><sic>your's</sic><reg>yours</reg></choice><signed><persName ref="#MRM">M.R. Mitford.</persName></signed><lb/></closer><postscript><p>Pray excuse all my blots &amp; blunders--I had better not have written. but I could not help it--</p></postscript><closer><address><addrLine> To <persName ref="#Talfourd_Thos">T. N. Talfourd</persName> Esq<hi rend="superscript"/>re.</addrLine><addrLine>No. 1. <placeName ref="#Pump_Court">Pump Court</placeName></addrLine><addrLine><placeName ref="#Temple">Temple.</placeName></addrLine></address></closer></div></body><back>
         <!-- backlist pulled to si-add-LMW 2015 10 05 --></back></text></TEI>