<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><?xml-model href="http://ebeshero.github.io/MRMValidate.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title xml:id="MRM0528">Letter to <persName ref="#Talfourd_Thos">T. N. Talfourd</persName>, June 21, 1821</title><author ref="#MRM">Mary Russell Mitford</author><editor ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</editor><sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford Project</orgName></sponsor><sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor><sponsor>Pittsburgh Supercomputing Center</sponsor><principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal><respStmt><resp>Transcription and coding by</resp><persName ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Date last checked: <date when="2015-10-05">2015-10-05</date>
                  Proofing and corrections by</resp><persName ref="#ebb"/><!--ebb: 29 May 2014: Prosop entered, but letter transcription needs to be checked.--></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>First digital edition in TEI, date: 3 June 2013<date when="2013-06-03"/>. P5.</edition><respStmt><resp>Edition made with help from photos taken by</resp><orgName>Digital Mitford editors</orgName></respStmt><respStmt><orgName>Digital Mitford</orgName><resp> photo files: <idno>DSCF6093.jpg, DSCF6094.jpg, DSCF6095.jpg, DSCF6096.jpg</idno></resp></respStmt></editionStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority><pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace><date>2013</date><availability><p>Courtesy of <orgName ref="#Rylands">The University of Manchester</orgName>.
               </p><licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                  License</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Mitford Letters: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc> <!-- This section of the header identifies the original manuscript source. --><msIdentifier><repository ref="#Rylands">The University of Manchester</repository><collection>Mitford-Talfourd Correspondence: Letters from Mary Russell Mitford to Thomas Noon Talfourd: vol. 665</collection><idno>JRL English Ms. 665 (R69047), Coles no. 7</idno></msIdentifier><head>Letter from Mary Russell Mitford to Sir William Elford, <date when="1821-06-21">1821 June 21</date>. 
               <note resp="#lmw">The envelope and postmark for this letter are reportedly at Harvard, not at Rylands. Rylands ms. letter indicates this date.</note>--&gt;
                  
               </head><physDesc><objectDesc><supportDesc><support><p>One sheet of <material>paper</material>, folded in half once, four surfaces photographed.</p><p>Missing address leaf.</p></support><condition><p>First leaf torn on top edge; does not affect text.</p></condition></supportDesc></objectDesc><sealDesc><p>No seal present.</p></sealDesc></physDesc></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><handNotes><handNote corresp="#pencil" medium="pencil"> Someone, apparently other than Mitford, perhaps cataloging letters and describing them, who left grey pencil marks and numbered her letters. This letter is numbered "1" in the top right of the first leaf.
            </handNote></handNotes></profileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><p>Mitford’s spelling and punctuation are retained, except where a word is split at the end of a line and the beginning of the next in the manuscript. Where Mitford’s spelling and hyphenation of words deviates from the standard, in order to facilitate searching we are using the TEI elements “choice," “sic," and “reg" to encode both Mitford’s spelling and the regular international standard of Oxford English spelling, following the first listed spelling in the Oxford English Dictionary. The long s and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="letter"><opener><dateline><name type="place" ref="#ThreeMileCross">Three Mile Cross</name><date when="1821-06-21">June 21<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> 1821</date>. 
               </dateline></opener><p>I can but thank you again &amp; again, <persName ref="#Talfourd_Thos">my dear Sir</persName>, for your exceeding kindness, &amp; lament more than ever the trouble that I give you--I assure you this regret is not a form of words but a real feeling--I am so sorry to trespass on your valuable time--so very sorry--&amp; yet when you bid me write and tease you with my doubts &amp; difficulties I have not resolution to relinquish the comfort of telling them to you &amp; the benefit of your advice.----What you say of the Plots is exactly what I feel--None of <persName ref="#James_Miss">Miss James’s</persName><!--Close friend of MRM, possibly an educator. According to Coles from MRM diary, letters were addressed to her at Bellevue, Lower Road, Richmond (Coles 26) LMW -->hit my fancy except that one last scene to which it seems difficult to adapt any train of events that should be unobjectionable--free I mean from licentious love, &amp; the lovely boy &amp; girl story which is totally unfit for representation, but of which if I be lucky enough to keep my footing in <title ref="#LondonMag">the London</title> I will certainly make a little Drama for that publication. <persName ref="#Hofland_B">Mrs. Hofland</persName>'s story seems the best--I knew from the first that the Catastrophe would never do--neither do I like the sort of posthumous jealousy the triple refined sentiments of the Mother--her character would be excessively difficult to manage &amp; scarcely worth the pains after all. Now I find on consulting <title ref="#Moore_ViewItaly">the History of Venice</title>that the <persName ref="#Doge_F_hist">Doge Foscari</persName> was turned out after a long &amp; glorious government at the age of 95--which affront rather than the death of his <persName ref="#Cosmo">son</persName> broke his heart. And on this hint I think it will be better to make the <persName ref="#Donato_hist">Senator Donato</persName> (for whose murder <persName ref="#Moore_DrJ">Dr. Moore</persName> says <persName ref="#Foscari_son_hist">young Foscari</persName> was sentenced) <pb n="2"/> grasping ambitiously at the Dogal Bonnet.  At the beginning of the <title ref="#Foscari_MRMplay">Play</title><persName ref="#Doge_F">Foscari</persName> may be absent commanding the armies of the Republic--<persName ref="#Donato">Donato</persName> may propose in the Senate the dismissal of <persName ref="#Doge_F">the Doge</persName> on account of his great age &amp;c--<persName ref="#Foscari_Fr">Foscari</persName> may return suddenly with news of a great Victory, detect &amp; overthrow <del rend="squiggles" unit="word" n="1"/><persName ref="#Donato">Donato</persName>'s faction &amp; reject indignantly the hand of his beloved <persName ref="#Camilla">Camilla</persName> when offered as the price of his fathers degradation.  This gives rise to a public quarrel between <persName ref="#Foscari_Fr">Foscari,</persName><persName ref="#Donato">Donato</persName> &amp; his son <persName ref="#Cosmo">Cosmo</persName>--&amp; a cloak found near the dead <persName ref="#Donato">Senator</persName><del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/><unclear/></del> left by <persName ref="#Foscari_Fr">Foscari</persName> in hastening from a stolen visit to <persName ref="#Camilla">Camilla</persName> will be sufficient ground for suspicion in <persName ref="#Cosmo">Cosmo Donato</persName>, whom I intend to make a bold gallant generous character, &amp; who the <!--Coles omits "the."  (#7, p. 47).  LMW --> moment the sentence is <choice><sic>past</sic><reg>passed</reg></choice> begins to harbour doubts of its justice which must be strengthened by the many small circumstances &amp; end in the detection by him of the real murderer too late however to save <persName ref="#Foscari_Fr">Foscari</persName> who in an agony of impatient grief had swallowed poison--or stabbed himself (which shall it be?)--&amp; dies on the stage in the midst of the friends <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/><unclear/></del> who come to announce his triumphant acquittal. Tell me if you think this will do? And pray if any alteration should suggest itself to you let me know it--I am not myself pleased with the scheme--but as I can hit on nothing better I think at least to write an act or two &amp; try if I can work myself up into something like passion. I am terribly afraid of the first scene before the Senate--&amp; still more of the Trial--but I will write an Act or two certainly--though if you should meet with any thing better I would relinquish this immediately. You will see that <persName ref="#Cosmo">Cosmo Donato</persName> is created for <persName ref="#Kemble_C">Mr. Charles Kemble</persName>--I could make nothing of <persName ref="#Doge_F">the Doge</persName>--an uphill character who has little to do but to suffer--No <persName ref="#Macready_Wm">Mr. Macready</persName> must be <pb n="3"/><persName ref="#Foscari_Fr">Foscari</persName>--Write to me, my dear <persName ref="#Talfourd_Thos">Mr. Talfourd</persName>, if you think he would not--write &amp; stop me immediately--one word would be enough--<persName ref="#Macready_Wm">Mr. Macready</persName> is my only inspiration. Amongst my other perplexities I don’t know whether <persName ref="#Cosmo">Cosmo Donato</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#Foscari_Fr">Foscari</persName> should be friends or enemies--Which would be best?  But these things will arrange themselves.  Pray forgive this unconscionable programme of <title ref="#Foscari_MRMplay">a Play</title> that may never be written. Your indulgence has completed the spoiling me--a job which was pretty far advanced before you took it in hand.</p><p><persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">My father</persName> had heard of your short visit to <placeName ref="#Reading_city">Reading</placeName> &amp; had likewise learnt from <persName ref="#Wakefield_D">Mr. Wakefield</persName> the curious story of the sturdy domestic &amp; the affronted Commissioner--What a scene must it have been!  By the bye your opponents <orgName ref="#Slades">the Slades</orgName> are Cousins of ours, as far off I suppose as the twentieth degree--&amp; as I have in all its injustice &amp; unreasonableness the true North country clannish feeling, I cannot help wishing my Cousins success, though I know very little <del rend="squiggles" quantity="1" unit="word"><unclear/><supplied resp="#ebb">against</supplied></del><add place="above">about</add> them &amp; never heard of the affair before--&amp; though their adversary has done such a right &amp; wise thing as to engage you in his cause. Did you hear when at <placeName ref="#Reading_city">Reading</placeName> that the dear <persName ref="#Valpy_Richard">Doctor Valpy</persName> has been annoyed again by persons encroaching on his play ground &amp; means to try the right at the next Assizes. Oh how sorry I am that these Assizes will be at <placeName ref="#Abingdon">Abingdon</placeName>! What a treat it would be to hear you on a subject which would authorise &amp; demand a kind of eloquence so glowing &amp; so genial--so different from the common run of law cases--And you will speak--will you not? Even if there should be half a dozen Senior Counsel? Oh you must speak for the dear <persName ref="#Valpy_Richard">Doctor</persName>'s sake--I am only afraid that the offenders will be penitent &amp; <persName ref="#Valpy_Richard">the Doctor</persName> placable &amp; that it will not be tried at all.<pb n="4"/> You will not doubt how exceedingly we lamented not seeing you--Shall you come to <placeName ref="#Reading_city">Reading</placeName> in your way to the Sessions? If you do we shall rely on that pleasure.</p><p> What you say of <title ref="#OurVillage_story">"Our Village"</title><note resp="#lmw #ebb"><persName ref="#coles">Coles</persName> suggests that <title>"Our Village"</title> here refers to the story/sketch of the same name rather than the entire series. This may be the sketch that became the first story in <title ref="#Our_Village1st_ed">Our Village</title> of <date>1824</date> (Coles #6, p. 40, note 11).</note> is encouraging &amp; comfortable--I had looked on prose composition as a thing not <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/><unclear/><supplied resp="#ebb">only</supplied></del> difficult merely, but impossible--I shall now take heart.  If <persName ref="#Baldwin_R">Mr. Baldwin</persName> should not find <title ref="#Claudias_Dr">Claudia's Dream</title> &amp; <orgName ref="#Taylor_Hessey">Taylor &amp; Hessey</orgName> should wish to have it, I will send another copy--though I have nothing but my rough draft--which bad as my finished things may be, is I assure <metamark rend="caret" place="below"/><add place="above" rend="metamark">you</add> much worse--to say nothing of the writing. My dear <persName ref="#Talfourd_Thos">Mr. Talfourd</persName> figure to yourself my worst hand!--all blots &amp; interlineations--&amp; the dialogue all in a mess! Oh there never was such a skein of tangled silk! Nevertheless I will wind it off at a moment's warning if the other copy be not found--I have the strongest possible desire not to be turned off for <persName ref="#Croly_G">Mr. Croly</persName>--a person whose doings I admire quite as little as you do. Perhaps I had better transcribe my little Drama at all events.</p><p>On looking up this page it seems dictated by the Demon of Tautology--But it's all my <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Father</persName>'s fault--I have been writing all this time in the room where he is settling a matrimonial difference between a young Couple in our neighborhood <note resp="#lmw"><persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">George Mitford</persName> was magistrate and chairman of the bench in the <placeName ref="#Reading_city">Reading</placeName> division, county of Berkshire, according to <persName ref="#coles">Coles</persName> (#7, p. 40, note 9). Presumably this is why he is "settling a matrimonial difference."</note>(Dear me--I never saw a finer man or prettier woman--to think that they should fight!  Oh dear!)--And <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</persName> is haranguing &amp; the husband explaining &amp; the wife crying--I wonder that I can write a word--Besides I am curious as to the termination--they came desiring to be parted, never to look at one another again--but there is a relenting I think--a touch of the old love--Yes they will certainly make up.  And <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</persName>'s admonitions will be an excuse to themselves &amp; to each other--Oh yes they will forgive. </p><p>Adieu, my dear Sir--</p><closer><lb/>Ever most sincerely &amp; gratefully your's
            <lb/><signed>M.R.M.</signed><lb/></closer></div></body><back>
        <!-- backlist pulled to si-add-LMW 2015-10-05 --></back></text></TEI>