<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><?xml-model href="http://ebeshero.github.io/MRMValidate.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title xml:id="MRM1778">Letter to <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir William Elford</persName>, <date when="1821-04-04"> April 4, 1821</date></title><author ref="#MRM">Mary Russell Mitford</author><editor ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</editor><sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford Project</orgName></sponsor><sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor><sponsor>Pittsburgh Supercomputing Center</sponsor><principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal><respStmt><resp>Transcription and coding by</resp><persName ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Proofing and corrections by</resp><persName ref="#mco">Molly C. O'Donnell</persName> <!--mco: proofed, checked against ms, updated TEI headers, and LMW added backlist. Some notes to self from LMW, but all related and appropriate ed notes input as well.--></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>First digital edition in TEI, date: <date when="2014-06-11"> June 11, 2014</date>. P5.</edition><respStmt><resp>Edition made with help from photos taken by</resp><orgName>Digital Mitford editors</orgName></respStmt><respStmt><orgName>Digital Mitford</orgName><resp> photo files: <idno>4April1821SirWilliamElford1a#.jpg, 4April1821SirWilliamElford2a#.jpg, 4April1821SirWilliamElford1b#.jpg, 4April1821SirWilliamElford2b#.jpg, 4April1821SirWilliamElford3a#.jpg, 4April1821SirWilliamElford4a#.jpg, 4April1821SirWilliamElford3b#.jpg, 4April1821SirWilliamElford4b#.jpg</idno></resp></respStmt></editionStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority><pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace><date>2013</date><availability><p>Reproduced by courtesy of the <orgName ref="#ReadingCL">Reading Central Library</orgName>.</p><licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                  License</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Mitford Letters: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><repository ref="#ReadingCL">Reading Central Library</repository><collection>The letters of Mary Russell Mitford, vol. 4, 1819-1823</collection><idno>qB/TU/MIT Vol. 4 Horizon No.: 1361550 ff. 434</idno></msIdentifier><head>Letter from <persName ref="#MRM">Mary Russell Mitford</persName> to <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir William Elford</persName>, <date when="1821-04-04">04 April 1821</date>.</head><physDesc><objectDesc><supportDesc><support><p>One sheet of folio <material>paper</material> folded in half to form four surfaces which are photographed. Letter text is on pages 1, 2, and 3, with the address on page 4.</p><p>Address leaf bearing black postmark, partially illegible, reading <stamp><lb/><placeName>READING</placeName> 4 2<lb/></stamp>.</p><p>The entire address has penned slashes across it, as well as a 2, a possible fee, written next to where the red seal would have been when the letter was sealed.</p></support><condition><p>Page 3 is torn on right edge where wax seal was removed.</p></condition></supportDesc></objectDesc><sealDesc><p>Red wax seal.</p></sealDesc></physDesc></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><handNotes><handNote corresp="#rc" medium="red_crayon"> Red crayon or thick red pencil. Probably a different hand from Mitford's that marks many of her letters, sometimes drawing diagonal lines across pages, and sometimes writing words overtop and perpendicularly across Mitford's writing. On this letter, a red line is drawn from the top left diagonally to the bottom right of pages 1-3.</handNote><handNote corresp="#pencil" medium="pencil"> Someone, apparently other than Mitford, perhaps cataloging letters and describing them left grey pencil marks. This letter is dated April 4, 1821, on the address leaf by that hand and numbered 29 on page 1.</handNote></handNotes></profileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><p>Mitford’s spelling and punctuation are retained, except where a word is split at the
              end of a line and the beginning of the next in the manuscript. Where Mitford’s
              spelling and hyphenation of words deviates from the standard, in order to facilitate
              searching we are using the TEI elements “choice," “sic," and “reg" to encode both
              Mitford’s spelling and the regular international standard of Oxford English spelling,
              following the first listed spelling in the Oxford English Dictionary. The long s and
              ligatured forms are not encoded.</p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="letter"><opener><dateline><persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">To Sir W. Elford</persName><date when="1821-04-04">April 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1821</date>. <placeName ref="#ThreeMileCross">Three Mile Cross</placeName></dateline></opener><p>You are the most provoking man that ever lived in the world--&amp; the most provoking part of your provokingness is that one cannot find in one's heart to quarrel with you. To think of your expecting a letter at <placeName ref="#Oakhampton_House">Oakhampton House</placeName>! Well you shall get one at <placeName ref="#Bickham_village">Bickham</placeName> instead for if you do not leave it till the <date when="1821-04-04">4th</date> I shall have time to catch you &amp; I wish to explain to you all my thoughts &amp; feelings respecting these letters. I should be as glad as you would, my always dear &amp; kind &amp; too partial friend, if I thought they would by any chance make some attractive volumes. But I do not. There is about them now a piquancy which results almost entirely from saucy criticism on the one hand, &amp; personal anecdotes no less saucy on the other. If I were to publish them as they are I have no doubt but they would sell--But to publish them as they are would be impossible--everything that could by the remotest chance hurt the feelings either of authors or acquaintances or whoever else might be mentioned must without hesitation be expunged--&amp; I blush to think how little would remain worth reading when this playful malice (excusable perhaps for a lively young woman to write but which she would be unpardonable in printing) should be taken away. With these feelings, I shall persist in my request for a loan of those letters--It seems to me that I may find <del rend="squiggles" unit="chars" n="1"/> bits in them which would dovetail in with great ease &amp; some effect--For instance I want to write an article on <placeName ref="#Richmond">Richmond</placeName>, &amp; if I remember right I wrote you an account of the impression which that beautiful &amp; elegant place made on me when I was there last year. If you will trust me with these letters I will promise you to look over them &amp; if I find your plan practicable to put it in execution in preference to my own--If not the letters will be just as good as new twenty <pb n="2"/>years hence, even though I should <emph rend="underline">get</emph> them now--for neither my Essays nor the Magazines will be remembered then more than the last year's clouds. If you should incline to yield to my reasons or my importunity, you can bring these epistles with you &amp; either leave them for me at <placeName ref="#Reading_city">Reading</placeName> or bring them yourself here on your return, when I hope we may depend on seeing you at all events. If you leave them at <placeName ref="#Reading_city">Reading</placeName> will you have the goodness to send a line to the Post Office as you pass through to let me know that you have done so. We must not let these precious pieces of impertinence be lost. I am quite ashamed to have made such a clatter about them. <metamark rend="jerk"/>My <title ref="#Fiesco_MRMplay">Tragedy</title> is still in <persName ref="#Macready_Wm">Mr. Macready</persName>'s hands--but I am afraid it will be ultimately rejected--Oh I shall never have the good luck to be damned!--<persName ref="#Macready_Wm">Mr. Macready</persName> wrote the other day to my friend &amp; his friend who gave him my <title ref="#Fiesco_MRMplay">Play</title>--&amp; this mutual <persName ref="#Talfourd_Thos">friend</persName> (who is on the circuit just now) copied his letter for my edification. It was in the first place the prettiest letter I ever read in my life--thoroughly careless simple &amp; unpresuming--showing great diffidence of his own judgment--the readiest goodnature--the kindest &amp; most candid desire to be pleased. I <unclear>wot</unclear><!--ebb: looks like I rite or I nite, but here coded as "wot."--> the letter of a scholar &amp; a gentleman, &amp; not the least like an Actor. As far as regarded my <title ref="#Fiesco_MRMplay">Tragedy</title> it contained much good criticism--<persName ref="#Macready_Wm">Mr. Macready</persName> thinks, &amp; he is right, that there is too little of striking incident &amp; too little fluctuation (Indeed I have made my <persName ref="#Fiesco_fict">Fiesco</persName> as virtuous &amp; as fortunate as <persName ref="#Chas_Grandison_fict">Sir Charles Grandison</persName>--&amp; he goes about <foreign xml:lang="fr">proné</foreign> <!--L'Estrange gives prôné. LMW --> by every body &amp; setting every body to rights much in the same style with that worthy gentleman--only that he has one wife instead of two mistresses) Nevertheless the dialogue which is my strong part has some how <q>"put salt upon <persName ref="#Macready_Wm">Mr. Macready</persName>'s tail"</q> as <persName ref="#James_Miss">Miss James</persName> says <note resp="#lmw">Not a quotation but a proverbial phrase. According to Brewer's Dictionary of Phrase and Fable (1898), the phrase usually means to "catch or apprehend" someone. Mitford seems to mean that Macready has been halted or frozen by indecision. <!-- "'Salt on His Tail (Lay).' Catch or apprehend him. The phrase is based on the direction given to small children to lay salt on a bird’s tail if they want to catch it.	 1 “His intelligence is so good, that were you to come near him with soldiers or constables, … I shall answer for it you will never lay salt on his tail.”—Sir W. Scott: Redgauntlet, chap. xi. (Brewer, E. Cobham. “Salt on His Tail (Lay).” Dictionary of Phrase and Fable. Philadelphia: Henry Altemus, 1898; Bartleby.com, 2000. www.bartleby.com/81/. [17 June 2014]). LMW.--></note>--so that he is in a very unhappy state of doubt about it &amp; cannot make up his mind one or the other. The only thing upon which he was decided was that <pb n="3"/>the handwriting was illegible &amp; that it must be copied for presentment to the Managers--which has been done accordingly &amp; <persName ref="#Macready_Wm">Mr. Macready</persName> &amp; they will now do exactly as they like.--I am delighted to find that you think I may succeed as a Dramatic writer--I am now occupied in Dramatic Sketches for <title ref="#LondonMag">Baldwin's Magazine</title>--slight stories of about one act developed in fanciful dialogues of loose blank verse.--I have written two--&amp; I suppose they will appear in May or June. By the way <persName ref="#Baldwin_R">Mr. Baldwin</persName> has not heard word yet of the felicity that is to <choice><sic>befal</sic><reg resp="#lmw">befall</reg></choice> him--for they are upon the Circuit with <persName ref="#Talfourd_Thos">my young Barrister friend</persName>--but as he is a great literary man, &amp; undertakes for their insertion I have not much doubt about the matter--Don't mention it though till we have actually made the bargain--If <persName ref="#Baldwin_R">Mr. Baldwin</persName> will accept a series of such articles they will be not merely extremely advantageous to one in a pecuniary point of view (for the p<damage agent="torn" unit="chars" n="2"><supplied resp="#lmw">ay</supplied></damage> is well up, they give 15 guineas a sheet) but excellent exercise for my Tragedies. At the same time I confess to you that nothing seems so tiresome &amp; unsatisfactory as writing poetry--Oh my dear <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir William</persName>! how much better I like working flowers! There when one had done a pattern one was sure that one had got on--&amp; I had the comfort of admiring one's work &amp; exulting in one's industry all the time that one was in fact indulging in the most comfortable indolence. Well courage <persName ref="#MRM">Missy Mitford</persName> (as <title ref="#Blackwoods">Blackwood's Magazine</title> has the impudence to call me!) Courage <foreign>Mon Amie</foreign>--If you go on dramatizing at this rate 6 years longer <del rend="squiggles" unit="chars" n="2">so</del> you will get as enured to it as to working flounces or writing to your dear <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir William</persName>--All your <del rend="squiggles" unit="chars" n="4"/> fidgettiness will disappear Missy--The <persName>postman</persName> is this moment waiting--(I did not expect him for this half hour)--</p><closer><lb/>I have only time to say God bless you--<signed><persName ref="#MRM">M.R. Mitford</persName></signed>.</closer><postscript><p>Of course you will not expect to hear at <placeName ref="#Oakhampton_House">Oakhampton House</placeName>.</p></postscript><pb n="4"/><closer><address><addrLine>To </addrLine><addrLine><persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir William Elford Bar<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi></persName></addrLine><addrLine><placeName ref="#Bickham_village">Bickham</placeName></addrLine><addrLine><placeName ref="#Plymouth_city">Plymouth</placeName></addrLine></address></closer></div></body><back><div>
 
<!-- LMW:  backlist finalized and pulled for my compilation. 09-30-2015 -->
        <!-- 
ELFORD, William (1749-1837), of Bickham, Devon.
Published in The History of Parliament: the House of Commons 1790-1820, ed. R. Thorne, 1986
Available from Boydell and Brewer
<http://www.historyofparliamentonline.org/volume/1790-1820/member/elford-william-1749-1837>

    
Constituency
Dates
PLYMOUTH
1796 - 1806
RYE
21 July 1807 - July 1808
Family and Education

b. Aug. 1749, 1st s. of Rev. Lancelot Elford of Bickham, vicar of Plympton, by Grace, da. of Alexander Wills of Kingsbridge. m. (1) 20 Jan. 1776, Mary (d.1817), da. and h. of Rev. John Davies of Plympton, 1s. d.v.p. 2da.; (2) 5 July 1821, Elizabeth, da. and coh. of Humphrey Hall of Manaton, wid. of Lt.-Col. Maine Swete Walrond, barrack master, Dominica, s.p. suc. fa. 1782; cr. Bt. 26 Nov. 1800.
Offices Held

Recorder, Plymouth 1797-1833, Totnes 1832-4.

Lt. S. Devon militia 1788, capt.-lt. 1790, capt. 1792, and maj. 1795, 1st maj. 1797, lt.-col. 1798.
Biography

Elford’s was one of the oldest families in the west country; his uncle Jonathan (1684-1755) had sat as a Tory for Saltash and Fowey from 1710 to 1722. A partner in the Plymouth Bank (Elford, Tingcombe and Purchase) which was in existence by 1782, he wrote to Pitt in 1790 offering comments on the plan to tax country banks and praising the government’s general record.1 He was a talented artist, who exhibited at the Royal Academy for over 60 years, and an able scientist, whose most notable work was on yeast substitutes.

At the 1796 general election he was involved in Sir William Molesworth’s futile challenge to the Northumberland interest at Newport, but also stood for Plymouth, which lay about seven miles from Bickham, secured government support and was returned unopposed. The following year he was elected recorder of Plymouth. In his maiden speech, delivered from the government side of the House, 18 Oct. 1796, he welcomed augmentation of the forces to meet the threat of invasion and commended the Treason and Sedition Acts of 1795, which had ‘preserved the tranquillity of the country, and maintained a proper spirit of subordination, which without them could not be expected from a factious tribe of revolutionary doctors’. He was, he boasted, ‘as independent of the favour or rewards of ministers’ as any self-righteous Whig, whatever Fox might say to the contrary of those who supported government. A devoted follower of Pitt to the end, he indeed had little to show for his loyalty in terms of material reward, though not as a result of any conspicuous self-denial. Pitt seems to have taken little notice of him." --></div></back></text></TEI>