<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Letter to <persName ref="#Talfourd_Thos">T.N. Talfourd</persName>, [16 November] 1821</title><author ref="#MRM">Mary Russell Mitford</author><editor ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</editor><sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford Project</orgName></sponsor><sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor><principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal><respStmt><resp>Transcription and coding by</resp><persName ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Proofing and corrections by</resp><persName ref="#ghb">[who?]</persName><!-- correct when proofed LMW -->
               <!--ebb: 29 May 2014: Prosop entered to site index, but transcription needs to be proofed.--></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>First digital edition in TEI, date: 24 May 2014. P5.</edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority><pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace><date>2013</date><availability><p>Reproduced by courtesy of the <placeName>The John Rylands University Library</placeName>.</p><licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                  License</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Mitford Letters: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><repository ref="#Rylands">The John Rylands University Library</repository><collection>Mitford-Talfourd Correspondence: Letters from Mary Russell Mitford to Thomas Noon Talfourd: vol. 665</collection><idno>JRL English MS 665 no. 8 Coles no. 21</idno></msIdentifier><head>Letter from Mary Russell Mitford to T.N. Talfourd, <date when="1821-11-16">1821 November 16</date>. <!-- Nov. 16 was a Friday.  LMW --> <!--DSCF6118, DSCF6119, DSCF6121, DSCF6122, DSCF6123 LMW --></head><physDesc><objectDesc><supportDesc><support><p>Folio sheet of <material>paper</material> folded in half to form four
                              quarto pages, with correspondence on 1-3 and address leaf on page 4,
                              then folded in thirds twice more and sealed for posting.</p><p>Address leaf bearing two postmarks, both illegible.  One black, one sepia: circle with crown (text illegible).</p></support><condition><p>A portion of page 1 has been torn away under the seal.</p></condition></supportDesc></objectDesc><sealDesc><p>Wax seal missing, traces of red wax remain.</p></sealDesc></physDesc></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><handNotes><handNote xml:id="pencilRy" medium="pencil">Someone cataloging the letters, apparently
               other than Mitford, numbered each on page 1. This letter numbered 8.</handNote></handNotes></profileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><p>Mitford’s spelling and punctuation are retained, except where a word is split at the
               end of a line and the beginning of the next in the manuscript. Where Mitford’s
               spelling and hyphenation of words deviates from the standard, in order to facilitate
               searching we are using the TEI elements “choice," “sic," and “reg" to encode both
               Mitford’s spelling and the regular international standard of Oxford English spelling,
               following the first listed spelling in the Oxford English Dictionary. The long s and
               ligatured forms are not encoded.</p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="letter"><opener><dateline><date when="1821-11-16">Friday Morning.</date></dateline><salute><rs type="person" ref="#Talfourd_TN">My dear Sir</rs></salute></opener><p>Here is another Catastrophe, <rs type="person" ref="#Talfourd_TN">my dear Sir</rs>, for <persName ref="#Macready_Wm"/>Mr. Macready's consideration--I only wait hearing from you to finish the poisoning Scene, which I shall send up as soon as I possibly can consistently with my natural slowness.  If you like none of them I shall be quite ready to try another--or to alter any of these--Of course they are submitted to you with the most full &amp; perfect liberty to cut &amp; alter &amp; <emph rend="underline">add</emph>  wherever you think is proper--the last would be the greatest favor that could be done.  Was it necessary to say this?--Not having the copy to which these two sheets may perhaps be appended I <gap reason="torn" quantity="2" unit="word"/><supplied>do not</supplied> exactly know where the page began--but I believe <gap reason="torn" quantity="2" unit="word"/><supplied>I am</supplied> not--far from the mark &amp; the <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/>cutting</del> striking out a few <gap reason="torn" quantity="1" unit="word"/><supplied>words</supplied> would not I suppose spoil the copy for presentation--I am quite sorry to give you this sort of petty trouble--but whilst I am talking of these details I must tell you two or three very trifling things <persName ref="#Milman_HH">Mr. Milman</persName> suggested--or rather marked as faults--In the first scene that part of <persName ref="#Erizzo">Erizzo's</persName> speech on <persName ref="Donato">Donato's</persName> return, "And such a boon as he would grant his Page to pay the song that lulls him off to sleep"<note resp="#lmw"><!--This line appears to be have been deleted from the play.--></note>--I rather think that may be like somebody else--I think he must mean that--at all events be so good as to strike it <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/>up</del> out. Early in the Senate scene I had made a very stupid mistake in accenting a name--In <persName ref="#Erizzo">Erizzo's</persName> Speech to his faction will you write "<persName ref="#Pisani_F">Pisani</persName>, or <persName ref="#Donato">Donato's</persName> riper years" instead of "<persName ref="#Donato">Donato</persName> or <persName ref="#Pisani_F">Count Pisani</persName> on thine" <note resp="#lmw">Printed text has:  <l>On vigorous manhood's clustering curls? On thine, </l><l><persName ref="#Donato">Donato</persName>? Or, Pisani, upon thine? </l><l>Or any man of us? Lords, have ye changed </l> This appears to be the only mention by name of Count Pisani in the play.</note>--In the third Act he objects to the getting off of <persName ref="#Laura_F"/>Laura--but that the Manager must manage--&amp; to <placeName ref="#Mt_Ida">Ida's</placeName><emph rend="underline">top</emph>in the <persName ref="#Doge_F">Doge's</persName> compliment to <persName ref="#Olivia_F">Olivia.</persName>--he says myrtles won't blow there--which I believe is time enough--Will <placeName ref="#Mt_Ida">Ida's</placeName><emph rend="underline">side</emph> do?  And will you be so good as to write it so--He has likewise marked "guiltless of brains" <note resp="#lmw"><!-- no such line in the printed play.  LMW --></note><del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="character"/></del> in the <persName ref="#Doge_F">Doge's</persName> account of the prophecy--but I don't know why--Should I alter it do <pb n="2"/><note resp="#lmw"><!-- The three sections that follow are all written on page two, around the address section. LMW--></note>you think? He has likewise made himself two or three verbal alterations of no great consequence one way or the other which I have retained in the copy for printing but which would never be noticed on the stage.--One thing I wish myself to submit to you. In the Trial scene <persName ref="#Erizzo">Erizzo</persName> in his last question to <persName ref="#Camilla">Camilla</persName> says--Did'st thou not hear <persName ref="#Donato">Donato</persName><emph rend="underline"> call on</emph><persName ref="#Doge_F">Foscari</persName>?" Now does not this approach too nearly to the real truth &amp; not to the inference which he intended to draw from it?  Would Didst thou not hear <persName ref="#Donato">Donato's</persName> voice cry <persName ref="#Foscari_Fr">Foscari</persName>?  be better?--And may the Audience be trusted to make out that <note resp="#lmw"><!--section break 1 LMW--></note><persName ref="#Donato">Donato</persName> knew he was with <persName ref="#Camilla">Camilla</persName> or should some such intimation be introduced?  This will probably appear better at the rehearsal.  Oh if it should ever come to that!  Do you really think it will?--<persName ref="#Milman_HH">Mr. Milman</persName> speaks very civilly of the <title ref="#Foscari_MRMplay">Play</title> as pretty &amp; affecting--increasing very much in interest as it proceeeds &amp; exceedingly likely to tell well in representation.  This is more than I expected a great deal--&amp; full as much as it deserves.  If you see <persName ref="#Quayle_Mr">Mr. Quale</persName><!-- same person, different spelling?  Coles also reads this "Quale" with no notation.  LMW --> &amp; tell him the state of our affair will you assure him of my sincere gratitude for his kindness--I am sure he was <note resp="#lmw"><!--section break 2 LMW--></note>sincere in his offers of service --How very very good my friends are to me <gap reason="torn" quantity="1" unit="word"/><supplied>--you </supplied> Shall certainly get the new act by the midd <gap reason="torn" quantity="2" unit="word"/><supplied>le of</supplied>next week--</p><pb n="3"/><p> Pray<note resp="#lmw"><!--Written across top of page one, runs horizontally LMW--></note> excuse the wafer as I am afraid of weight--My <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Father</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#M_Russell">Mother</persName> join in a thousand thanks &amp; good wishes &amp;</p><closer><lb/>I am always your very grateful &amp; troublesome friend--<lb/><signed><persName ref="#MRM">M.R. Mitford</persName></signed><lb/></closer><closer><address><addrLine> To <persName ref="#Talfourd_Thos">T. N. Talfourd</persName> Esq<hi rend="superscript">re</hi></addrLine><!--No posting address on this one.  Talfourd's name is underlined. LMW --></address></closer></div></body><back>
         <!--ebb: 29 May 2014: Prosopography added to site index.--></back></text></TEI>