<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><?xml-model href="http://ebeshero.github.io/MRMValidate.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Letter to <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir William Elford</persName>, <date when="1821-11-23">23 November 1821</date>.</title><author ref="#MRM">Mary Russell Mitford</author><editor ref="#ajc">Amy Colombo</editor><sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitfrod Project</orgName></sponsor><sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor><principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal><respStmt><resp>Transcription and coding by</resp><persName ref="#ajc">Amy Colombo</persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Proofing and corrections by</resp><persName ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</persName><!-- lmw:  Proofed against ms. on 2015 09 27. Header still needs to be updated/revised. --><persName ref="#ebb">Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>First digital edition in TEI, date: 19 June 2014. P5.</edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority><pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace><date>2014</date><availability><p>Reproduced by courtesy of the <placeName>Reading central Library</placeName>.</p><licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Mitford Letters: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><repository ref="#ReadingCL">Reading Central Library"</repository><collection>The letters of Mary Russell Mitford, vol.r, 1819-1823</collection><idno>qB/TU/MIT Vol. 4 ff.441 Horizon No.: 1361550</idno></msIdentifier><head>Letter from Mary Russell Mitford to Sir William Elford, <date>23 November 2821</date></head><physDesc><objectDesc><supportDesc><support><p>Three folio sheets of <material>paper</material> with correspondence on
                     recto and verso 1-6. The address is written perpendicular to last comments on page 6. The pages are folded in
                     half and thirds twice more and were sealed for posting. This letter is glued into a scrapbook. The
                     address leaf bears the remnants of a red circular wax seal, and an illegible black stamped Reading mileage stamp. The address
                     appears to be written in another hand.
                           <stamp>READING<lb/></stamp></p></support><condition><p>Mitford notes that these pages are
                           "soiled" because they were previously used to protect a MSS. Page 5 has a pieces torn out along the
                        right border--probably due to opening the letter.Page 6 appears to have been repaired.</p></condition></supportDesc></objectDesc></physDesc></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><handNotes><handNote xml:id="rc" medium="red_crayon"> Red or thick red pencil. Probably a different hand from
           Mitford's drawning a diagonal line (top left to bottom right) across pages 1-5</handNote><handNote corresp="#pencil" medium="pencil">Someone wrote "3]" on the first page of the letter above
           "William" near the upuper left of the page.</handNote></handNotes></profileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><p>Mitford’s spelling and punctuation are retained, except where a word is split at the end of a line and 
              the beginning of the next in the manuscript. Where Mitford’s spelling and hyphenation of words deviates 
              from the standard, in order to facilitate searching we are using the TEI elements “choice," “sic," and
              “reg" to encode both Mitford’s spelling and the regular international standard of Oxford English 
              spelling, following the first listed spelling in the Oxford English Dictionary. The long s 
              and ligatured forms are not encoded</p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="letter"><opener><dateline><name type="place"><placeName ref="#ThreeMileCross">Three Mile Cross</placeName></name><date when="1821-11-24">Nov. 23<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> 1821.</date></dateline><salute>To <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir W. Elford</persName></salute></opener><p><orgName ref="#Mitfords_Ma_Pa">They</orgName> are all gone to bed, my dear <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir William</persName>, &amp; I have not a sheet
           of paper <choice><sic>comeatable</sic><reg resp="#ajc">come-at-able</reg></choice> but one which has already done hard duty in keeping clean some <choice><sic>M.S.S.</sic><reg resp="#lmw">ms.'s</reg></choice> so you have only your choice of the soiled paper or no letter <choice><sic>to night</sic><reg resp="#ajc">tonight</reg></choice>--Which do you choose? Eh? I rather think the unclean paper--so I write. I began to think that you &amp; I were trying as for a wager which should be silent longest &amp; that you had taken one of the oaths by Styx that you wot of not to write first--&amp; I was--(only that I would not tell the dear man so for the world for fear he should take it as a hint never to write in a fair honest battledore &amp; <choice><sic>shuttle-cock</sic><reg resp="#ajc">shuttlecock</reg></choice> way again) I was actually meditating a second letter when <choice><sic>your's</sic><reg resp="#ajc">yours</reg></choice> arrived. Very delightful it is that long expected letter--quite full of your charming vein. Yes by all manner of means put in the dog it is exactly what I wonder He--the great Unknown! did not put in himself--for he is a dear lover of the faithful race &amp; generally foists in some dog or other wherever it is possible.<note resp="#lmw">A reference to <persName ref="#Scott_Wal">Walter Scott</persName>'s love of dogs. The title "The Great Unknown" was given by the press to Scott after he was revealed as the anonymous author of <title ref="#Waverley">Waverley</title>.</note><foreign>Vide</foreign><title ref="#Letters_to_Heber">Letters to <persName ref="#Heber_Rich">R. Heber Esq</persName><hi rend="superscript">re</hi></title> tending to prove <persName ref="#Scott_Wal">Walter Scott</persName> (<emph rend="underline">Sir Walter</emph>--I beg pardon of his Baronetship) the Author of <title ref="#Waverley">Waverley</title>--which letters as you are a mighty Scotch Noveller I recommend to your perusal--They seem to me quite unanswerable. Pray have you read <title ref="#Valerius_novel">Valerius</title> yet? &amp; don't you think there is a touch of his pen there? <note resp="#lmw"><title ref="#Valerius_novel">Valerius: A Roman Story (1821)</title> was not written by <persName ref="#Scott_Wal">Walter Scott</persName> but by <persName ref="#Lockhart_JG">J.G. Lockhart</persName>, who had married <persName ref="#Scott_Wal">Scott</persName>'s daughter in 1820.</note>You will like it I promise you--for I did in spite of a strong predisposition to dislike the Romans who always seemed to me a sad sensual heartless race whose best virtues have a prodigious resemblance to crimes. Your<pb n="2"/>picture<note resp="#lmw"><persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Elford</persName>'s painting, to which <persName ref="#MRM">Mitford</persName> refers, is as yet unknown.</note> (Pray my dear friend invent for me a <choice><sic>nack</sic><reg resp="#lmw">knack</reg></choice> of getting back to a subject when one has unluckily strayed) Your picture must with your fine taste &amp; execution be charming--I have always had a preference for close, <choice><sic>shut in</sic><reg resp="#ajc">shut-in</reg></choice> scenes, both in a landscape &amp; in nature, &amp; prefer the end of a woody lane with a rustic bridge over a little stream, or a bit of an old cottage <add place="above"><metamark place="below" function="insertion" rend="caret"/>or farm House</add> with a porch &amp; a vine &amp; clustered chimneys peeping out amongst <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/></del> trees to any prospect that I ever saw in my life. I dare say that this taste of mine is as wrong as I confess it to be ignoble--for I never met with any one who agreed with me in my opinion. But your picture will be quite poetry. I hope you will send it to <placeName ref="#Somerset_House">Somerset House</placeName>. Talking of pictures (this is not a jerk)<note resp="#lmw"><persName ref="#MRM">Mitford</persName> uses the term "jerk" to refer to wavy lines she draws when changing subjects in her letters. Here, she seems to indicate to Elford that this is not a change of subject.</note> we were a little astonished in common with all his friends, for he had kept it a profound secret at <persName ref="#Haydon">Mr. Haydon</persName>'s marriage. It is entirely a love match &amp; I hope &amp; trust that it will make him as happy as he deserves to be all his life long. He speaks of <persName ref="#Haydon_Mrs">her</persName>(for I have heard from him several times) as still more amiable than beautiful, &amp; as it has been a long acquaintance &amp; not a very short courtship there is every reason to believe that he is right.<note resp="#lmw"><persName ref="#Haydon">Haydon</persName> wed <persName ref="#Haydon_Mrs">Mary Cawse Hyman</persName> on <date when="1821-10-10">October 10, 1821</date>.</note> She is in <placeName ref="#Devonshire_county">Devonshire</placeName> just now to put the final close to some matters of business &amp; he is gone to <placeName ref="#Scotland">Scotland</placeName> to put up his picture. I had a letter from him <choice><sic>to day</sic><reg resp="#ajc">today</reg></choice> dated <placeName ref="#Edinburgh">Edinburgh</placeName>--He says that <persName ref="#Allan_SrWm">Allan</persName>(whom <persName ref="#Morris_DrP">Dr. Peter Morris&gt;</persName>, Alias <persName ref="#Lockhart_JG">John Lockhart</persName>, lauded so incredibly) is very much improved indeed &amp; will be an honour to <placeName ref="#Scotland">Scotland</placeName>. He has just finished--no not quite finished is about--a picture which <persName ref="#Haydon">Mr. Haydon</persName> praises exceedingly. It is called <title corresp="#BrokenFiddle_WA">the broken fiddle</title>--an old wooden legged sailor has just broken his fiddle over the pate of a young dog who had been playing him some mischievous trick,--the boy's Grandam is clenching her fist at him &amp; the sailor totally disregarding the old woman's scolding is enjoying the roaring <!--ajc:  See letter to MRM from Haydon 11-1821 in Benjamin Robert Haydon: Correspondence and Table-talk(1876), Volume 2 p.74--><pb n="3"/>of the unlucky lad. Pray do you know if <persName ref="#Haydon">Mr. Haydon's</persName> family were aware of his marriage? &amp; if they approved it? Is his <persName ref="#Haydon_Father">Father</persName> living? His <persName ref="#Haydon_Mother">Mother</persName> I know is not--for he often speaks of her with great regret &amp; affection. He says that <persName ref="#Haydon_Mother">Mrs. H</persName> was married by her friends when very young to her first husband--whom he describes as to person pretty much as you do <metamark rend="jerks"/> Pray can you give me any news of my very dear friend <persName ref="#Dickinson_Mrs">Mrs. Dickinson</persName>? She is somewhere about your <placeName ref="#Devonshire_county">Devonshire Coast</placeName>--three months ago she disappeared from these parts &amp; for six whole weeks I thought I had lost her--then she came to life again in two letters dated Plymouth in which she spoke <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/></del><add>in</add> such raptures of <placeName ref="#Devonshire_county">Devonshire</placeName> &amp; the sea that she declared she did not think she could ever resign herself to living <emph rend="underline">inland</emph> again. Since these letters I have lost her <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/></del> once more &amp; only that I know the <placeName ref="#Devonshire_county">Devonshire</placeName> air has sometimes an anti-epistolary effect upon my best &amp; dearest &amp; cleverest friends. I should really be afraid that some sea God had taken her at her word &amp; whisked her off to live with the mermaids &amp; those worthy people. I hope this foggy November will drive her home--Or at least drive her to letter writing--she sometimes sends a little bit of journalizing which is charming--quite as naturally &amp; sweetly written as if it <add place="above"><metamark place="below" function="insertion" rend="caret"/>were</add> all <choice><sic>make believe</sic><reg resp="#ajc">make-believe</reg></choice> &amp; got up for the Magazines. This will seem to you an odd compliment--but it is so--the really natural in writing is an exquisitely laboured &amp; difficult thing--the very perfection of art--which is the reason why my letters in spite of a little pertness &amp; sprightliness are I am afraid altogether good for nothing. They are at present in status quo--for I have been engaged in the tormenting business of altering &amp; re-altering my poor <title ref="#Foscari_MRMplay">Play</title>. You cannot--unless you write a Tragedy yourself with <emph rend="underline">five</emph> different catastrophes as I have done--form the slightest notion what a miserable business<pb n="4"/>alteration is. At present <persName ref="#Macready_Wm">Mr. Macready</persName> has my <title ref="#Foscari_MRMplay">Tragedy</title> with four different conclusions (that is to say four fifth Acts) of which he is to take his choice! He enters into it heart &amp; soul &amp; is a most warm &amp; zealous friend, but I am still afraid that it will be refused by the manager--all is intrigue behind the curtain--&amp; to add to my misfortunes <persName ref="#Byron"> Lord Byron</persName> has written a <title ref="#The_Two_Foscari">Tragedy</title> on the same subject--which will of course be as bold &amp; daring as mine is feeble &amp; womanish.</p><lb/><p>Monday. I have <del rend="squiggle"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/><supplied resp="#lmw">just</supplied></del> got a frank <add place="above"><metamark place="below" function="insertion" rend="caret"/>for the day</add> &amp; having unluckily been hindered by those Gadflies morning visitors must finish at the gallop. Apropos to franks I have not seen that accomplished Franker <persName ref="#Palmer_CF">Mr. Palmer</persName> or his charming <persName ref="#Palmer_Mad">wife</persName> since last September twelvemonth!--We have been very gay at <placeName ref="#Reading_city">Reading</placeName> with our triennial Theatricals--<persName ref="#Valpy_Richard">Dr. Valpy</persName>'s <title ref="#Orestes_play">Greek Play</title>. There is nothing so charming as that classical amusement (by the way the <persName ref="#Valpy_Richard">Doctor</persName> always makes me write the official <emph rend="underline">puff</emph> account &amp; I have been hunting more minutes than I ought to have spared from my letter to find a <placeName ref="#Reading_city">Reading</placeName> paper to<choice><sic>shew</sic><reg resp="#ajc">show</reg></choice> you what a famous <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/></del> theatrical critic I am--but I can't find it so you must belive my own puff of my puffing)--Nothing so charming as the <title ref="#Orestes_play">Greek Play</title>, with its beautiful accuracy of costume, every fold copied after some antique statue, its fine groupings &amp; the delicious sound of that magnificient language. The Play this year was <title ref="#Orestes_play">Orestes of <persName ref="#Euripides">Euripides</persName></title> of which the opening scene is perhaps one of the finest &amp; truest exhibitions of nature that has ever been given by any Poet in any language. The <title ref="#Orestes_play">Greek Play</title> was enchanting--but every pleasure has its alloy, &amp; <persName ref="#Valpy_Richard">Dr. Valpy</persName> against all prayer &amp; all warning was determined to make us pay for our previous delight by inflicting on us after the <title ref="#Orestes_play">Orestes</title> the three last Acts of
<title ref="#King_John_play">King John</title> as altered <pb n="5"/> from <persName ref="#Shakespeare">Shakespeare</persName> by himself. Fancy the worst parts of <persName ref="#Shakespeare">Shakespeare's</persName> worst play with the most iniquitous alterations ever devised by schoolmaster acted by a rabble of boys of all ages &amp; sizes--all bad. Some thick &amp; shaped like <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="3" unit="word"/></del> pincushions--others pointed &amp; angular &amp; sharp limbed as it were, like <choice><sic>scissars</sic><reg resp="#ajc">scissors</reg></choice>--the <persName ref="#Dauphin_WS">Dauphin</persName> a little round short fellow not taller than a thimble &amp; <persName ref="#King_Philip_WS">King Philip</persName>a shot up limber lad, tall, &amp; bent in the middle like a broken <choice><sic>thread paper</sic><reg resp="#ajc">thread-paper</reg></choice>! Oh that <title ref="#King_John_play">King John</title>! I shan't recover it these two years.--Ever since the <title ref="#Orestes_play">Greek Play</title> I have been trying as well asI can in French &amp; English &amp; Italian Translations to get at the Greek Dramatists, &amp; am so in love with <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/></del><persName ref="#Aeschylus">Aschylus</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#Sophocles">Sophocles</persName> (<persName ref="#Euripides">Euripides</persName> though very fine rather in a lower style--more pathetic than sublime) that I can really hardly think or talk of <choice><sic>any thing</sic><reg resp="#ajc">anything</reg></choice> else. <persName ref="#Sophocles">Sophocles</persName> in particular--&amp; of all <persName ref="#Sophocles">Sophocles</persName><title ref="#Philoctetes_play">Philoctetes</title> exceeds all that I have ever seen before. There never was &amp; never will be <choice><sic>any thing</sic><reg resp="#ajc">anything</reg></choice> like the Greek Dramatists. The moulds are broken--the English romantic Drama is not more different from them in form than the French in spirit. The English Translations of <persName ref="#Sophocles">Sophocles</persName> are <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/></del> abominable--I find that I get at him best from <damage agent="smudge" unit="word" quantity="1"/><unclear><supplied resp="ajc">a</supplied></unclear> literal version in French prose--&amp; I have half a mind to <emph rend="underline">do</emph> the <title ref="#Philoctetes_play">Philoctetes</title> into English from that source--declaring of course in the Preface that I know nothing at all of Greek &amp; took it from <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="3" unit="word"/></del><add place="above">the <persName ref="#Brumoy_Pierre">Abbe Brumoy</persName></add>--<note resp="#lmw"><persName ref="#MRM"> Mitford refers to <title ref="#Th_d_Gr">Théâtre des Grecs</title> by <persName ref="#Brumoy_Pierre"/>Pierre Brumoy,</persName> a work she names elsewhere as having read.</note>--but this I have not resolved upon.</p><closer><choice><sic>Godbless</sic><reg resp="#ajc">God bless</reg></choice> you my dear friend--I hope to hear a better account of both your Invalids--Kindest regards from all--Ever yours<lb/><signed><persName ref="#MRM">MRM</persName></signed><pb n="6"/><lb/></closer><postscript><p>We have mentioned your Residence to let wherever we thought it probable to produce a tenant--but in vain.--Once more goodbye!</p><pb n="7"/><!--lmw: these lines are written back on page one. --><p>Pray write very soon indeed--Don't expect another letter till you have.--<choice><sic>Godbless</sic><reg resp="#ajc">God bless</reg></choice> you my dear <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Friend</persName>!</p></postscript><closer><address>
       <!--ajc: address written (in another hand) perpendicular to the last remarks on the top of page 6--><addrLine><placeName ref="#Reading_city">Reading</placeName><date when="1821-11-25">November twenty <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="2" unit="chars"/>fo</del>five</date><date when="1821">1821</date></addrLine><lb/><addrLine><persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> W<hi rend="superscript">m</hi> Elford Bar<hi rend="superscript"><emph rend="underline">t</emph></hi></persName></addrLine><lb/><addrLine><placeName ref="#Bickham_village">Bickham</placeName></addrLine><lb/><addrLine><persName ref="#Monck_JB">J.B. Monck</persName></addrLine><addrLine><placeName ref="#Plymouth_city">Plymouth</placeName></addrLine><lb/></address></closer></div></body><back>
<!-- LMW:  added backlist to my si-add-LMW file.
        --></back><!--ebb: Amy: I just fixed the problem, which was just some extra <div> tags making things uneven. Have a look at this in outline view: I've wrapped all the backlists in a single outer <div> element, and then inside it are your specialized div "boxes" for places, people, organizations, and publications. Thanks for the helpful contributions to the site index!--></text></TEI>