<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><?xml-model href="http://ebeshero.github.io/MRMValidate.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Letter to <persName ref="#Talfourd_Thos">T.N. Talfourd</persName>, 1821 [July 31]</title><author ref="#MRM">Mary Russell Mitford</author><editor ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</editor><editor ref="#tlh">Tracy L. Harnish</editor><sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford Project</orgName></sponsor><sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor><principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal><respStmt><resp>Transcription and coding by</resp><persName ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</persName><persName ref="#tlh">Tracy L. Harnish</persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Proofing and corrections by</resp><persName ref="#ebb">Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName><!-- correct when proofed LMW -->
               <!--ebb: 29 May 2014: Prosop entered, but letter transcription needs to be checked.-->
               <!--ebb: 24 April 2016: Added Project Schematron Line to correct mistyped @ref attributes with the site index.--></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>First digital edition in TEI, date: 22 May 2014. P5.</edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority><pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace><date>2013</date><availability><p>Reproduced by courtesy of the <placeName>The John Rylands University Library</placeName>.</p><licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                  License</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Mitford Letters: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><repository ref="#Rylands">The John Rylands University Library</repository><collection>Mitford-Talfourd Correspondence: Letters from Mary Russell Mitford to Thomas Noon Talfourd: vol. 665</collection><idno>JRL English MS 665 no. 2 Coles no. 9</idno></msIdentifier><head>Letter from Mary Russell Mitford to T.N. Talfourd, <date when="1821-07-31">1821 July 31</date>. <!-- Coles, #9, note 1:  "the letter is undated but the diary records that the 'two first Acts of Foscari' were sent off on July 31." July 31 was a Tuesday.  LMW --> <!-- DSCN1146, DSCN1147, DSCN1148, DSCN1149 LMW --></head><physDesc><objectDesc><supportDesc><support><p>Folio sheet of <material>paper</material> folded in half to form four
                              quarto pages, with correspondence on 1-3 and address leaf on page 4,
                              then folded in thirds twice more and sealed for posting.</p><p>Address leaf bearing no postmarks.</p> <!-- Many stray marks, "Mr." and figures, perhaps transferred from another document, perhaps in another hand? LMW --></support><condition><p>A portion of page 3 has been torn away under the seal.</p></condition></supportDesc></objectDesc><sealDesc><p>Red wax seal missing, traces of red wax remain.</p></sealDesc></physDesc></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><handNotes><handNote xml:id="pencilRy" medium="pencil">Someone cataloging the letters, apparently
               other than Mitford, numbered each on page 1. This letter numbered 2.</handNote></handNotes></profileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><p>Mitford’s spelling and punctuation are retained, except where a word is split at the
               end of a line and the beginning of the next in the manuscript. Where Mitford’s
               spelling and hyphenation of words deviates from the standard, in order to facilitate
               searching we are using the TEI elements “choice," “sic," and “reg" to encode both
               Mitford’s spelling and the regular international standard of Oxford English spelling,
               following the first listed spelling in the Oxford English Dictionary. The long s and
               ligatured forms are not encoded.</p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="letter"><opener><dateline><name type="place" ref="#ThreeMileCross">Three Mile Cross</name>--<date when="1821-07-31">Tuesday</date>.
               </dateline><salute><persName ref="#Talfourd_Thos">My dear Sir</persName></salute></opener><p>I send you the first two Acts, all that I have yet put together of <title ref="#Foscari_MRMplay">Foscari</title>--Not, I assure you, with any view to encroach on your time &amp; attention at a place where they will be so much better occupied but simply to relieve my good friend <persName ref="#Monck_JB">Mr. Monck</persName>, for whose unwearied kindness I can never be sufficiently thankful--by sending off three frankfuls by a private hand.--So now put the papers by--&amp; do not read another word till you are again in progress. You will get the rest of the play in about ten days. I cannot express to you how much I am dissatisfied &amp; disappointed at it--I expected to have done better--but you will tell me what to put out &amp; suggest what to put in &amp; perhaps it may be mendable. If not it can at any time go into the fire, where, by the bye, it very nearly had gone without reaching you.  You will find that I have conformed to <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/>your</del><add place="above">the</add> representation of the Venetian government as we find it in the great Dramatists, &amp; confined myself to a Doge &amp; a Senate insted of entering into the real &amp; inextricable complexity of that most intricate State. I did this as much for effect as for convenience.--for in the Drama it seems to me that too strict a preservation of costume is as great an evil as too wide a departure from it--a Dramatic writer cannot explain as a Novelist may do &amp; therefore should not shock the prejudices of an audience by any outstanding novelty.  The "Signors of the Night" in <rs type="title" ref="#Marino_Faliero">Lord Byron's Play</rs> seemed to me enough to have broken any illusion--Am I right in this?  If not <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/>we</del><add place="above">I</add> could easily break the Senate into such divisions as come nearer to the real form of the Venetian Government.</p><pb n="2"/><p><title ref="#Foscari_MRMplay">My play</title> as I have writen it ia an odd compound of <persName ref="#Hofland_B">Mrs. Hofland's</persName> Legend &amp; the real History of the <persName ref="#Doge_F_hist">Doge Foscari</persName>--The prophecy belongs to the latter division--but I have managed the political part so ill as to have repented fifty times of having departed from the domestic opening, &amp; should certainly write the whole tragedy over again upon the original plan if it were not for the difficulty of finding any one to represent the <persName type="fict">Mother</persName>.<!-- xml:id?  I don't see a Mother role in Foscari; is this a deleted character?  LMW -->  My Villain <persName ref="#Erizzo">Erizzo</persName>hangs like a night mare <choice resp="#lmw"><reg>nightmare</reg></choice>over the drama.--&amp; yet I don't know how to get rid of him.--Have I stolen the opening scene--or any part of it <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/>of</del> from some thing that I ought to remember? Tell me if I have--&amp; pray mark as many parts that occur to you as borrowed.  Have I not in my abhorrence to the pompus strut the artifical elevation of the French School <!-- needs note? LMW -->fallen into the contrary error &amp; become too familiar? And in trying to preserve the subtle spirit of the dialogue is there not too much<del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/>of</del> transition &amp; abruptness--too much left to be inferred by the reader or explained by the Actor? Oh my dear <persName ref="#Talfourd_Thos">Mr. Talfourd</persName>--what would become of me if I had not the comfort of resorting to your kindness &amp; your judgement! How can I ever be grateful enough for your goodness to me!  I say this for the hundredth time because I am always thinking it.</p><p>How sorry I am that your delicacy (I wonder whether any body else ever had so much?) stood in the way of your visiting<placeName ref="#Reading_city">Reading</placeName> just now--It would have been such a pleasure to have seen you here--&amp; really my flowers are worth looking at--not for rarity or beauty as a florist understands the word, but for gaiety abundance profusion! I never saw such a crowd of bright blossoms--But they will soon be over--this balmy dropping weather which brings them out so beautifully will carry them off--Do you love flowers? Do you sympathize with my passion for them? Or do you laugh at it?--I don't know what I should do without them.</p><pb n="3"/><p>I return to <persName ref="#Baldwin_R">Mr. Baldwin's</persName> letter which I put into my pocket intending to give it you in <placeName ref="#Reading_city">Reading</placeName>, but forgot it--How many thanks do I owe you on that score too. <persName ref="#Colburn">Mr. Colburn</persName> has I think paid for more than I have furnished him with even including the unprinted articles--When <title ref="#Foscari_MRMplay">Foscari</title> is finished I will take care to get out of his debt.--</p><p>I hope you have a great deal to do in<placeName ref="#Abingdon">Abingdon</placeName> &amp; at <placeName ref="#Oxford_city">Oxford</placeName> &amp; that the good report will spread along the line of the circuit &amp; briefs pour in at Towns that were barren last time--We shall be very anxious to hear what you did in <placeName ref="#Abingdon">Abingdon</placeName>--It will be <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</persName>'s first question on Saturday when he sees<persName ref="#May_J">Mr. May</persName>--he and my dear <persName ref="#Russell_M">Mother</persName> join in kindest remembrances &amp; good wishes.</p><closer><lb/>I am always most gratefully your's<lb/><signed><persName ref="#MRM">M.R. Mitford.</persName></signed><lb/></closer><postscript><p>Of course you will keep the two Acts till you get the rest--Is <persName ref="#Macready_Wm">Mr. Macready</persName>likely to act at <placeName ref="#Covent_Garden_Theatre">Covent Garden</placeName>? Oh to lose him would be almost as bad as losing you!--Good bye.</p><p>Am I wrong to bring in <persName ref="#Sforza">Sforza</persName>'s name since he does not appear? It looks a little like the introduction of <persName ref="#ElizI">Queen Elizabeth</persName> <!-- list as fict or hist?  LMW -->in the Play in <title ref="#Critic_play">the Critic</title><!-- Need note: Reference to II.ii LMW -->--But as he is a great historical personage &amp; was the real <persName ref="#Sforza_hist">General of Venice</persName> at the time I thought it would give something of truth &amp; reality to the scene--He can however be very easily omitted if you think it better--So could the prophecy.--Once more good bye!--I have marked with a pencil two or three passages which I suspect as borrowed--Do you remember them? For the third &amp; last time Good bye!--Had not I better call it <rs type="title" ref="#Foscari_MRMplay"><emph rend="underline">the</emph>Foscari</rs> <!--Is this okay? It is a proposed alternative title for the play, not used.  LMW -->for fear the <persName ref="#Doge_F">old Doge</persName> be taken as the Hero? Though of course in the two last acts his part is quite subordinate. I shall seal my letter--there is no other security against my going on over the page &amp; then crossing the whole epistle--I won't say Good bye again because it seems in my hands to have changed its meaning.</p></postscript><closer><address><addrLine> To <persName ref="#Talfourd_Thos">T. N. Talfourd</persName> Esq<hi rend="superscript">re</hi></addrLine><!--No posting address on this one.  Talfourd's name is underlined. LMW --></address></closer></div></body><back>
         <!--ebb: 29 May 2014: Entered new prosop data in Site Index.--></back></text></TEI>