<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><?xml-model href="http://ebeshero.github.io/MRMValidate.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Letter to <persName ref="#Haydon">B.R. Haydon</persName>, <date when="1821-05-02">2 May 1821</date>.</title><author ref="#MRM">Mary Russell Mitford</author><editor>James Rovira</editor><sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford
               Project</orgName></sponsor><sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor><principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal><respStmt><resp>Transcription and coding by</resp><persName>James Rovira</persName><persName>Rebecca Nesvet</persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Date last checked: <date when="2014-06-02">2014-06-02</date>. Proofing and corrections by: </resp><persName ref="#esh">Eric Hood</persName><persName ref="#lmw"/> <!-- lmw:  proofed against ms. 2015 09 27.  Needs header checked and some backlist developed. --></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>First digital edition in TEI, date: 1 June 2014. P5.</edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority><pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace><date>2013</date><availability><p>Reproduced by courtesy of the <placeName>Reading Central Library</placeName>.</p><licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                  License</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Mitford Letters: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><repository ref="#ReadingCL">Reading Central Library</repository><collection>The letters of Mary Russell Mitford, vol. 4, 1819-1823</collection><idno>qB/TU/MIT Vol. 4 ff.441 Horizon No.: 1361550</idno></msIdentifier><head>Letter from Mary Russell Mitford to B. R. Haydon, <date>2 May 1821</date>. </head><physDesc><objectDesc><supportDesc><support><p>Folio sheet of <material>paper</material> folded in thirds both ways because it was not mailed with an envelope, with correspondence on 1-3 and address leaf on page 4, then folded in thirds twice more and sealed for posting.</p><p>Address leaf bearing the following postmarks: 1) black circular mileage stamp <!-- Applied upon deposit of letter at local PO --> reading <stamp>READING<lb/><unclear><gap quantity="1" unit="chars" reason="illegible"/></unclear></stamp>. 2) Red double circle Evening Duty stamp<!-- Applied upon arrival in London --> reading <date when="1821-11-01"><stamp>C<lb/>4 MY<lb/>1821</stamp></date>. 3) Sepia-inked oval Delivery stamp
                              <!-- Applied upon transfer from Inland Mail to
                                 London's local Penny Post for delivery. -->
                              reading <stamp><time>10 o'Clock</time><lb/><date>MY 4</date><lb/><date>1821</date> F.N<hi rend="superscript">n </hi></stamp></p><p>A large 7 denoting the fee for a single-sheet letter has been written
                              in black ink by the postal service across the address leaf.</p></support></supportDesc></objectDesc><sealDesc><p>1/2 red wax seal, only partially visible in image 2May1821BRHaydon4a.JPG
                        from 2007. Two halfs of monogram visible.</p></sealDesc></physDesc></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><handNotes><handNote xml:id="rc" medium="red_crayon"> Red crayon or thick red pencil. Probably a
               different hand from Mitford's drawing a diagonal line across pages 1-3.</handNote><handNote xml:id="black_ink" medium="black_ink"> Someone cataloging the letters,
               apparently other than Mitford, wrote From B R. Haydon Esq at the top of page
               1.</handNote><handNote corresp="#pencil" medium="pencil">Someone cataloging the letters, apparently
               other than Mitford, added no. 32 underneath the cataloging notation.</handNote></handNotes></profileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><p>Mitford’s spelling and punctuation are retained, except where a word is split at the
               end of a line and the beginning of the next in the manuscript. Where Mitford’s
               spelling and hyphenation of words deviates from the standard, in order to facilitate
               searching we are using the TEI elements “choice," “sic," and “reg" to encode both
               Mitford’s spelling and the regular international standard of Oxford English spelling,
               following the first listed spelling in the Oxford English Dictionary. The long s and
               ligatured forms are not encoded.</p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc></teiHeader><text><front><div type="witness"><listWit><witness xml:id="ebb">Elisa Beshero-Bondar</witness><witness xml:id="LEst1870"><bibl><title>The Life of Mary Russell Mitford Related in a Selection from Her
                     Letters to Her Friends, Second and Revised edition</title>, 3 vols., Ed.
                     <author>Alfred Guy Kingan L’Estrange</author>. <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>Richard Bentley</publisher>, <date>1870</date>. </bibl></witness></listWit></div></front><body><div type="letter"><opener><dateline><date when="1821-10-31">May 2<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> 1821.</date><placeName ref="#SeymourCt">Seymour Court</placeName> near <placeName ref="#Marlow">Marlow</placeName></dateline></opener><p>How much I thank you, my dear Sir, for your very interesting account of poor <persName ref="#Keats">John Keats</persName>--It explains at once the only want that I ever found in his poetry--a want of heart. Oh he should have lived to have become happier, better, wiser, with his fine perception of beauty he could not have failed to discover what was right--&amp; health &amp; happiness would have done <choice><sic>every thing</sic><reg>everything</reg></choice> for him--poor <persName ref="#Keats">John Keats</persName>!--Do not you see with what a shaking hand I am writing? I must tell you how it happens. A very kind &amp; partial <del rend="squiggles"/> old friend, <persName ref="#Johnson_Mr">Mr. Johnson</persName>, the owner of this beautiful  <rs type="place" ref="#SeymourCt">place</rs> is lately dead--&amp; his <persName ref="#Johnson_Miss">Sister</persName> sent for me to assist her in arranging &amp; cataloguing his very curious &amp; valuable library. <persName ref="#Johnson_Mr">Mr. Johnson</persName><persName ref="#Johnson_Mr">Mr. Johnson</persName> was a great Politician, an active member of the <orgName ref="#Hampden_Club">Hampden Club</orgName>, &amp; all his political books <del rend="squiggles"/> are left to your Countryman <persName ref="#Northmore_Thos">Mr. Northmore</persName>. So we are dividing as well as we can the Politics from the History &amp; getting the rest into order for sale--never I believe had mortal such a job since the Princess in the fairy tale who was ordered to separate the plumage of each bird from a room full of feathers.--I have got a room entirely full of books French English Italian &amp; Latin all pell mell--no two in their proper place &amp; nobody to help but a <rs type="person" ref="#Johnson_Miss">mistress</rs><del rend="squiggles"/><add place="above">partly</add> blind &amp; a maid wholly stupid. Oh dear me! to have been lifting about heavy books for these three days, &amp; making something like a catalogue between whiles, &amp; I am now sat down to talk to you to comfort &amp; refresh myself. In addition to the other difficulties of this booksorting, I have the strongest possible desire to <emph rend="underline">crib</emph> as much as I can from <persName ref="#Northmore_Thos">Mr. Northmore</persName>--for <persName ref="#Johnson_Mr">Mr. Johnson</persName> having <pb n="2"/> unfortunately neglected to renew the lives this lovely place &amp; the valuable estate round it fall immediately to the Dean &amp; Chapter of <placeName ref="#Bristol">Bristol</placeName>, &amp; the excellent sister who has devoted so many years to his comfort will return to comparative poverty. I hope the library will sell well.--Do you know <choice><sic>any thing</sic><reg>anything</reg></choice> of the scenery round <placeName ref="#Marlow">Marlow</placeName>? Oh it is so beautiful! Especially the view from this house which stands on the brow of a hill &amp; looks down on <placeName ref="#Marlow">Marlow</placeName> (a town made to be looked at a mile off the charm vanishes when you approached nearer)--<placeName ref="#Marlow">Marlow</placeName> so intermixed with trees--&amp; and the <placeName ref="#Thames">Thames</placeName> winding like a snake--showing himself only by glimpses, but given the perpetual consciousness of his presence--<placeName ref="#Bisham_Abbey">Bisham Abbey</placeName>that oldest &amp; most venerable place--&amp; the whole prospect crowned by hanging beech woods just in their young shining leaves <del rend="squiggles"/> so enchantingly varied by gleams of the sun wandering over them--&amp; the hills folding in so exquisitely! Oh it is beautiful! I wished for you very much last night when I went out to hear the nightingales--for you &amp; <persName ref="#James_Miss">Miss James</persName>. You will see her I hope for she is in <placeName ref="#London_city">London</placeName>--So tell me how she looks--for I am afraid she takes no care of herself--she has been very ill.</p><p>I have such an opinion of your critical talents that I cannot help asking you to take the trouble to read a little dramatic sketch called <title ref="#Emily_DS">Emily</title>in the present number of the <persName ref="#Baldwin_R">Baldwin</persName>'s <title ref="#LondonMag">Magazine</title><note resp="#rnes">Mitford is likely referring to <title ref="#Emily_DS">"Emily, A Dramatic Sketch"</title>, which appeared in the <title ref="#LondonMag">London Magazine</title> 3.17 (May 1821): 499-505.</note>--&amp; to tell me if <persName ref="#Talfourd_Thos">Mr. Talfourd</persName>'s kindness misleads him when he says that there is some indication of dramatic talent in the dialogue. I don't ask you to tell me the truth without flattery--because you are truth itself. I have written some more of those little dramas &amp; intend giving a series in the <persName ref="#Baldwin_R">Baldwin</persName>'s <title ref="#LondonMag">Magazine</title>, <persName ref="#Baldwin_R">Mr. Baldwin</persName> having expressed himself pleased with them though I don't believe he knows the name of his new correspondent. By the bye I have not seen the <title ref="#LondonMag">Magazine</title>--but<pb n="2"/> know it is inserted &amp; I feel quite proud at being in such good company--I was quite astonished when I found my sketch was accepted.--Oh my dear <persName ref="#Haydon">Mr. Haydon</persName> you have no notion how much <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</persName> laughs at your complimenting my handwriting.--he always says I write worse than <choice><sic>any one</sic><reg>anyone</reg></choice> in the  world--&amp; very unluckily <persName ref="#Macready_Wm">Mr. Macready</persName> to whom <persName ref="#Talfourd_Thos">Mr. Talfourd&gt;</persName> gave my <title ref="#Fiesco_MRMplay">Fiesco</title> could scarcely make it out--there's an affront! My very best specimen of penmanship!--so that I was obliged to have it copied out to be sent to the <persName>Manager</persName>. I don't know its fate yet--but I dare say it's rejected, &amp; I shall write another.</p><p>What you say of your picture is delightful to all of us--I have no doubt but you will paint on till <title corresp="#ChrstEJrslm_Haydon"><add place="above">Christ's</add><del rend="squiggles"/> entrance</title> shall be to your future pictures as <title ref="#Macbeth_play">Macbeth</title> is to that. I am sure you will--quite sure. Oh how proud <placeName ref="#England">England</placeName> will be of her great <gap quantity="1" unit="word" reason="hole"/><supplied>painter</supplied> And how worthy of such a painter is our glorious <placeName ref="#England">England</placeName>!</p><p>My candle is going out--&amp; I must go out too--that is to say I must go in.--I believe the dogs came to us <date from="1820-10-01" to="1820-10-07">the first week in October</date>--so that the man has had them rather more than half a year--I mention this as you desire it &amp; as the man is not rich. The dogs are quite well--especially the dear <persName ref="#Daphne_pet">Daphne</persName>.--<rs type="person" ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</rs> &amp; <rs type="person" ref="#Russell_M">Mama</rs> are <add place="above"><metamark place="below" function="insertion" rend="caret"><del rend="strikethrough">not</del></metamark></add> at home--or they would send every sort of kind message--I want them very much--but I shall go to them next <date when="1821-05-08">Tuesday</date> thank God! I long to be back at my own dear home beautiful as this place is, &amp; kind as is its mistress--In the <choice><sic>mean time</sic><reg>meantime</reg></choice> I must go to bed or I shall be in the dark.</p><closer><lb/>Good bye--God bless you--
               <lb/>Ever most sincerely <choice><sic>your's</sic><reg>yours</reg></choice><signed><persName ref="#MRM">M. R. Mitford</persName></signed></closer><postscript><p>So you think <persName ref="#Hofland_TC">Mr. Hofland</persName>'s Exhibition will answer? I fear not.</p></postscript></div></body><back><div>   <!--LMW:  adding these to my SI-add-LMW compilation 2015-09-30--><bibl xml:id="EmilyDS"><title>Emily, A Dramatic Sketch</title><author ref="#MRM"/><note resp="#rnes lmw"> Originally appeared in the <title ref="#LondonMag">London Magazine</title> 3.17 (May 1821): 499-505. Later reprinted in
                  <title ref="#DramaticScenes">Dramatic Scenes, Sonnets, and Other Poems</title>.</note></bibl><listPerson type="hist" subtype="animal"><person xml:id="Daphne_pet"><persName>Daphne</persName><note resp="#lmw">Mitford's dog, possibly a female greyhound.</note><!--LMW: update SI entry --></person></listPerson><listOrg><org xml:id="Hampden_Club"><orgName>Hampden Club</orgName></org></listOrg><listPlace><place xml:id="SeymourCt"><placeName>Seymour Court</placeName><note resp="#lmw #jjr">Home of <persName ref="#Johnson_Mr #Johnson_Miss">Mr. and Miss Johnson</persName>, until <persName ref="#Johnson_Mr">Mr. Johnson</persName>'s death in <date when="1821">1821</date>.  Near <placeName ref="#Marlow">Marlow</placeName></note></place><place xml:id="Bristol"><placeName>Bristol</placeName></place><place xml:id="Bisham_Abbey"><placeName>Bisham Abbey</placeName><note resp="#lmw"><placeName>Bisham Abbey</placeName>, in <placeName ref="#Berkshire">Berkshire</placeName> <!--LMW See http://www.bishamabbeynsc.co.uk/ --></note></place></listPlace></div></back></text></TEI>