<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><?xml-model href="http://ebeshero.github.io/MRMValidate.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Letter to <persName ref="#Talfourd_Thos">T.N. Talfourd</persName>[1822 May 19]</title><author ref="#MRM">Mary Russell Mitford</author><editor ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</editor><sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford Project</orgName></sponsor><sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor><principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal><respStmt><resp>Transcription and coding by</resp><persName ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Proofing and corrections by</resp><persName ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</persName><!--updated schema and tags. LMW 2015 09 30-->
               <!--ebb: 29 May 2014: Entered prosop. Transcription needs to be checked.--></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>First digital edition in TEI, date: 24 May 2014. P5.</edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority><pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace><date>2013</date><availability><p>Reproduced by courtesy of the <placeName>The John Rylands University Library</placeName>.</p><licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                  License</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Mitford Letters: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><repository ref="#Rylands">The John Rylands University Library</repository><collection>Mitford-Talfourd Correspondence: Letters from Mary Russell Mitford to Thomas Noon Talfourd: vol. 665</collection><idno>JRL English MS 665 no. 12 Coles no. 36</idno></msIdentifier><head>Letter from Mary Russell Mitford to T.N. Talfourd, <date when="1822-05-19">[1822 May 19]</date>. <!-- Coles dates this fragment based on MRM's diary: "The letter is undated, but is certainly the one recorded in the diary on May 19, with which Miss Mitford sent part of Julian to Macready.  It was taken on the following day to London by her father." (Coles #36, note 1).  The first part of the letter is missing and so the letter has no date or opener. LMW --> <!--DSCF1166, DSCF1167, DSCF1168, DSCF1169  LMW --></head><physDesc><objectDesc><supportDesc><support><p>Folio sheet of <material>paper</material> folded in half to form four
                              quarto pages, with correspondence on 1-3 and address leaf on page 4,
                              then folded in thirds twice more and sealed for posting.</p><p>Address leaf bearing no postmarks</p></support><condition><p>A small portion of page 1 has been torn away under the seal but it does not affect any text. </p></condition></supportDesc></objectDesc><sealDesc><p>Partial red wax seal, right side up.</p></sealDesc></physDesc></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><handNotes><handNote xml:id="pencilRy" medium="pencil">Someone cataloging the letters, apparently
               other than Mitford, numbered each on page 1. This letter numbered 12.</handNote></handNotes></profileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><p>Mitford’s spelling and punctuation are retained, except where a word is split at the
               end of a line and the beginning of the next in the manuscript. Where Mitford’s
               spelling and hyphenation of words deviates from the standard, in order to facilitate
               searching we are using the TEI elements “choice," “sic," and “reg" to encode both
               Mitford’s spelling and the regular international standard of Oxford English spelling,
               following the first listed spelling in the Oxford English Dictionary. The long s and
               ligatured forms are not encoded.</p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="letter"><p>propitiated our <rs type="person" ref="#Kemble_C">Manager</rs>--whose childishness is really in a man of his ripe years incredible.  In the mean time would you advise me to try another Tragedy?  If I could ever hope to do any thing really good--any thing worthy of <persName ref="#Macready_Wm">Mr. Macready</persName>--But oh I never Shall!--Would you try <title ref="#Julian_MRMplay">Julian</title>?  I don't think you like the subject, &amp; I have many fears myself--&amp; the dear <persName ref="#Valpy_Richard">Doctor</persName>'s admiration is seriously a bad sign--for you know he likes nothing but the melodramatic.  Do you think that <persName ref="#Macready_Wm">Mr. Macready</persName> who has already been so very very kind would take the trouble to read the first scenes <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/></del> &amp; say whether he thought it promising?  I shall enclose it to you--but I depend on you not to mention it to him if he is at all likely to consider it as an intrusion--&amp; mind (as <persName ref="#Cobbett_Wm">Cobbett</persName> says) that I shall not take his advice to continue it--if such should be his advice--as at all pledging him to patronize the <title ref="#Julian_MRMplay">Play</title>.  I had much rather that you would would give me a final answer--make up <emph rend="underline">my</emph> mind for me yourself--without troubling him--both because I have a great reluctance to take a liberty which he may well thinking unwarrantable with a gentleman whom I know only by his admirable talents &amp; his admirable kindness--&amp; because I still hold that old faith.  Which you wot of in your infallibility--but on this subject you have always seemed almost as undecided as myself. Perhaps I ought to have taken your indecision as an absolute No, because you never fail to give encouragement where you can honestly--&amp; yet you do pay me the Compliment of telling me the truth sometimes too.  You need not take the trouble to retain the M.S. as I have another copy--I have marked the little bits of <persName ref="#Euripides">Euripides</persName>. <!-- See Coles #12, p. 183, note 6 for background on Euripides reference.  LMW --> The worst of <title ref="#Julian_MRMplay">Julian</title> is that I don't see there can be any part at all for <persName ref="#Kemble_C">Mr. Kemble</persName>--for I suppose to think of his ever playing a father to <persName ref="#Macready_Wm">Mr. Macready</persName> is quite out of the <pb n="2"/> question--unless in his love of young characters he should take a fancy to "do" the little King.  I wish with all my heart I had some high historical subject.  <persName ref="#James_Miss">Miss James</persName> was recommending to me the story of the <persName ref="#GastonII"><persName ref="#GastonIII">two Gaston de Foix Counts of Orthe</persName></persName> in <persName ref="#Froissart">Froissart</persName>--Do you remember it?  I do not--but I have sent to her for it--If the subject be good--&amp; unoccupied &amp; there were a Father who might be made the real hero &amp; a son who might pass for such it would just do, &amp; I need not have troubled you with <title ref="#Julian_MRMplay">Julian</title>.  I am quite astonished to find myself planning new plays again after this disappointment.  It is just like the poor silly birds who begin to build afresh the moment their nests have been taken.  But really there is some little hope even in the caprice of these Managers--&amp; I do not know what to do better--I wish I did.</p><p>During the negotiation about poor <title ref="#Foscari_MRMplay">Foscari</title> I have had another affair with another Manager, &amp; have fallen out &amp; fallen <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/></del> in with <persName ref="#Valpy_John">John Valpy's</persName><persName ref="#Bayley_P">Mr. Bayley</persName>--the Editor of the <title ref="#Museum_per">Museum</title>.  It is the worst consequence of this sort of anxiety--&amp; I suppose of all anxiety--that it makes one nervous as it is called--that is to say unquiet &amp; irritable--So that I have lost my only good gift the serenity of a naturally calm &amp; cheerful temper, &amp; things fret me now which two years ago would only have amused me.  In this mood I was so affronted at a certainly impertinent notice in No. 1 of the <title ref="#Museum_per">Museum</title> that I wrote to <persName ref="#Valpy_John">John Valpy</persName> &amp; desired him to return the three Articles <!-- listed in Coles.  LMW -->which I had sent him.  Instead of doing so <persName ref="#Valpy_John">John</persName> wrote back a letter so very kind &amp; friendly that it was quite irresistible &amp; with it came an epistle from the <rs type="person" ref="#Bayley_P">Editor</rs> in which amidst a shower of compliments he reiterates his original charge of imitation &amp; conjured me not to waste my powers by catching up <pb n="2"/> the peculiarities of a style &amp;c. &amp;c.  Now I am so guiltless of intentional imitation that I did not even guess what poet he meant till a letter from <persName ref="#Nooth_C">Miss Nooth,</persName> who was I suppose behind the scenes, explained the mystery by advising me not "to pervert my dramatic Style by the example of <persName ref="#Procter_BW">Barry Cornwall</persName>--not to be pretty &amp; simple but pointed &amp; polished &amp; concise" &amp; so on.  You know her notions on poetry &amp; the drama--&amp; by the bye I don't believe that she ever <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/></del> read a line of <persName ref="#Procter_BW">Barry Cornwall</persName>s &amp; I am pretty sure that she has never seen any dramatic poetry of mine.  But I don't see why <persName ref="#Bayley_P">Mr. Bayley</persName> should fancy an imitation if none existed &amp; I have mentioned the circumstance in order to implore you to tell me frankly if there is in my <title ref="#DramaticScenes">Dramatic Scenes</title> any culpable "catching at the peculiarities of <persName ref="#Procter_BW">Mr. Proctor</persName>'s style."  There is a resemblance in form certainly--&amp; though I have never seen his delightful work since I read it very hastily &amp; admired it very much soon after its <gap reason="torn" quantity="1" unit="word"/><unclear><supplied resp="#lmw">publication</supplied></unclear> yet I am aware that certain forms of dialogue may <gap reason="torn" quantity="2" unit="word"/><unclear><supplied resp="lmw">have fixed</supplied></unclear> themselves in my mind &amp; may have been unconsciously transferred to my own pages.  Do tell me if it is so.--I have just heard of a worse affair in these <title ref="#Museum_per">Museum</title> Managers than the notice.--They have actually lost my articles, &amp; want to throw the blame on the poor dear <persName ref="#Valpy_Richard">Doctor</persName> whom I believe to be as innocent in the matter as a Dove.  Well. <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</persName> will take them in hand--I have not made him promise not to scold them--&amp; <persName ref="#Bayley_P">Mr. Bayley</persName> is likely enough to come in for a small portion of the hoarded wrath excited by <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/>Mr.</del> his friend <persName ref="#Kemble_C">Mr. Kemble.</persName>--Perhaps his is one of the Rotation Tragedies--<persName ref="#Valpy_John">John Valpy</persName> said he had one in the Theatre--at least he said the <persName ref="#Bayley_P">Editor</persName> had one--whom we then took for<persName ref="#Soane_G">Mr. Soane</persName> .--I am quite ashamed of this interminable letter--I hope <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</persName> will find you quite recovered.--Adieu my dear &amp; kind <rs type="person" ref="#Talfourd_Thos">friend</rs>--</p><closer><lb/> I cannot tell you with how much gratitude I am always your's<lb/><signed><persName ref="#MRM">M.R. Mitford</persName></signed><lb/></closer><postscript><p>Do you think there would be any use in shewing the altered <title ref="#Foscari_MRMplay">Foscari</title> to <persName ref="#Milman_HH">Mr. Milman</persName>--It is much better than the original play certainly (thanks to you!)--&amp; his good word would go far with <orgName ref="#Kemble_family">the Kemble's</orgName>--but then I suppose he is pledged to the <title ref="#Vespers_of_Palermo">Sicilian Vesper Tragedy</title>--What do you think--I have never yet had the heart to write out the alterations--but that would soon be done.</p><p>You will tell <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</persName> whether <persName ref="#Macready_Wm">Mr. Macready</persName> is really coming &amp; when.--&amp; whether you come too--Oh do pray.--And whether you are really &amp; truly quite quite well again--Once more Good bye.--I am ashamed of this sad scrawl.</p></postscript><closer><address><addrLine> To <persName ref="#Talfourd_Thos">T. N. Talfourd</persName> Esq<hi rend="superscript"/>re.</addrLine></address></closer></div></body><back>
        <!--ebb: 29 May 2014: Prosopography entered in Site Index.--></back></text></TEI>