<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><!--<?xml-model href="http://ebeshero.github.io/MRMValidate.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>--><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Letter to <persName ref="#Haydon">B.R. Haydon</persName>, 1823 October
               1</title><author ref="#MRM">Mary Russell Mitford</author><editor ref="#hbl">Hailey Lown</editor><sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford Project</orgName></sponsor><sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor><principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal><respStmt><resp>Transcription and coding by</resp><persName ref="#hbl">Hailey Lown</persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Date last checked: 23 February 2015<date/>. Proofing and corrections by: </resp><persName>Rebecca Tang</persName></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>First digital edition in TEI, date: 11 August 2014. P5.</edition><respStmt><orgName>The Digital Mitford</orgName><resp> editors' photos from this archive are not permitted for public distribution.<!--ebb: This will be the case for most of our archive photos. We can remove the "not permitted for public distribution" phrase from Reading CL letters, since we are permitted to post these.--> Photo files: <idno>1Oct1823BRHaydon1b#.JPG, 1Oct1823BRHaydon2a#.JPG</idno></resp></respStmt></editionStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority><pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace><date>2014</date><availability><p>Reproduced by courtesy of the <placeName>The Reading Central
                  Library</placeName>.</p><licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                  License</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Mitford Letters: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><repository ref="#ReadingCL">The Reading Central Library</repository><collection><!-- err: Need to find which collection these letters are from! --></collection><idno><!-- err: mansucript/collection numbers still needed. --></idno></msIdentifier><head>Letter from Mary Russell Mitford to B.R. Haydon, <date when="1823-10-01">1823
                  October 1</date>.</head><physDesc><objectDesc><supportDesc><support><p>One octavo sheet of <material>paper</material> folded in thirds. 
                              The second page bears the end of the letter on one side, and (after
                              being folded into three panels) exposes the address on the other side.</p><p>Address leaf bearing the following
                              postmarks:<!-- err: These descriptions should be checked carefully for clarity/accuracy by whomever proofreads this letter. Thanks! -->
                              1) Sepia-colored oval delivery stamp, that is intact, in the top right of the address leaf page. 
                              Seems to say: 2A NOON 2, OC+1, 1823.
                              2) Sepia-colored badge shaped delivery stamp, that is intact, at the top left of the address leaf page.
                              It was applied upon deposit of the letter at the local PO. Seems to say: 4 EVEN 4, 1.00, 1823. 
                              3) Black, rectangular, Recieving House Stamp. Seems to say: Fleed St. 
                              4) A large 3, denoting the fee for a single-sheet letter, has been written in black ink by the postal service across the address leaf.</p></support><condition> </condition></supportDesc></objectDesc><sealDesc><p>Red wax seal.</p></sealDesc></physDesc></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><handNotes><handNote xml:id="pen" medium="pencil">Someone, possibly B.R. Haydon, drew a picture
               of what seems to be a cow in black ink on the middle of the back third of the octavo
               folio. The reasoning behind it having been B.R. Haydon who drew it is that it was drawn 
               in a different hand than Mitford. Also, it would be remiss to forget that B.R. Haydon was an artist.
            </handNote><handNote xml:id="rc" medium="red_crayon">Red crayon or thick red pencil. Probably a
               different hand from Mitford's that marks many of her letters, sometimes drawing
               diagonal lines across pages, and sometimes writing words overtop and perpendicularly
               across Mitford's writing. On this letter, a red diagonal line is drawn from the top left to the bottom right of page 1 of the manuscript. Another one is drawn from the bottom right to the top left of page 2.</handNote></handNotes></profileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><p>Mitford’s spelling and punctuation are retained, except where a word is split at the
               end of a line and the beginning of the next in the manuscript. Where Mitford’s
               spelling and hyphenation of words deviates from the standard, in order to facilitate
               searching we are using the TEI elements “choice," “sic," and “reg" to encode both
               Mitford’s spelling and the regular international standard of Oxford English spelling,
               following the first listed spelling in the Oxford English Dictionary. The long s and
               ligatured forms are not encoded.</p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p> I have a sneaking kindness for portraits. I do not mean the faces on the <placeName ref="#Royal_Academy">Royal <del rend="squiggles">Academy</del></placeName> walls- but those portraits which <emph rend="escaped"/>" from the great painters -<persName ref="#Titian">Titian</persName>- <persName ref="#Rubens">Rubens</persName>- <persName ref="#Rembrandt">Rembrandt</persName>- and that is the way that yours will be considered not only by posterity but by that main part of the next generation the posterity of twenty years hence. Paint plenty of portraits - and plenty of humourous pictures - it is your peculiar talent - &amp; Do tell me what this one is about- I am so stupid that I have not been able to guess- Tell me this secret- &amp; I will tell you one in return. &amp; you must mot even let any <gap reason="torn" quantity="1" unit="word"/><unclear><supplied resp="#rct">one</supplied></unclear>know that there is in my care a secret to tell. _ I am sorry for what you tell me of <persName ref="#Hazlitt_Wm">Mr. Hazlitt</persName>- because the good faith his writing was their greatest charm - but in the forthwhile affair much may be said on <pb n="2"/><gap reason="torn" unit="word" quantity="2"/>- had all events there is nobody like him. -Tell dear <persName ref="#Haydon_Mrs">Mrs. Haydon</persName> with my kindest love that now <persName ref="#Macready_Wm">Mr. Macready</persName> has left <placeName ref="#Covent_Garden_Theatre">Covent garden</placeName>. I hope the <title ref="#Foscari_MRMplay">Foscari</title> will be brought out there this season. -And now goodbye and Godbless you- </p><closer><lb/>Ever your's<lb/><signed>M. R. Mitford</signed><lb/><lb/><address><addrLine><persName ref="#Haydon">B. R. Haydon Esqre</persName></addrLine><addrLine><placeName ref="#8 Paddington Green">8 Paddington Green</placeName></addrLine><addrLine>Near the Church</addrLine><addrLine><placeName ref="#Paddington">Paddington</placeName></addrLine></address></closer></body><back><div type="places"><listPlace><place xml:id="Royal_Academy"><placeName>Burlington House, Piccadilly, London</placeName><note resp="#hbl">The Royal Academy of Arts was founded through a personal act of King George III on 10 December 1768 with a mission to promote the arts of design in Britain through education and exhibition. The motive in founding the Academy was twofold: to raise the professional status of the artist by establishing a sound system of training and expert judgment in the arts, and to arrange the exhibition of contemporary works of art attaining an appropriate standard of excellence. Supporters wanted to foster a national school of art and to encourage appreciation and interest in the public based on recognized canons of good taste.</note></place></listPlace></div><div type="historical_people"><listPerson type="hist"><person xml:id="Rembrandt" sex="1"><persName>Rembrandt van Rijn</persName><persName><forename>Rembrandt</forename><forename>Harmenszoon</forename><surname>van Rijn</surname></persName><birth when="1606-06-15"><placeName>Leiden</placeName></birth><death when="1669-10-04"><placeName ref="#Amsterdam">Amsterdam,Netherlands</placeName></death><occupation>artist</occupation><note type="bio" resp="#hbl">A prolific painter, draftsman, and etcher, Rembrandt is usually regarded as the greatest artist of Holland's "Golden Age." Rembrandt never went abroad, but he voraciously surveyed the work of Northern artists who had lived in Italy. Even by Dutch standards, Rembrandt's preoccupation with direct observation was exceptional and continued throughout his career. Despite the constant evolution of his style, Rembrandt's compelling descriptions of light, space, atmosphere, modeling, texture, and human situations may be traced back even from his late works.</note></person><person xml:id="Rubens" sex="1"><persName>Peter Paul Rubens</persName><persName><forename>Peter</forename><forename>Paul</forename><surname>Rubens</surname></persName><birth when="1577-06-28"><placeName>Siegan</placeName></birth><death when="1640-05-30"><placeName ref="#Antwerp">Antwerp, Amsterdam</placeName></death><occupation>artist</occupation><note type="bio" resp="#hbl">A German painter who specialized in Baroque art. After study with local Antwerp painters, Rubens began finding his style in Italy, copying works from antiquity, Renaissance masters such as Michelangelo and Titian, and contemporaries like Annibale Carracci and Caravaggio. He worked principally in Rome and Genoa, where Giulio Romano's frescoes influenced him greatly. Returning to Antwerp, Rubens became court painter to the Spanish Viceroys, eventually receiving commissions from across Europe and England. </note></person><person xml:id="Titian" sex="1"><persName>Tiziano Vecellio</persName><persName><forename>Tiziano</forename><surname>Velcellio</surname></persName><birth when="1485"><placeName>Pieve di Cadore</placeName></birth><death when="1576-08-27"><placeName ref="#Venice">Venice,Italy</placeName></death><occupation>artist</occupation><note type="bio" resp="#hbl">Known as Titian, Velcellio is thought of as the greatest Venetian artist of the sixteenth century, eventually gaining international fame. He is known above all for his remarkable use of color; his painterly approach was highly influential well into the seventeenth century. Titian contributed to all of the major areas of Renaissance art, painting altarpieces, portraits, mythologies, and pastoral landscapes with figures.</note></person></listPerson></div></back></text></TEI>