<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><?xml-model href="http://ebeshero.github.io/MRMValidate.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title xml:id="MRM0546">Letter to <persName ref="#Talfourd_Thos">T.N. Talfourd</persName>, [11 May] 1825</title><author ref="#MRM">Mary Russell Mitford</author><editor ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</editor><sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford Project</orgName></sponsor><sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor><sponsor>Pittsburgh Supercomputing Center</sponsor><principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal><respStmt><resp>Transcription and coding by</resp><persName ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</persName><persName>Heather Sarsfield</persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Date last checked: <date when="2016-01-19">2016-01-19</date>
                  Proofing and corrections by</resp><persName ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</persName><!-- Notes updated. Still needs proofing against ms. --></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>First digital edition in TEI, date: 22 May 2014. P5.</edition><respStmt><resp>Edition made with help from photos taken by</resp><orgName>Digital Mitford editors</orgName></respStmt><respStmt><orgName>Digital Mitford</orgName><resp> photo files: <idno>DSCN1172.JPG, DSCN1173.JPG, DSCN1174.JPG, DSCN1175.JPG </idno></resp></respStmt></editionStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority><pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace><date>2013</date><availability><p>Courtesy of <orgName ref="#Rylands">The University of Manchester</orgName>.</p><licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                  License</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Mitford Letters: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><repository ref="#Rylands">The John Rylands University Library</repository><collection>Mitford-Talfourd Correspondence: Letters from Mary Russell Mitford to Thomas Noon Talfourd: vol. 665</collection><idno>JRL English MS 665 no. 18 Coles no. 87</idno></msIdentifier><head>Letter from Mary Russell Mitford to T.N. Talfourd, <date when="1825-05-11">11 May 1825</date>. <note resp="#lmw"><persName ref="#coles">Coles</persName> dates as 11 May 1825 (postmarked 13 May); May 11 was a Wed. as checked on perpetual calendar.</note></head><physDesc><objectDesc><supportDesc><support><p>Sheet of <material>paper</material> folded in half to form four
                              pages, with correspondence on 1-3 and address leaf on page 4,
                              then folded in thirds twice more and sealed for posting.</p><p>Address leaf bearing four postmarks, three illegible: Coles has "Postmarks (the first two partly illegible):  13 MY 1825; T P; 2; a fourth postmark is illegible" (87). Sepia-inked oval Delivery stamp reading <stamp><lb/><date>13 MY 1825</date></stamp></p><p>A large 2 denoting the fee for a single-sheet letter has been written
                              in black ink by the postal service across the address leaf.</p></support><condition><p>A portion of page 3 has been torn away under the seal.</p></condition></supportDesc></objectDesc><sealDesc><p>Red wax seal, partially intact.</p></sealDesc></physDesc></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><handNotes><handNote xml:id="pencilRy" medium="pencil">Someone cataloging the letters, apparently
               other than Mitford, numbered each on page 1. This letter numbered 18.</handNote></handNotes></profileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><p>Mitford’s spelling and punctuation are retained, except where a word is split at the
               end of a line and the beginning of the next in the manuscript. Where Mitford’s
               spelling and hyphenation of words deviates from the standard, in order to facilitate
               searching we are using the TEI elements “choice," “sic," and “reg" to encode both
               Mitford’s spelling and the regular international standard of Oxford English spelling,
               following the first listed spelling in the Oxford English Dictionary. The long s and
               ligatured forms are not encoded.</p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="letter"><opener><add hand="#pencil">18</add><dateline><name type="place" ref="#ThreeMileCross">Three Mile Cross</name><date when="1825-05-11">Wednesday</date></dateline><salute><persName ref="#Talfourd_Thos">My dear friend--</persName></salute></opener><p>I have had the kindest of all kind letters from <persName ref="#Kemble_C">Mr. Kemble</persName> from his sick room, offering to give <persName ref="#Fitzharris">Mr. Fitzharris</persName> a trial early next season and promising to do all he possibly can to forward his views in <placeName ref="#London_city">London,</placeName> &amp; expressing himself very desirous to see <title>my play</title> which is too late of course for this season--You cannot think how kind &amp; friendly the letter is--I shall of course do my very best with <title ref="#CharlesI_MRMplay">"Charles"</title>--because I really think if we could make a successful play of that that <persName ref="#Elliston_Robt">Mr. Elliston</persName> would then wish to take <title ref="#Rienzi">Rienzi</title>--But I have as always had my doubts of <title ref="#CharlesI_MRMplay">Charles</title>--I shall do my best though my very best--&amp; (I am going to make a strange admission) I would give the whole profits of <title ref="#OurVillage_3rd">my last edition</title><note resp="#lmw"><persName ref="#coles">Coles</persName> proposes that Mitford here refers to her latest edition of Our Village, the third (Coles 87, note 1).</note> (whatever they may be for I don't know) that is to say all that I am worth in the world to know really &amp; truly what <persName ref="#Macready_Wm">Mr Macready</persName>'s plan was with regard to that <title ref="#Rienzi">Tragedy.</title> I am aware that I might just as well wish for the moon--It is however a great comfort &amp; relief to me that the play had<pb n="1"/> it been ready three months ago could not have come out this season (without superseding poor <title ref="#Orestes_PB"><persName ref="#Bayley_Mrs">Mrs Bayley</persName>'s</title> which of course I would not have done)<note resp="#lmw"><persName ref="#MRM">Mitford</persName> here refers to <persName ref="#Bayley">Peter Bayley</persName>'s tragedy <title ref="#Orestes_PB">Orestes in Argos</title>, first performed at <placeName ref="#Covent_Garden_Theatre">Covent Garden</placeName> on <date when="1825-04-25">25 April 1825</date>. <persName ref="#Bayley">Bayley</persName> died suddenly on <date when="1823-01-25">25 January 1823</date>, and <persName ref="#Bayley_Mrs">his widow</persName> arranged for the posthumous publication of a volume of poetry and the performance and publication of his tragedy.</note>--&amp; now I shall have time to do the best I can with it and then <emph rend="underline">I promise you</emph> I will go heartily to work at <title ref="#Heiress_MRM">the Novel</title>. I am quite ashamed at the utter prostration of mind &amp; faculty in which I have remained since the winter--It is a weakness so wrong, so much against conviction and necessity as to be almost wickedness--but I will do better if God grant me a continuance of health &amp; strength--I am ashamed of myself to have waited so many months in lamentation.--Have we any chance of seeing you at Whitsuntide?--Could not you come down on the Sunday &amp; dine here?  It would be such a comfort.--I have seen more of this young <persName ref="#Fitzharris">Fitzharris,</persName> &amp; continue to like his warmth of heart his modesty &amp; <gap reason="smudged" quantity="1" unit="word"/><unclear><supplied resp="#lmw">his</supplied></unclear> frankness--although there is a great deal about him that is most abominably Irish &amp; a sad want of literature.</p><p>I am going to see him tonight in <title ref="#Othello_play">Othello</title> &amp; shall not finish my letter till I can give my opinion, such as it is, of his performance--There certainly is extraordinary feeling in some of his touches.</p><pb n="2"/><p><date when="1825-05-11">Wednesday Night</date>--I am just <gap reason="smudged" quantity="1" unit="word"/><unclear><supplied resp="#lmw">returned</supplied></unclear> from <title ref="#Othello_play">Othello</title> &amp; have been more struck more astonished more charmed than ever I was in my life--There is as much difference between this <persName ref="#Fitzharris">young man</persName> in <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/>Othello</del><hi rend="superscript">the play</hi> &amp; in <title ref="#Stranger_play">the Stranger</title> as between <persName ref="#Shakespeare">Shakespeare</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#Kotzebue">Kotzebue</persName>--His <persName ref="#Othello_O">Othello</persName> is splendid magnificent--full of passion tenderness &amp; power--That he must one day be at the very head of his profession seems to me certain--that he will make an immediate hit almost certain--but he says that he does not know a creature in <placeName ref="#London_city">London</placeName> &amp; is frightened to death of the thought of going there next season. I wish you had been at the <placeName ref="#Reading_Theatre">Reading Theatre</placeName> tonight because I am sure of your judgement &amp; very doubtful of my own--but there is a sort of excellence which no one with any feeling can mistake--&amp; besides I have seen <persName ref="#Kean_Edmund">Kean</persName> in the part-- <persName ref="#Fitzharris">Fitzharris</persName>'s <persName ref="#Othello_O">Othello</persName> seems to me less terrible than his but far grander--far more an excuse for <persName ref="#Desdemona_O">Desdemona</persName>'s choice--&amp; his fine deep <gap reason="torn" quantity="1" unit="word"/><unclear><supplied resp="#lmw">voice</supplied></unclear> holds out to the very last amidst <gap reason="torn" quantity="2" unit="word"/><unclear><supplied resp="#lmw">all the</supplied></unclear> tumult of three acts of strong <gap reason="torn" quantity="1" unit="word"/><unclear><supplied resp="#lmw">passions</supplied></unclear>--The only thing that he seems to me to want is the faculty of expressing bitterness &amp; scorn--the venom is not in him--for which on <persName ref="#Rienzi_Cola">Rienzi's</persName> account I am heartily sorry--He is a <persName ref="#Shakespeare">Shakespearean</persName> Actor--best in the best. How I wish you could <pb n="3"/> have seen him. Of course I shall not mention his playing <persName ref="#Rienzi_Cola">Rienzi</persName> till we see how he succeeds--Nor should it stand in the way of other chances--but if he does make a hit I am quite sure of his good feeling.--God bless you <persName ref="#Talfourd_Thos">My dear friend</persName>--</p><closer><lb/>Ever most sincerely your's <choice><reg resp="#lmw">yours</reg></choice>,<lb/><signed><persName ref="#MRM">M.R.M.</persName></signed><lb/></closer><postscript><p>Kindest regards from all here to dear <persName ref="#Talfourd_Mrs">Mrs. Talford</persName> as well as yourself.<pb n="4"/></p></postscript><closer><address><addrLine> To <persName ref="#Talfourd_Thos">T. N. Talfourd</persName> Esq<hi rend="superscript">re</hi></addrLine><addrLine>2 <placeName ref="#Elm_Court"/>Elm Court</addrLine><addrLine><placeName ref="#Temple"/>Temple</addrLine></address></closer></div></body><back>
        
     <!--ebb: 30 May 2014 Prosopography entered in site index.--></back></text></TEI>